DEV-MUC3-0676 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 11 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH UNIDENTIFIED "SPOKESMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES" BY UNIDENTIFIED STATION REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] GOOD EVENING, SALVADORAN PEOPLE. RIGHT NOW, WE ARE IN THE STREETS OF SAN SALVADOR AND WE WANT TO BRING YOU AN BEXTREMELY IMPORTANT MESSAGE FROM A SPOKESMAN OF THE JOINTS CHIEFS OF STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES. HE WILL PROVIDE US WITH IMPORTANT STATEMENTS ABOUT THE URGENT SITUATION PREVAILING IN THE CITY. COULD YOU TELL US WHERE THE MOST VIOLENT EVENTS HAVE TAKEN PLACE IN SAN SALVADOR CITY?

[SPOKESMAN] WE HAVE TOURED SOME PLACES WHERE NON-MILITARY POSITIONS HAVE BEEN HARASSED. THESE ARE THE VANGUARD POSTS OF THE MILITARY POSITIONS THAT DETECTED THE TERRORISTS WHEN THEY TRIED TO ATTACK. THAT IS HOW THESE CLASHES BEGAN.

THE MAIN AREAS WHERE THIS HARASSMENT HAS TAKEN PLACE ARE IN THE SOUTHERN AREA OF SAN SALVADOR, SPECIFICALLY IN THE AREAS OF LA GUADALUPE AND MEJICANOS, AS WELL AS IN THE AREA OF SANTA TECLA. HOWEVER, WE WANT TO REPORT, THAT THIS IS ONLY HARASSMENT. THE PEOPLE SHOULD REMAIN CALM, AS WE ARE WORKING FOR THEIR BENEFIT.

[REPORTER] AS OF NOW, WE HAVE HAD REPORTS THAT THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE WAS ATTACKED. WHAT CAN YOU TELL US ABOUT THAT?

[SPOKESMAN] WELL, AS I WAS SAYING EARLIER, THE TERRORIST CRIMINALS HARASSED THE VANGUARD POSTS OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE. THE INSTALLATIONS OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, PER SE, HAVE NOT BEEN DAMAGED AT ALL, AND THE ARMED FORCES HAVE EVERYTHING UNDER CONTROL.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS YOUR MESSAGE TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE?

[SPOKESMAN] WE TELL OUR PEOPLE: REMAIN CALM, YOUR ARMED FORCES ARE WORKING TO SOLVE THIS SITUATION. WE REMIND YOU THAT IF YOU SEE ANY SUSPICIOUS MOVEMENT NEAR YOUR HOMES, YOU MUST REPORT IT TO THE NEAREST MILITARY UNIT. HAVE ON HAND THE TELEPHONE NUMBERS OF THE PUBLIC SECURITY CORPS, OR TELEPHONE NUMBER 123. THE COOPERATION THAT OUR PEOPLE CAN PROVIDE US IS OF VITAL IMPORTANCE SO THAT WE CAN SOLVE THIS SITUATION IMMEDIATELY. AS IT IS EVIDENT, THE HARASSMENT BEING WAGED BY THE CRIMINAL TERRORISTS IS NOT AGAINST THE MILITARY UNITS. WE MUST CONSIDER THIS IS JUST ONE MORE INDISCRIMINATE ATTACK THAT SEEKS A BLOODBATH [PASSAGE INDISTINCT].

DEV-MUC3-0677 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] NINE PEOPLE WERE WOUNDED--SEVEN CIVILIANS AND TWO SOLDIERS--DURING AN OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS IN THE CAPITAL AND OTHER SALVADORAN CITIES, HUMANITARIAN INSTITUTIONS HAVE REPORTED.

DURING THE OFFENSIVE, GUERRILLAS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) ATTACKED PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S RESIDENCE AND MILITARY GARRISONS IN THE CAPITAL AND OTHER CITIES.

THE RED CROSS SENT DOZENS OF AMBULANCES TO THE AREAS MOST EFFECTED TO EVACUATE THE INJURED AND CITIZENS WHO WERE TRAPPED IN THE CROSSFIRE BETWEEN THE ARMY AND THE GUERRILLAS.

EARLY SUNDAY MORNING, SPORADIC BOMB EXPLOSIONS AND MACHINEGUN FIRE COULD STILL BE HEARD IN SOME PARTS OF SAN SALVADOR. THE ARMY HAS IMPLEMENTED STRICT CONTROL ON THE DESERTED STREETS.

RADIO STATIONS WERE ASKED TO JOIN A RADIO NETWORK FROM WHERE THE GOVERNMENT HAS URGED THE POPULATION TO REMAIN CALM. THE NETWORK IS CARRYING INSTRUMENTAL MUSIC WHICH IS INTERRUPTED BY "NEWS BULLETINS" READ BY ARMY SPOKESMEN.

ALTHOUGH ACCORDING TO REPORTS, NINE PEOPLE WERE HURT, NEITHER THE ARMY NOR THE GUERRILLAS HAVE ISSUED AN OFFICIAL REPORT ON THE POSSIBLE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES.

ACCORDING TO POLITICAL OBSERVERS, THIS HAS BEEN THE GUERILLAS' LARGEST MILITARY OFFENSIVE IN THE PAST FEW YEARS, AND THE ONE HAVING THE MOST SERIOUS EFFECTS IN THE CAPITAL.

DEV-MUC3-0678 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] ONE OF THE DAUGHTERS OF THE ISRAELI AMBASSADOR TO EL SALVADOR WAS SERIOUSLY WOUNDED AND TWO AMBULANCES OF THE SALVADORAN RED CROSS WERE MACHINEGUNNED IN A CROSSFIRE DURING HEAVY CLASHES TONIGHT IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE CAPITAL.

DIPLOMATIC SOURCES CONFIRMED TO AFP THAT ONE OF THE ISRAELI AMBASSADOR'S DAUGHTERS WAS SHOT TWICE IN HER CHEST DURING A SHOOTOUT BETWEEN URBAN GUERRILLA COMMANDOS AND POLICEMEN AT THE MAQUIISHUAT NEIGHBORHOOD, IN WESTERN SAN SALVADOR.

ACCORDING TO REPORTS, SHE WAS TAKEN TO A HOSPITAL IN THE CAPITAL.

MEANWHILE, RED CROSS SPOKESMEN REPORTED THAT TWO AMBULANCES OF THAT HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATION WERE HIT BY RIFLE FIRE DURING A CROSSFIRE. ONE OF THE VEHICLES WAS TOTALLY DESTROYED, THE RED CROSS SPOKESMAN ADDED.

THE CLASHES BEGAN SIMULTANEOUSLY IN VARIOUS PARTS OF SAN SALVADOR AT 2000 LOCAL (0200 GMT). BY MIDNIGHT, RIFLE FIRE AND STRONG EXPLOSIONS COULD STILL BE HEARD. SEVERAL AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS WERE OVERFLYING THE METROPOLITAN AREA.

THOUSANDS OF PERSONS WHO WERE AT THE INTERNATIONAL FAIR OF EL SALVADOR WILL HAVE TO SAY OVERNIGHT AT THE FAIR GROUNDS IN VIEW OF THE SITUATION PREVAILING TONIGHT IN THIS CAPITAL CITY.

THE GENERAL STAFF OF THE ARMED FORCES URGS THE PEOPLE TO REFRAIN FROM GOING OUT IN THE STREETS.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES, THE FOLLOWING ARE AMONG THE TARGETS THAT WERE ATTACKED: THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, LOCATED IN THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR; THE PUBLIC SECURITY ACADEMY, AND AT LEAST 10 OTHER MILITARY POSITIONS IN SEVERAL POINTS OF THE CAPITAL CITY.

MILITARY SOURCES CONFIRMED THAT THE ARMY IS CLASHING WITH FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GUERRILLAS IN SAN MIGUEL AND USULUTAN DEPARTMENTS, IN THE EASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY.

LARGE SECTORS OF THE CAPITAL CITY ARE WITHOUT ELECTRICITY AS A RESULT OF THE SABOTAGE ACTIONS CARRIED OUT TONIGHT BY THE REBELS AGAINST THE ELECTRICITY SYSTEM.

RESIDENTS OF ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD, ONE OF THE MOST DENSELY POPULATED ONES IN SAN SALVADOR, REPORTED THAT CLOSE TO MIDNIGHT, THE GUERRILLAS WERE CONTINUING TO OCCUPY THIS NORTHERN AREA OF SAN SALVADOR.

THE ARMED FORCES HAVE PLACED ALL RADIO STATIONS IN A NETWORK AND ANNOUNCED SHORTLY BEFORE MIDNIGHT THAT A REPORT ABOUT WHAT IS HAPPENING IN SAN SALVADOR WILL BE ISSUED WITHIN THE NEXT FEW HOURS.

DEV-MUC3-0679 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 -- [STATEMENT] [COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE GENERAL ARCE NEIGHBORHOOD WAS ALSO A TARGET OF A COWARDLY ATTACK FROM THE CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY AREA. NO PROPERTY DAMAGE OR CASUALTIES HAVE BEEN REPORTED AS A RESULT OF THIS ACTION.

THERE HAVE ALSO BEEN CLASHES IN CIUDAD DELGADO, MEJICANOS, THE METROPOLIS AND MAQUIISHUAT NEIGHBORHOODS, AND AREAS NEAR EL ESPINO FARM. THERE ARE STILL NO DEFINITE REPORTS ON THE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES SUSTAINED BY THE TERRORISTS DURING THE CLASHES. HOWEVER, WE CAN SAY THAT THE FMLN HAS TREACHEROUSLY ATTACKED GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, POLITICIANS, AND THE METROPOLITAN COMMUNITY IN GENERAL.

THE ARMED FORCES EXPRESSES ITS RECOGNITION TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE FOR THE COURAGE AND SERENITY WITH WHICH THEY FACED THE COMPLEX SITUATION TONIGHT.

THE FRANK DEMONSTRATION BY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO EXPRESSED THEMSELVES THROUGH THE MEDIA AGAINST THE MURDERERS OF THE PEOPLE, THE SELF-STYLED FMLN, THEIR CONFIDENCE IN THE ARMED FORCES AND THEIR CLEAR SUPPORT OF OUR ACTIONS, OBLIGES US TO RESPOND TO THIS TERRORIST PROVOCATION AS THE SITUATION WARRANTS IN ORDER TO BRING PEACE TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND MAINTAIN PUBLIC ORDER IN COMPLYING WITH OUR CONSTITUTIONAL DUTIES. THIS SHOULD ALSO MAKE THE FMLN TERRORISTS REALIZE THAT IT IS NOT THROUGH VIOLENCE THAT THEY WILL ACHIEVE THEIR POLITICAL OBJECTIVES.

WE REITERATE ONCE AGAIN OUR GRATITUDE TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE FOR THEIR SUPPORT AND TRUST IN THE ARMED FORCES. WE ALSO THANK THE MEDIA, PARTICULARLY THE RADIO AND TELEVISION FOR THEIR COOPERATION.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: LET US HAVE FAITH IN GOD IN ORDER TO ACHIEVE PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY.

I ALSO WANT TO EXPRESS OUR RECOGNITION FOR THE BOLDNESS, COURAGE, AND PROFESSIONALISM SHOWN BY THE COMMANDERS, OFFICERS, AND TROOPS OF ALL THE MILITARY PERSONNEL AND PUBLIC SECURITY BODIES IN THE METROPOLITAN AREA AND THE DEFENSE ACTIVITIES CARRIED OUT BY OUR HEROIC SOLDIERS IN THE 3D AND 6TH BRIGADES.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: WE CAN ASSURE YOU THAT YOU HAVE AN ARMED FORCES AT YOUR SERVICE, READY TO PROTECT EACH ONE OF YOU.

DEV-MUC3-0683 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [REPORT] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] AT 2340 ON 11 NOVEMBER, FMLN UNITS, USING RPG-7 ROCKET LAUNCHERS, GRENADE LAUNCHERS, AND RIFLE FIRE, ATTACKED A PARATROOPER BATTALION AT THE COMALAPA AIRPORT. WE REPEAT, THE COMALAPA INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT WAS ATTACKED AT MIDNIGHT. WE ATTACKED A PARATROOPER BATTALION THAT WAS GUARDING THE COMALAPA AIRPORT; WE USED RPG-7 ROCKET LAUNCHERS, GRENADE LAUNCHERS, AND RIFLE FIRE. WE ATTACKED AIRCRAFT BOTH INSIDE AND OUTSIDE THE HANGAR.

THE ATTACK AGAINST THE BRACAMONTE BATTALION, USING 81-MM MORTARS, PROVOKED A FIRE INSIDE BRACAMONTE BATTALION INSTALLATIONS. ATTENTION, THE REPORT FROM COMALAPA STATES THAT THREE HELICOPTERS WERE COMPLETELY DESTROYED, ONE OR TWO SMALL PLANES DESTROYED, AND TWO HANGARS AND THE AIRCRAFT INSIDE THEM PARTIALLY DESTROYED.

THE REPORT STATES THERE WERE NUMEROUS CASUALTIES AT THE COMALAPA AIRPORT, INCLUDING AIR FORCE PILOTS. IN SUM, THREE HELICOPTERS AND ONE OR TWO SMALL PLANES WERE DESTROYED AT COMALAPA AIRPORT. AS OF NOW, A TOTAL OF FOUR HELICOPTERS AND ONE SMALL PLANE HAVE BEEN DESTROYED.

AS REPORTED EARLIER, AN HELICOPTER WAS DOWNED IN SAN MIGUEL AND FELL OVER THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAY. THE REPORT STATES THAT AT 0630 [1230 GMT] TODAY, FMLN UNITS DOWNED AN HELICOPTER AT THE 15 SEPTEMBER NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN MIGUEL; IT FELL ON THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAY. THIS CONFIRMS OUR EARLIER REPORT.

ATTENTION, HERE IS A REPORT FROM THE CAPITAL SAN SALVADOR: OUR COMBATANTS IN THE CAPITAL REPORT THAT THEY HAVE BESIEGED THE AREA BETWEEN THE INTERSECTION OF THE NORTHERN HIGHWAY AND NORTH 5TH AVENUE AND THE 1ST IFANTRY BRIGADE.[AS HEARD] OUR FORCES HAVE OCCUPIED POSITIONS IN THAT AREA AND NORTHERN AVENUE NEAR PANAMA STREET. THEY HAVE ATTACKED ALL POSITIONS IN THE NORTHERN AREA.

ATTENTION, ATTENTION: IN THE CAPITAL, IN THE AREA ADJACENT TO THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, WE RECOVERED RIFLES, MACHINEGUNS, GRENADES, AND OTHER MATERIEL. ATTENTION, ATTENTION: THERE ARE ALSO REPORTS OF VERY SUCCESSFUL ATTACKS IN ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD. OUR COMRADES ARE REPORTING FROM THE CAPITAL THAT A NATIONAL POLICE TRUCK, WHICH WAS LEAVING THE MONSERRAT GARRISON, WAS AMBUSHED. WE ARE TOLD THAT THIS AMBUSHED TRUCK WAS GOING TO REINFORCE STAFF INSTALLATIONS IN ARCE NEIGHBORHOOD.

DEV-MUC3-0684 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] NINE HOURS AFTER A SERIES OF ATTACKS WERE LAUNCHED SIMULTANEOUSLY BY THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE CAPITAL, ONE CAN STILL HEAR THE EXPLOSIONS OF POWERFUL BOMBS, THE STRAFING OF REBEL POSITIONS BY AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS, AND HEAVY RIFLE FIRE.

A HIGH-POWERED BOMB SHOOK THE AFP OFFICES IN SAN SALVADOR A FEW MINUTES AGO. IT IS JUST BEFORE DAYBREAK, 0500 ON SUNDAY MORNING. FROM THE WINDOWS, ONE CAN SEE THAT THE HELICOPTERS ARE DROPPING FLARES BEFORE FIRING TO BETTER LOCATE THEIR TARGETS.

URBAN CELLS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) ATTACKED AT LEAST 10 MILITARY POSITIONS IN THE CAPITAL AT 2000 ON SATURDAY NIGHT, AND THE ATTACKS ARE APPARENTLY CONTINUING THIS MORNING.

IN ADDITION TO ATTACKING MILITARY POSITIONS, THE REBELS ALSO LAUNCHED SIMULTANEOUS ATTACKS ON THE PRESIDENTIAL PALACE, PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S PRIVATE HOME, THE HOME OF RICARDO ALVARENGA, PRESIDENT OF THE CONGRESS, AND THE INSTALLATIONS OF THE CENTRAL ELECTORAL COUNCIL.

AIR FORCE HELICOPTER GUNSHIPS ARE STILL FIRING AT ALLEGED GUERRILLA POSITIONS, PRIMARILY IN THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR. AN EXCHANGE OF RIFLE FIRE HAS ALSO INTENSIFIED. THE NOISE CAN BE HEARD THROUGHOUT THE CAPITAL, WHERE CITIZENS ARE EXPERIENCING THE WORST ANXIETY OF THE PAST FEW YEARS OF CIVIL WAR IN EL SALVADOR.

ON A NATIONAL RADIO NETWORK, THE ARMED FORCES URGED THE PEOPLE NOT TO LEAVE THEIR HOMES BEFORE 0600 (1200 GMT).

DESPITE THE INTENSITY OF THE FIGHTING, THE ARMY HAS NOT YET REPORTED ON CASUALTIES ON EITHER SIDE.

A MILITARY SPOKESMAN SAID OVER THE RADIO NETWORK THAT THE MILITARY UNITS HAVE SURROUNDED THE LAST REBEL STRONGHOLDS IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE, IN THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR.

IN CIUDAD DELGADO, ALSO ON THE NORTHERN SIDE, "HEAVY FIGHTING IS CONTINUING, BUT OUR UNITS ARE BRINGING THE SITUATION UNDER CONTROL," THE MILITARY SPOKESMAN SAID OVER THE RADIO NETWORK.

IMPORTANT SECTORS OF THE CITY REMAIN DARK BECAUSE THE GUERRILLAS SABOTAGED SEVERAL ELECTRIC PYLONS AT THE SAME TIME THAT THEY LAUNCHED THE ATTACKS ON THE MILITARY POSITIONS.

COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE ARMED FORCES JOINT STAFF, LAST WEEK NOTED WHAT HE DESCRIBED AS A "PRE-INSURRECTIONAL STAGE" ON THE PART OF THE FMLN, PRIMARILY IN URBAN AREAS.

VIOLENCE BROKE OUT ON SATURDAY MORNING, WHEN GUERRILLA URBAN COMMANDS LAUNCHED A MORTAR ATTACK ON THE NATIONAL GUARD HEADQUARTERS IN THE CAPITAL. TWO CHILDREN AND EIGHT OTHER PEOPLE (THREE SOLDIERS AND FIVE CIVILIANS) WERE WOUNDED.

DEV-MUC3-0686 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE A REPORT WHICH SAYS THAT FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] FORCES HAVE SEIZED CONTROL OF THE SAN SALVADOR - SANTA ANA HIGHWAY, INTERRUPTING TRAFFIC ALONG THIS IMPORTANT HIGHWAY TO SANTA ANA. THE 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE, WHICH IS LOCATED AT THE SANTA ISABEL NEIGHBORHOOD IN SANTA ANA, HAS BEEN ATTACKED, AND THE FIGHTING CONTINUED THROUGHOUT THE CITY EARLY THIS MORNING.

THE INFORMATION REVEALS THAT ROADBLOCKS HAVE BEEN BUILT ON THE HIGHWAY TO SAN SALVADOR AND THE ROAD TO TACACHICO. IT HAS ALSO BEEN CONFIRMED THAT THREE RIFLES WERE SEIZED FROM THE 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS.

ATTENTION, REPORTS FROM THE CAPITAL CONFIRM THAT FIERCE FIGHTING HAS TAKEN PLACE AROUND THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE; AND LOTS OF RIFLES, MACHINEGUNS, AND OTHER WEAPONS WERE SEIZED FROM DEATH SQUAD LEADER [COLONEL FRANCISCO] ELENA FUENTES' TROOPS AT THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE. OUR MEN HAVE SEIZED THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS' RIFLES AND MACHINEGUNS, WHILE AMBUSHES IN DIFFERENT POINTS OF THE CAPITAL HAVE MULTIPLIED.

THE ARMY'S DETACHMENTS HAVE BEEN IMMOBILIZED SO THE AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS ARE NOW BEING USED TO EVACUATE PERSONNEL, LANDING IN SEVERAL POINTS OF THE CAPITAL WHICH THE ARMY CANNOT REACH.

MEANWHILE, FMLN FORCES ATTACKED A POLICE PATROL CAR IN THE CAPITAL, ANNIHILATED ALL THE PASSENGERS, AND SEIZED THE VEHICLE.

DEV-MUC3-0687 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CRISTIANI, IN PROGRESS] ...ADDRESS YOU ON THIS OCCASION TO EXPLAIN THE SITUATION WHICH HAS ARISEN, A REPREHENSIBLE SITUATION CAUSED BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WHICH ONCE AGAIN IS ENDANGERING THE LIVES OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN EL SALVADOR.

WE BELIEVE IT IS UNJUSTIFIABLE, UNDER ANY CIRCUMSTANCES, FOR THE FMLN TO CARRY OUT THIS TYPE OF ACTION, WHICH IS NOT A MILITARY ACTION, KNOWING THAT A PEACE PROCESS IS UNDERWAY. THESE ARE ACTIONS THAT GO....[CHANGES THOUGHT] THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE ALWAYS THE ONES WHO PAY MOST DEARLY FOR THE F M L N'S IRRATIONAL ATTITUDE. THIS IS PROVED BY THE DEPLORABLE INCIDENT WHICH OCCURRED YESTERDAY MORNING, WHEN TWO SMALL CHILDREN -- 4- YEARS OLD AND 1- YEAR OLD -- DIED AS A RESULT OF THE F M L N'S IRRATIONAL ACTIONS.

WE BELIEVE, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THAT THE PEACE PROCESS IS IRREVERSIBLE AND IT SHOULD OCCUR; AND IT HAS BEEN SUPPORTED -- NOT ONLY BY YOU, AS PEOPLE WHO DEMAND PEACE AND TRANQUILITY, BUT ALSO BY THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY -- THROUGHOUT THESE MONTHS. YOU HAVE BEEN THE BEST WITNESSES OF THE EFFORTS EXERTED BY YOUR GOVERNMENT AT THE INTERNATIONAL LEVEL AND OF THE SUPPORT....[CORRECTS HIMSELF] THE UNDENIABLE SUPPORT RECEIVED FROM ALL THE NATIONS WHO ARE FRIENDS OF EL SALVADOR. ACTIONS LIKE THE ONES WHICH THE FMLN IS TRYING TO CARRY OUT ARE NO LONGER JUSTIFIABLE.

WE WOULD LIKE TO THANK YOU THIS MORNING FOR THE WAY IN WHICH YOU, WHO ARE PART OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE [AS HEARD], HAVE BEHAVED. WE CANNOT BUT STATE OUR GRATITUDE FOR THE MANY STATEMENTS WE HAVE BEEN HEARING THROUGH THE NATIONAL NETWORK WHICH BEGAN LAST NIGHT, PARTICULARLY THE SUPPORT YOU HAVE GIVEN TO YOUR ARMED FORCES.

THE ARMED FORCES ARE BENT ON STOPPING THE TERRORISTS AND PROTECTING YOU, MEANING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THE ARMED FORCES ARE A PROFESSIONAL CORPS; AND THE ARMED FORCES ARE PREPARED TO COUNTER ANY IRRATIONAL FMLN ACTION -- EVEN THIS ONE, WHICH IS ONLY BEING CARRIED OUT FOR PUBLICITY PURPOSES WITH THE SUPPORT OF THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT, WHICH IS ISSUING FALSE STATEMENTS THROUGH A NETWORK THAT HAS BEEN ESTABLISHED BETWEEN RADIO SANDINO AND RADIO VENCEREMOS.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, OUR ARMED FORCES CONTROL THE SITUATION. THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN ABLE TO DO THIS THANKS TO YOUR SUPPORT AND COOPERATION; AND THE TERRORISTS WILL BE FORCED TO GATHER IN INCREASINGLY SMALLER PLACES. WE BELIEVE THAT THE ARMED FORCES WILL DEFINITELY CONTROL THE SITUATION IN A SHORT TIME. HOWEVER, IT IS NECESSARY TO CONTINUE RECEIVING YOUR SUPPORT. THE ARMED FORCES DO NOT WANT, UNDER ANY CIRCUMSTANCES, TO ENDANGER THE LIFE OF EVEN ONE SINGLE CIVILIAN; BUT THEY WILL SEE TO IT THAT THE TERRORISTS RECEIVE WHAT THEY DESERVE ON THIS OCCASION, WHEN THEY HAVE CAUSED SO MUCH DAMAGE TO THE POPULATION, ITSELF.

WE BELIEVE IT IS NECESSARY FOR YOU TO HEED THE CALL NOT TO GO OUT ON TO THE STREETS; TO STAY AT HOME OR AT THE RESIDENCE IN WHICH YOU ARE RIGHT NOW -- EVEN IF IT IS NOT YOUR OWN -- BECAUSE IT IS NOW A MATTER OF TIME. I REPEAT, WE DO NOT WANT ANY MORE CASUALTIES AS A RESULT OF THE F M L N'S IRRATIONAL ATTITUDE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0689 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE ARMED FORCES EXISTS TO PROTECT YOU AND THAT IS WHAT IT WANTS TO DO. HOWEVER, THE ARMED FORCES MUST ALSO CARRY OUT ITS CONSTITUTIONAL DUTY, WHICH IS TO COUNTER THE TERRORISTS WHO ARE THE ONES CAUSING SO MANY PROBLEMS FOR OUR COUNTRY AND FOR YOU, SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

WE REGRET THE FACT THAT 7 INNOCENT PERSONS HAVE DIED AND 23 HAVE BEEN INJURED. THESE ARE PERSONS WHO YESTERDAY WERE PROBABLY THINKING ABOUT ENJOYING THEMSELVES WITH THEIR FAMILIES AND WHO TODAY ARE DEAD AS A RESULT OF THOSE IRRATIONAL ACTIONS. THE ARMED FORCES WANTS TO PROTECT YOUR LIVES AS BEST IT CAN. PLEASE, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, LET US REMAIN INSIDE OUR HOMES. DO NOT GO OUT ON THE STREETS, ESPECIALLY IN THE AREAS WHERE SPORADIC INCIDENTS ARE STILL BEING REPORTED. WE FEEL THAT IT IS NECESSARY THAT YOU REMAIN CALM AND ALWAYS TRUST THE ARMED FORCES. THIS SITUATION IS GOING TO BE CONTROLLED. IT IS GOING TO BE CONTROLLED, AND WE ARE GOING TO FIND THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR ALL THE HARM CAUSED.

I HAVE ALSO SUMMONED AND MET WITH THE CABINET. I BELIEVE THAT IT IS ALWAYS NECESSARY TO ANALYZE THE ATTITUDE OF THE GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES WITHIN OUR COUNTRY'S LEGAL FRAMEWORK. I BELIEVE THAT THIS IS THE TIME FOR THE TERRORISTS TO KNOW THAT THERE ARE LAWS TO FIGHT THEIR IRRATIONAL ACTIONS. WE ARE STUDYING WHETHER IT WILL BE NECESSARY TO IMPLEMENT A STATE OF SIEGE AND A CURFEW. LATER WE WILL ADVISE YOU OF THE DECISION THAT THE MINISTERS MAY REACH SO THAT YOU WILL BE INFORMED. I BELIEVE THAT IF A STATE OF SIEGE AND A CURFEW ARE DISCUSSED, IT IS PRECISELY TO PROTECT YOU, TO PROTECT THE CIVILIANS FROM THE IRRATIONAL FMLN TERRORISTS. THAT IS THE ONLY REASON FOR THIS. THESE MEASURES ARE THE TOOLS THAT OUR STATE OF LAW OFFERS FOR THE GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES TO PROTECT YOUR LIVES SO THAT WE WILL NO LONGER HAVE TO REGRET INCIDENTS SUCH AS THE ONES WE HAVE SEEN THE PAST 2 DAYS.

WE BELIEVE THAT YOUR ATTITUDE DESERVES OUR RECOGNITION AND THE RECOGNITION OF ALL THE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD. EVERYONE HAS SEEN THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE LOVE DEMOCRACY AND FREEDOM AND DO NOT WANT MORE VIOLENCE, AND UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES DO THEY SUPPORT THESE IRRATIONAL ACTIONS CARRIED OUT BY THE FMLN.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THE ARMED FORCES AND THE PEOPLE WILL AGAIN WIN. THEY WILL TRIUMPH OVER THE FMLN TERRORISTS. WE ASK YOU TO CONTINUE SUPPORTING US, THAT YOU CONTINUE TO GIVE US THE OPPORTUNITY TO ACT EFFECTIVELY , WITHOUT ENDANGERING MORE CIVILIAN LIVES. THROUGHOUT THE DAY WE WILL CONTINUE TO REPORT ON THE SITUATION, AND WE REPEAT, THE ARMED FORCES WILL CONTROL THE SITUATION SHORTLY.

THANK YOU FOR YOUR ATTENTION AND YOUR EFFECTIVE COOPERATION. REST ASSURED THAT YOUR ARMED FORCES AND YOUR GOVERNMENT WILL RESPOND AS YOU HAVE ORDERED. THANK YOU.

DEV-MUC3-0692 (GE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 12 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA] [EXCERPT] [PASSAGE OMITTED] ....THE SALVADORAN [WORD INDISTINCT] IS DOING THE SAME THING SOMOZA DID WITH THE CITIES OF NICARAGUA, AND THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT IS CONCERNED OVER THIS, OVER A MASSACRE, A GENOCIDE GAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. WHAT IS REQUIRED IS A PEACEFUL SOLUTION OF THAT CONFLICT, NOT THE BOMBING OF SALVADORAN CITIES. WHEN THOSE AIRPLANES BOMB CITIES THEY ARE REALLY BOMBING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. HOW CAN THEY KNOW WHO THE BOMBS, ROCKETS, OR SHOTS WILL HIT? IT IS A TRULY DANGEROUS SITUATION.

I URGE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY -- JUST AS IT BECOMES CONCERNED, CARRIES OUT CAMPAIGNS, AND MAKES STATEMENTS WHEN THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT ADOPTS HARSH MEASURES -- WHEN THESE EVENTS ARE TAKING PLACE IN EL SALVADOR TO DRAW ATTENTION TO THE SITUATION. THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY MUST SPEAK OUT AND PREVENT THE BOMBING OF SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND CITIES.

THIS MORNING, BROTHERS OF NAGOROTE, I HAVE WALKED THESE STREETS WITH A GREAT DEAL OF ENTHUSIASM, WARMTH, AND HAPPINESS. YOU KNOW PERFECTLY WELL THAT THE BATTLE WE ARE WAGING IN THE ELECTORAL FIELD IS THE SAME BATTLE WE HAVE WAGED IN THE MILITARY FIELD WITH THE CONTRAS, THE ONLY DIFFERENCE BEING THAT THIS BATTLE IS IN THE ELECTORAL FIELD. THE ELECTIONS WILL BE BETWEEN NICARAGUA AND THE UNITED STATES, BETWEEN NICARAGUA'S INDEPENDENCE AND THE UNITED STATES, WHICH DOES NOT WANT NICARAGUA TO BE INDEPENDENT.

WHO, THEN, WILL WE VOTE FOR ON 25 NOVEMBER? [CROWD RESPONSE UNMONITORABLE] WE MUST VOTE FOR NICARAGUA, AND WE MUST INVITE ALL NICARAGUANS TO VOTE FOR NICARAGUA, EVEN IF THOSE NICARAGUANS ARE NOT MEMBERS OF THE FSLN [SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT -], EVEN IF THOSE NICARAGUANS WERE MEMBERS OF OTHER PARTIES, EVEN IF THOSE NICARAGUANS WERE INVOLVED WITH SOMOZISM IN THE PAST. IT IS A MATTER OF VOTING FOR NICARAGUA, AGAINST THE IMPERIALIST POLICY; IT IS A MATTER OF CHOOSING BETWEEN NICARAGUA AND THE IMPERIALIST POWER; AND NICARAGUA IS REPRESENTED BY THE FSLN. NO ONE MUST BE MISTAKEN ABOUT THIS. [APPLAUSE].

THE FSLN IS THE ONLY FORCE THAT CAN GUARANTEE STABILITY FOR ALL THE SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC SECTORS OF THIS COUNTRY: LARGE- SMALL- AND MEDIUM-SCALE PRODUCERS, MERCHANTS, INDUSTRIALISTS, EVERYONE. ONLY THE FSLN CAN GUARANTEE THIS BECAUSE THE UNO [NATIONAL OPPOSITION UNITY] IS SIMPLY A MESS OF PEOPLE, A BADLY MADE AND WRAPPED TAMALE. THAT IS WHAT UNO IS, AND NO ONE CAN EAT IT. [APPLAUSE, SHOUTS]

YOU LIKE BASEBALL, RIGHT? YOU LIKE BASEBALL. WHEN THE BATTER IS UP, THE PITCHER THROWS AND THE BATTER HITS THE BALL, BUT THE BALL VEERS LEFT, WHAT IS THAT? [CROWD RESPONDS: FOUL TO THE LEFT]. IF HE BATS AGAIN AND THE BALL GOES THE OTHER WAY, WHAT IS THAT? [CROWD RESPONDS: FOUL TO THE RIGHT]. AND HE HITS IT THROUGH THE CENTER, WAY UP THERE .... [CROWD RESPONDS: HOME RUN] IT IS A HOMERUN. THEREFORE, ONE SHOULD BAT NEITHER TO THE LEFT NOR TO THE RIGHT BUT THROUGH THE CENTER; 25 IN THE FIFTH [AS HEARD]. YOU MUST HIT A HOME RUN, 25 IN THE FIFTH. THAT IS WHERE THE FSLN IS, IN THE FIFTH. THAT IS WHERE THE VOTE MUST BE CAST, AND THAT IS WHERE SILVIO MAYORGA AND ALL THE PEOPLE OF NAGAROTE WILL CAST THEIR VOTES FOR THE FSLN ON 25 [FEBRUARY 1990].

DEV-MUC3-0693 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 12 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN, CENTRAL AMERICAN, LATIN AMERICAN BROTHERS: YOU ARE LISTENING TO RADIO VENCEREMOS, THE VOICE OF PEOPLE WHO ARE STRUGGLING WITH DETERMINATION TO ATTAIN DEMOCRACY. WE REPORT TO OUR FIGHTERS THAT HAVE BEEN ABLE TO TUNE IN, TO ALL OUR PEOPLE, AND THE PEOPLE OF THE WORLD THAT THE FLMN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] FORCES HAVE CONDUCTED MORE THAN 18 HOURS OF HEROIC COMBAT IN SAN SALVADOR, THE COUNTRY'S MAIN CITIES, AND IN THE HIGHWAYS. AT THIS POINT, OUR MEN HAVE DOWNED TWO HELICOPTERS AND DESTROYED THREE MORE HELICOPTERS THAT WERE ON LAND. THIS BRINGS THE TOTAL NUMBER OF HELICOPTERS TAKEN OUT OF COMBAT TO FIVE. WE HAVE ALSO DAMAGED TWO MORE ARMY ARMED VEHICLES AND THIS BRINGS THE TOTAL TO HALF A DOZEN. THESE NUMBERS HAVE BEEN CONFIRMED. WE HAVE ALSO DESTROYED 12 LIGHT TANKS. OUR PERSONNEL HAVE TAKEN CONTROL OF THE MUNICIPAL MAYORS' OFFICES IN SEVERAL PLACES THROUGHTOUT THE COUNTRY, INCLUDING THE CAPITAL CITY. ALSO, IN SAN SALVADOR WE HAVE TAKEN SEVERAL PRISONERS OF WAR. THEY ARE PART OF THE REPRESSIVE FORCES OF THE NATIONAL POLICE AND THE BELLOSO BATTALION. WE HAVE ALSO CONFISCATED A LARGE SUPPLY OF WAR MATERIEL FROM THE FASCISTS ENEMY FORCES. THESE WEAPONS ARE NOW IN THE HANDS OF OUR PEOPLE AND ARE NOW GOING TO BE USED TO SHOOT THE FASCISTS. THESE WEAPONS ARE IN THE HANDS OF PEOPLE WHO ARE WILLING TO USE THEM TO ATTAIN JUSTICE FOR THE MURDERS OF FEBE ELIZABETH VELASQUEZ, OTHER COOPERATIVISTS, THE TEN UNION LEADERS, AND MSGR ARNULFO ROMERO. THESE WEAPONS IN THE HANDS OF THE PEOPLE ARE A GUARANTEE FOR JUSTICE, DEMOCRACY, AND PEACE.

ATTENTION, ATTENTION, THIS IS LAST MINUTE INFORMATION THAT HAS BEEN RECEIVED BY RADIO VENCEREMOS. ATTENTION SALVADORANS AND PRESS AGENCIES THAT ARE MONITORING OUR GUERRILLA RADIO STATION. WE HAVE RECEIVED REPORTS THAT BOMBINGS CONTINUE IN SAN SALVADOR. INDISCRMINATE BOMBING CONTINUES IN SAN SALVADOR. WE HAVE RECEIVED REPORTS OF INDISCRIMINATE BOMBING IN ZACAMIL, SOYAPANGO, AND SAN MARCOS NEIGHBORHOODS. THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE LIVE IN THESE AREAS. THESE NEIGHBORHOODS ARE DENSELY POPULATED. WE ALSO RECEIVED THE REPORT THAT A DEATH SQUAD HEADED BY COLONEL FRANCISCO ELENA FUENTES HAS AGAIN TAKEN ACTIONS AGAINST A CIVILIAN POPULATION JUST BECAUSE THEY ARE UNABLE TO COMBAT OUR PERSONNEL. THIS SQUAD ENTERED THE SALVADORAN UNIVERSITY FROM THE AREA WHERE THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE IS LOCATED. WE MUST NOTE THAT THE UNIVERSITY IS NEAR THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE HEADQUARTERS. THEY CAPTURED 13 CIVILIANS, BLINDFOLDED, TIED, AND TOOK THEM INTO THAT MILITARY HEADQUARTERS. ELENA FUENTES -- THAT REPUDIABLE MURDERER, THAT ASSASSIN GORRILLA -- COWARDLY ATTACKS THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AS HE IS UNABLE TO COMBAT THE PEOPLE'S ARMED PERSONNEL. FUENTES IS UNABLE TO STRIKE BACK SO HE ATTACKS MOTHERS AND UNION MEMBERS. THIS IS WHAT THIS TWO-BIT COLONEL IS ACCUSTOMED TO DOING. HE STRIKES OUT AT THE PEOPLE. LET HIM COME OUT AND FIGHT THE REBELS IN SAN SALVADOR. OUR PEOPLE ARE SICK AND TIRED OF DEATH SQUADS, POVERTY, REPRESSION, AND FASCIST TOTALITARIANISM. WE ARE TOTALLY DECIDED AND FIRMLY DETERMINED TO OVERCOME THE FASCIST LATANDONA OFFICERS [NAME GIVEN TO 1966 GRADUATES OF CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY]. SALVADORAN PEOPLE: AS ONE STRONG FIST, LET US ALL JOIN TOGETHER AND STRIKE THE FASCISTS. LET'S TAKE IT TO THE HILT.

DEV-MUC3-0694 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 -- [TEXT] SAN SALVADOR DOMESTIC SERVICE IN SPANISH AT 2005 GMT ON 12 NOVEMBER BEGINS COVERAGE OF A LIVE SPEECH BY SALVADORAN DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS ON THE ONGOING REBEL OFFENSIVE IN EL SALVADOR.

LARIOS BEGINS BY ASSURING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THAT THE ARMED FORCES WILL SPARE NO EFFORT OR SACRIFICE IN DEFENDING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. HE ADDS: "WE ARE DEEPLY THANKFUL FOR THE ENCOURAGEMENT THE PEOPLE HAVE GIVEN THE ARMED FORCES. WE TAKE IT AS A CHALLENGE, AND YOU CAN REST ASSURED, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THAT JUST AS I, A SOLDIER OF THIS FATHERLAND AND OF OUR ARMED FORCES, HAVE, ALL OF THOSE BEHIND ME HAVE THE SAME RESOLVE TO STRUGGLE AND THE SAME SPIRIT TO FACE -- TODAY, TOMORROW, AND ALWAYS -- THE TERRORIST CHALLENGE TO WHICH, TODAY AND IN THE COMING HOURS, WE WILL RESPOND BY GIVING THEM A LESSON IN PROFESSIONALISM.

"MY ATTITUDE IS PRECISELY ONE OF DEFENDING AND GUARANTEEING THOSE RIGHTS, THAT SPIRIT, AND THAT RESOLVE, AND OF DEFENDING AND GUARANTEEING THE SUPREME POSTULATES CONTAINED IN THE CONSTITUTION."

REGARDING THE ONGOING FIGHTING IN SAN SALVADOR, LARIOS SAYS:

"THE MAIN PROBLEMS NOW ARE IN THE NORTHERN SECTOR OF THE THE CAPITAL CITY. WE BELIEVE THAT WE WILL HAVE FULL CONTROL OF THE SITUATION WITHIN THE NEXT FEW HOURS. MEANWHILE, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, HAVE FAITH, HOPE, AND CONFIDENCE IN YOUR ARMED FORCES, IN GOD AND IN THE DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS OF OUR PEOPLE. THANK YOU AND GOOD AFTERNOON."

LARIOS CONCLUDES HIS ADDRESS AT 2013 GMT.

FURTHER AS AVAILABLE

DEV-MUC3-0695 (GE)

HUANCAYO, 12 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] CIVILIAN AUTHORITIES IN THE CITY OF HUANCAYO, 415 KM EAST OF LIMA, HAVE REPORTED THAT 35 EXPLOSIONS WERE REPORTED TODAY BEFORE THE OPENING OF THE BALLOTING STATIONS FOR THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS. THE EXPLOSIONS DID NOT RESULT IN ANY CASUALTIES.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL REPORTS, IN HUARAZ, THE CAPITAL OF ANCASH DEPARTMENT, 409 KM NORTH OF LIMA, EIGHT EXPLOSIONS WERE REPORTED NEAR THE HOUSES OF THE PREFECT (GOVERNOR), A DISTRICT MAYOR, AND AN AGRICULTURE MINISTRY OFFICIAL, AS WELL AS NEAR FOUR SHOPS AND WAREHOUSES OF A STATE-OWNED ENTERPRISE.

IN HUANCAYO, THE CAPITAL OF JUNIN DEPARTMENT, THE HOUSE OF A CANDIDATE, SEVERAL SHOPS, SOME GOVERNMENT OFFICES, AND SCHOOLS HAVE BEEN BOMBED, ACCORDING TO THE LOCAL PREFECTURE.

SATURNINO PALOMINO TUNQUI, 25, WAS INJURED WHILE HE WAS STANDING IN A LINE IN FRONT OF ONE OF THE FIVE SCHOOLS WHERE VOTES ARE BEING CAST IN HUANCAYO. THE BULLET WAS THE SAME CALIBER AS THOSE USED BY THE ARMY.

THE TERRORIST SHINING PATH HAS CALLED AN "ARMED STRIKE" FROM 11 NOVEMBER UNTIL 13 NOVEMBER IN JUNIN, AYACUCHO, PASCO, AND HUANUCO DEPARTMENTS.

THE "ARMED STRIKE" TODAY CAUSED SERIOUS DELAYS IN THE BUS SERVICE AS PERUVIANS GO TO ELECT ABOUT 13,700 LOCAL, PROVINCIAL, AND DISTRICT OFFICIALS, INCLUDING MAYORS AND COUNCIL MEMBERS.

IN THE CITIES OF HUANCAYO AND HUARAZ, THE ARMED FORCES, WHICH ALONG WITH THE NATIONAL POLICE HAVE BEEN MOBILIZED NATIONWIDE TO PROTECT THE ELECTIONS, WERE IN CHARGE OF BUS SERVICE. ON 11 NOVEMBER, THE SHINING PATH DYNAMITED A BUS NEAR THE CITIES OF HUANCAYO AND HUARAZ AFTER THE PASSENGERS WERE FORCED TO DISEMBARK.

DEV-MUC3-0696 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 -- [SPEECH] [DEFENSE MINISTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE PEOPLE ARE PUNISHING THE FMLN. THIS VIOLENCE, THIS BLOODSHED CAUSED BY THIS TERRORIST AGGRESSION -- SPECIFICALLY THAT BLOOD -- IS PRECISELY THE INSPIRATION WE HAVE FOR DEFEATING AND BREAKING THE WILL TO FIGHT OF THIS TERRORIST FMLN. WE WILL PREVAIL; WE WILL WIN. FIRST, BECAUSE WE HAVE THE TRUTH; SECOND, BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THAT, AS CHRISTIANS, GOD IS WITH US; AND THIRD, BECAUSE WE HAVE AN INDOMITABLE ESPRIT DE CORPS AS A PROFESSIONAL ARMY, AND WE ARE DETERMINED TODAY -- AS BEFORE AND AS ALWAYS -- TO DEFEND OUR TERRITORY, OUR HISTORY, OUR VALUES, OUR PRINCIPLES, AND TO DEFEND AND PROTECT THE DIGNITY OF EACH AND EVERY SALVADORAN CITIZEN.

WE ARE DEEPLY THANKFUL TO OUR PEOPLE FOR THEIR COURAGEOUS AND HEROIC ATTITUDE. WE ARE DEEPLY THANKFUL FOR THE ENCOURAGEMENT THE PEOPLE HAVE GIVEN THE ARMED FORCES. WE TAKE IT AS A CHALLENGE, AND YOU CAN REST ASSURED, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THAT JUST AS I, A SOLDIER OF THIS FATHERLAND AND OF OUR ARMED FORCES, HAVE, ALL OF THOSE BEHIND ME HAVE THE SAME RESOLVE TO STRUGGLE AND THE SAME SPIRIT TO FACE -- TODAY, TOMORROW, AND ALWAYS -- THE TERRORIST CHALLENGE TO WHICH, TODAY AND IN THE COMING HOURS, WE WILL RESPOND BY GIVING THEM A LESSON IN PROFESSIONALISM. OUR ATTITUDE IS PRECISELY ONE OF DEFENDING AND GUARANTEEING THOSE RIGHTS, THAT SPIRIT, AND THAT RESOLVE, AND OF DEFENDING AND GUARANTEEING THE SUPREME POSTULATES CONTAINED IN THE CONSTITUTION.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WE ASK FOR YOUR CONFIDENCE, FAITH, AND HOPE IN GOD AND IN THE ARMED FORCES. REST ASSURED THAT VERY SHORTLY WE WILL HAVE VICTORY ON OUR SIDE. THANK YOU FOR THE SUPPORT, FOR THE ENCOURAGEMENT, AND -- SALVADORAN PEOPLE -- RECEIVE FROM THE ARMED FORCES RESPECTFUL AND CORDIAL GREETINGS, AND THE ASSURANCES THAT YOUR ARMED FORCES WILL VERY SOON RESOLVE THIS VIOLENCE IMPOSED BY INTERNATIONAL TERRORISM.

AS THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC REQUESTED, WE RECOMMEND THAT YOU REMAIN CALM AND STAY AT HOME. I BELIEVE THAT FOR REASONS OF YOUR OWN SECURITY, IT IS NOT ADVISABLE TO LEAVE YOUR HOMES. THE SITUATION IS BEING CONTROLLED SLOWLY.

THE MAIN PROBLEMS NOW ARE IN THE NORTHERN SECTOR OF THE CAPITAL CITY. WE BELIEVE THAT WE WILL HAVE FULL CONTROL OF THE SITUATION WITHIN THE NEXT FEW HOURS. MEANWHILE, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, HAVE FAITH, HOPE, AND CONFIDENCE IN YOUR ARMED FORCES, IN GOD AND IN THE DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS OF OUR PEOPLE. THANK YOU AND GOOD AFTERNOON.

DEV-MUC3-0697 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 12 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] HERE IS REPORT FROM THE COUNTRY'S CENTRAL ZONE, NAMELY, SAN SALVADOR AND THE OUTSKIRTS AREA. PLAY CLOSE ATTENTION. THE REPORT SAYS THAT FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] FIGHTERS, FIGHTERS OF THE GREAT ARMY OF THE RED FLAG WITH THE WHITE STAR, OF THE WORKERS' ARMY, WHICH WILL HONORABLY HOIST OUR FATHERLAND'S WHITE AND BLUE FLAG....[CHANGES THOUGHT] WE REPORT THAT GUERRILLA UNITS ATTACKED THE CEL [LEMPA RIVER HYDROELECTRIC EXECUTIVE COMMISSION] MINISTATION IN AGUA CALIENTE, SOYAPANGO, SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT. THE ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT WITH GRENADES. OUR PERSONNEL ARE MAINTAINING BARRICADES FROM THE LOS ALPES NEIGHBORHOOD TO THE HEART OF SOYAPANGO. THE ENEMY HAS SENT THE TREASURY POLICE'S LIBERTADOR BATTALION TO REINFORCE POSITIONS NEAR THE PRADOS DE VENECIA NEIGHBORHOOD.

DURING THE FIGHTING, THE ENEMY SUSTAINED SEVERAL CASUALTIES; A SUBSERGEANT WAS KILLED. THE GUERRILLA UNITS ARE MAINTAINING CONTROL OF THE BOSQUES DEL RIO NEIGHBORHOOD, AND IN SAN JOSE, LOS ANGELES, UNICENTRO, LOS CONACASTES AREAS, AND EL PEPETO NEIGHBORHOOD. IN THESE AREAS, OUR FORCES INFLICTED 50 CASUALTIES ON THE FASCIST ARMY, INCLUDING A FULL SECTION OF THE PARATROOPERS BATTALION. EARLIER, WE REPORTED THAT A HUGHES-500 HELICOPTER WAS DAMAGED.

ANOTHER REPORT FROM NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR INDICATES THAT GUERRILLA UNITS THAT ENTERED APOPA, 12 KMS FROM SAN SALVADOR, TOOK CONTROL OF THE TICAL 1 AND 2, NUEVO APOPA, SAN ANDRES, LA CRUCITA, MADRE TIERRA, AND SIERRA NUESTRA NEIGHBORHOODS. IN THIS SECTOR, FIVE CASUALTIES WERE INFLICTED ON THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE'S LIBERTAD BATTALION AND THREE CASAULTIES ON THE NATIONAL GUARD. FIGHTING IS RAGING AT THE CENTER OF APOPA AND FIVE MORE CASUALTIES WERE INFLICTED ON THE PARATROOPERS BATTALION IN THE SAN JOSE 2 NEIGHBHORHOOD IN SOYAPANGO. ONE UH-1H HELICOPTER WAS SEVERLY DAMAGED IN THIS SECTOR. THIS IS A LAST MINUTE REPORT THAT HAS REACHED RADIO VENCEREMOS.

DEV-MUC3-0699 (GE)

CLANDESTINE, 12 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] RADIO VENCEREMOS NOW ANNOUNCES TO OUR PEOPLE, AS WELL AS TO THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL PRESS, WAR REPORT NO. 1 ON OUR NATIONAL MILITARY MANUEVER.

AT 2000 ON 11 NOVEMBER [0200 GMT ON 12 NOVEMBER], THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL FRONT] LAUNCHED THE MILITARY - POLITICAL PLAN DRAFTED BY THE GENERAL COMMAND CONSISTING OF A NATIONAL MILITARY MANEUVER CALLED: "OUT WITH THE FASCISTS! FEBE ELIZABETH LIVES!" THE PLAN BEGAN WITH AN ATTACK FROM AT LEAST 50 DIRECTIONS ON THE ENEMY POSITIONS IN THE CITY OF SAN SALVADOR. SINCE THAT TIME, OUR UNITS HAVE BEEN WAGING FIERCE COMBAT WITH THE ENEMY FORCES, OCCUPYING POSITIONS IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE CITY THAT WE ARE STILL HOLDING.

OTHER GROUPS LATER JOINED THE MANEUVER AND ATTACKED IN THE CITIES OF SAN MIGUEL, ZACATECOLUCA, USULUTAN, SANTA ANA, CHALATENANGO, AND THE COMALAPA INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT. THERE WERE ALSO DOZENS OF ATTACKS AGAINST POSITIONS IN TOWNS AND HIGHWAYS OF THE COUNTRY.

AFTER 18 HOURS OF COMBAT, THE FOLLOWING ARE THE ESTIMATED RESULTS: OVER 400 CASUALTIES ON THE ARMED FORCES, INCLUDING KILLED AND WOUNDED; 12 ARMORED VEHICLES HAVE BEEN DESTROYED; 3 HELICOPTERS AND 1 OR 2 SMALL SMALL AIRPLANES WERE DESTROYED ON THE GROUND; AND 2 HELICOPTERS WERE DOWNED; TENS OF THOUSANDS OF CARTRIDGES, OVER 50 RIFLES, MACHINEGUNS, AND OTHER TYPES OF WEAPONS HAVE BEEN RECOVERED.

THESE RESULTS GREATLY EXCEED THE EXPECTATIONS OF THIS MANEUVER DUE TO THE IMPACT AND EFFECTIVENESS OF THE FIGHTING. OUR FIGHTERS HAVE FULFILLED THIS PART OF THE PLAN IN A DARING, COURAGEOUS, AND EFFECTIVE MANNER, PROVING THEIR HIGH COMBAT MORALE. NOW THEY MUST HOLD THE POSITIONS THEY HAVE TAKEN, THUS GUARANTEEING THAT THE GOALS OF THE PLAN ARE ACHIEVED.

WE DENOUNCE THE INDISCRIMINATE BOMBING BY THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE. WE CALL ON THE PEOPLE TO PROTECT THEMSELVES FROM THE BOMBING. TO DO THIS, THE PEOPLE ARE COUNTING ON SUPPORT AND GUIDANCE FROM OUR FIGHTERS. WE ALSO CALL ON THE COUNTRY'S CIVILIAN POPULATION TO JOIN THOSE WHO HAVE ALREADY JOINED THE COMBAT OR ARE HELPING OUR FORCES. WE CALL ON THE SOLDIERS AND OFFICERS FORCED TO FIGHT AGAINST THEIR OWN PEOPLE TO SUSPEND THE BOMBING, TO REFUSE TO CARRY OUT A GENOCIDAL ACTION, AND TO DESERT AND JOIN OUR FORCES. WE URGE INTERNATIONAL HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS AND RELIEF GROUPS TO HELP PROTECT CIVILIANS WHO ARE BEING HARASSED BY THE ARMY OR WHO ARE IN ANY OTHER EMERGENCY SITUATION.

OUT WITH THE FASCISTS! FEBE ELIZABETH VELASQUEZ LIVES!

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND, EL SALVADOR, 12 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0700 (GE)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 OCT 89 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] COLONEL FRANCISCO ELENA FUENTES, COMMANDER OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, TODAY REFUTED THE CHARGES RAISED BY THE NONGOVERNMENTAL HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION THAT HIS BRIGADE HAS DEATH SQUADS AND CLANDESTINE JAILS.

THE CHARGE, WHICH WAS RAISED ON 13 OCTOBER BY THE NONGOVERNMENTAL HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION, LINKS THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE WITH THE DEATH SQUADS. THE COMMISSION PRESENTED THE TESTIMONY OF CESAR VIELMAN JOYA MARTINEZ, A FORMER SOLDIER IN THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, WHO DESCRIBED IN A VIDEO REPORT FILMED IN MEXICO HOW THE CLANDESTINE STRUCTURES IN THAT MILITARY GARRISON OPERATE. ACCORDING TO JOYA, THESE CLANDESTINE STRUCTURES ARE DIRECTED BY HIGH-RANKING OFFICERS WHO KIDNAP, MURDER AND CAUSE THE DISAPPERANCE OF LABOR UNION MEMBERS. AFTER DENYING ALL CHARGES AGAINST HIM AND HIS GARRISON, COL ELENA SAID THAT JOYA INDEED SERVED IN THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE; THAT HE DESERTED WHEN HE WAS PLACED UNDER INVESTIGATION FOR OVERRIDING HIS AUTHORITY; AND THAT IT WAS PROVED LATER THAT ON 5 JULY, AT TRES CEIBAS CANTON, IN APOPA, HE MURDERED A PEASANT AND TORTURED ANOTHER ONE WHO DIED LATER AT ROSALES HOSPITAL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ELENA] THIS MAN IS A MURDERER, DESERTER, AND THIEF. IMMEDIATELY AFTER WE LEARNED ABOUT THE ABUSES OF AUTHORITY HE COMMITTED AT THE 1ST BRIGADE, WE PLACED HIM UNDER INVESTIGATION. HE FLED FROM THE GARRISON WHEN HE REALIZED THAT THE HIGH COMMAND HAD ORDERED THE INVESTIGATION.

I WISH TO STATE THAT THERE IS NO GROUP OF DEATH SQUADS AS WAS STATED IN A CERTAIN NEWSCAST BECAUSE WE ARE PROFESSIONALS AND DO NOT HAVE THESE KINDS OF FORCES, WHICH WE MIGHT CALL OBSCURE. WE ACT ACCORDING TO LAW. THIS IS WHAT I CAN TELL YOU.

I ALSO WISH TO STATE THAT I HAVE HERE IN MY HANDS A RECORD THAT WAS BUILT SINCE THE FIRST DAY THIS INDIVIDUAL COMMITTED THE ABUSES OF AUTHORITY. HE WAS TAKEN TO AN OPERATION IN THE NEJAPA AREA WHERE HE CAPTURED EIGHT PEOPLE AND MURDERED ONE. HE THEN TOOK THEM TO THE 1ST BRIGADE AND ONE OF THEM WAS SEVERLY BEATEN. [END RECORDING]

THE NATIONAL GUARD IS IN CHARGE OF INVESTIGATING THESE MURDERS AND THE CASE IS AT THE 1ST PEACE COURT, ACCORDING TO COL ELENA. THE DESERTER WAS RECRUITED DURING FEBRUARY 1989, COMMITTED THE MURDERS ON 5 JULY, AND DESERTED FROM THE 1ST BRIGADE IN AUGUST. BASED ON THE VIDEO REPORT, HE MAY BE LIVING IN MEXICO, FROM WHICH -- IT WAS HINTED -- THE FORMER SOLDIER'S EXTRADITION MAY BE REQUESTED.

FINALLY, COL ELENA DENIED THAT ANY CLANDESTINE JAILS HAVE EVER EXISTED IN HIS MILITARY GARRISON. HE ALSO DENIED THAT A FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] WOMAN LEADER BY THE LAST NAME OF CHAN CHANG IS BEING HELD PRISONER THERE.

DEV-MUC3-0701 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 12 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE RECEIVED A LAST MINUTE REPORT FROM SAN MIGUEL. WE HAVE BEEN INFORMED THAT, PAY SPECIAL ATTENTION, DURING CLASHES WITH THE ENEMY IN LA ESMERALDA NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN MIGUEL, OUR REBEL ARMY CONFISCATED THREE 22-MM RIFLES, TWO .38-CAL PISTOLS, ONE 22-MM PISTOL, AND ONE CZECH PISTOL. ON 6TH EAST STREET OF THE CITY, AN ENEMY OFFICER AND A SERGEANT WERE KILLED AND TWO SOLDIERS WERE CAPTURED. WE REPEAT, TWO SOLDIERS WERE CAPTURED AT 6TH EAST STREET IN SAN MIGUEL. ONE OF THE SOLDIERS SURRENDERED TO THE PEOPLE BECAUSE HE WAS WOUNDED. THERE IS A MARKED DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THE ENEMY AND OUR GUERRILLA ARMY. WHEN FASCIST TROOPS CAPTURE WOUNDED REBELS IN SAN SALVADOR, THEY QUESTION THEM FIRST AT THE NATIONAL GUARD AND 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE HEADQUARTERS AND THEN MURDER THEM. OUR ARMY RESPECTS THE GENEVA AGREEMENTS.

WE CONTINUE OUR SAN MIGUEL REPORTING. AT 1030 TODAY, WE DESTROYED A LIGHT TANK ON 6TH NORTH AVENUE THEREBY INCREASING THE NUMBER OF LIGHT TANKS THAT WE HAVE DESTROYED ALL OVER THE COUNTRY. OTHER REPORTS THAT HAVE BEEN RECEIVED BY RADIO VENCEREMOS INDICATE THAT THE TOTAL NUMBER OF CASUALTIES IN ZACATECOLUCA AS OF 1618, IS 45, INCLUDING TWO SECTION CHIEFS. HEAVY FIGHTING CONTINUES IN ZACATECOLUCA NEIBORHOODS. IN SOYAPANGO, WHERE WE HAD RECEIVED A REPORT OF 50 CASUALTIES, WE HAVE NOW BEEN INFORMED THAT THE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES INFLICTED ON THE ENEMY HAS INCREASED TO 70. WE HAVE INFLICTED 70 CASUALTIES ON AIR FORCE COMMANDER GENERAL JUAN RAFAEL BUSTILLO'S CRIMINAL AIR FORCE. THIS NUMBER INCLUDES AN OFFICER. WE HAVE INFLICTED 10 CASUALTIES ON THE TREASURY POLICE FORCES. WE HAVE RECEIVED REPORTS THAT 3 HELICOPTERS WERE DAMAGED IN SOYAPANGO WHERE CLASHES HAVE ENSUED AND CONTINUE AT 1619. REPORTS FROM SAN SALVADOR AND SAN MIGUEL INDICATE THAT AT THIS TIME CLASHES ARE INCREASING IN INTENSITY IN BOTH PLACES. A FEW MINUTES AGO, WE RECEIVED A REPORT FROM SAN MIGUEL THAT OUR COMRADES WERE IN GOOD SPIRITS AND FORCING THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS TO WITHDRAW.

DEV-MUC3-0702 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] A GUERRILLA MEMBER DIED ON SATURDAY 11 NOVEMBER WHILE ATTACKING THE RESIDENCE OF LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY VICE PRESIDENT ROBERTO ANGULO, WHO ESCAPED THE ATTACK UNHARMED.

ACCORDING TO WITNESSES, URBAN GUERRILLA MEMBERS ENTERED THE RIGHT-WING NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) LEADER'S RESIDENCE WHERE SEVERAL SHOTS WERE FIRED, BUT THERE ARE NO OFFICIAL REPORTS ON THE CASUALTIES.

THE RESIDENCE IS LOCATED IN CAMPESTRE NEIGHBORHOOD, WHICH IS LOCATED IN NORTHWESTERN SAN SALVADOR, CLOSE TO SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S RESIDENCE AND THE PRESIDENTIAL HOUSE, WHICH WERE ALSO ATTACKED LAST EVENING.

ARMED FORCES CHIEF OF STAFF COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE CONFIRMED THE ATTACK ON CRISTIANI'S RESIDENCE, BUT THE PRESIDENT ESCAPED UNHARMED AND IS IN A SAFE PLACE.

ANGULO'S NEIGHBORS SAID THAT THE DEPUTY WAS NOT INJURED BECAUSE HE MANAGED TO ESCAPE TO A NEIGHBOR'S HOUSE, FROM WHERE SEVERAL PEOPLE OPENED FIRE AGAINST THE REBELS.

ONE OF THE ATTACKING GUERRILLAS DIED IN FRONT OF ANGULO'S RESIDENCE AND HIS BODY WAS FOUND THIS MORNING.

CONGRESS PRESIDENT RICARDO ALVARENGA VALDIVIESO'S HOUSE WHICH IS LOCATED IN MIRAMONTE NEIGHBORHOOD IN WESTERN SAN SALVADOR WAS ALSO ATTACKED.

THE REBELS ALSO ATTACKED THE "GENERAL ARCE" NEIGHBORHOOD, A MILITARY HOUSING COMPLEX, AS WELL AS THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE HEADQUARTERS AND THE NATIONAL POLICE HEADQUARTERS IN "ZACAMIL," ONE OF THE MOST DENSELY-POPULATED NEIGHBORHOODS IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0703 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] GOOD AFTERNOON, SALVADORAN PEOPLE. ON 19 MARCH, OUR GOVERNMENT WAS ELECTED BY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO DEMANDED POLITICAL STABILITY, PEACEFUL COEXISTENCE, AS WELL AS JUDICIAL AND SOCIAL SECURITY IN OUR COUNTRY. THESE IRRATIONAL ACTIONS THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HAS UNLEASHED IN THE LAST FEW DAYS, AND PARTICULARLY AS OF YESTERDAY, MAKE IT NECESSARY FOR THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC TO TAKE ACTION, TO TAKE FIRM ACTION WITHIN THE LEGAL FRAMEWORK OF OUR COUNTRY.

WE MUST ACCEPT THE PEOPLE'S MANDATE OF 19 MARCH, AND THE GOVERNMENT MUST NOW RESPOND WITH FIRM ACTION, WITHIN THE LEGAL FRAMEWORK. WE MUST RESPOND BECAUSE THE FMLN IS ATTACKING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION -- MORE THAN ANYONE ELSE -- IN A BRUTAL AND SAVAGE MANNER. THE ARMED FORCES OF EL SALVADOR ARE CONTROLLING THE SITUATION, AND THEY HAVE CONTROLLED THE SITUATION.

HOWEVER, THESE FMLN TERRORISTS, WHO ALREADY FEEL THEY HAVE BEEN DEFEATED BY THE ARMED FORCES, ARE NOW BEGINNING TO CARRY OUT INDISCRIMINATE ACTS OF TERRORISM. THEY ARE EVEN GOING AS FAR AS ENTERING INNOCENT HOMES TO PRESSURE FAMILIES WHO ARE TRYING TO LIVE THROUGH THESE HARSH TIMES THAT ALL SALVADORANS HAVE EXPERIENCED.

THAT IS WHY WE MUST ACT FIRMLY BUT WITHIN THE LAW. TO THIS EFFECT, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS MET AT 1400 IN THE PRESIDENTIAL HOUSE TO TRY TO SOLVE SOMETHING WE ARE COMPLETELY SURE IS WHAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WANT. WHEN WE SAT DOWN TO TALK WITH THE MEMBERS OF THE CABINET, WE RECALLED ARTICLE 2 OF OUR CONSTITUTION, WHICH SAYS: ALL PERSONS HAVE A RIGHT TO LIFE, PHYSICAL AND MORAL INTEGRITY, FREEDOM, SECURITY, WORK, PROPERTY, AND THE RIGHT TO BE PROTECTED AND HAVE THEIR LIVES AND POSSESSIONS DEFENDED.

THAT IS WHY THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS THIS AFTERNOON MADE A DECISION, BASED ON THE LEGAL MECHANISMS GRANTED TO IT BY THE CONSTITUTION. FIRST, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, I WILL READ ARTICLE 29 OF THE CONSTITUTION, WHICH READS AS FOLLOWS:

ARTICLE 29. IN CASES OF WAR, INVASION OF THE TERRITORY, REBELLION, SEDITION, CATASTROPHE, EPIDEMIC, OR OTHER GENERAL CALAMITY, OR IN CASES OF GRAVE DISRUPTION OF THE PUBLIC ORDER, THE GUARANTEES ESTALISHED IN ARTICLES 5, ARTICLE 6, SUBPARAGRAPH 1, ARTICLE 7, SUBPARAGRAPH 1, AND ARTICLE 24 CAN BE SUSPENDED, EXCEPT WHEN REFERRING TO MEETINGS OR GROUPS FOR RELIGIOUS, CULTURAL, ECONOMIC, AND SPORTS PURPOSES. THE SUSPENSION CAN AFFECT THE ENTIRE COUNTRY OR PART OF IT AND WILL BE DONE THROUGH A DECREE ISSUED BY THE LEGISLATIVE BRANCH OR THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH, AS APPROPRIATE. THE GUARANTEES CONTAINED IN ARTICLE 12, SUBPARAGRAPH 2, AND IN ARTICLE 13, SUBPARAGRAPH 2, OF THE CONSTITUTION CAN BE SUSPENDED, WHEN THE LEGISLATIVE BRANCH SO DECIDES BY A THREE-FOURTHS MAJORITY VOTE OF THE ELECTED DEPUTIES, BUT THE ADMINISTRATIVE SUSPENSION DETENCION ADMINISTRATIVA SHOULD NOT BE LONGER THAN 15 DAYS.

THE SUSPENSION OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL GUARANTEES WILL NOT EXCEED 30 DAYS. ONCE THIS PERIOD EXPIRES, THE SUSPENSION CAN BE EXTENDED FOR A SIMILAR PERIOD OF TIME, THROUGH A NEW DECREE, IF THE CIRCUMSTANCES THAT LED TO IT CONTINUE. IF THAT DECREE IS NOT ISSUED, THE SUSPENDED GUARANTEES WILL BE FULLY RESTORED.

AS YOU WILL SEE, THIS ARTICLE STATES THAT IT IS THE LEGISLATIVE BRANCH OR THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH, AS APPROPRIATE... [CHANGES THOUGHT] FOR THAT PURPOSE WE ACT BASED ON ARTICLE 167, NO. 6, WHICH READS: IT IS UP TO THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS TO SUSPEND AND RESTORE THE CONSTITUTIONAL GUARANTEES MENTIONED IN ARTICLE 29 OF THIS CONSTITUTION IF THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY IS NOT IN SESSION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0704 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] IN THE FIRST CASE, THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS WILL IMMEDIATELY NOTIFY THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY'S DIRECTORATE BOARD OF THE REASONS FOR SUCH A MEASURE AND THE ACTIONS THAT WERE CARRIED OUT IN REGARD TO THE MEASURE.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE JUDICIAL NORMS STATED IN OUR CONSTITUTION, TODAY THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS HAS DECIDED TO DECLARE A STATE OF SEIGE AS A MEASURE TO PROTECT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO ARE BEING UNJUSTLY ATTACKED BY THE IRRATIONALITY AND SAVAGERY OF THE FMLN'S TERRORISM, WHICH THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC CANNOT AND MUST NOT ALLOW. TOMORROW WE WILL SUBMIT TO THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY'S DIRECTORATE BOARD THE MINUTES OF THE MEETING IN WHICH THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS TODAY DECIDED TO SUSPEND THE CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS STATED IN ARTICLE 29 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF THE REPUBLIC.

IN THIS REGARD, WE WISH TO ISSUE AN APPEAL TO THE POLITICAL PARTIES. THIS IS NOT THE TIME TO REMAIN DOUBTFUL. NOW IS THE TIME FOR ALL THOSE WHO INTEND TO WORK WITHIN A DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM TO STATE -- IN A CATEGORICAL MANNER -- THAT THEY ABIDE BY AND SUPPORT THE REPUBLIC'S INSTITUTIONS AND THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS THAT ALLOWS THEM TO WORK AND PEACEFULLY WAGE A STRUGGLE TO ATTAIN POWER. WE CAN NO LONGER ALLOW POLITICAL PARTIES TO QUESTION WHETHER OR NOT THE FMLN IS OR IS NOT TRYING TO DO AWAY WITH THE RIGHTS THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAVE DEMANDED TIME AND AGAIN IN A DEMOCRATIC WAY.

WE ALSO URGE THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS TO TELL THEIR RESPECTIVE PEOPLES AND GOVERNMENTS OF THE TRUE NATURE OF THE FMLN AND HOW IT WANTS TO SUBJUGATE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

THEY MUST ALSO LISTEN AND CONDEMN DANIEL ORTEGA FOR WHAT HE HAS BEEN SAYING THESE DAYS. HE SHOULD BE CONDEMNED BECAUSE HE HAS BEEN TRYING TO CONFUSE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY BY SAYING THAT IN EL SALVADOR THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN CARRYING OUT INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS. HOWEVER, EVERYBODY HERE KNOWS THAT THE FMLN HAS BEEN PLANTING BOMBS, AND SO FAR 8 CIVILIANS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND MORE THAN 100 HAVE BEEN WOUNDED AS A RESULT OF THAT INDISCRIMINATE TERRORISM.

IT IS NECESSARY TO CONDEMN ORTEGA AND MAKE HIM RESPONSIBLE FOR SENDING THE WEAPONS USED TO KILL AND TO BLEED THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO DEATH. HE SHOULD NO LONGER BE ALLOWED TO CONTINUE THESE ACTIONS WHILE TRYING TO HIDE THEM AND TO DECEIVE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY.

IT IS ALSO TIME TO OPENLY CONDEMN THE FMLN FOR ITS IRRATIONAL ACTIONS. EVERYBODY KNOWS THAT SINCE THE 1ST DAY OF THIS ADMINISTRATION, THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OFFERED TO BEGIN A DIALOGUE PROCESS. IT OFFERED TO SOLVE THIS PROBLEM THROUGH RATIONAL AND PEACEFUL MEANS, SINCE THAT IS WHAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WANTED AND THAT IS WHAT THEY DEMANDED ON 19 MARCH ELECTION DAY.

WE CAN NO LONGER ALLOW THE FMLN LEADERS TO TRAVEL FREELY THROUGHOUT THE WORLD IN AN ATTEMPT TO DISINFORM THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, WHICH INSTEAD OF FALLING INTO THE TRAP OF DISINFORMATION SHOULD CATEGORICALLY CONDEMN THE FMLN'S IRRATIONAL ACTIONS [WORDS INDISTINCT].

WE ARE NOT ISSUING THIS CALL TO THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS ON BEHALF OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. WE ARE MAKING THIS CALL ON BEHALF OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO ARE SUBJECT TO THE SAVAGERY OF INDISCRIMINATE TERRORISM. WE ISSUE THIS CALL BECAUSE WE BELIEVE AND WE ARE CONVINCED THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE DO NOT DESERVE THIS FATE. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE DO NOT DESERVE TO BE ATTACKED WITH TERRORIST BOMBS. THEY SHOULD NOT BE FACING THE THREATS THE FMLN IS TRYING TO CARRY OUT. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAVE SHOWN THE WORLD DURING THESE LONG 10 YEARS THAT THEY WANT PEACE, DEMOCRACY, PROGRESS, AND DO NOT WANT TO LIVE UNDER SYSTEMS THAT ARE ALREADY OBSOLETE IN HISTORY, THAT ARE NO LONGER JUSTIFIED OR ACCEPTED AT THIS TIME WHEN THE WORLD IS EVOLVING TOWARD PEACE AND DEMOCRACY.

ON BEHALF OF THE PEOPLE, WE ARE ASKING YOU TO CONDEMN THE FMLN'S IRRATIONAL ATTITUDE.

WE ALSO WANT TO TELL THE FMLN THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE SUPPORTING THEIR PEOPLE AND WILL NEVER PERMIT TERRORIST ACTIONS TO LEAD TO ANYTHING ELSE BUT THE DESTRUCTION OF THAT MOVEMENT THAT HAS TAINTED OUR HISTORY. WE WANT THEM TO KNOW THAT THE WAY TO SOLVE PROBLEMS IN EL SALVADOR IS THROUGH REASONING AND PEACEFUL MEANS AND THAT THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC WILL CONTINUE TRYING TO ACHIEVE PEACE AS SOON AS POSSIBLE AND WITHIN THAT FRAMEWORK: THROUGH REASONING AND PEACEFUL MEANS.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AGAIN WE URGE YOU TO REMAIN CALM. THE ARMED FORCES ARE CONTROLLING THE SITUATION. WE WILL SOON LIVE NORMAL LIVES AGAIN. HOWEVER, AT THIS TIME WE ASK ALL OF YOU TO SUPPORT THE PEACE PROCESS, TO JOIN FORCES IN ORDER TO ACHIEVE PEACE. THE FMLN SHOULD FEEL THE PEOPLE'S PRESSURE AGAINST ITS IRRATIONAL ACTIONS.

WE ARE SURE THAT WITH YOU -- THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, ARMED FORCES, AND GOVERNMENT -- WE WILL ACHIEVE PEACE IN EL SALVADOR. GOD BLESS YOU ALL.

DEV-MUC3-0705 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS] [TEXT] [LARIOS, IN PROGRESS] ....PRINCIPLES AND EXPLANATIONS GIVEN BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND COMMANDER GENERAL OF THE ARMED FORCES AND IN COMPLIANCE WITH THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS' MANDATE, THE ARMED FORCES HEREBY ANNOUNCE THE PROCEDURES FOR THE CURFEW AS A RESULT OF THE SUSPENSION OF THE CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS.

THE CURFEW ESSENTIALLY SEEKS TO PREVENT ANY ABUSE OR DISRESPECT OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S DIGNITY AND PHYSICAL WELFARE, RESULTING FROM THE MARXIST-LENINIST TERRORISTS' AGGRESSION. NOTING THIS AND SEEKING TO STRICTLY ENFORCE THE CURFEW, THE FOLLOWING MEASURES ARE ESTABLISHED:

1. THE CURFEW WILL BE IN EFFECT BASED ON THE FOLLOWING SCHEDULE: FROM 2000 ON 12 NOVEMBER UNTIL 0600 ON 13 NOVEMBER, AND FROM 1800 TO 0600 STARTING ON 13 NOVEMBER UNTIL NOTIFIED OTHERWISE. ALSO, THE CURFEW'S SCHEDULE RESTRICTS ALL VEHICLE AND PEDESTRIAN MOVEMENT NATIONWIDE. THE FOLLOWING ARE EXEMPT FROM THE MEASURE: MILITARY VEHICLES; VEHICLES BELONGING TO NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS SUCH AS THE SALVADORAN RED CROSS, GREEN CROSS, INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS, AND HOSPITAL AMBULANCES WHICH WILL ATTEND ONLY EMERGENCY CASES. AN AUTHORIZATION WILL BE ISSUED BY THE CORRESPONDING DEPARTMENT COMMANDERS WHO WILL ACT AS THE GARRISON COMMANDERS JEFE DE PLAZA IN THE DEPARTMENT CAPITALS, EFFECTIVE TODAY, THEREBY ENABLING THESE ORGANIZATIONS TO CARRY OUT THEIR WORK IN STRICT COMPLIANCE WITH THE MEASURES.

THE SAME PROCEDURES WILL BE FOLLOWED IN THE MUNICIPALITIES WHERE THE AUTHORIZATION WILL BE GRANTED BY THE CORRESPONDING MILITARY AUTHORITY.

FURTHERMORE, COLONEL JUAN CARLOS CARRILLO SCHLENKER, DIRECTOR GENERAL OF THE NATIONAL GUARD, IS APPOINTED GARRISON COMMANDER IN SAN SALVADOR EFFECTIVE TODAY.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES SALUTE YOU WITH RESPECT AND ADMIRATION. WE URGE YOU TO CALL TELEPHONE NUMBER 123 IF YOU HAVE ANY QUESTIONS, AND WE WILL GLADLY ANSWER THEM. THANK YOU FOR YOUR ATTENTION.

DEV-MUC3-0710 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] FIGHTING HAS CONTINUED IN SAN MIGUEL. FORCES FROM THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE HAVE BEEN DISLODGED FROM THE URBINA BRIDGE AND MANY CASUALTIES WERE INFLICTED ON THEM THERE.

IN ADDITION, AS WE HAVE ALREADY REPORTED, A HELICOPTER WAS HIT AT THE 15 SEPTEMBER HOUSING DEVELOPMENT. IT WAS SHOT DOWN BY OUR ANTIAIRCRAFT FIRE AT THE 15 SEPTEMBER HOUSING DEVELOPMENT IN SAN MIGUEL AND FELL ON THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAY. LATER, ANOTHER HELICOPTER WAS DAMAGED IN SAN MIGUEL, WHERE HELICOPTER PILOTS DO NOT WANT TO LAND BECAUSE THEY ARE AFRAID OF OUR ANTIAIRCRAFT FIRE.

ACCORDING TO REPORTS, NATIONAL POLICE POSITIONS IN NUEVA CONCEPCION, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, HAVE BEEN ATTACKED. AT 0645, FIGHTING CONTINUES. THE MESS HALL, THE AMMUNITION WAREHOUSE, AND THE TRAINING FIELD HAVE BEEN AFFECTED. THE GARRISON OF THE NATIONAL POLICE HAS SUFFERED CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE.

FURTHER FIGHTING WAS REPORTED AT 0646 IN ZACATECOLUCA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT. OUR COMRADES IN ZACATECOLUCA REPORT THAT THE FIGHTING IS HEAVY. WE URGE THE PEOPLE TO ORGANIZE TO OBTAIN WATER AND FOOD. WE URGE THE PEOPLE TO ORGANIZE AND JOIN THE RANKS OF THE REVOLUTIONARY ARMY.

REPORTS ARE THAT THERE IS FIGHTING AT THIS MOMENT IN THE MONTSERRAT DISTRICT, NEAR CUSCATLAN STADIUM IN SAN SALVADOR. THE CAPITAL HAS NO POWER AND WATER IS BECOMING SCARCE.

WITH REGARD TO ELECTRICAL POWER, THE SITUATION IS THE SAME THROUGHOUT THE NATION'S TERRITORY. IN A NUTSHELL, THE HIGH COMMAND HAS COMPLETELY LOST CONTROL OF THE SITUATION. THERE IS NO ELECTRICITY IN MOST OF EL SALVADOR'S TERRITORY AND THERE IS NO TRANSPORTATION BECAUSE IT IS 100 PERCENT PARALYZED. FIGHTING IS TAKING PLACE IN DEPARTMENT CAPITALS AT THIS MOMENT, WHILE THE GUERRILLAS HAVE BEEN FIGHTING IN THE CAPITAL FOR 30 CONSECUTIVE HOURS. HOWEVER, THERE IS ONE IMPORTANT FACTOR NOW. OUR COMRADES' COMMAND ECHELONS, WHO ARE COMMUNICATING WITH US FROM THE CAPITAL'S DISTRICTS, ARE TELLING US THAT YOUTHS ARE MASSIVELY JOINING THE FORTIFICATION WORK -- DIGGING DITCHES, CARRYING FOOD AND AMMUNITION, AND HANDLING LIGHT ARTILLERY PIECES AND MACHINEGUNS; IN OTHER WORDS, ALL THAT IS NECESSARY TO FIGHT INSIDE THE CITIES AND IN THE SUBURBS. THEIR INCORPORATION IN ALL CITIES IS A VERY IMPORTANT FACTOR.

FOR THIS REASON, WE CALL ON YOUNG PEOPLE IN ALL DEPARTMENTAL CAPITALS TO LOOK FOR OUR FORCES, TO LOOK FOR OUR COMRADES, TO ORGANIZE IN EACH DISTRICT AND HOUSING DEVELOPMENT THE BRIGADES THAT WILL BE IN CHARGE OF THE FOOD SUPPLY, TO DIG MORE DITCHES, TO BUILD ANTIAIRCRAFT SHELTERS, AND TO SUPPLY INFORMATION, WHICH IS ABSOLUTELY IMPORTANT AT THIS MOMENT. WE MUST ORGANIZE THE INFORMATION NETWORK. WE MUST HAVE VIGILANCE IN EVERY CORNER IN EVERY DISTRICT AND NEIGHBORHOOD.

WE HAVE BEEN TOLD THAT EARLY TODAY THE ARMED FORCES CARRIED OUT A NUMBER OF SEARCHES AND ARRESTS IN THE CAPITAL. WELL, WE CALL ON THE POPULATION TO ORGANIZE AGAINST THE SEARCHES AND ARRESTS. ESTABLISH VIGILANCE. DO NOT LET THEM TAKE AWAY ANYBODY. ARM YOURSELVES -- TAKE OUT YOUR PISTOLS, MAKE MOLOTOV COCKTAILS WITH BOTTLES AND GASOLINE -- IN OTHER WORDS, DEFEND YOURSELVES.

AT 0704, IT WAS REPORTED TO US FROM SAN SALVADOR THAT FIGHTING IS TAKING PLACE IN EL CARMEN AGAINST THE NATIONAL POLICE. A NEW PLACE HAS BEEN ADDED TO THOSE IN WHICH MILITARY ACTIVITY IS TAKING PLACE.

MEANWHILE, OTHER REPORTS INDICATE THAT FMLN SNIPERS ARE HARASSING THE ARMY'S MOVEMENTS IN VARIOUS PLACES IN THE CAPITAL. THE REPORT SAYS THAT OUR SNIPERS POSTED IN THE TALLEST BUILDINGS ARE EFFECTIVELY KEEPING THE ARMY PATROLS AND MOVEMENTS AT BAY. THE ARMY IS BEGINNING TO HAVE TROUBLE EVACUATING ITS WOUNDED, BECAUSE IN THE CAPITAL EPISODES ARE NOW TAKING PLACE WHICH HAD BEEN ONLY SEEN IN MORAZAN BEFORE; THAT IS, HELICOPTERS FLYING IN TO PICK UP THE WOUNDED, AS THEY DID IN THE VALLEYS AND THE PLAINS. THIS IS HAPPENING NOW IN THE CAPITAL BECAUSE THE ARMY TROOPS CANNOT ADVANCE INTO CERTAIN AREAS TO PICK UP THEIR DEAD AND WOUNDED, WHO ARE VERY, VERY NUMEROUS. THE HELICOPTERS NOW HAVE TO LAND IN SOCCER FIELDS AND IN OTHER PLACES TO EVACUATE THE WOUNDED. SUCH IS THE SITUATION IN SAN SALVADOR. AS WE HAVE ALREADY REPORTED, FIGHTING CONTINUES IN VARIOUS PLACES IN THE CAPITAL, WHERE THERE ARE FMLN-CONTROLLED AREAS.

DEV-MUC3-0711 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO CIVILIAN EYEWITNESSES, SALVADORAN ARMY TROOPS BOMBED THE UNIVERSITY'S SCHOOL OF MEDICINE.

THE SAME SOURCES REPORTED THAT SOLDIERS OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE CAPTURED AND BLINDFOLDED 10 UNIVERSITY GUARDS YESTERDAY AND THEN TOOK THEM OFF THE CAMPUS.

ACCORDING TO THESE EYEWITNESSES, ARMY TROOPS ENTERED THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR USING AN ARMORED VEHICLE AND A 105-MM CANNON. THEY SAID THAT THE SCHOOL OF MEDICINE WAS BOMBED LATER ON. HOWEVER, OFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE NEITHER CONFIRMED NOR DENIED THIS REPORT.

THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES HAVE ACCUSED THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR OF BEING A GUERRILLA "SANCTUARY" AND HAVE SAID THAT THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE WAS ATTACKED FROM THE CAMPUS.

IN ADDITION, THESE EYEWITNESSES SAID THAT 10 UNIVERSITY "GUARDS" WERE CAPTURED ON CAMPUS, WHICH IS LOCATED NEAR THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE, ONE OF THE GARRISONS ATTACKED BY THE GUERRILLAS WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE REBEL OFFENSIVE BEGUN ON THE NIGHT OF 11 NOVEMBER.

ACCORDING TO THESE SOURCES, THE SOLDIERS SEIZED PROPAGANDA MATERIAL.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) BEGAN AN OFFENSIVE ON 11 NOVEMBER, WHICH HAS INCLUDED AN ATTACK ON THE HOMES OF IMPORTANT GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, INCLUDING THAT OF SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI.

ON THE SAME NIGHT, THE REBELS ALSO ATTACKED THE NATIONAL POLICE HEADQUARTERS IN ZACAMIL, ONE OF THE MOST POPULATED NEIGHBORHOODS IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR, AS WELL AS MILITARY POSITIONS IN A DOZEN RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS LOCATED IN VARIOUS SECTORS OF THIS CAPITAL. THE FIGHTING THEN SPREAD TO SANTA ANA, CABANAS, LA PAZ, SAN VICENTE, SAN MIGUEL, AND USULUTAN DEPARTMENTS IN THE COUNTRY'S NORTH, CENTRAL, AND EASTERN PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

THE REBEL OFFENSIVE HAS ALREADY RESULTED IN HUNDREDS OF CASUALTIES -- APPROXIMATELY 300 ACCORDING TO THE ARMY, AND 400 ACCORDING TO THE GUERRILLAS. THIS COMPELLED THE GOVERNMENT TO IMPOSE A STATE OF SIEGE AND A CURFEW THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

DEV-MUC3-0712 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] THIS IS A LAST MINUTE REPORT FROM THE CAPITAL. ATTENTION, OUR PEOPLE, AND ALSO OTHER FRATERNAL PEOPLES WHO ARE LISTENING TO US IN SEVERAL PARTS OF THE WORLD, ESPECIALLY IN LATIN AMERICA. ATTENTION. AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS ARE NOW BOMBING AND FIRING ROCKETS AT VARIOUS PARTS OF THE CAPITAL.

A HELICOPTER IS BOMBING A STRETCH OF THE NORTHERN TRUNK HIGHWAY NEAR CIUDAD DELGADO, AND THERE ARE CIVILIAN CASUALTIES AS A RESULT OF THIS CRIMINAL ACTION BY THE ARMY AND AIR FORCE. AT 0933 TODAY A HELICOPTER BOMBED HEAVILY POPULATED AREAS IN CIUDAD DELGADO.

AT 0900, MORE THAN 30 MINUTES AGO, A C-47 PLANE FITTED WITH .50-CALIBER MACHINEGUNS STRAFED DOWNTOWN MEJICANOS. MEANWHILE, AN A-37 PLANE, WHICH IS A FIGHTER-BOMBER PLANE KNOWN AS DRAGONFLY, FITTED WITH ROCKET LAUNCHERS AND 7.62-MM MACHINEGUNS AND CAPABLE OF DROPPING BOMBS OF 200, 500, AND EVEN 750 POUNDS, ALONG WITH A PUSH- PULL PLANE, ALSO FITTED WITH ROCKETS, BOMBED THE AREA NEAR THE MARIONA JAIL TO THE NORTH OF THE CAPITAL.

WE ARE DENOUNCING THESE CRIMINAL ACTIONS OF THE FASCIST REGIME HEADED BY ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND ROBERTO D'AUBUISSION IN THE CAPITAL. THESE BOMBINGS ARE UNPRECEDENTED IN SAN SALVADOR. IN PREVIOUS YEARS, WE HAVE DENOUNCED BOMBINGS IN RURAL AREAS. THE AERIAL DEATH SQUAD, HEADED BY THE GENOCIDAL JUAN RAFAEL BUSTILLOS SINCE THE WAR BEGAN, HAS CAUSED HUNDREDS OF DEATHS, INCLUDING MUTILATIONS AND INJURIES.

NOW, BEFORE THE VERY EYES OF THE INTERNATIONAL PRESS AND DIPLOMATS ACCREDITED IN SAN SALVADOR, AND A MILLION INHABITANTS IN THE CAPITAL, THE AIR FORCE IS BOMBING POOR NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE CAPITAL. WE ARE TOLD THAT A HELICOPTER HAS BEEN BOMBING THE NORTHERN TRUNK HIGHWAY IN CIUDAD DELGADO. THESE HELICOPTERS FITTED WITH ROCKETS ARE KNOWN AS UH-1H. THEY HAVE BEEN MODIFIED AND ARE FITTED WITH 7.62-MM MACHINEGUNS AND SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILES. THIS U.S.-MADE HELICOPTER HAS BEEN DROPPING ROCKETS ON THE NORTHERN TRUNK HIGHWAY IN CIUDAD DELGADO.

IN SUM, A C-47 PLANE MACHINEGUNNED DOWNTOWN MEJICANOS, AND AN A- 37 PLANE AND A PUSH-AND-PULL PLANE, WHICH IS ALSO KNOWN AS 0-2 PLANE, BOMBED THE MARIONA AREA.

A LAST MINUTE REPORT FROM THE CAPITAL AT 1541 GMT: OUR FORCES CONTINUE TO ADVANCE IN SAN SALVADOR. FMLN UNITS HAVE TAKEN CONTROL OF A PART OF THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, THE TRADITIONAL NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE THE OLIGARCHY WITH THE MOST WELL-KNOWN SURNAMES LIVES, A NEIGHBORHOOD WITH THE MOST LUXURIOUS MANSIONS AND THE LATEST MODEL CARS. OUR MEN HAVE TAKEN UP POSITIONS IN THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, EXACTLY ATOP THE SAN SALVADOR ARCHBISHOPRIC. OUR MEN REPORTED THAT AT 1530 THEY TOOK CONTROL OF A PART OF THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, IN THE WESTERN PART OF THE CAPITAL. THEY ARE ALSO MOVING IN TO TAKE UP POSITIONS AT THE PABLO ARNOLDO GUZMAN NATIONAL GEOGRAPHICAL INSTITUTE IN MEJICANOS. POSITIONS HAVE BECOME CONSOLIDATED IN THE NORTHERN PART OF THE CITY, AND CLASHES CONTINUE AROUND THE NATIONAL POLICE GARRISONS IN ZACAMIL AND CUSCATANCINGO.

DEV-MUC3-0713 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE REAFFIRM OUR APPEAL TO HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS, THE OAS, AND DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENTS, AND WE MAKE A SPECIAL CALL TO COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS, NOBEL PEACE PRIZE LAUREATE, TO CONTACT THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND THE HIGH COMMAND OF THE FASCIST ARMED FORCES TO PRESSURE THEM TO STOP THEIR BOMBINGS.

INTERNATIONAL JOURNALISTS HAVE ALREADY CONFIRMED THAT THESE BOMBINGS ARE TAKING PLACE IN DENSELY POPULATED AREAS OF THE CAPITAL. WE LEARNED THAT VIDEO REPORTS ARE ALREADY GOING AROUND THE WORLD SHOWING IMAGES OF THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD. THE BOMBINGS DESTROYED SOME BUILDINGS THERE AND SOME HOUSES IN OTHER AREAS OF THE CAPITAL. THERE ARE DOZENS OF CIVILIAN CASUALTIES.

THERE WERE INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS THIS MORNING IN SAN MIGUEL'S ESMERALDA NEIGHORHOOD AND IN OTHER NEIGHORHOODS. AT ABOUT 0900, A PLANE DROPPED A BOMB THAT HIT A CIVILIAN HOME IN SAN MIGUEL. A 12- YEAR-OLD GIRL WAS INJURED IN SOYAPANGO.

WE CALL ON DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENTS, THE UNITED NATIONS, AND THE OAS TO PRESSURE THE FASCIST GOVERNMENT TO STOP ITS BOMBINGS AGAINST THE PEOPLE, TO STOP THE INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS.

DEV-MUC3-0714 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [COLONEL MAURICIO VARGAS, COMMANDER OF THE 3RD INFANTRY BRIGADE] [TEXT] [VARGAS, IN PROGRESS] ...CARRY OUT THE PERTINENT AND NECESSARY ACTIONS AND THUS CONTRIBUTE TO THE STABILIZATION OF THE SITUATION SO THAT WE MAY AGAIN ENJOY THE SAFETY AND CALM CURRENTLY BEING AFFECTED BY TERRORIST RAIDS IN SOME AREAS AROUND SAN MIGUEL. WE AS AN INSTITUTION WILL GUARANTEE THAT IN THE NEXT 8 OR 10 HOURS THE PEACE YOU NEED WILL BE REGAINED. THIS IS A PROMISE WE ARE MAKING, AND WE WILL KEEP IT SO THAT YOU WILL REALLY HAVE THAT TRANQUILITY YOU NEED. HOWEVER, I MUST ASK THE PEOPLE WHO ARE OUT ON THE STREET TO PLEASE REFRAIN FROM DOING THIS. IF YOU ARE OUT ON THE STREET, PLEASE DO NOT RUN IF YOU SEE SOLDIERS. WALK IN THE MIDDLE OF THE STREET. YOU WILL NOT HAVE TROUBLE. WE DO NOT USE VIOLENCE. WE USE MILITARY CONTROL TECHNIQUES. WE DO NOT USE IRRATIONAL TERROR. WE USE STRICTLY MILITARY TECHNIQUES AND TACTICS.

WE ASK THAT YOU REFRAIN FROM GOING OUT IN THE NEXT 8 HOURS, OR AT LEAST STAY OFF THE STREETS. IF YOU MUST GO OUT, DO IT, BUT WALK IN THE MIDDLE OF THE STREET. DO NOT RUN, AND DO NOT FEAR THE AUTHORITIES. THE AUTHORITIES ARE THERE TO PROTECT YOUR SAFETY WHICH IS BEING AFFECTED. THE AUTHORITIES WISH TO GIVE YOU BACK YOUR TRANQUILITY. I WANT YOU TO REST ASSURED THAT WE WILL NOT FAIL YOU. BEFORE A MARXIST-LENINIST PLAN TAKES OVER ONE OF OUR CITIES OR TOWNS, THEY WILL HAVE TO WALK OVER THE BODIES OF EACH AND EVERY SOLDIER. THE SOLDIERS ARE WILLING TO DEFEND EACH AND EVERY ONE OF YOU.

THAT IS WHAT I WANTED TO TELL YOU. I JUST WANTED TO SEND YOU THIS MESSAGE OF FAITH, HOPE, AND TRUST IN YOUR GOVERNMENT AND YOUR INSTITUTION. THAT IS ESSENTIAL. WE MUST NOT YIELD WHEN CONFRONTED BY MARXIST OR COMMUNIST PLANS. OUR GOVERNMENT AND OUR ARMED FORCES NEED YOUR SUPPORT TODAY MORE THAN EVER. SUPPORT OUR STRUGGLE IN DEFENSE OF THE DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM. REST ASSURED THAT ALONG THIS PATH THERE IS NO RETURN. WE EITHER ACHIEVE OUR FINAL GOAL OF CONSOLIDATION, OR WE FALL ALONG THE PATH. WE MUST GIVE OUR FUTURE GENERATIONS A FREE AND DEMOCRATIC HOMELAND. IF YOU HAVE ANY QUESTIONS, I WILL BE MORE THAN GLAD TO ANSWER THEM; HOWEVER, THIS WAS THE MESSAGE I WANTED TO LEAVE WITH YOU.

DEV-MUC3-0715 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] IN FRONT OF US WE HAVE A MAP OF SAN SALVADOR, WHERE OUR COMRADES ARE BUILDING BARRICADES THROUGHOUT THE CITY. WE HAVE THE MAP OF SAN SALVADOR SHOWING THE NORTHERN PART OF THE CITY COVERED WITH LITTLE RED FLAGS. THESE ARE POINTS UNDER THE CONTROL OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. THESE ARE AREAS WHERE OUR FORCES ARE ATTACKING ARMY POSITIONS AND WHERE AMBUSHES HAVE BEEN SET. THERE ARE FLAGS POINTING TO AREAS WHERE AMBUSHES HAVE BEEN SET, AREAS FROM WHICH SOLDIERS HAVE BEEN DISLODGED, AND AREAS UNDER FMLN CONTROL.

IF WE LOOK AT THE NORTHERN PART OF THE CITY MAP WE CAN SEE LITTLE RED FLAGS IN THE AREA OF ZACAMIL, EL CARMEN NEIGHBORHOOD, EL CARMEN HILL AREA, UNIVERSITARIA NEIGHBORHOOD, MEJICANOS, EL PORVERNIR NEIGHBORHOOD, CIUDAD DELGADO, SAN SEBASTIAN NEIGHBORHOOD, GUADALCANAL NEIGHBORHOOD, CUSCATLAN AND LOMAS DE RIO NEIGHBORHOODS, AND ALL OF SOYAPANGO. FMLN FORCES ARE ALL OVER THE SOYAPANGO AREA.

RED AND WHITE FLAGS DENOTE FIRING LINES, AND THESE ARE FOUND IN CIUDAD CREDISA AND DOWNTOWN AMATEPEQUE. THE SAME RED AND WHITE FLAGS ALSO SHOW HOW OUR REVOLUTIONARY FORCES ARE ADVANCING. WE SEE THESE RED AND WHITE FLAGS IN ANTIGUO CUSCATLAN. LIKEWISE, IN SANTA TECLA OUR FORCES ARE MOBILIZING AND STRENGTHENING THEIR POSITIONS.

OUR LATEST REPORT STATES THAT IN DOWNTOWN SAN SALVADOR, ONLY 10 BLOCKS FROM THE PRESIDENTIAL PALACE, HUGE BARRICADES HAVE BEEN BUILT BY THE PEOPLE AND THE FMLN, THUS CONSOLIDATING OUR POSITION. THIS LATEST REPORT CONFIRMS THIS INFORMATION, AND WE ARE GOING TO STICK A LITTLE RED FLAG ONE, TWO, THREE, FOUR, FIVE, SIX, SEVEN, EIGHT, NINE, 10 BLOCKS FROM THE PRESIDENTIAL PALACE. THE LITTLE RED FLAG CAN NOW BE SEEN IN SAN JACINTO NEIGHBORHOOD.

DEV-MUC3-0716 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE VEHICLE OF MEXICAN TELEVISION NEWSMAN EPIGMENIO IBARRA WAS TOTALLY DESTROYED BY A POWERFUL BOMB TODAY, BUT IBARRA WAS NOT HURT.

IT IS NOT YET KNOWN WHO PLACED THE BOMB IN THE VEHICLE WHILE IBARRA WAS AWAY.

THE BOMB IN IBARRA'S VEHICLE EXPLODED TODAY IN AN AREA OF SAN SALVADOR WHERE HEAVY FIGHTING BETWEEN THE ARMY AND THE GUERRILLAS IS CURRENTLY UNDER WAY. ON SATURDAY THE GUERRILLAS LAUNCHED THE MOST POWERFUL OFFENSIVE IN THE PAST 8 YEARS.

THE BLOODY FIGHTING BETWEEN THE ARMY AND THE GUERRILLAS CONTINUES TODAY FOR THE THIRD CONSECUTIVE DAY, AND THERE HAVE BEEN APPROXIMATELY 400 CASUALTIES INCLUDING SOLDIERS, REBELS, AND CIVILIANS.

TODAY, MONDAY, SAN SALVADOR IS PRACTICALLY AT A STANDSTILL DUE TO THE FIGHTING AND THE "TRANSPORTATION STRIKE" CALLED BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, WHICH ON SATURDAY LAUNCHED ITS LARGEST MILITARY OFFENSIVE SINCE 1981.

ACCORDING TO THE ARMED FORCES, 127 PERSONS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND 240 WOUNDED SINCE THE FIGHTING BEGAN. FOR THEIR PART, THE GUERRILLAS CLAIM THAT THEY HAVE INFLICTED MORE THAN 400 CASUALTIES ON THE ARMY, BUT HAVE PROVIDED NO FIGURES ON LOSSES OR ON THE DEAD AND INJURED AMONG ITS RANKS.

DEV-MUC3-0717 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] A SPOKESMAN FOR THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) HAS REPORTED THAT, IN ADDITION TO 30 DEAD CIVILIANS, MORE THAN 200 SOLDIERS AND GUERRILLAS HAVE BEEN KILLED IN FIERCE CLASHES THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE AT NIGHT SINCE 11 NOVEMBER IN THE CAPITAL AND SEVERAL KEY SALVADORAN CITIES.

THE SOURCE ADDED THAT THERE COULD BE MORE THAN 300 WOUNDED CIVILIANS AND MILITARY MEN.

COPREFA STATED THAT 127 GUERRILLAS AND ABOUT 50 ARMY TROOPS WERE REPORTED DEAD EARLY THIS MORNING, BUT THE FIGURES ARE GROWING BECAUSE STRONG FIGHTING CONTINUES THROUGHOUT THE ENTIRE NORTHERN AREA OF THE CAPITAL AND THE COUNTRY'S EASTERN AREA.

THE ROSALES HOSPITAL, THE MAIN ONE IN THE CAPITAL, WAS ASSISTING MORE THAN 100 CIVILIANS WOUNDED IN THE INTENSE CLASHES THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE SINCE 11 NOVEMBER WHILE MEDICAL AUTHORITIES ARE CALLING ON DOCTORS AND NURSES TO HELP THE WOUNDED.

ANOTHER 100 WOUNDED WERE TAKEN TO THE SOCIAL SECURITY HOSPITAL AND ABOUT 100 MORE WERE TAKEN TO OTHER HOSPITALS IN THE CAPITAL AND COUNTRYSIDE.

MEANWHILE, THE SANTA TERESA HOSPITAL IN ZACATECOLUCA, 56 KM EAST OF THE CAPITAL, WAS OCCUPIED BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GUERRILLAS THIS MORNING. FIGHTING INTENSIFIED IN THE IMMEDIATE AREA THIS MORNING.

THERE WAS FIERCE FIGHTING IN ZACATECOLUCA TODAY AND ACCORDING TO PRESS REPORTS, 13 BODIES WERE SEEN ON THE STREETS; EIGHT GUERRILLAS, FOUR SOLDIERS, AND A CIVILIAN.

THE GUERRILLAS, WHO, CARRYING AK-47 RIFLES AND PISTOLS, HAVE ASKED FOR WATER AND FOOD IN SOME HOUSES, HAVE OCCUPIED FIVE NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN MIGUEL, THE THIRD MOST IMPORTANT CITY IN THE COUNTRY, 140 KM FROM THE CAPITAL. SAN MIGUEL AND ZACATECOLUCA HAVE NO ELECTRICITY OR WATER TODAY.

ACCORDING TO GUERRILLA SOURCES, SAN VICENTE AND USULUTAN, IN THE COUNTRY'S EAST-CENTRAL AREA, WERE SITES OF FIERCE FIGHTING THIS MORNING.

DEV-MUC3-0718 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] THIS IS A LAST MINUTE REPORT BROUGHT TO YOU THROUGH THE NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY NETWORK, RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI AND RADIO VENCEREMOS IN NETWORK BROADCASTING TO THE WHOLE COUNTRY. THIS LAST MINUTE REPORT STATES THAT THE AIR FORCE HAS BOMBED AND STRAFED THE AREA ACROSS FROM THE INCA FACTORY AND PRADOS DE VENECIA IN SOYAPANGO. AS A RESULT OF THIS BOMBING AND STRAFING ACTION 3 PERSONS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND 12 INJURED. IN PRADOS DE VENECIA HOUSES HAVE BEEN TOTALLY DESTROYED.

ATTENTION, WE CALL THIS INFORMATION TO THE ATTENTION OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS, AND INTERNATIONAL HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS. THE NUMBER OF VICTIMS AS A RESULT OF THE BOMBINGS IN SAN SALVADOR IS INCREASING. ACROSS FROM THE INCA FACTORY AND PRADOS DE VENECIA IN SOYAPANGO, THE AIR FORCE IS INDISCRIMINATELY BOMBING AND STRAFING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. ATTENTION, THE REPORT WE HAVE RECEIVED FROM SAN SALVADOR ADVISES US THAT 3 PERSONS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND 12 INJURED AND HOUSES DESTROYED IN PRADOS DE VENECIA AS A RESULT OF THE INDISCRIMINATE BOMBING BY THE AIR FORCE.

THE GENOCIDAL AND COWARDLY ATTITUDE OF THE AIR FORCE, BOMBING AREAS JUST LIKE ANASTASIO SOMOZA DID DURING THE LAST DAYS OF HIS DICTATORSHIP, IS SHOWING THE WORLD:

1. THE FASCIST NATURE OF ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S REGIME. THE FASCIST NATURE OF LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO THE 1966 GRADUATES OF CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMNY] HAS REMOVED THE CIVILIAN MASK OFF THE GOVERNMENT'S FACE AND SHOWN ITS REAL MILITARY AND FASCIST FACE.

2. THESE BOMBINGS PROVE THAT AS THE HOURS GO BY THEY BECOME MORE DESPERATE AND HAVE LOST TOTAL CONTROL OF THE SITUATION. THE PROMISES MADE BY CRISTIANI AND THE DEFENSE MINISTER THAT THEY WOULD GET THE SITUATION UNDER CONTROL ON SATURDAY HAS FAILED. ON SATURDAY NIGHT COLONEL [RENE] PONCE PROMISED TO BRING THE SITUATION UNDER CONTROL ON SATURDAY NIGHT, HOWEVER, MORE THAN 32 HOURS HAVE GONE BY AND THE ARMED FORCES AND THE HIGH COMMAND HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO STOP THE REVOLUTIONARY ADVANCE IN SAN SALVADOR, SAN MIGUEL, AND THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT'S [FMLN] MILITARY POSITIONS IN SAN SALVADOR ARE BEING CONSOLIDATED AFTER MORE THAT 32 HOURS OF UNINTERRUPTED FIGHTING. THE PLAN FOR THE DEFENSE OF SAN SALVADOR HAS FAILED. THE U.S. ADVISERS AND THE HIGH COMMAND HAVE BEEN PREPARING THIS PLAN FOR MONTHS. WE HEREBY ADVISE THE PEOPLE THAT THE PLAN FOR THE DEFENSE OF SAN SALVADOR HAS FAILED. THEY WERE NOT ABLE TO PREVENT OUR FORCES FROM ARMING AND GETTING SUPPLIES; THEY WERE NOT ABLE TO STOP OUR FMLN FORCES FROM ENTERING SAN SALVADOR, AND THEY HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO STOP OUR ADVANCE OR RECOVER A SINGLE INCH OF THE CITY OCCUPIED BY THE FMLN. WE CAN STATE THAT THE ARMED FORCES HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO WIN BACK A SINGLE INCH OF TERRITORY UNDER OUR CONTROL IN MEJICANOS, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, CUSCATANCINGO, ZACAMIL, UNIVERSITARIA NORTE, OR SOYAPANGA. THE ARMED FORCES HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO ADVANCE A SINGLE INCH. EVERY SINGLE STEP IN AN ATTEMPT TO WIN BACK THE NEIGHBORHOODS WE OCCUPY HAS COST THEM DEARLY IN DEAD AND WOUNDED.

DEV-MUC3-0719 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] REBEL GUERRILLA UNITS HAVE TAKEN CONTROL OF THE COASTAL RAILROAD LINES NEAR LA CASONA, JIQUILISCO JURISDICTION. THE REBELS HAVE SET UP BARRICADES AND HAVE COMPLETELY PARALYZED VEHICLE TRAFFIC. A RAILROAD BRIDGE BETWEEN TIERRA BLANCA AND JIQUILISCO HAS BEEN PARTIALLY DESTROYED WITH DYNAMITE. THE STRETCH BETWEEN SAN MARCOS LEMPA AND TIERRA BLANCA HAS BEEN CONTROLLED IN THE VICINITY OF THE 14 JULY NEIGHBORHOOD.

A REPORT FROM LA PAZ DEPARTMENT SAYS THAT AT 1145 [1745 GMT] TODAY A SOLDIER FROM THE ARMED FORCES ENGINEERS' MILITARY DETACHMENT [DMIFA] FIRED A RIFLE AT A CIVILIAN WOMAN, WOUNDING HER IN THE HEAD. THIS HAPPENED IN THE 27 SEPTEMBER NEIGHBORHOOD IN ZACATECOLUCA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT. DMIFA SOLDIERS CONTINUE TO INFLICT CASUALTIES AMONG THE CIVILIANS, AS A RESULT OF THEIR DESPERATION.

RADIO VENCEREMOS AND RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI IN A NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY NETWORK REPEAT THE REPORT THAT THE AIR FORCE IS STRAFFING THE INCA FACTORY IN SOYAPANGA AND PRADOS DE VENECIA, WHERE IT HAS KILLED 3 AND WOUNDED 12 CIVILIANS. HOMES HAVE BEEN TOTALLY DESTROYED IN PRADOS DE VENECIA AS A RESULT OF THE INDISCRIMINATE STRAFFING BY THE ARMED FORCES.

WE HAVE A REPORT FROM THE FELICIANO AMA WESTERN FRONT TO THE EFFECT THAT THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] IS HOLDING POSITIONS IN VILLA LOS NARANJOS AND LA UNION NEIGHBORHOOD IN SANTA ANA. REPORTS ADD THAT REVOLUTIONARY FIGHTING IS TAKING PLACE IN SANTA ANA, WHERE THE FMLN RED AND WHITE FLAG IS BEING HOISTED. GREETINGS TO THE FIGHTERS IN SANTA ANA CITY, AND FORWARD!

DEV-MUC3-0722 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 13 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] IS USING DISINFORMATION BECAUSE IT HAS BEEN BEATEN BY THE ARMED FORCES. THE FMLN TODAY RESORTED TO THE STRATEGY OF DISINFORMATION SINCE THEY HAVE BEEN DEFEATED BY OUR BRAVE AND PROFESSIONAL ARMED FORCES. IN A DESPERATE MANNER AND THROUGH THEIR CLANDESTINE RADIO STATION, THE FMLN IS BROADCASTING FALSE REPORTS, SUCH AS THE FOLLOWING. THEY SAID THEY WERE FIGHTING THE ARMED FORCES WITH THE PEOPLE'S SUPPORT THIS MORNING AND THAT THIS OCCURRED 10 BLOCKS FROM THE PRESIDENTIAL PALACE. THE FMLN INSISTED THAT CIVILIANS HAD HELPED THEM AT THE REBEL BARRICADES. THIS IS TOTALLY FALSE.

THE ARMED FORCES CONTINUE TO PROTECT THE CIVILIAN RESIDENTS OF SAN JACINTO NEIGHBORHOOD AND THE INVENTIONS BROADCAST BY THE FMLN ARE A STRATEGY TO CONFUSE PEOPLE. THE ARMED FORCES CALL ON ALL SALVADORANS NOT TO BE SURPRISED BY THESE STRATEGIES AND TO CONTINUE REPUDIATING THE TERRORIST CRIMINALS, WHO HAVE ONLY BROUGHT AGGRESSION, PAIN, AND GRIEF TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THE ARMED FORCES CONTROL THE ENTIRE NATIONAL TERRITORY, INCLUDING SAN SALVADOR. THE SHOTS THAT ARE HEARD OR WERE HEARD A FEW HOURS AGO ARE PART OF THE ARMED FORCES DEFENSE AGAINST INDISCRIMINATE FMLN ATTACKS ON THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

DEV-MUC3-0723 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [NATIONAL INFORMATION CENTER] [TEXT] 1. GIVEN THE STATE OF SIEGE THAT HAS PREVAILED IN THE COUNTRY SINCE 11 NOVEMBER, AND ACCORDING TO THE NATIONAL CONSTITUTION, THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IS REQUIRED TO COOPERATE WITH THE ARMED FORCES AND THE VARIOUS SECURITY CORPS WHEN NECESSARY -- MAKING SURE THIS COOPERATION INVOLVES ARMY MEMBERS OR DULY AUTHORIZED JUDICIAL OFFICIALS.

2. UPON LEARNING THAT ARMED TERRORISTS ARE OPERATING NEAR YOUR AREAS OF RESIDENCE, YOU MUST IMMEDIATELY CALL TELEPHONE NUMBER 123 OR NOTIFY THE NEAREST MILITARY POST.

3. THE POPULATION MUST REMAIN CALM AND GO TO WORK, WHILE AT THE SAME TIME MAKING SURE THAT YOU ARE IN YOUR RESPECTIVE RESIDENCES WHEN THE CURFEW GOES INTO EFFECT AT 1800.

4. THE SALVADORAN POPULATION MUST REMAIN IN THEIR RESIDENCES AND STAY OFF THE STREETS, EVEN UPON HEARING THAT AN ANTISUBVERSIVE OPERATION IS TAKING PLACE NEARBY -- THIS IS PARTICULARLY NECESSARY FOR MINORS.

5. THE SALVADORAN POPULATION ENGAGED IN COMMERCIAL ACTIVITIES, PARTICULARLY THE SALE OF STAPLES, MUST REMEMBER THAT THERE IS A DECREE THAT FORBIDS MARKING UP PRICES, SINCE THIS WOULD BE AN ANTIPATRIOTIC ACTION DURING THESE CRUCIAL TIMES FOR THE COUNTRY.

6. THE SALVADORAN POPULATION MUST REMAIN ALERT TO THE INFORMATION BEING ISSUED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES, BECAUSE IT WILL BE PROVIDED ON A REGULAR BASIS AND ACCORDING TO THE TRUTH. THE CIVILIAN POPULATION CAN ALSO REST ASSURED THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ARE EFFICIENTLY AND PROFESSIONALLY CONTROLLING THE GROUPS OF FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORIST CRIMINALS. THEREFORE, THE POPULATION MUST REMAIN CALM AND REJECT THE DISINFORMATION BEING ISSUED BY THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL SUBVERSION.

DEV-MUC3-0724 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT DENOUNCES BEFORE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY THE MEDDLING OF THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT IN THE ACT OF AGGRESSION AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AT THE HANDS OF FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORIST GROUPS. IN A SPEECH ON 12 NOVEMBER, NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA OPENLY MADE IRRESPONSIBLE STATEMENTS REGARDING DEVELOPMENTS IN EL SALVADOR WHICH ARE TOTALLY REMOVED FROM REALITY. PRESIDENT ORTEGA SAID THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS ATTACKING THE PEOPLE WHEN THE TRUTH IS THAT THE FMLN UNLEASHED THIS TERRORIST ESCALATION BY USING WEAPONS AND AMMUNITIONS SUPPLIED BY THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT.

THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY SHOULD INVESTIGATE THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT'S MEDDLING IN THIS CRIMINAL ATTACK ON THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE MORE CLOSELY. THE PUBLIC KNOWS THAT MAJOR CRIMES HAVE BEEN PLANNED ON NICARAGUAN TERRITORY, EVEN AGAINST FMLN LEADERS. THE LATE TOP FMLN LEADER, CAYETANO CARPIO, ORDERED THE MURDER OF MELIDA ANAYA MONTES, WHOM THE REBELS CALLED COMMANDER ANA MARIA FROM NICARAGUA. FMLN COMMANDER JOAQUIN VILLALBOS, WHO ORDERED THE MURDER OF MARXIST POET ROQUE DALTON GARCIA, CONTINUES TO LIVE IN NICARAGUA. THE MARXIST - LENINIST CONSPIRACY WHICH WANTS TO SUBJECT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO A TOTALITARIAN DICTATORSHIP IS PLANNED, LED, AND IMPLEMENTED ON NICARAGUAN TERRITORY.

HOWEVER, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO HAVE SUFFERED FOR MANY YEARS FROM THE BLOODTHIRSTY FMLN ATTACKS, KNOW THAT FMLN IS THE ONE WHO HAS CRUELLY MURDERED CHILDREN, WOMEN, AND THE ELDERLY, AND HAS NOT RESPECTED SEX OR AGE. THIS IS THE FMLN THAT IS MERCILESSLY ATTACKING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. AT PRESENT, THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ARE FULFILLING THEIR CONSTITUTIONAL MANDATE TO PROTECT AND DEFEND LIVES AND THE PROPERTIES OF SALVADORAN SOCIETY. THE FMLN HAS FAILED IN ITS TERRORIST OFFENSIVE. IT ENTERED THE CITY, THE WAY ALL COWARDS ENTER TO KILL BY SURPRISE AND IN COLD BLOOD DEFENSELESS PEOPLE.

HOWEVER, THE PEOPLE'S ARMED WING, NAMELY, THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, HAVE REPELLED THE AGGRESSORS WHO ARE BEING DIRECTED FROM NICARAGUA WITH PROFESSIONALISM. SO FAR, NOT ONE OF THE COWARDLY FMLN LEADERS HAS SHOWN UP IN SALVADORAN TERRITORY. THESE CRIMINALS HAVE PUSHED THEIR MURDEROUS HOARDES TO INDISCRIMINATELY FIRE AT THE ENTIRE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAVE CONDEMNED, REJECTED, AND REPUDIDATED THE FMLN'S TERRORIST ATTACK.

THE MURDEROUS LEADERS BELIEVED THAT THE PEOPLE WOULD RALLY BEHIND AND ACCOMPANY THEM IN THEIR FAILED REBELLIOUS OFFENSIVE; THEY TRIED TO HAND OUT WEAPONS IN SOME TOWNS. JUST AS THE PEOPLE TURNED THEIR BACKS ON THE TERRORISTS AT THE POLLS, THEY REJECT THEM NOW ONCE AGAIN BECAUSE THEY KNOW THAT THE FMLN IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THEIR HUNGER, POVERTY, AND SUFFERING. TO THE FREE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD WHO RESPECT THE PRINCIPLE OF NONINTERVENTION IN THE INTERNAL AFFAIRS OF STATES, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND GOVERNMENT DEMAND THE CONDEMNATION OF THE MEDDLING BY THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT WITH ITS LOGISTICAL SUPPORT TO THE FMLN AND THAT NICARAGUA STOPS LENDING ITS TERRITORY FOR THE AGGRESSION AGAINST THIS NATION THAT WANTS TO LIVE PEACEFULLY IN DEMOCRACY BASED ON A RESPECT FOR THE LAW AND FULL LIBERTY.

DEV-MUC3-0725 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] COLONEL PONCE, WHAT IS THE CURRENT MILITARY SITUATION IN SAN SALVADOR AND IN THE OTHER DEPARTMENTS?

[PONCE] GOOD EVENING, SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THE ARMED FORCES WANT TO PUBLICLY RECOGNIZE AND THANK THE PEOPLE FOR THEIR COOPERATION DURING THIS TIME WHEN THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORIST HORDES ARE CARRYING OUT AN ARMED AGGRESSION AGAINST ALL OF OUR PEOPLE.

THE SITUATION IN SAN SALVADOR CAN BE SUMMARIZED AS FOLLOWS: FIGHTING IS ONGOING IN THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR -- IN MEJICANOS, CUSCATANCINGO, AND THE ZACAMIL AREAS. THERE ARE ALSO SOME CLASHES IN THE NORTHWESTERN AREA OF SOYAPANGO, IN THE RESIDENTIAL AREAS OF BOSQUES DEL RIO, MONTE FRESCO, EL PETETE, AND SAN JOSE.

THERE IS SOME SPORADIC FIGHTING IN CIUDAD CREDISA, AS WELL AS IN SANTA MARTA. THAT IS WHAT WE CAN TELL YOU AT THIS MOMENT ABOUT THE FIGHTING IN THE AREA OF SAN SALVADOR.

IN THE OTHER DEPARTMENTS, ON SATURDAY, 11 NOVEMBER, THERE WAS FIGHTING IN SAN MIGUEL, SANTA ANA, ZACATECOLUCA, USULUTAN, AND SOME SPORADIC FIGHTING IN CHALATENANGO. OF ALL THESE PLACES, THE TERRORISTS INCREASED THEIR AGGRESSION TODAY ONLY IN ZACATECOLUCA. THE TERRORISTS, UNFORTUNATELY, TOOK OVER THE HOSPITAL IN ZACATECOLUCA, KILLING ONE SOLDIER WHO WAS RECEIVING MEDICAL TREATMENT. THE ARMED FORCES HAVE REGAINED CONTROL OF THE FIRST AND SECOND FLOORS OF THE HOSPITAL. APPROXIMATELY 10 TO 15 TERRORISTS ARE ON THE THIRD AND FOURTH FLOORS, AND THE TROUBLE IS THAT THERE ARE SICK PEOPLE ON THOSE FLOORS.

SO, WE BELIEVE THAT THE ARMED AGGRESSION, THE INDISCRIMINATE TERRORISM THAT THE FMLN HAS LAUNCHED AT THIS TIME IN AN IRRATIONAL MANNER AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, HAS BEEN CONTROLLED. THE ARMED FORCES ARE FIGHTING IN A PROFESSIONAL MANNER AGAINST THESE TERRORISTS.

[REPORTER] TO SUM UP, WE COULD THEN SAY THAT THERE ARE ONLY A FEW GUERRILLA RESISTANCE POCKETS IN THE AREAS THAT YOU HAVE MENTIONED. THIS CONTRADICTS THE REPORTS FROM THE CLANDESTINE RADIO STATIONS TO THE EFFECT THAT THEY CONTROL CERTAIN AREAS.

[PONCE] I MUST ALSO ADD THAT THERE IS ALSO SOME FIGHTING IN CIUDAD DELGADO. I CAN CATEGORICALLY STATE THAT THE FMLN DOES NOT CONTROL ANY POINT IN OUR NATIONAL TERRITORY. THEY ARE SHOUTING ABROAD THAT THEY CONTROL CERTAIN POINTS IN SAN SALVADOR. THE PEOPLE THEMSELVES, THE MEDIA, AND THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS ARE WITNESSES TO THE FACT THE FMLN DOES NOT CONTROL ANY PLACES IN SAN SALVADOR OR IN THE OTHER DEPARTMENTS. THERE ARE STILL SOME FMLN REDOUBTS, WHICH WE ARE CURRENTLY CONTROLLING IN ORDER TO EXPEL FROM THE URBAN AREAS THE TERRORISTS WHO ARE ATTACKING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

NATURALLY, WE HAVE SOME COMBAT LIMITATIONS IN THE URBAN AREAS, BECAUSE THE TERRORISTS ARE SHIELDING THEMSELVES BEHIND THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AND ARE HOLDING MANY FAMILIES HOSTAGES IN THEIR OWN HOMES. THE TERRORISTS HAVE ALSO PLACED SNIPERS ON SOME TALL BUILDINGS. THAT IS WHY THE ARMED FORCES ARE ASKING FOR THE PEOPLE'S UNDERSTANDING. IF WE WERE TO USE OUR MILITARY POWER, AS WE COULD DO IN A COMBAT ZONE, WE WOULD KILL MANY INNOCENT PEOPLE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0726 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 NOV 89 -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [PONCE] AND WE NOT WANT TO DO THAT. WE WANT TO RESOLVE THIS SITUATION IN A CAUTIOUS WAY, ALWAYS RESPECTING AND PROTECTING OUR CIVILIAN POPULATION. THAT IS WHY WE ASK THOSE PERSONS WHO HAVE BEEN KIDNAPPED OR ARE BEING HELD HOSTAGE BY TERRORISTS TO BE PATIENT. THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ARE MAKING AN EFFORT TO REACH ALL THE AREAS WHERE THIS SITUATION PREVAILS SO THAT WE CAN RESCUE ALL OF OUR SALVADORAN BROTHERS.

[REPORTER] THESE REMARKS ARE INTENDED TO REVEAL THE PROFESSIONAL NATURE OF THE ARMED FORCES AND REAFFIRM SOMETHING MANY SALVADORANS HAVE IN MIND. REGARDING THIS MILITARY OFFENSIVE, HAS THE FMLN RECEIVED MILITARY AND PERSONNEL AID FROM ABROAD?

[PONCE] SURE, NICARAGUA HAS ALWAYS SUPPORTED THE FMLN. PRESIDENT ORTEGA IS DOING THIS [3-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION]. THE NICARAGUAN FOREIGN MINISTER, WHO IS CURRENTLY IN MEXICO, IS GIVING HIS FULL SUPPORT TO THE FMLN. HE SAYS THAT THE REVOLUTIONARY FORCES HAVE ALREADY ACHIEVED THEIR VICTORY IN EL SALVADOR. THE FMLN ARE LIARS. THEY FOLLOW THE SAME COMMUNISTS' SLOGANS: LIE, LIE, AND LIE. HERE NO ONE BELIEVES THAT. A TRUCK LOADED WITH WEAPONS IN SANTA ANA WAS DRIVEN BY AN EAST GERMAN. SOME OF THE CAPTURED PEOPLE ARE FOREIGNERS. I CANNOT TELL YOU WHERE THEY COME FROM.

[REPORTER] YOUR REMARKS CONFIRM THE PRESENCE OF MERCENARIES IN THE CURRENT ARMED STRUGGLE, WHICH WOULD BE....

[PONCE, INTERRUPTING] I CAN ALSO ADD THAT WE RECEIVED INFORMATION BEFORE 10 NOVEMBER THAT A GROUP OF TERRORIST FIGHTERS HAD COME TO THE COUNTRY'S EASTERN ZONE FROM NICARAGUA. THEY MAY BE PARTICIPATING IN THIS TERRORIST ACTION.

[REPORTER] AS FOR THE TOTAL NUMBER OF CASUALTIES INFLICTED ON THE FMLN NOW, CAN YOU TELL HOW MANY FMLN REBELS HAVE DIED IN THIS OFFENSIVE?

[PONCE] NATIONWIDE, WE COUNTED 230 TERRORISTS KILLED, AND 136 TERRORIST WOUNDED; 72 TERRORIST WERE CAPTURED. ONE TERRORIST WAS PRESENTED TO THE PRESS.

[REPORTER] CAN THE NUMBER OF CIVILIANS KILLED AND WOUNDED BE TOTALLED NOW?

[PONCE] THAT IS THE MOST REGRETTABLE ASPECT OF THIS IRRATIONAL FMLN ACTION. THIS ACTION HAS IMPERILED THE PEOPLE WHO ARE NOT INVOLVED IN THE ARMED UPRISING. WE REGRET THAT 17 PEOPLE HAVE DIED AND 86 HAVE BEEN WOUNDED.

[REPORTER] THIS FIGURE IS REALLY REGRETTABLE. MANY PEOPLE HAVE BEEN TUNED INTO THIS NATIONAL NETWORK. WE HAVE HEARD MANY TELEPHONE CALLS REITERATING SUPPORT FOR THE CURRENT GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES' ACTIONS. IN CASE OF AN EMERGENCY IN AREAS WHERE THE CURFEW WAS ORDERED. WHAT SUGGESTIONS CAN YOU OFFER PEOPLE IN THE CAPITAL CITY?

[PONCE] TO REPORT AN EMERGENCY THEY CAN DIAL 3 IF THEY HAVE A TELEPHONE AVAILABLE. OTHERWISE, OR IF THEY DO NOT HAVE A TELEPHONE, IT IS IMPORTANT THAT THEY LEAVE THEIR HOMES WITH THEIR ARMS UP CARRYING SOME WHITE FLAG OR CLOTH AND GO TO A NEARBY UNIT TO GET AID. PEOPLE MUST KEEP IN MIND THE ARMED FORCES ARE THE FRIENDS OF THE PEOPLE AND WILL SERVE THE PEOPLE. TRUST AND GO TO YOUR ARMED FORCES.

[REPORTER] THESE WERE THE REMARKS OF COL RENE EMILIO PONCE. HE IS NOW LEAVING THIS NATIONAL RADIO NETWORK.

[PONCE] I CAN TELL YOU THAT A LARGE NUMBER OF WEAPONS HAVE BEEN SEIZED. WE CAN CONFIRM THE MEDDLING OF SOME COMMUNIST BLOC COUNTRIES IN THIS. WE SEIZED RUSSIAN AND NORTH KOREAN WEAPONS WHICH PROBABLY ENTERED THROUGH CUBA AND NICARAGUA. I CAN ALSO TELL YOU THAT SINCE THE FMLN FIRED MORTARS FROM THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY ON SATURDAY AND SUNDAY MORNING, WE HAD TO REMOVE THE TERRORISTS FROM SEVERAL POINTS. WE FOUND WEAPONS, EXPLOSIVES, AND A LARGE AMOUNT OF MEDICINE INSIDE THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY. SOME MEN WERE KILLED WITH THEIR RIFLES IN THEIR HANDS; WE ALSO CAPTURED OTHERS WHO WERE INSIDE THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY.

I ALSO WANT TO ASK THE CIVILIAN POPULATION FOR ITS UNDERSTANDING AND TO TRUST THEIR ARMED FORCES. THESE ARMED FORCES BELONG TO THE PEOPLE AND SERVE THEM. WE ARE ACTING IN A PROFESSIONAL MANNER. BE PATIENT, REMAIN CALM, AND WE WILL MOVE AHEAD WITH GOD'S BLESSING AND HELP. ALSO, I WANT TO PUBLICLY RECOGNIZE THE MILITARY CHIEFS, OFFICERS, ENLISTED MEN, SECURITY CORPS OFFICIALS, AND ALL THE ARMED FORCES' ACTIVE PERSONNEL FOR THEIR HEROIC WORK IN DEFENDING OUR PEOPLE, DEMOCRACY, LIBERTY, AND PEACE. YOUR ACTIONS HAVE BEEN HEROIC, AND ALL OF US RECOGNIZE THIS. MAY HISTORY DO YOU JUSTICE TOMORROW. YOU MUST FEEL PROUD BECAUSE YOU ARE DOING WHAT EVERY PATRIOT MUST DO, DEFEND THE FATHERLAND.

DEV-MUC3-0728 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [STATEMENT] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] SINCE 1981 THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HAS BEEN INSISTING ON THE NEED FOR A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE WAR. ITS EFFORTS MET WITH THE STUBBORN OPPOSITION OF THE ARMED FORCES AND THE COUNTRY'S ULTRARIGHTIST SECTORS, WHO ARE THE ONES WHO IN REALITY HAVE WIELDED TOTAL POWER.

WE PRESENTED DOZENS OF NEGOTIATING PROPOSALS IN WHICH WE INCREASINGLY MADE OUR POSITIONS MORE FLEXIBLE, EVEN THOUGH THE MILITARY REALITY DEMONSTRATED THAT WE WERE INVINCIBLE. WE PRESENTED TO THE CURRENT NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA] GOVERNMENT A PROPOSAL THAT HAD REAL POSSIBILITIES OF BRINGING ABOUT PEACE. HOWEVER, THE RESPONSE WE RECEIVED WAS AN ESCALATION OF REPRESSION BY MEANS OF TORTURE AND MURDER, WHICH CULMINATED WITH THE MASSACRE OF THE WORKERS OF THE SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION [FENASTRAS].

THE GOVERNMENT REJECTED OUR FORMULAS FOR NEGOTIATION IN WORD AND IN DEED, AND INSTEAD DEEPENED THE CAUSES BEHIND THE WAR BY WORSENING THE SOCIAL CRISIS AND REDUCING THE RANGE OF ACTIVITY OF THE POPULAR SECTORS. FACED WITH A DANGEROUS SITUATION THAT THREATENED NOT ONLY TO SHUT OFF A PEACEFUL SOLUTION TO THE WAR, BUT INSTEAD TO INCREASE THE KILLINGS AND OTHER FLAGRANT VIOLATIONS OF OUR PEOPLE'S DEMOCRATIC RIGHTS, THE FMLN DECIDED TO LAUNCH A FORCEFUL AND STRATEGIC MILITARY OFFENSIVE THAT WOULD PUT A HALT TO THE FASCISTS AND OPEN UP A POSSIBILITY TO BRING AN END TO THE WAR.

CONSEQUENTLY, AT 2000 ON 11 NOVEMBER OUR FORCES ENTERED INTO COMBAT AGAINST ALL THE TARGETS DESIGNATED IN OUR OFFENSIVE PLAN, DESPITE ALL THE PREVENTIVE MEASURES AND ARRANGEMENTS SET UP BY THE ARMY TO TRY TO HALT US. OUR EXPERIENCED FIGHTERS, IN SPITE OF THE DISADVANTAGE IN FORCES AND ARMS, HAVE FULFILLED OUR GOALS BEYOND OUR EXPECTATIONS, CARRYING OUT ONE OF THE MOST GLORIOUS MILITARY BATTLES IN THE HISTORY OF THE PEOPLE'S WAR. IN UNDER 15 HOURS, WE GAINED CONTROL OVER STRATEGIC TERRITORIES, WIPED OUT DOZENS OF ENEMY TROOPS, TOOK PRISONERS, RECOVERED WEAPONS, AND DESTROYED ARMORED VEHICLES AND AIRPLANES.

AFTER 4 CONTINUOUS DAYS OF FIGHTING, OUR FORCES HAVE REJECTED ALL COUNTERATTACKS BY THE ENEMY AND HAVE GAINED NEW POSITIONS. THOUSANDS OF RESIDENTS OF THE CITIES HAVE STAGED POPULAR UPRISINGS TO SUPPORT OUR FORCES, WHICH HAVE BEEN AUGMENTED BY NEW FIGHTERS. FACED WITH THIS SITUATION, THE ARENA GOVERNMENT AND THE CLIQUE OF CORRUPT MILITARY OFFICERS KNOWN AS LA TANDONA WHO COMMAND THE ARMED FORCES, HAVE ORDERED CRIMINAL BOMBINGS OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION WITH THE PURPOSE OF PUTTING DOWN THE POPULAR UPRISINGS. THIS HAS BROUGHT ABOUT MORE SUPPORT FOR OUR FORCES AND REDOUBLED THE PEOPLE'S RAGE AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT LED BY CRISTIANI AND THE ARMY. A SITUATION HAS THUS COME ABOUT WHICH DEMANDS THAT OUR FORCES CARRY OUT THE DECISION TO CONTINUE THE OFFENSIVE THAT OUR FORCES AND THE PEOPLE HAVE UNLEASHED UNTIL ITS FINAL CONSEQUENCES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0729 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [STATEMENT] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] PEACE IS POSSIBLE ONLY IF WE EVICT FROM POWER THOSE WHO HAVE PROFITED FROM WAR. CONSEQUENTLY, THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND:

1. ORDERS THAT ALL OUR UNITS MUST HOLD THE POSITIONS CONQUERED, ORGANIZE THE GENERAL UPRISING OF OUR PEOPLE, AND CARRY OUT ALL THE TASKS DEALING WITH THE POPULATION'S SECURITY AND DEFENSE AND THE COLLECTION OF FOOD AND ITS DISTRIBUTION TO THE NEEDY.

2. CALLS THE PEOPLE TO A GENERAL UPRISING SO THEY CAN JOIN US IN BATTLE IN EVERY POSSIBLE WAY WITH ALL TYPES OF WEAPONS TO DEFEND THEMSELVES AND STRIKE THE ENEMY.

3. ANNOUNCES THAT, EFFECTIVE AS SOON AS THIS MANIFESTO IS ANNOUNCED, WE DECLARE AS TERRITORIES LIBERATED BY THE PEOPLE ALL THE AREAS UNDER OUR CONTROL IN MORAZAN, SAN MIGUEL, LA UNION, USULUTAN, CUSCATLAN, CHALATENANGO, SAN VICENTE, AND CABANAS DEPARTMENTS. IN ACCORDANCE WITH THIS, OUR FORCES AND THE PEOPLE WILL ORGANIZE POPULAR GOVERNMENTS IN EVERY MUNICIPALITY IN THESE DEPARTMENTS. SIMULTANEOUSLY, OUR FORCES THAT CONTROL TERRITORIES IN THE CITIES MUST INTENSIFY THE STRUGGLE TO ENSURE TOTAL CONTROL OF THE COUNTRY.

4. URGES ALL THE WORKERS TO STOP WORKING AS PART OF THE GENERALIZED STRUGGLE, WHICH WILL HELP WEAKEN THE JANUARY GOVERNMENT AND WILL ENABLE ALL TO JOIN US IN COMBAT. THEREFORE, WE HEREBY ANNOUNCE THAT THE CURRENT TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE, THE SABOTAGING OF THE ENERGY SUPPLY, AND THE CLOSING OF GASOLINE STATIONS WILL CONTINUE FOR AN INDEFINITE TIME. FOR THIS REASON, THE PEOPLE MUST PREPARE FOR THIS SITUATION. WE STERNLY WARN THOSE EMPLOYERS WHO FORCE THEIR WORKERS TO GO TO WORK THAT OUR FORCES HAVE BEEN INSTRUCTED TO IMPOSE OBEDIENCE TO THIS MEASURE.

5. ASKS THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY AND HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS TO SEND HELP TO THE CIVILIAN VICTIMS OF BOMBINGS AND CONTRIBUTE TO THE CREATION OF REFUGES AND CENTERS TO PROTECT THE POPULATION FROM THE CRIMINAL ACTIONS UNLEASHED BY CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND.

6. URGENTLY CALLS ALL POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES, POPULAR ORGANIZATIONS, AND PRIVATE BUSINESSMEN IN OUR COUNTRY TO ASSUME AT THIS TIME THE HISTORIC ROLE OF MAKERS AND BUILDERS OF A NATIONAL DEMOCRATIC SOLUTION THAT CAN BRING LASTING PEACE TO OUR COUNTRY.

7. MAKES A PATRIOTIC EXHORTATION TO OFFICERS AND THE RANK AND FILE OF THE ARMY NOT TO LET THE BIG BATCH [LA TANDONA, THE GRADUATING CLASS OF THE MAJORITY OF THE CURRENT ARMY STAFF MEMBERS], ARENA, AND THE U.S. INTERESTS LEAD THEM TO CONFRONT THE PEOPLE, THUS STAINING THEIR HANDS WITH BLOOD. THE FMLN DOES NOT REGARD THEM AS ENEMIES AND IS READY TO MAKE PEACE WITH THE ARMY SECTORS WHO DESIRE JUSTICE, SOVEREIGNTY, AND TRUE DEMOCRACY FOR OUR PEOPLE. THE ENEMY OF THE PEOPLE AND ALL OF OUR COUNTRY'S SOCIAL AND POLITICAL FORCES IS LA TANDONA, WHO HAVE ENRICHED THEMSELVES WITH WAR, AND THE ARENA DEATH SQUADS. THEY ARE THE ENEMIES OF PEACE AND DEMOCRACY. THEY ARE THE ONES WHO DO NOT WANT A REGIME OF JUSTICE. WE CALL ALL THE NATION TO FIGHT THEM SO WE CAN SING THE NATIONAL ANTHEM, WHICH THE TYRANNY HAS TRIED TO BURY, AND WHICH SAYS: FREEDOM IS ITS DOGMA AND GUIDELINE, WHICH IT HAS SWORN TO DEFEND A THOUSAND TIMES, AND JUST AS MANY TIMES, HAS SWORN TO REJECT THE HATEFUL POWER OF A BOLD TYRANNY.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANCHEZ SEREN, EDUARDO SANCHO, FRANCISCO JOVEL, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS.

EL SALVADOR, 13 NOVEMBER 1989.

DEV-MUC3-0730 (U NEBRASKA)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 14 NOV 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [TEXT] NICARAGUA PRESENTED A DRAFT RESOLUTION TO STOP THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT AND SEEK A DIPLOMATIC SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN SITUATION AT THE 29TH ANNUAL OAS MEETING HELD ON 13 NOVEMBER 1989.

THE DRAFT WAS INTRODUCED BY NICARAGUAN FOREIGN MINISTER MIGUEL D'ESCOTO AND READ FOR RADIO SANDINO FROM THE NICARAGUAN EMBASSY IN WASHINGTON.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED PERSON] WHEREAS THE SITUATION OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE IS MARKED BY THE INCREASING ARMED STRUGGLE AND FLAGRANT VIOLATIONS OF HUMAN RIGHTS AND MAN'S FUNDAMENTAL LIBERTIES: THE ENORMOUS HUMAN SUFFERING CAUSED BY THIS SITUATION HAS RESULTED IN THE LOSS OF NUMEROUS CIVILIAN LIVES AS AN EFFECT OF THE INDISCRIMINATE REPRESSION ON THE NONCOMBATANT POPULATION. ACCORDING TO ARTICLE 2, PARAGRAPH A OF THE OAS CHARTER, AMENDED BY THE CARTAGENA PROTOCOL, ONE OF THE ORGANIZATION'S MAIN PURPOSES IS TO STRENGTHEN PEACE AND SECURITY IN THE CONTINENT. SOLIDARITY AMONG AMERICAN STATES [WORDS INDISTINCT] MAKES IT AN URGENT MATTER THAT THE ORGANIZATION DEVOTES SPECIAL AND CONSIDERABLE EFFORTS TO HELP ACHIEVE A NEGOTIATED POLITICAL SOLUTION OF THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT AND TO END THE BLOODSHED. THEREFORE:

1. WE URGENTLY CALL ON THE SALVADORAN REGIME TO IMMEDIATELY STOP THE BOMBINGS OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AND THE ACTS OF REPRESSION LIKE AT SAN SALVADOR UNIVERSITY.

2. WE MAKE AN APPEAL SO THAT THE HOSTILITIES CAN BE STOPPED IMMEDIATELY, THE WOUNDED CAN BE EVACUATED, AND THE CIVILIAN POPULATION CAN BE SUPPLIED WITH STAPLES IN FULL SECURITY.

3. WE APPEAL TO THE SIDES IN CONFLICT THAT NEGOTIATIONS BE IMMEDIATELY INITIATED THROUGH THE UNITED NATIONS AND THE OAS, LEADING TO A CEASE - FIRE UNDER CONDITIONS THAT ENSURE FULL RESPECT FOR ALL HUMAN RIGHTS.

4. WE URGE MAKING THE NECESSARY ARRANGEMENTS SO THE UN OBSERVERS FOR CENTRAL AMERICA [ONUCA], CREATED BY THE UN SECURITY COUNCIL ON 7 NOVEMBER 1989, CAN GO TO EL SALVADOR IMMEDIATELY TO A) MAKE SURE THERE IS NO FOREIGN INTERFERENCE IN THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT, WHICH COULD PREVENT THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S RIGHT TO FULL AND UNRESTRICTED SELF-DETERMINATION; B) ENFORCE THE PRINCIPLES OF INTERNATIONAL LAW REGARDING HUMANITARIANISM, PARTICULARLY ARTICLE 3 OF THE GENEVA CONVENTIONS SIGNED IN 1949, WHICH DEAL WITH EXPENDITURES DUE TO WAR, PROTECTION OF CIVILIANS, AND [WORDS INDISTINCT].

5. WE ASK THE OAS SECRETARY GENERAL TO UTILIZE ALL AVAILABLE INDIRECT AND DIRECT MEANS, ACCORDING TO ARTICLE 115 OF THE AMENDED CHARTER, TO OBTAIN CURRENT AND OBJECTIVE INFORMATION ON THE SALVADORAN SITUATION AND TO KEEP ALL OAS MEMBER STATES POSTED ON THIS. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0731 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, ATTENTION, WE HAVE JUST RECEIVED A REPORT FROM SAN MIGUEL ON INDISCRIMINATE SHELLING IN SAN MIGUEL. THE REPORT ADDS THAT THE INDISCRIMINATE SHELLING AND BOMBINGS BEING CARRIED OUT BY A-37 PLANES CONTINUED TODAY IN LA ESMERALDA, LA COQUERA, LOPEZ, EL GRANILLO, AND SANTA LUISA NEIGHBORHOODS. IT HAS ALSO BEEN REPORTED THAT THERE ARE SEVERAL DEAD AND WOUNDED CIVILIANS AND MANY DESTROYED HOMES.

ONCE AGAIN WE DENOUNCE THESE CRIMINAL ACTIONS BY THE FASCIST GOVERNMENT; WE DENOUNCE THE SHELLING AND BOMBING ACTIONS AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. WE REPEAT OUR CALL TO THE INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS, HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS, GREEN CROSS, AND RESCUE COMMANDS TO COME TO THESE PLACES TO HELP THE CIVILIAN VICTIMS.

WE HAVE ALSO RECEIVED A REPORT FROM ILOBASCO; WE HAVE RECEIVED A PRELIMINARY WAR BULLETIN FROM CINQUERA, CABANAS DEPARTMENT.

TODAY, 14 NOVEMBER, AT 0000 [0600 GMT], REBEL UNITS ENTERED ILOBASCO, CABANAS DEPARTMENT, AND ATTACKED THE REPRESSIVE NATIONAL POLICE AND CIVIL DEFENSE TRENCHES LOCATED IN DOWNTOWN ILOBASCO WITH RIFLES AND RPG-7 ROCKET LAUNCHERS. TODAY, 14 NOVEMBER, AT 0630 [1230 GMT], HEAVY FIGHTING WAS STILL BEING REPORTED. IT HAS BEEN CONFIRMED THAT DURING THE ATTACK ON ILOBASCO, THE NATIONAL POLICE, 2ND MILITARY DETACHMENT, AND CIVIL DEFENSE TROOPS SUFFERED 12 CASUALTIES. AT 0740 [1340 GMT] FIGHTING CONTINUES IN ILOBASCO.

DEV-MUC3-0733 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THIS MORNING OUR UNITS TOURED SEVERAL AREAS IN SAN SALVADOR AND THE OUTLYING MUNICIPALITIES. IN REALITY, SALVADORAN BROTHERS, OUR ARMED FORCES HAVE COMPLETELY WIPED OUT THE REDOUBTS OF THE TERRORISTS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. IN SEVERAL PLACES IN SAN SALVADOR THERE IS HEAVY MOVEMENT. WE HAVE SEEN HUNDREDS OF SALVADORANS IN THE STREETS, THOUSANDS IN SOME AREAS, GOING TO THEIR WORKPLACES. THERE IS ACTIVITY IN THE STREETS.

WE CONGRATULATE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO ARE MOVING ABOUT WITH OPTIMISM, FOR THEIR COURAGE AND BRAVERY. THEY ARE DEFYING THE BULLETS OF THE FMLN CRIMINALS AND MURDERERS, WHO ARE SOWING GRIEF AND MOURNING AMONG THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THE FMLN DID NOT TAKE INTO ACCOUNT, HOWEVER, THAT EL SALVADOR HAS A PROFESSIONAL AND POWERFUL ARMED FORCES THAT THE PEOPLE SUPPORT. THIS ARMED FORCES IS DESTROYING ALL THE GUERRILLA REDOUBTS.

SALVADORANS: IF YOU ARE STILL AT HOME, YOU CAN GO OUT TO WORK UNLESS YOU ARE IN ONE OF THE FEW REMAINING RESTRICTED AREAS WHERE TERRORIST SNIPERS ARE OPERATING. THERE IS ACTIVITY AND MOVEMENT IN THE LARGE URBAN AREAS OF THE CITY AND ON THE MAIN STREETS OF THE CAPITAL. THE MARKETS AND COMMERCIAL ESTABLISHMENTS ARE OPENING FOR BUSINESS. THE SUPERMARKETS ARE OPENING THEIR DOORS. BUSES ARE OPERATING. WE WILL KEEP YOU INFORMED OF WHAT IS TAKING PLACE SO THAT YOU CAN MOVE ABOUT FREELY, KNOWING THAT YOUR ARMED FORCES IS SUPPORTING YOU, THAT EACH SOLDIER IS GUARDING YOUR LIFE. YOU HAVE TO TRUST IN YOUR ARMED FORCES, AS YOU ALWAYS HAVE, BECAUSE IT IS THE ARM THAT IS DEFENDINAMAPOLAS, SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOOD, SAN SALVADOR; IN THE VICINITY OF THE TORRE DEMOCRACIA BUILDING IN SAN SALVADOR; AND IN EL LIMON CANTON, SOYAPANGO. THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES AS A RESULT OF ANY OF THESE ENCOUNTERS.

AN ATTEMPT WAS MADE AGAINST THE DEPUTY FOREIGN MINISTER'S LIFE THROUGH AN ATTACK ON A RESIDENCE IN THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN SALVADOR. NO ONE WAS HURT, HOWEVER.

THE ARMED FORCES ALSO REPORTED THAT A HARRASSMENT ATTACK WAS MADE ON THE GARRISON OF THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, BUT THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES. THREE EXPLOSIONS HAVE BEEN HEARD IN APASTEPEQUE, BUT THEIR ORIGIN HAS NOT YET BEEN DETERMINED.

ARMED FORCES PERSONNEL WERE ALSO HARRASSED NORTH OF THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE AND NATIONAL POLICE INSTALLATIONS IN BERLIN, BUT AGAIN NO CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED.

DEV-MUC3-0735 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] HERE IS A REPORT ON ARMED FORCES MILITARY ACTIONS: IN THE 1ST MILITARY ZONE CLASHES WERE REPORTED IN THE AREAS OF SAN JOSE GUAYABAL AND SAN MARTIN, WHERE THE REBELS WERE TURNED BACK BY THE SOLDIERS ASSIGNED TO THE AREAS. THE REBELS LEFT SUPPLIES AND AMMUNITION BEHIND.

IN THE MAQUILISHUAT NEIGHBORHOOD IN SOUTHWESTERN SAN SALVADOR, SOLDIERS FROM THE BELLOSO BATTALION FORCED TERRORIST TROOPS WHO WERE ROAMING THE AREA TO FLEE. CLASHES WERE REPORTED IN THE VICINITY OF THE SAN BENITO AND SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOODS, WHERE THE TROOPS REPELLED THE TERRORISTS WHO WERE TRYING TO CLOSE IN ON THESE RESIDENTIAL AREAS.

IN THE TOWNSHIP OF EL TULE AGUILARES, CLASHES WERE REPORTED BETWEEN 4TH BRIGADE TROOPS AND TERRORISTS FROM THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. THE TERRORISTS WERE REPELLED AND FLED IN DISARRAY.

ENCOUNTERS WITH FMLN TERRORISTS ALSO OCCURRED ON SAN ANTONIO AVENUE, IN THE AREA OF CUSCATACINGO. THE ATTACKERS FLED, CARRYING SEVERAL WOUNDED COMRADES WITH THEM.

IN SOYAPANGO, THE FMLN SUBVERSIVES COLDBLOODEDLY MURDERED TWO WATCHMEN AT THE INSA FACTORY.

FEELING HOUNDED AND HEMMED IN BY THE ARMED FORCES TROOPS, THE FMLN TERRORISTS CONTINUE TO RESORT TO [3-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] TO KIDNAP YOUTHS, ON THIS OCCASION FROM THE AMATEPEC NEIGHBORHOOD ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR.

IN CIUDAD DELGADO, MEMBERS OF THE SECURITY CORPS ARRESTED THREE PERSONS AND CONFISCATED THE FOLLOWING MATERIAL THEY WERE CARRYING: THREE M-16 RIFLES, A 45-CALIBER PISTOL, AND AMMUNITION FOR M-16 AND AK-47 RIFLES. IN THE TOWN OF SAN MARCOS, THE BRACAMONTE BATTALION CONFISCATED AN AK-47 RIFLE AND A HAND GRENADE.

THE FMLN TERRORISTS WHO ARE MAKING A DESPERATE RETREAT FROM THE SUBURBS OF SAN SALVADOR HAVE ABANDONED 27 OF THEIR DEAD COMRADES IN CIUDAD CREDISA. THESE PEOPLE SHED THEIR BLOOD IN VAIN FOR IDEALS THAT DO NOT TRULY SEEK THE WELFARE OF SALVADORANS, BUT INSTEAD THE IMPLEMENTATION OF THE OPPROBIOUS AND TOTALITARIAN DICTATORSHIP THAT THE FMLN TERRORISTS WOULD LIKE TO IMPOSE. THERE IS NO PLACE FOR THE FMLN HERE IN EL SALVADOR. IT HAS ALWAYS HAD A WARLIKE, VIOLENT POSITION OPPOSED TO THE INTERESTS OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

THE ARMED FORCES HAS CONTROL OVER THE SMALL REDOUBTS IN WHICH THE TERRORISTS, TRYING TO SAVE THEIR LIVES, ARE HIDING IN THE HOMES OF DEFENSELESS SALVADORANS.

DEV-MUC3-0738 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] OUR FORCES HAVE ALSO ENGAGED TROOPS POSTED AT THE PRESIDENTE HOTEL AND IN ITS VICINITY, BUT ONCE AGAIN RESPECTED THE U.S. AMBASSADOR'S RESIDENCE. DURING THE ENTIRE MANEUVER WE INFLICTED APPROXIMATELY 20 CASUALTIES ON THE ENEMY, BUT WE DID NOT LOSE ANY MEN.

MEANWHILE, WE HAVE HAD REPORTS FROM SAN SALVADOR THAT THE AIR FORCE IS BOMBING HEAVILY DENSELY POPULATED AREAS IN THE SECTOR OF CIUDAD DELGADO. COMMANDER CARLOS ANNOUNCED THIS AT A NEWS CONFERENCE IN SAN SALVADOR: A GOVERNMENT THAT BOMBS THE PEOPLE IS AN ILLEGITIMATE GOVERNMENT; A GOVERNMENT FACING THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS IN ARMS IS AN ILLEGITIMATE GOVERNMENT; AND A GOVERNMENT THAT MASSACRES THE PEOPLE IS AN ILLEGITIMATE GOVERNMENT; AND AN ILLEGITIMATE GOVERNMENT MUST BE TOPPLED BY OUR FORCES.

NOW, WE HAVE A LAST-MINUTE REPORT FROM SAN SALVADOR. AT THIS VERY MOMENT, AN O-2 AIRPLANE IS THROWING ROCKETS AT THE AREA OF ZACAMIL, WHERE HEAVY FIGHTING IS UNDER WAY. IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT THERE HAVE BEEN CIVILIAN CASUALTIES IN THIS ATTACK. IT HAS ALSO BEEN CONFIRMED THAT THE THREE ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS THAT WERE DESTROYED IN ZACAMIL WERE DESTROYED ON THE STREET THAT JOINS THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD WITH THE METROPOLI NEIGHBORHOOD.

IN ANOTHER REPORT FROM OUR COMPANEROS IN SOYAPANGO, THEY HAVE INFORMED US THAT THEY HAVE SEEN A U.S. ADVISER LEADING THE TROOPS IN THE SECTOR OF SOYAPANGO. IT IS PRESUMED THAT THIS NORTH AMERICAN IS THE ONE WHO IS DIRECTING THE AIR ATTACK IN THE SECTOR OF SOYAPANGO. C-47 AIRPLANES AS WELL AS UH-1M, HUEY 500, AND UH-1H HELICOPTERS, ALL U.S. MADE, HAVE BEEN THROWING ROCKETS ON AND MACHINEGUNNING THE SECTORS OF SOYAPANGO AND CIUDAD DELGADO. THE FASCIST REGIME OF LA TANDONA [NAME GIVEN TO 1966 GRADUATES OF CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY], CRISTIANI, AND D'AUBUISSON HAVE DECREED A CURFEW IN ALL OF THE AREAS UNDER THE CONTROL OF OUR FORCES IN THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR TO ENSURE THAT THERE ARE NO WITNESSES OF THEIR INDISCRIMINATE BOMBING. WE ISSUE AN URGENT CALL TO THE RED CROSS AND OTHER HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS TO GO TO SOYAPANGO, WHERE THERE HAVE BEEN DOZENS OF CIVILIAN CASUALTIES. WE ALSO ISSUE AN URGENT APPEAL TO THE DEMOCRATIC LATIN AMERICAN GOVERNMENTS SO THAT THEY CAN [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE FASCIST GOVERNMENT OF ALFREDO CRISTIANI, TO GET HIM TO STOP THIS INDISCRIMINATE BOMBING ONCE AND FOR ALL.

A REPORT FROM THE CAPITAL STATES THAT FMLN FORCES THIS AFTERNOON ARE ATTACKING ZACAMIL BATTALION POSITIONS AND HARRASSING THE ARMED FORCES' JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF. ON THIS 4TH DAY OF FIGHTING IN THE CAPITAL, ROADBLOCKS CONTINUE TO MULTIPLY THROUGHOUT. THIS IS THE SECOND ATTACK ON THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF IN LESS THAN 24 HOURS.

AS REPORTED ON THE EVENING OF 13 NOVEMBER, WE ATTACKED THE SAN BENITO BATTALION AT THE NATIONAL FAIR GROUNDS AND THE FORCES GUARDING THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF. THIS IS THE SECOND HARRASSMENT ATTACK ON THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF. THIS COMPLICATES THE ARMED FORCES' SITUATION IN THE CAPITAL BECAUSE THE ENEMY ARMED FORCES' TOP LEADERSHIP IS BEING ATTACKED AND HARRASSED. FMLN FORCES ARE BESIEGING THE ENEMY.

AIR FORCE AIRCRAFTS CONTINUE TO OVERFLY THE NORTHERN AREA OF THE CAPITAL THIS AFTERNOON. THEY CONTINUE TO MACHINEGUN AND BOMB THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. MOMENTS AGO, WE REPORTED THAT THERE WAS HEAVY BOMBING IN ZACAMIL AGAINST THE POPULATION. WE CALL ON THE INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS COMMITTEE TO GO IMMEDIATELY TO ZACAMIL TO EVACUATE CIVILIANS WHO MIGHT HAVE SURVIVED THESE COWARDLY AND BLOODY AIR FORCE BOMBINGS.

DEV-MUC3-0739 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE A REPORT FROM OUR COMMANDING POST IN SAN SALVADOR. WE HAVE AN INTERVIEW WITH COMMANDER CLAUDIO RABINDRANATH ARMIJO. BECAUSE OF CERTAIN PROBLEMS WITH THE COMMUNICATIONS, THE QUESTIONS WILL NOT BE CLEAR, BUT THE ANSWERS WILL BE.

[REPORTER] COMMANDER CLAUDIO RABINDRANATH ARMIJO, WE ARE INTERVIEWING YOU FROM RADIO VENCEREMOS HERE IN MORAZAN DEPARTMENT. WE HAVE HEARD REPORTS FROM CENTRAL AMERICAN RADIO STATIONS SPEAKING ABOUT ROCKET FIRE AND BOMBINGS IN ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD. COULD YOU TELL US ABOUT THE CURRENT SITUATION?

[ARMIJO] WE HAVE BEEN HOLDING OUR POSITION FOR ABOUT 3 DAYS [WORDS INDISTINCT]. CURRENTLY, THERE IS ROCKET AND MACHINEGUN FIRE BEING LAUNCED AGAINST OUR POSITIONS. THE ENEMY IS DESPERATE. THIS MORNING WE REPELLED AN ATTACK. THEY FLED IN DISARRAY BECAUSE NO ONE CAME TO SUPPORT THEM.

[REPORTER] THE FASCIST DISINFORMATION NETWORK HAS BEEN SAYING THAT THE PEOPLE ARE NOT SUPPORTING THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. WHAT IS THE PEOPLE'S ATTITUDE TOWARD THE FMLN FIGHTERS IN ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD?

[ARMIJO] THEIR CONDUCT HAS BEEN POSITIVE. THEY HAVE BEEN HELPING US TREAT THE WOUNDED. THEY HAVE HELPED US WITH FOOD PROBLEMS. THEY HAVE SUPPORTED US COMPLETELY BY PLACING BARRICADES ON THE STREETS. THE PEOPLE'S SUPPORT IN THIS AREA IS COMPLETELY DIFFERENT FROM WHAT THE ENEMY'S PSYCHOLOGICAL WAR IS TRYING TO ACCOMPLISH.

[REPORTER] WE HAVE RECEIVED INFORMATION FROM OUR COMRADES IN SOYAPANGO WHO SAY THAT THEY HAVE SEEN A U.S. ADVISER LEADING ENEMY TROOPS IN SAN SALVADOR. HAVE ANY OF YOUR MEN SEEN ANY U.S. ADVISERS? [ARMIJO] [WORD INDISTINCT] NOT SEEN THEM, BUT [PASSAGE INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] WHAT IS THE MORALE OF THE FMLN TROOPS PARTICULARLY IN THE ZACAMIL AREA? THE FASCIST INFORMATION NETWORK HAS BEEN SAYING THAT FMLN TROOPS ARE LEAVING THEIR POSTS.

[ARMIJO] THEIR MORALE IS HIGH. WE ARE ENCOURAGED BY THE PEOPLE'S SUPPORT. WE ARE VERY DETERMINED. THE ENEMY'S ATTACKS HAVE BEEN REPELLED.

[REPORTER] COULD YOU SEND A MESSAGE TO FMLN TROOPS IN ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD AND TO THOSE IN THE NORTHERN AND SOUTHERN PARTS OF THE CAPITAL AS WELL AS TO FMLN FIGHTERS HOLDING THEIR POSITIONS IN OTHER PARTS OF THE COUNTRY?

[ARMIJO] THE PEOPLE ARE CURRENTLY SUPPORTING US. WE ARE WAGING ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT BATTLES IN THE LAST FEW YEARS. THE OUTLOOK FOR VICTORY DEPENDS ON WHAT EACH OF US DOES. WE MUST KEEP MOVING FORWARD.

THIS HAS BEEN A RECORDED INTERVIEW. WE INTERVIEWED COMMANDER CLAUDIO RABINDRANATH ARMIJO A FEW MINUTES AGO. HE IS CURRENTLY AT A COMMAND POST IN SAN SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0740 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, ATTENTION, SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THIS IS CADENA NACIONAL, THE NETWORK OF FREEDOM, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S NETWORK. ATTENTION, SALVADORAN PEOPLE:

THE TERRORIST HORDES OF THE FARBUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN) HAVE BEEN DEFEATED BY OUR BRAVE ARMED FORCES, WHO HAVE GONE OUT TO DEFEND OUR SOVEREIGNTY, INTEGRITY, AND THE LIVES AND PROPERTIES OF ALL SALVADORANS.

THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE SUPPORTING THEIR ARMED FORCES AND PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI.

AT THIS TIME, THE FMLN CRIMINALS ARE RECEIVING THE PUNISHEMENT THEY DESERVE THROUGH THE GLORIOUS WEAPONS OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES.

THE COWARDLY FMLN TERRORIST GROUPS HAVE BEEN HIDING SINCE 11 NOVEMBER IN THE HOMES OF DEFENSELESS CIVILIANS. THEY ARE COWARDS. THEY ARE LIKE THOSE COWARD CRIMINALS WHO AFTER COMMITTING MURDER RUN TO HIDE BEHIND A WOMAN'S SKIRT. THAT IS WHAT THOSE TERRORISTS ARE DOING. THEY ARE HIDING UNDER THE BEDS OF THE POPULATION, WHICH IS SUFFERING BECAUSE OF THE TERRORISTS' ATTACKS. THEY ARE COWARDS WHO HAVE TREACHEROUSLY ATTACKED AND BOMBED THE PEOPLE.

A FEW HOURS AGO, THE LIAR TERRORIST JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, FROM HIS HOTEL ROOM IN MANAGUA -- WHERE HE HAS AIR CONDITIONING AND LOTS OF FOOD -- SAID THAT THE FMLN HAS SEIZED POSITIONS, WHICH IS NOT TRUE. ALL TOWNS IN THE COUNTRY ARE UNDER THE GOVERNMENT'S POLITICAL CONTROL AND UNDER THE ARMED FORCES' MILITARY CONTROL.

WE MUST INFORM YOU THAT THERE ARE ONLY A FEW AREAS WHERE TERRORISTS HAVE SOUGHT REFUGE IN HOUSES AND ARE ACTING AS SNIPERS. HOWEVER, THE ARMED FORCES ARE TRYING TO DISLODGE THEM IN A PROFESSIONAL MANNER IN ORDER NOT TO HARM CIVILIANS.

THE COWARDS ARE HIDING IN A FEW AREAS. WE MUST TELL YOU THAT THE AREAS WHERE THERE IS SOME RESISTANCE ARE ILOPANGO, COLONIA SANTA LUCIA, SOYAPANGO, MEJICANOS, ZACAMIL, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, AND CIUDAD DELGADO.

SALVADORANS WHO ARE IN THOSE AREAS, VICTIMS OF THE TERRORISTS: FROM HERE YOUR SALVADORAN BROTHERS, YOUR BROTHERS IN THE ARMED FORCES, TELL YOU THAT WE ARE AT YOUR SIDE AT THIS TIME OF STRUGGLE, DURING THIS SAD TIME WHEN YOU ARE FACED WITH HUNGER AND DEATH THREATS BY THE FMLN TERRORIST HORDES. WE ARE AT YOUR SIDE, COMPATRIOT! WE ARE WITH YOU SALVADORAN PEOPLE! YOUR ARMED FORCES WILL NOT ABANDON YOU. YOU CAN BE SURE THAT ALL THIS WILL SOON BE OVER. WE WILL SOON DISLODGE THESE MANGY DOGS WHO HAVE COME WITH [NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL] ORTEGA'S WEAPONS AND TERRORIST HORDES, WHO HAVE COME HERE TO MASSACRE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. WE ARE WITH YOU COMPATRIOT! STAY WHERE YOU ARE. REMAIN CALM, AS YOU WILL SOON BE FREED FROM THE TERRORIST HORDES.

ILOPANGO, COLONIA SANTA LUCIA, SOYAPANGO, MEJICANOS, ZACAMIL, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, AND CIUDAD DELGADO: REMEMBER THAT YOUR GOVERNMENT AND CRISTIANI ARE AT THE HEAD OF THE ARMED FORCES, AND THAT YOUR ARMED FORCES ARE UNITEDLY, PROFESSIONALLY, AND PATRIOTICALLY STRUGGLING TO DEFEND YOU FROM THIS BRUTAL AND BESTIAL ATTACK THAT WE DENOUNCE BEFORE THE WORLD.

WHY IS IT THAT NO ONE SAYS ANYTHING? WHY DO JOURNALISTS IN EUROPE SAY NOTHING ABOUT WHAT IS HAPPENING? WHY DO THEY NOT TELL THE TRUTH? THEY ONLY REPEAT THE LIES OF RADIO VENCEREMOS AND THE LIAR RADIO FARABUNDO MARTI. THE PEOPLE'S TRUTH IS HERE. HERE IS THE TRUTH OF OUR PEOPLE, WHO HAVE ENDURED THE TERRORIST ATTACKS FOR 10 YEARS!

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: BE BRAVE AND UNITED, FULL OF PATRIOTISM, AND SURE OF OUR VICTORY. OUR FATHERLAND IS FREE! OUR ARMED FORCES ARE GLORIOUSLY FIGHTING! FORWARD, ARMED FORCES! FORWARD, SALVADORAN PEOPLE!

DEV-MUC3-0741 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, THIS IS A LAST-MINUTE REPORT FROM SAN SALVADOR: OUR FORCES HAVE OCCUPIED POSITIONS HELD BY THE NATIONAL POLICE IN CUSCATANCINGO. THE POLICEMEN WERE FORCED TO FLEE IN DISARRARY FROM A POSITION THAT THEY HAD HELD IN CUSCATANCINGO, NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

MEANWHILE, THE ENEMY IS USING M-79 ROCKET LAUNCHERS IN DOWNTOWN MEJICANOS. THE MARKET AREA AND THE PROJECTS HAVE BEEN AFFECTED.

WE REPEAT: A NATIONAL POLICE POSITION WAS ATTACKED BETWEEN 1310 AND 1350 [1910 AND 1950 GMT]. THE POLICEMEN, WHO ARE EXCELLENT AT REPRESSING THE PEOPLE AND THE COMMITTEES OF MOTHERS, FLED CUSCATANCINGO IN DISARRAY AFTER BEING ATTACKED BY FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT FORCES.

AT 1407 [2007 GMT], AN A-37 DRAGONFLY PLANE OVERFLEW AYUTUXTEPEQUE, MEJICANOS, AND ZACAMIL. OUR FIGHTERS ARE TRAINED TO FIRE AT THESE PLANES. THIRTY MINUTES AGO, A PUSH-AND-PULL 0-2 PLANE DROPPED BOMBS ON ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD AND A C-47 MACHINEGUNNED THE AREA.

AN A-37 PLANE IS NOW OVERFLYING NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR AFTER OUR COMRADES OCCUPIED A POSITION THAT THE NATIONAL POLICE HAD HELD IN CUSCATANCINGO.

DEV-MUC3-0742 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC SOURCES TODAY REVEALED THAT THE GUERRILLAS TRIED TO KIDNAP SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND OTHER OFFICIALS OF THE RIGHT-WING GOVERNMENT ON 11 NOVEMBER WHEN THEY LAUNCHED THE LARGEST MILITARY OFFENSIVE OF THE PAST 10 YEARS.

A NEIGHBOR OF THE PRESIDENT IN THE LUXURIOUS RESIDENTIAL AREA OF "MAQUILISHUAT," IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR, SAID THAT "THE GUERRILLAS MANAGED TO ENTER PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S HOME, BUT COULD NOT KIDNAP HIM BECAUSE HE WAS NOT THERE."

LEADERS OF THE RULING NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE (ARENA) HAVE CONFIRMED THAT GUERRILLAS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) HAD PLANNED TO KIDNAP PRESIDENT CRISTIANI "BUT WE DO NOT KNOW FOR WHAT PURPOSE."

A RANKING OFFICIAL TOLD ACAN - EFE THAT "WE HAVE AGREED THAT IN THE EVENT OF A KIDNAPPING THERE WOULD BE NO RESCUE."

"EVER SINCE WE WERE INSTALLED IN GOVERNMENT WE KNEW THAT WE COULD END UP ON THE FLOOR (DEAD)," SAID AN OFFICIAL WHO ASKED TO REMAIN ANONYMOUS.

DIPLOMATIC CIRCLES ARE ALSO COMMENTING ON REPORTS REGARDING THE KIDNAPPING OF CRISTIANI AND TOP GOVERNMENT LEADERS. THEY CONFIRMED TO ACAN - EFE THAT THE GUERRILLAS WHO ATTACKED CRISTIANI'S RESIDENCE WERE WEARING MILITARY UNIFORMS.

SOME SOURCES MAINTAIN THAT THE DISGUISED GUERRILLAS SUBDUED PRESIDENTIAL RESIDENCE GUARDS AND ENTERED CRISTIANI'S HOME, BUT NEITHER THE PRESIDENT NOR ANY OF HIS RELATIVES WERE THERE.

SOURCES CLOSE TO THE PRESIDENT ASSURE THAT CRISTIANI, HIS WIFE MARGARITA, AND OTHER RELATIVES WERE AT A COUNTRYSIDE HOME IN "COATEPEQUE LAKE," HOWEVER, THIS CLAIM COULD NOT BE CONFIRMED.

MOST MINISTERS AND GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS WERE RESTING AT COUNTRYSIDE HOMES IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE COUNTRY, BUT CONGRESS PRESIDENT RICARDO VALDIVIESO AND VICE PRESIDENT ROBERTO ANGULO WERE IN THEIR RESPECTIVE HOMES WHEN THE GUERRILLAS ATTACKED AND BOTH OF THEM FOUGHT BACK WITH THEIR WEAPONS.

THE FMLN ON 11 NOVEMBER BEGAN A LARGE-SCALE MILITARY OFFENSIVE WHICH INCLUDED ATTACKS AT MORE THAN 50 POINTS NATIONWIDE, ESPECIALLY ARMY POSITIONS. THESE ATTACKS HAVE YIELDED ABOUT 1,000 CASUALTIES AMONG CIVILIANS, REBELS, AND SOLDIERS.

SOME SOURCES CLAIM THAT THE RESIDENCE OF JULIO ADOLFO REY PRENDES, LEADER OF THE AUTHENTIC CHRISTIAN MOVEMENT (MAC), WAS ALSO ATTACKED BY THE GUERRILLAS, BUT THIS REPORT HAS NOT YET BEEN CONFIRMED.

FIERCE FIGHTING BETWEEN THE ARMY AND GUERRILLAS, ESPECIALLY IN DENSELY POPULATED NEIGHBORHOODS IN NORTHEAST SAN SALVADOR, WHERE THE REBELS ARE ENTRENCHED, CONTINUES THREE DAYS AFTER THE OFFENSIVE BEGAN.

COMMANDER JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, ONE OF THE FIVE TOP FMLN LEADERS, ANNOUNCED THAT 7 OF THE COUNTRY'S 14 DEPARTMENTS WERE DECLARED "FREED ZONES."

THE REBELS MAINTAIN THAT THE OFFENSIVE IS DESIGNED TO BRING THE GOVERNMENT AND FMLN "TO AN EQUAL FOOTING" IN SEEKING A NEGOTIATED POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE WAR CONFLICT.

A GUERRILLA WHO WAS INTERVIEWED BY ACAN - EFE IN A SAN SALVADOR NEIGHBORHOOD SAID THAT "THE OFFENSIVE AIMS TO TOPPLE PRESIDENT CRISTIANI AND DESTROY THE FASCIST REPRESSIVE PLAN."

SOME DIPLOMATS MAINTAIN THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND ARMY HAD BEEN EXPECTING THIS OFFENSIVE FOR SEVERAL MONTHS, BUT UNDERESTIMATED IT, BECAUSE THEY THOUGHT THAT THERE WOULD BE TWO OR THREE VIOLENT OUTBREAKS AND NOT A NATIONWIDE LARGE-SCALE OFFENSIVE SUCH AS THE ONE THAT BEGAN ON 11 NOVEMBER.

"WE CANNOT FIGURE OUT HOW THE GUERRILLAS MANAGED TO REACH CRISTIANI'S RESIDENCE," A SOURCE SAID.

DEV-MUC3-0744 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [INTERVIEW WITH MERCEDES DEL CARMEN LETONA, FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT COMMANDER, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH HYPOCRITICALLY REGRETTED TODAY THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HAS TURNED THE REGION'S PEACE AGREEMENTS INTO A SENSELESS BLOODBATH WITH THE OFFENSIVE IT LAUNCHED ON 11 NOVEMBER. WHAT CAN YOU SAY ABOUT THIS?

[LETONA] I WOULD SAY THAT PRESIDENT BUSH'S REMARKS ARE VERY CYNICAL. HE SAID THAT A POLITICAL SOLUTION WAS BEING SOUGHT IN CENTRAL AMERICA AND WITH THIS ACTION, WE HAD BROKEN THE POLITICAL PATH AND SOUGHT OTHER OPTIONS. I THINK THE PEOPLE WHO BROKE THE PATH ARE THE UNITED STATES. WE MUST RECALL THAT WHILE WE WERE HOLDING TALKS IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA AND DEMANDING THE REMOVAL OF LA TANDONA [NAME GIVEN TO 1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] AND DEMANDING JUSTICE AGAINST THE DEATH SQUADS IN ORDER TO FIND A POLITICAL SOLUTION AND PARTICIPATE IN ELECTIONS, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT APPROVED MORE AID FOR THE FASCIST SECTORS, THE VERY SECTORS THAT WERE IN FACT REPRESSING THE PEOPLE AND CARRYING OUT SUCH DRAMATIC AND HORRIBLE ACTIONS AS THE ONE PERPETRATED AGAINST THE FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] BUILDING. THESE ACTIONS CONTINUE AND HAVE BEEN REPEATED EVERY DAY IN EL SALVADOR.

THEREFORE, THE FIRST ONES TO BURY THE POLITICAL POSSIBILITY WERE THE UNITED STATES. THE FIRST ONES TO GIVE WEAPONS TO THE FASCISTS TO CONTINUE KILLING PEOPLE WERE THE UNITED STATES. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE CANNOT WAIT FOR THE FASCISTS TO KILL THEM ALL. THAT IS NO WAY TO ATTAIN PEACE, MUCH LESS DEMOCRACY IN EL SALVADOR. THAT IS WHAT THE UNITED STATES DID. RIGHT NOW WHEN WE ARE INVOLVED IN AN OFFENSIVE, WHO ARE THE ONES GUILTY OF GENOCIDE AGAINST THE PEOPLE? THE UNITED STATES. THOSE BOMBS AND THOSE ROCKETS THAT ARE FALLING ON CIVILIANS ARE BOMBS AND ROCKETS PROVIDED BY THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION TO THE SALVADORAN ARMY.

THE ONES WHO HAVE BLOCKED THE POSSIBILITY OF PEACE AND NEGOTIATION IN EL SALVADOR ARE THE UNITED STATES. WE WANTED TO REMOVE LA TANDONA AND THE GOVERNMENT'S DEATH SQUADS THROUGH POLITICAL MEANS BUT THAT WAS IMPOSSIBLE. SO, WE ARE DOING IT THROUGH THE COMBAT OF OUR FORCES AND WITH THE COOPERATION OF ALL THE PEOPLE.

DEV-MUC3-0745 (U NEBRASKA)

MANAGUA, 14 NOV 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] A LEADER OF THE INSURRECTIONAL MOVEMENT IN EL SALVADOR TODAY SAID IN MANAGUA THAT THE MILITARY CAMPAIGN THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS HAVE LAUNCHED AGAINST ARMY TROOPS ON VARIOUS FRONTS AIMS TO CREATE THE APPROPRIATE CONDITIONS FOR A "GENUINE DIALOGUE" WITH GUARANTEES FOR THE PEOPLE.

COMMANDER MARIO LOPEZ, MEMBER OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT'S (FMLN) POLITICAL COMMISSION, SAID THAT THE REBELS HAVE ORDERS TO "ADVANCE" AND CONTROL THE "FREED ZONES" AS PART OF ITS STRUGGLE AGAINST THE ARMY OF ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S "FASCIST GOVERNMENT, WHICH IS MAINTAINING A SOCIALLY UNJUST REGIME.

LOPEZ, WHO IS ALSO KNOWN AS "COMMANDER VENANCIO SALVATIERRA," SAID THAT THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HAS USED MORE THAN 15 AIRCRAFTS TO BOMB CIVILIANS IN SOYAPANGO, ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR, AND NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN MIGUEL, CAUSING SERIOUS STRUCTURAL DAMAGE AND KILLING CIVILIANS.

THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLA LEADER POINTED OUT THAT THE FMLN MILITARY CAMPAIGN, WHICH BEGAN WITH NATIONWIDE ATTACKS ON 11 NOVEMBER, HAS ENJOYED "POPULAR SUPPORT" WHICH MAKES IT "AN INSURRECTION WHOSE SCOPE IS DIFFICULT TO GAUGE."

HE ADDED THAT THIS REACTION MEANS THAT THE FMLN "CANNOT ALLOW BLOWS AGAINST THE PEOPLE TO TAKE PLACE WITH IMPUNITY."

"WE ARE SEEKING A CHANGE IN THE CORRELATION OF FORCES THAT WOULD BRING ABOUT APPROPRIATE CONDITIONS FOR A GENUINE DIALOGUE," MARIO LOPEZ POINTED OUT. HE ADDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT OF ALFREDO CRISTIANI MUST "QUIT HOPING FOR A MILITARY VICTORY OVER THE FMLN."

AS FOR EFFORTS TO BRING ABOUT A DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT, LOPEZ SAID THAT EFFORTS ARE BEING MADE BY VARIOUS GOVERNMENTS TO PREVENT THE GENOCIDAL ACTIONS OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY. HE SAID THAT THE FMLN IS MAKING SUCH EFFORTS AT THE UNITED NATIONS AND OAS WHERE NICARAGUA HAS PROPOSED A RESUMPTION OF NEGOTIATIONS.

HE ADDED THAT FOR THE TIME BEING, THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS ARE ORGANIZING "POPULAR GOVERNMENTS" IN THE "FREED ZONES," HOWEVER, HE SAID NOTHING ABOUT THE ETABLISHMENT OF A PROVISIONAL FMLN GOVERNMENT.

LOPEZ SAID THAT AN INTERVENTION BY THE GUATEMALAN ARMY IN THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT, BY SUPPORTING THE CRISTIANI ARMY, "WOULD BE DANGEROUS FOR CENTRAL AMERICA BECAUSE THE CONFLICT COULD BE SPREADED." HE RECALLED THAT GUATEMALA IS FACING A GUERRILLA STRUGGLE WHICH IS OLDER THAN THE ONE IN EL SALVADOR.

LOPEZ DENIED THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS EXIST BECAUSE OF THE USSR, CUBA, AND NICARAGUA AND ADDED THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLA STRUGGLE IS OLDER THAN THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT ITSELF (1979). HE ADDED THAT THE FMLN HAS DEVELOPED ITS OWN STRATEGIES AND EVEN ITS OWN WEAPONS, HOWEVER, HE ADMITTED THAT IT RECEIVES WEAPONS FROM ABROAD. HE PROVIDED NO FUTHER DETAILS ON THE FMLN'S "OWN" WEAPONS.

DEV-MUC3-0747 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 14 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [STATEMENT] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] THE ARMY FAILED TODAY IN ITS ATTEMPT TO RECOVER THE POSITIONS TAKEN OVER BY OUR FORCES ON 11 NOVEMBER IN THE COUNTRY'S MAIN CITIES.

THE ENEMY'S COUNTEROFFENSIVE RESULTED IN MORE BLOODSHED AMONG ITS RANKS. THE ARMY SOWED TERROR AND DEATH AMONG THE CIVILIAN POPULATION BY CARRYING OUT INDISCRIMINATE MACHINEGUNNING AND BOMBINGS AGAINST DENSELY POPULATED AREAS IN APOPA, THE HERMITA AND OBRERA NEIGHBORHOODS, THE CEMETERY AREA, THE SANTA ELENA NEIGHBORHOOD, THE OUTSKIRTS OF USULUTAN, LA ESMERALDA NEIGHBORHOOD, LA COQUERA AND EL GRANILLO IN SAN MIGUEL, THE NORTHERN MAIN HIGHWAY, ZACATECOLUCA, SOYAPANGO, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, AND ZACAMIL.

IN MANY OF THESE PLACES, THE AIR RAIDS LASTED PRACTICALLY ALL DAY, PRODUCING NUMEROUS CASUALTIES AMONG MEN, WOMEN, AND CHILDREN, AND DESTROYING MANY HOUSES AND OTHER BUILDINGS.

IN OVERCOMING THE ARMY'S COUNTEROFFENSIVE, WE HAVE MAINTAINED ABSOLUTE CONTROL OF ALL OUR POSITIONS IN THE VARIOUS PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

WE HAVE INFLICTED THE FOLLOWING CUMULATIVE DAMAGE TO THE ENEMY: APPROXIMATELY 760 CASUALTIES, 24 ARMORED VEHICLES OUT OF COMBAT, AS WELL AS 11 HELICOPTERS AND PLANES.

SUPPORT FOR THE TRANSPORTATION STOPPAGE HAS BEEN TOTAL IN ALMOST ALL PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

ONLY 24 HOURS AFTER SUMMONING THE PEOPLE FOR A GENERAL REBELLION, PEOPLE HAVE MASSIVELY JOINED IN THE TASKS OF COLLABORATION AND SUPPORT OR HAVE DIRECTLY PARTICIPATED IN COMBAT.

THE DECREE DECLARING A 24-HOUR CURFEW IN THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR SHOWS THAT WHAT THE ARMY IS FACING THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY IS NOT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] BUT THE PEOPLE'S GROWING REBELLION.

OUR HEROIC FIGHTERS HAVE RESPONDED WITH THE USUAL VIGOR AND EFFICIENCY TO THE ORDER GIVEN BY OUR GENERAL COMMAND TO HOLD THE POSITIONS CONQUERED AND IMMEDIATELY ORGANIZE THE PEOPLE'S GENERAL UPRISING.

OUT WITH THE FASCISTS; FEBE ELIZABETH LIVES!

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANCHEZ SEREN, FRANCISCO JOVEL, EDUARDO SANCHO, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, AND JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS EL SALVADOR, 14 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0748 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 NOV 89 (LA PRENSA GRAFICA) -- [TEXT] OFFICIALS REPORTED THAT 220 TERRORISTS HAVE BEEN KILLED, 196 WOUNDED, AND 22 CAPTURED DURING THE CLASHES THAT TOOK PLACE IN THE AREA OF THE UNIVERSITY AND ITS OUTSKIRTS.

AMONG THE WAR MATERIEL CONFISCATED: A SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILE, 140 HIGH-CALIBER RIFLES, 6 LAW ROCKET LAUNCHERS, AND MACHINEGUNS.

AN ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE COPREFA SPOKESMAN STATED THAT THEY WERE NOT AUTHORIZED TO RELEASE ANY OFFICIAL INFORMATION ON THE 11, 12, AND 13 NOVEMBER EVENTS.

MILITARY SOURCES WHO WERE QUESTIONED STATED THAT ACCORDING TO INITIAL REPORTS--REPORTS WHICH ARE UNOFFICIAL AND COVER ONLY UP TO THE AFTERNOON OF 13 NOVEMBER--RECEIVED FROM SOLDIERS WHO FOUGHT AGAINST THE EXTREMISTS POSITIONED AT THE EL SALVADOR UNIVERSITY, THE TERRORISTS SUFFERED MORE THAN 400 CASUALTIES. THESE CASUALTIES WERE DISTRIBUTED IN THE FOLLOWING MANNER: 220 KILLED, 196 WOUNDED, AND 22 CAPTURED.

THE CONFISCATED WAR MATERIEL INCLUDED A SOVIET-MADE SURFACE-TO- AIR MISSILE--CONSIDERED THE MOST IMPORTANT CATCH; 140 HIGH-CALIBER RIFLES INCLUDING 74 AK-47 ASSAULT RIFLES, LAW ROCKET LAUNCHERS, 2 M- 79 GRENADE LAUNCHERS, 3 UZI MACHINEGUNS, 50 GRENADES, 2 DRAGUNOV RIFLES FOR SNIPERS, AND 38 BLASTING CAPS, APPROXIMATELY 1000 M-16 CARTRIDGES; AND 136 AK-47 CARTRIDGES.

ALSO CONFISCATED WERE FOUR KNAPSACKS CONTAINING CLOTHING AND COMMUNIST PROPAGANDA, FIVE TNT BLOCKS, TWO OLIVE-GREEN UNIFORMS, AND MATERIAL TO MANUFACTURE EXPLOSIVES.

OFFICIALS REPORTED THAT THE CONFISCATED SOVIET MISSILE WAS PART OF A 15-MISSILE LOT THAT ENTERED SALVADORAN TERRITORY FROM NICARAGUA AND THAT HAD ORIGINALLY BEEN STORED IN PERQUIN, MORAZAN DEPARTMENT.

THE SOURCE ADDED THAT IT WAS A VERY SOPHISTICATED WEAPON AND THAT ITS PRESENCE IN SALVADORAN TERRITORY CONFIRMS THAT ONCE AGAIN THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT HAS SUPPLIED WEAPONS TO THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT CONTINUES TO SUPPLY WEAPONS DESPITE THE PROMISE MADE BY PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA AT TELA, HONDURAS THAT HIS REGIME WOULD NO LONGER SUPPLY WEAPONS TO THE SALVADORAN TERRORIST GROUPS.

DEV-MUC3-0749 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] GOOD EVENING, SALVADORAN PEOPLE--IF I MAY SAY, SO DESPITE THE CIRCUMSTANCES AFFECTING THE CAPITAL CITY. IT IS REGRETTABLE AND INCONCEIVABLE THAT THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] SHOULD PERSIST WITH THE AGGRESSION IT HAS UNLEASHED AGAINST OUR CAPITAL CITY AND SURROUNDING MUNICIPALITIES. OUR POPULATION HAS SUFFERED THE MOST FROM THIS FMLN AGGRESSION.

THIS AGGRESSION, SALVADORAN FRIENDS, MUST BE SEEN AS AN ACT OF DESPERATION BY THE FMLN, AS THIS IS THE ONLY WAY WE CAN EXPLAIN THEIR IRRATIONAL ACTIONS. I HAVE USED THE WORD DESPERATION BECAUSE THE FMLN KNOWS THAT IT IS OUT OF STYLE AND THAT ITS ATTITUDES ARE NO LONGER ACCEPTED IN THE WORLD. WE CAN SEE IN EUROPE THAT COUNTRIES HAVE PASSED FROM TOTALITARIAN REGIMES SUCH AS THE ONE THAT THE FMLN WANTS TO IMPLEMENT HERE, AND WALLS ARE OPEN FOR LIBERTY AND DEMOCRACY.

WE ARE SURE THAT THIS IS WHAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WANT: LIBERTY AND DEMOCRACY. THAT IS WHY THEY HAVE NOT SUPPORTED AND WILL NEVER SUPPORT THE FMLN TERRORISTS WHO WANT TO SUBJECT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO TOTALITARIAN REGIMES, TO DICTATORSHIPS OF OPPRESSION, REPRESSION, AND VIOLATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS.

I WAS SAYING THAT THIS IS A DESPERATE ACT BECAUSE WE CANNOT SEE HOW ANYONE WHO IS NOT DESPERATE COULD CAUSE SO MUCH HARM TO INNOCENT PEOPLE AND TO THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THERE ARE ALREADY MORE THAN 100 DEAD OR WOUNDED BECAUSE OF THE FMLN'S IRRATIONAL ACTIONS. OF COURSE, TO THAT WE MUST ADD THAT THEY DESTROYED MANY HOMES WHICH THEY ENTERED AND HAVE HELD FAMILIES AS HOSTAGES. THEY HAVE DAMAGED THE ELECTRICITY, POTABLE WATER, AND TELEPHONE SYSTEMS, DEPRIVING THE POPULATION OF THOSE ESSENTIAL SERVICES, NOT TO MENTION THE LACK OF FOOD AFFECTING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN THE AREAS WHERE THEY ARE HOLDING HOSTAGES.

IN ADDITION, IT IS APPROPRIATE TO SEE HOW FAR THE FMLN TERRORISTS' IRRATIONAL MINDS CAN GO, BECAUSE THEY HAVE CARRIED OUT ACTS OF SAVAGERY THAT WE CANNOT UNDERSTAND. HOW CAN THERE STILL BE ANYONE LIKE THE NICARAGUANS--AND I AM TALKING ABOUT THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT, OF COURSE, NOT ALL NICARAGUANS--AND THE CUBANS, WHO SUPPORT SUCH ACTS OF SAVAGERY.

HOLDING CIVILIANS AS HOSTAGES, PUTTING THEM IN THE MIDDLE SO THAT THEY WILL BE THE ONES WHO ARE HURT, AND SHIELDING THEMSELVES BEHIND INNOCENT PEOPLE IS AN ACT OF SAVAGERY, SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

TAKING OVER A CENTER FOR ORPHAN CHILDREN IN ORDER TO PROTECT THEMSELVES BEHIND LITTLE CHILDREN WHO DO NOT HAVE A FATHER OR A MOTHER IS AN ACT OF SAVAGERY, SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

THEY EVEN DID SOMETHING WORSE AT THE ZACATECOLUCA HOSPITAL AND THE PEOPLE WITNESSED THIS. WHEN THEY ENTERED THE HOSPITAL IN ZACATECOLUCA, THEY MURDERED, AT GUNPOINT, A SOLDIER WHO WAS RECEIVING MEDICAL ATTENTION; THEY PLACED BOMBS INSIDE THE HOSPITAL AND THEN FLED.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: THE FMLN IS ALREADY A DESPERATE BEAST. THIS IS THE ONLY THING WE CAN SAY ABOUT SUCH IRRATIONAL MINDS. HOWEVER, WE MUST REALIZE AND UNDERSTAND, AND ABOVE ALL, BE SURE THAT THE MAJORITY OF OUR PEOPLE REPUDIATE THE FMLN TERRORISTS.

THE PEOPLE MUST KNOW THAT THEY CAN COUNT ON THEIR ARMED FORCES WHICH HAVE ADVANCED SLOWLY, BUT SURELY. IT IS ADVANCING SLOWLY BECAUSE IT WANTS TO FULLY PROTECT THE LIVES OF CIVILIANS. THE ARMED FORCES COULD DRIVE THOSE TERRORISTS OUT OF WHERE THEY ARE; HOWEVER, THERE ARE CIVILIANS THERE, AND WE WOULD NEVER WANT TO EXPOSE THOSE CIVILIANS TO THE DANGER THE FMLN IS TRYING TO LEAD THEM INTO. THE ARMED FORCES HAVE CONTINUED TO ADVANCE. THEY HAVE EFFECTIVELY ADVANCED, USING PROFESSIONAL MEANS. FOR EXAMPLE, NEIGHBORHOODS SUCH AS BOSQUES DEL RIO ARE TOTALLY CALM NOW, BECAUSE THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ALREADY ENTERED AND FORCED THE TERRORISTS OUT. WE KNOW THAT ALL OF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SEE AN END TO THIS TERROR THAT THE FMLN WANTS TO CREATE. HOWEVER, WE MUST ALSO UNDERSTAND, PARTICULARLY THOSE OF US WHO ARE NOT AS ANGUISHED AT THIS MOMENT AS THOSE FAMILIES THAT HAVE BECOME FMLN HOSTAGES. THEY TOO, DESERVE THAT WE DO EVERYTHING WE CAN TO ACHIEVE OUR OBJECTIVE; HOWEVER, WE MUST DO SO RESPECTING THE LIVES OF THOSE INNOCENT PEOPLE. THE FMLN FAILED TO ACHIEVE ITS OBJECTIVE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0750 (U NEBRASKA)

HAVANA (CUBA), 15 NOV 89 (TELE-REBELDE NETWORK) -- [EXCERPTS] COMMANDER IN CHIEF FIDEL CASTRO RUZ, FIRST SECRETARY OF THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF CUBA AND PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCILS OF STATE AND MINISTERS, LAST NIGHT GRANTED AN EXCLUSIVE INTERVIEW TO OUR REPORTER, OSCAR SUAREZ, AT THE INAUGURATION OF THE MADRID RESTAURANT IN HABANA VIEJA. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CASTRO] TODAY IS AN IMPORTANT DAY. TODAY, WHEN WE ARE COMMEMORATING THE 470TH ANNIVERSARY OF HAVANA, WE RECEIVED THE NEWS OF THE CRUSHING TRIUMPH OF THE SOUTH-WEST AFRICAN PEOPLE'S ORGANIZATION IN THE NAMIBIAN ELECTIONS BY 57 PERCENT. IT IS A VERY GOOD PERCENTAGE.

ON THE OTHER HAND, WE ALSO RECEIVED THE NEWS....[REPHRASES] WE ADMIRE THE HEROISM WITH WHICH THE SALVADORANS ARE FIGHTING. IT IS SOMETHING VERY IMPRESSIVE. IT IS A LIKE A LESSON TO IMPERIALISM WHICH IS EUPHORIC AND THINKS THAT THE WORLD IS AT ITS FEET. THEY THINK THAT...

[SUAREZ, INTERRUPTING] [WORDS INDISTINCT] WHICH IS TERRIBLE.

[CASTRO] I BELIEVE THE ACTIONS THAT THE SALVADORANS ARE PRESENTLY CARRYING OUT ARE ONE OF THE MOST EXTRAORDINARY FEATS THAT HAVE EVER BEEN WRITTEN. DESPITE THE 10 YEARS [OF STRUGGLE], THE BILLIONS THAT THE UNITED STATES HAS INVESTED IN CREATING THE SALVADORAN ARMY AND SUPPLYING IT WITH THE MOST MODERN TYPES OF ARMS, NOTICE HOW THOSE PEOPLE CAN FIGHT. NOTICE WHAT IS BEING DONE. HOW ARE THEY USING THE YANKEE BOMBS AND PLANES? THEY ARE BEING USED TO MASSACRE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. JUST NOTICE HOW THEY ARE INDISCRIMINATELY BOMBING THE PEOPLE'S NEIGHBORHOODS WHICH ARE IN THE HANDS OF THE REVOLUTIONARIES. WHAT THE IMPERIALISTS ARE DOING IS SOMETHING REPUGNANT. HOWEVER, I THINK THAT WHAT THE SALVADORANS ARE DOING IS AMAZING, ADMIRABLE. WHAT THEY ARE DOING IS SHOWING THE IMPERIALISTS THAT THE PEOPLE ARE FAR FROM KNEELING BEFORE THEM. THEIR ACTIONS ARE SHOWING IMPERIALISM THAT THE PEOPLE WILL CONTINUE FIGHTING WITHOUT CARING ABOUT THE EUPHORIA THAT CURRENTLY OVERCOMES THEM UNDER THESE CIRCUMSTANCES.

[SUAREZ] COMMANDER, WHAT ELSE CAN YOU SAY ON THE SUBJECT OF WHY WE HAVE SO MANY FRIENDS? WE, THE CUBANS ARE WHAT WE ARE BECAUSE WE ARE A MIXTURE OF SPANISH AND AFRICAN.

[CASTRO] I THINK WE HAVE THE FRIENDS WE DO BECAUSE WE HAVE FOLLOWED A POLICY OF PRINCIPLE. I THINK THE FRIENDS WE HAVE ARE BASICALLY DUE TO THE PRESTIGE OF THE REVOLUTION, THE RESPECT THE REVOLUTION MERITS, THE ETHICS OF THE REVOLUTION, AND THE PRINCIPLES OF THE REVOLUTION. NOW, THE FACT THAT WE ARE ALSO A MIXTURE OF CARIBBEANS, THAT IS SOMETHING ELSE. THAT HAS NOTHING TO DO WITH POLITICS. [WORD INDISTINCT] REASONS WE CAN HAVE CONGENIALITY. HOWEVER, CONGENIALITY DOES NOT ALWAYS TURN INTO TRUE FRIENDSHIP. THERE COULD BE CONGENIALITY BUT IT DOES NOT RESULT IN FRIENDSHIP. FRIENDSHIP IS MORE A RESULT OF RECOGNITION, ADMIRATION FOR A COUNTRY.

[SUREZ] DO YOU BELIEVE THAT...

[CASTRO] THIS SMALL COUNTRY WAS FACING THE EMPIRE, IT BECAME A BASTION OF DIGNITY FOR THE WORLD. I THINK THIS MERITS CERTAIN RECOGNITION AND LIKING. WE CAN BE PROUD OF THAT AND OF THE FRIENDS WE HAVE. I APPRECIATE THESE FRIENDS WHO ARE FRIENDS OF CUBA DESPITE YANKEE PRESSURES. THEY ARE FRIENDS OF CUBA DESPITE YANKEE THREATS, INTRIGUES, AND CAMPAIGNS. THIS SAYS A LOT. THE YANKEES WANTED TO BURY AND DISCREDIT THE REVOLUTION WITH THE MEDIA AGENCIES THEY OWN. HOWEVER, THEY HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO ACHIEVE THAT. THAT IS WHY UNDER THESE CIRCUMSTANCES WE REALLY APPRECIATE THE FRIENDSHIP AND SOLIDARITY THAT OTHER NATIONS RENDER US. ASIDE, FROM THAT, WE ARE CARIBBEANS. WE ARE A GOOD MIXTURE. WE ARE A MIXTURE OF WHICH WE ARE PROUD. WE ARE A MIXTURE OF INDIAN, AFRICAN, AND EUROPEAN. THAT MIXTURE HAS TURNED OUT TO BE VERY GOOD.

[SUAREZ] WE ALSO HAVE CHINESE MIXTURE IN US.

[CASTRO] THAT IS TRUE, YOU ARE CORRECT IN REMINDING US OF IT. I THINK THIS MIXTURE HAS ALSO HELPED TO ENRICH THE VIRTUES OF OUR NATION. [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0753 (U NEBRASKA)

GUATEMALA CITY, 15 NOV 89 (ACAN EFE) -- [TEXT] GUATEMALAN SECURITY FORCES LAST NIGHT DEFUSED A BOMB PLANTED IN FRONT OF THE SALVADORAN EMBASSY IN GUATEMALA CITY, THE POLICE REPORTED TODAY.

THE POLICE ALSO REPORTED THAT TWO BOMBS EXPLODED LAST NIGHT AND DESTROYED TWO TELEPHONE JUNCTION BOXES IN SEPARATE LOCATIONS IN THE CAPITAL. THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES. THE EXPLOSIONS, HOWEVER, CAUSED GREAT ALARM AND PROMPTED SEVERAL POLICE PATROL CARS TO COMB THE AREAS IN SEARCH OF THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ACTIONS, THE SOURCE ADDED.

A SQUAD DEFUSED A HIGH - POWER BOMB THAT HAD BEEN PLANTED IN FRONT OF THE SALVADORAN EMBASSY.

NO VICTIMS AT THE SITE OF THE EXPLOSIONS WERE REPORTED. THE DAMAGE ON THE JUNCTION BOXES, HOWEVER, WILL PROBABLY BE COSTLY TO THE STATE TELEPHONE ORGANIZATION.

THESE ATTACKS ARE IN ADDITION TO THE ONE SUSTAINED BY THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE OPPOSITION RIGHTIST NATIONAL LIBERATION MOVEMENT [MLN] LAST WEEK. THE EXPLOSION DEMOLISHED MOST OF THE OFFICE.

SO FAR, NO GROUP OR ORGANIZATION HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THESE TERRORIST ATTACKS.

DEV-MUC3-0754 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 15 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMY TODAY ATTACKED BY LAND AND AIR THE GUERRILLAS WHO EARLY THIS MORNING OCCUPIED CIUDAD MERLIOT, A MIDDLE-CLASS RESIDENTIAL AREA IN SOUTHWESTERN SAN SALVADOR.

AN "A-37" SALVADORAN AIR FORCE PLANE FLEW OVER THE AREA AND STRAFED CERTAIN POINTS, WHILE ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS WENT THROUGH THE STREETS AND INFANTRY SOLDIERS CONFRONTED THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GUERRILLAS.

THE REBELS, WHO HAVE BEEN FIGHTING SINCE 11 NOVEMBER IN THE CAPITAL CITY, TOOK POSITIONS IN CIUDAD MERLIOT VERY EARLY THIS MORNING AND BURNED BUSES AND TRUCKS, AND THEN PLACED THE CHARRED VEHICLES AS BARRICADES ON THE MAIN ENTRANCES TO THE RESIDENTIAL AREAS.

THE GUERRILLAS ALSO CUT OFF ACCESS TO THE MAIN HIGHWAY JOINING SAN SALVADOR TO SANTA ANA, THE SECOND MOST IMPORTANT CITY IN THE COUNTRY, AND LA LIBERTAD PORT.

AT LEAST FIVE ARMY ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS WERE CONTINUOUSLY FIRING ON THE GUERRILLA POSITIONS IN CIUDAD MERLIOT.

"GET AWAY. THIS IS A PROHIBITED AREA. THERE IS HEAVY SHOOTING AGAINST THE GUERRILLAS," SHOUTED A SOLDIER FROM ONE OF THE ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS TO AN ACAN-EFE CORRESPONDENT WHO WAS MOMENTARILY TRAPPED ON ONE OF THE MAIN STREETS OF THE RESIDENTIAL AREA.

THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS ON 11 NOVEMBER BEGAN THE GREATEST MILITARY OFFENSIVE OF THE LAST 10 YEARS, INFLICTING OVER 1,000 CASUALTIES, ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES.

DEV-MUC3-0755 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 15 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] "ATTENTION, PAY CLOSE ATTENTION. WE CALL ON THE INTERNATIONAL COMMITTEE OF THE RED CROSS, THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS, BROTHER PEOPLES OF THE WORLD. WE HAVE CONTACTED [FMLN GUERRILLA COMMANDER] MARISOL GALINDO IN SAN MIGUEL CITY. SHE REPORTS THAT RIGHT NOW COLONEL VARGAS IS FOLLOWING A SUICIDAL AND GENOCIDAL ATTITUDE AND IS BOMBING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN SAN MIGUEL.

"THERE ARE MANY DEAD AND WOUNDED DUE TO THE 500-LB BOMBS, THE ROCKETS, AND THE STRAFING BY THE AIR FORCE IN THE NORTHERN AREA OF SAN MIGUEL CITY. BOMBS AND ROCKETS HAVE BEEN DROPPED IN THE CITY, KILLING AND WOUNDING MANY PERSONS IN SAN MIGUEL CITY.

"WE URGENTLY CALL ON THE INTERNATIONAL COMMITTEE OF THE RED CROSS TO IMMEDIATELY EVACUATE DOZENS OF WOMEN, CHILDREN, AND ELDERLY WHO HAVE BEEN GRAVELY WOUNDED BY THIS IRRESPONSIBLE AND GENOCIDAL BOMBING BY COL MAURICIO VARGAS, CHIEF OF THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE. WE CALL ON THE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD SO THAT IMMEDIATELY THEY WILL DENOUNCE BEFORE THE WORLD WHAT IS HAPPENING IN SAN MIGUEL CITY. SOMOZA'S BOMBING OF THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE IS ONE-THOUSAND TIMES WORSE IN EL SALVADOR."

DEV-MUC3-0758 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 16 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, ATTENTION, THE ARMED FORCES' COUNTERATTACK ON OUR POSITIONS IN ZACAMIL HAS FAILED. ATTENTION, AT THIS TIME RADIO VENCEREMOS PROCLAIMS THAT THE NEW ARMED FORCES' COUNTEROFFENSIVE TO ATTACK OUR POSITIONS IN ZACAMIL HAS FAILED.

A REPORT SENT BY COMRADES COMMANDER CLAUDIO RABINDRANATH ARMIJO AND CARLOS ARGUETA INDICATE THAT THE ENEMY ATTEMPT TO TAKE OUR POSITIONS IN ZACAMIL FAILED.

AT 0400 TODAY, AN IMPORTANT BATTLE WAS FOUGHT IN ZACAMIL. COMBINED TROOPS OF THE BELLOSO AND BRACAMONTE BATTALIONS, AND A CAVALRY UNIT, WITH THE SUPPORT OF ONE HELICOPTER AND ONE OR TWO LIGHT PLANES, TRIED TO ATTACK OUR FORTIFIED POSITIONS. HOWEVER, THIS ATTEMPT ENDED IN A RESOUNDING FAILURE. THE ENEMY SUSTAINED 45 CASUALTIES IN THE ATTACK, WHICH LASTED FROM 0400 UNTIL 1100. THESE CASUALTIES, WHICH HAVE BEEN CONFIRMED, INCLUDED A SECTION CHIEF. IN ADDITION, OUR FORCES DESTROYED ONE ARMORED VEHICLE AND DAMAGED ANOTHER. WE ALSO HAVE A BELLOSO BATTALION PATROL TRAPPED IN ONE OF THE BUILDINGS. SOME MEMBERS OF THIS PATROL WERE WOUNDED, OTHERS WERE KILLED IN ACTION.

IN ITS DESPERATION, THE ARMY HAS USED THE AIR FORCE FOR ITS INDISCRIMINATE ATTACKS.

THIS IS A LAST-MINUTE REPORT WE HAVE FROM SAN SALVADOR: THE ENEMY COUNTERATTACK FAILED IN ZACAMIL. BY NOON, OUR FORCES HAD HAD CONTROLLED THIS ATTACK. THE SITUATION IN SAN SALVADOR IS BECOMING MORE CRITICAL FOR THE GENERAL STAFF WITH THE FALL OF THE CUSCATANCINGO GARRISON, WHERE OUR FORCES SEIZED THOUSANDS OF ITEMS OF MILITARY SUPPLIES AND AMMUNITION.

DEV-MUC3-0760 (U NEBRASKA)

WASHINGTON DC (UNITED STATES), 16 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN FOREIGN MINISTER JOSE MANUEL PACAS CASTRO TODAY CONDEMNED THE ASSASSINATION OF SIX JESUITS AND TWO WOMEN IN HIS COUNTRY, AND HE BLAMED THE ULTRALEFTIST GROUPS FOR IT, ALTHOUGH HE SAID HE HAD NO PROOF.

"IT IS A REPUGNANT CRIME," SAID THE FOREIGN MINISTER, WHO WAS ATTENDING THE 19TH OAS GENERAL ASSEMBLY, AND HE DESCRIBED THE ASSASSINATIONS AS A "DESPERATE ACTION TAKEN BY THE LEFT."

JOAO BAENA SOARES, SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE OAS, WAS ASKED TODAY TO REPORT TO THE ASSEMBLY ON THE SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR IN COMPLIANCE WITH THE RESOLUTION ON THAT COUNTRY THAT WAS APPROVED ON TUESDAY.

A COMMUNIQUE RELEASED TODAY BY A FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] SPOKESMAN IN WASHINGTON BLAMED THE SALVADORAN ARMY FOR THE CRIME, AND ADDED THAT "ALL OF THE BODIES HAD BULLET WOUNDS IN THE HEAD, INDICATING THAT THEY WERE EXECUTED."

PACAS CASTRO SAID TODAY THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT, HEADED BY ALFREDO CRISTIANI, WILL MAINTAIN ITS COMMITMENT TO A DIALOGUE TO DISCUSS THE SUSPENSION OF THE HOSTILITIES AND TO IMPLEMENT AN INTERNAL PEACE PROCESS.

MOREOVER, HE ANNOUNCED THAT AN OFFICIAL MISSION, CAPABLE OF MAKING DECISIONS AND COMMITMENTS, WILL TRAVEL TO CARACAS IN THE HOPE OF MEETING WITH REPRESENTATIVES OF THE FMLN GUERRILLAS.

THE SALVADORAN FOREIGN MINISTER SAID THE SITUATION IN HIS COUNTRY IS UNDER CONTROL AND THAT ARMY TROOPS ARE SLOWLY MOVING INTO THE DENSELY POPULATED AREAS TO AVOID BLOODSHED AMONG THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

AS FOR A REQUEST BY THE INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS TO CALL FOR A CEASE-FIRE FOR HUMANITARIAN REASONS TO TREAT THE WOUNDED AND CIVILIAN VICTIMS, PACAS CASTRO SAID THAT THE FIRST-AID BRIGADES CONTINUE TO DO THEIR WORK IN EL SALVADOR.

AS FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF THE SIX JESUITS AND THE TWO WOMEN, HE SAID "HE CONDEMNED THIS TYPE OF VIOLENCE" BECAUSE IGNACIO ELLACURIA, ONE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS WHO WAS KILLED, "WAS MY TEACHER," AND HE DESCRIBED THE PRIEST AS A VERY VALUABLE MAN WHO WORKED FOR PEACE AND FOR THE ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT OF THE POPULATION.

COSTA RICAN FOREIGN MINISTER RODRIGO MADRIGAL NIETO, IN STATEMENTS TO THE PRESS, REGRETTED THE DEATH OF THE CLERGYMEN. "WORKING FOR PEACE IS VERY DIFFICULT," HE SAID.

MADRIGAL NIETO SAID TODAY HE HOPED THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS WOULD CONTINUE DESPITE THE WAR.

GUATEMALAN FOREIGN MINISTER ARIEL RIVERA IRIAS SUPPORTED THE STATEMENTS OF HIS COSTA RICAN COLLEAGUE, AND HE CONDEMNED THE USE OF VIOLENCE AS A POLITICAL TOOL.

DEV-MUC3-0761 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 16 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] GENERAL COMMAND REPORTS THE FOLLOWING TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY:

1. IT WAS LEARNED THROUGH MILITARY INTELLIGENCE SOURCES THAT THERE WERE DISCUSSIONS BETWEEN U.S. PENTAGON ADVISERS AND THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES' GENERAL STAFF ON THE INEFFECTIVENESS OF SALVADORAN AIR FORCE PILOTS.

2. AS A RESULT OF THESE ASSESSMENTS, ON 13 NOVEMBER, U.S. COMBAT PILOTS ARRIVED AT THE ILOPANGO AIR FORCE BASE FROM HONDURAS.

3. IN THE PAST 48 HOURS, THESE U.S. PILOTS HAVE BEEN CARRYING OUT THE BOMBING MISSIONS IN SAN SALVADOR. NIGHT BOMBINGS ARE CARRIED OUT EXCLUSIVELY BY THESE YANKEE PILOTS, AND THEY ARE DIRECTLY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE EXTENSIVE DAMAGE INFLICTED AMONG THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

4. ON 15 NOVEMBER, [WORD INDISTINCT] COMPANY TROOPS FROM GUATEMALA ARRIVED IN OUR COUNTRY AS A RESULT OF PRESSURE BY THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION TO GET REGIONAL ARMIES TO INTERVENE IN THE SALVADORAN WAR.

THE FMLN BELIEVES THAT THESE ARE VERY SERIOUS DEVELOPMENTS THAT COULD LEAD TO THE EXPANSION OF THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT TO THE REST OF THE REGION. WE CALL ON THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY AND, PARTICULARLY, ON THE U.S. PUBLIC TO DENOUNCE BEFORE THE WORLD THE ESCALATION OF THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION'S MEDDLING IN EL SALVADOR. WE WARN THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY ABOUT THE DANGER OF THIS ESCALATION AND THAT WE WILL NOT BE THE ONES RESPONSIBLE FOR THE DEATHS OF NORTH AMERICANS IN OUR FATHERLAND. WE CALL ON CENTRAL AMERICA'S PRESIDENTS TO BECOME AWARE THAT THIS U.S. INTERVENTION HARMS THE ESQUIPULAS AND TELA ACCORDS AND CONSTITUTES A DIRECT ATTACK ON THE REGION'S PROCESS OF DEMOCRATIZATION AND PEACE.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND -- COMMANDERS FRANCISCO JOVEL, JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, AND EDUARDO SANCHO, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL

EL SALVADOR, 16 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0762 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 16 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN] [TEXT] IN VIEW OF THE SINISTER MASSACRE OF JESUIT PRIESTS TODAY, THE FMLN REPORTS THE FOLLOWING TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE:

1. THE MASSACRE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS IGNACIO ELLACURIA, SEGUNDO MONTES, IGNACIO MARTIN BARO, JOAQUIN LOPEZ, AMANDO LOPEZ, AND JUAN RAMON MORENO, ALONG WITH MRS JULIA ELBA RAMOS AND HER DAUGHTER CELINA RAMOS, WAS PERPETRATED BY ARMED FORCES DEATH SQUADS AT DAWN TODAY.

A GROUP OF ABOUT 30 MEN DRESSED IN GREEN STORMED INTO THE PRIESTS' RESIDENCE AND RIDDLED THEM WITH BULLETS FIRED FROM HEAVY CALIBER WEAPONS. THREE OF THE BODIES WERE DRAGGED OUT TO THE PATIO WHERE THEY WERE GIVEN DEATH BLOWS THAT COMPLETELY CRUSHED THEIR SKULLS.

2. THIS ABSURD MASSACRE AND THE GENOCIDAL BOMBINGS AGAINST HEAVILY POPULATED AREAS IN SAN SALVADOR AND SAN MIGUEL HAVE BEEN ORDERED BY ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND THE ARMED FORCES' HIGH COMMAND, AND ARE PART OF A COUNTERINSURGENT PLAN TO DESTROY THE POLITICAL OPPOSITION AND CREATE A STATE OF TERROR AMONG THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. PUBLIC DEATH THREATS WERE MADE AGAINST PRIEST IGNACIO ELLACURIA OVER THE ARMED FORCES NATIONAL NETWORK.

THE NIGHT OF WEDNESDAY, 15 NOVEMBER, THE SECURITY CORPS SEARCHED THE OFFICES OF THE OPPOSITION GROUPS LOOKING FOR THE LEADERS IN ORDER TO KILL THEM. THIS IS THE SAME SCHEME THEY USED IN 1979 AND 1980 WHEN THEY MURDERED MONSIGNOR ROMERO AND MASSACRED THE REVOLUTIONARY DEMOCRATIC FRONT LEADERS, UNIVERSITY RECTOR DR FELIX ULLOA, AND TENS OF THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS.

3. THERE IS NO ROOM FOR DOUBT THAT THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE] REGIME AND THE ARMED FORCES ARE FASCIST BEASTS THAT HAVE BEEN MORTALLY WOUNDED. THEREFORE, WE CALL ON DEMOCRATIC PEOPLES AND RELIGIOUS LEADERS TO PROTEST SUCH AN UNFORTUNATE MASSACRE, AND ON THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TO ISOLATE THE FASCIST REGIME OF ALFREDO CRISTIANI.

4. WE CALL ON THE ARMED FORCES OFFICERS WHO KNEW FATHER IGNACIO ELLACURIA -- AND RESPECTED HIM FOR HIS PAST HISTORY IN THE FIELDS OF EDUCATION, RESEARCH, AND SCIENTIFIC ANALYSIS OF THE TRUE SITUATION -- TO TAKE A DIGNIFIED AND DETERMINED STAND AND NOT STAIN THEIR HANDS WITH THE BLOOD OF GENOCIDE.

THERE HAVE ALWAYS BEEN HONEST PATRIOTS IN THE ARMED FORCES WHO DO NOT HAVE TO SINK WITH THE CRIMINALS. WE OFFER THEM OUR HANDS, SO THAT TOGETHER WE WILL SAVE THE COUNTRY, AND SO THEY WILL BE ABLE TO SAVE PART OF THE ARMED FORCES. ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND THE ARMED FORCES ASSASSINATED THE JESUIT PRIESTS, BUT THEY ARE COMMITTING SUICIDE.

5. THE FMLN CONDEMNS THIS CRIME AND JOINS IN THE SORROW OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WHO LOSE IN SUCH AN ABSURD MANNER SOME OF THE MOST APPRECIATED INTELLECTUALS OF OUR COUNTRY. THEIR INTELLIGENCE AND SENSIBILITY WERE ALWAYS AT THE SERVICE OF CHANGE AND PROGRESS IN OUR SOCIETY. THEIR WORK WILL BE ETERNAL, AND THE FASCIST IRRATIONALITY WILL NEVER PUT AN END TO THAT WORK.

WE CALL ALL OF OUR COMMANDS, FIGHTERS, MILITANTS, AND OUR PEOPLE IN GENERAL, TO UNTIRING COMBAT. THIS STRUGGLE IS THE ONLY ANSWER WE HAVE FOR THIS DESPICABLE MASSACRE. WE MUST OUST ARENA AND LA TANDONA [1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY SCHOOL]. THE FATHERLAND IS COUNTING ON OUR STRENGTH AND OUR DETERMINATION, AND WE WILL NOT FAIL THE FATHERLAND.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND: COMMANDER SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, COMMANDER JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, COMMANDER FRANCISCO JOVEL, COMMANDER SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, COMMANDER EDUARDO SANCHO

16 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0763 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE FIGHTING BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN ARMY AND THE GUERRILLAS AND THE CONSTANT AIR FORCE BOMBINGS OF POPULATED AREAS CONTINUED FOR THE 6TH CONSECUTIVE DAY TODAY, WHILE THOUSANDS OF CIVILIANS FLED FROM THE MAIN AREAS OF FIGHTING.

IN SAN SALVADOR, ESPECIALLY IN NORTHWESTERN NEIGHBORHOODS, EFE REPORTERS WERE ABLE TO CONFIRM THE PERSISTENT CLASHES AND CONTINUOUS LAUNCHING OF ROCKETS BY AIR FORCE PUSH AND PULL AIRCRAFT AGAINST THE REBEL POSITIONS IN DENSELY POPULATED AREAS.

AT LEAST TWO BLOCKS OF HOMES IN LOW-INCOME ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD HAVE BEEN ABLAZE SINCE MID-MORNING AS A RESULT OF THE REBEL OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED ON SATURDAY, WHICH HAS LEFT MORE THAN 600 DEAD AND 1,000 WOUNDED.

THE NEIGHBORHOODS OF ZACAMIL, MEJICANOS, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, AND CUSCATANCINGO ARE THE PRINCIPAL AREAS OF FIGHTING IN THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL WHERE, ACCORDING TO ARMY SOURCES, THE MILITARY HAVE "LAID SIEGE TO THE REBELS AND WILL EVICT THEM IN A FEW HOURS."

THE SALVADORAN ARMY, SUPPORTED BY AIRCRAFT AND ARTILLERY, ARE ATTACKING THESE NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE APPROXIMATELY 300,000 PERSONS LIVE AND WHERE THE GUERRILLAS HAVE TAKEN UP POSITIONS.

FOR THEIR PART, SPOKESMEN FOR THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN), ENTRENCHED IN BUILDINGS AND BEHIND BARRICADES IN DENSELY POPULATED NEIGHBORHOODS CLAIM THAT THEY "WILL NOT RETREAT" AND THAT "THEY HAVE CONSOLIDATED THEIR POSITIONS IN THE CAPITAL AND OTHER CITIES OF THE COUNTRY."

ACCORDING TO THE FMLN, FIGHTING IS UNDER WAY IN AT LEAST 7 OF THE 24 DEPARTMENTS OF EL SALVADOR, WHILE THE FIERCEST CLASHES ARE TAKING PLACE IN USULUTAN, LA PAZ, SAN MIGUEL, AND MORAZAN IN THE EASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY.

INDEPENDENT CIVILIAN SOURCES REPORTED THAT IN THE COUNTRY'S EASTERN DEPARTMENT OF SAN MIGUEL THE GUERRILLAS HAVE OCCUPIED POSITIONS IN VARIOUS NEIGHBORHOODS, WHICH ARE UNDER HEAVY AIR AND ARTILLERY FIRE.

HOWEVER, THE ARMY AND THE GOVERNMENT CLAIM THAT THE SITUATION IS UNDER CONTROL THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY, AND THAT "THERE ARE GUERRILLA REDOUBTS" IN SAN SALVADOR ONLY.

MEANWHILE, THOUSANDS OF RESIDENTS IN NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE CLASHES ARE TAKING PLACE ARE SEEN RUNNING TERRIFIED THROUGH THE STREETS OF SAN SALVADOR SEEKING PLACES OF REFUGE.

THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE -- MEN AND WOMEN WITH CHILDREN IN THEIR ARMS -- CAN BE SEEN CARRYING A FEW BELONGINGS AND HOLDING WHITE FLAGS AS THEY WALK TO SHELTERS OPENED BY VARIOUS CHURCHES, WHERE THEY RECEIVE FOOD AND MEDICINE.

THE PRECARIOUS SITUATION OF THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS "IS VERY [WORDS INDISTINCT] THOUSANDS OF REFUGEES.

THE EXODUS OF SALVADORANS HAS GROWN EVEN MORE IN VIEW OF THE STRICT SECURITY MEASURES IMPLEMENTED THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY, SUCH AS THE STATE OF SIEGE AND THE 24-HOUR CURFEW ENFORCED IN THE DEPARTMENTS WHERE CLASHES ARE TAKING PLACE AND 12 HOURS IN THE REST OF THE COUNTRY.

SO FAR WE HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO OBTAIN INFORMATION ON THE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES AS A RESULT OF CLASHES AND THE BOMBINGS THAT TOOK PLACE LAST NIGHT AND THIS MORNING.

THE INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS HAS NOT BEEN ABLE TO ENTER THE NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE CLASHES ARE TAKING PLACE DUE TO THE HEAVY FIGHTING, AND THE AUTHORITIES HAVE REJECTED A PROPOSAL FOR A TEMPORARY TRUCE TO EVACUATE THE WOUNDED AND PERMIT THE BURIAL OF BODIES STILL LAYING IN THE STREETS OF SAN SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0764 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION. PAY CLOSE ATTENTION. ZACAMIL, CUSCATANCINGO, AND SOYOPANGO RESIDENTS: IT IS RECOMMENDED THAT YOU LEAVE YOUR HOMES IMMEDIATELY TO KEEP THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORISTS FROM USING THEM AS PLACES WHERE THEY CAN SHIELD THEMSELVES FROM THE VICTORIOUS ADVANCES OF OUR ARMED FORCES.

THE CATHOLIC CHURCH HAS OFFERED THE FOLLOWING PLACES TO BE USED AS REFUGE: BUEN SAMARITANO SCHOOL IS READY TO ACCEPT SANTA MARTA RESIDENTS, AND SAN ROQUE PARRISH, WE CORRECT OURSELVES, IT IS THE JESUS OBRERO PAROCHIAL SCHOOL, IS ALSO OPEN. REFUGE CAN ALSO BE TAKEN AT THESE FOLLOWING SCHOOLS: SAN JOSE BOARDING SCHOOL, SAGRADO CORAZON, AND LA ASUNCION.

THIS URGENT CALL IS MADE PRIMARILY FOR FAMILIES WHOSE HOUSES ARE CLOSE TO THE LAST TERRORIST POCKETS LOCATED IN THE PLACES MENTIONED. WE DO ALL THIS FOR THE SAFETY OF YOU AND YOUR FAMILY. WE ASK YOU TO COME OUT WITH WHITE FLAGS AND YOUR HANDS UP HIGH. TOGETHER -- GOVERNMENT, PEOPLE, AND THE ARMED FORCES -- WE ADVANCE TOWARD PEACE.

DEV-MUC3-0765 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] COMMANDER FACUNDO GUARDADO, ONE OF THE FOUNDERS OF THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLA MOVEMENT IN THE PAST DECADE, TODAY SAID THAT THE ARMY'S COUNTEROFFENSIVE IN SAN SALVADOR "IS AT A STALEMATE," WHILE THE "REBELS ARE ADVANCING."

GUARDADO, WEARING AN OLIVE GREEN UNIFORM, TOLD THE PRESS THAT THE GUERRILLAS' OFFENSIVE, WHICH BEGAN ON 11 NOVEMBER, SURPRISED THE ARMED FORCES AND THE UNITED STATES, WHICH HAS "MOTIVATED WARMONGERING SECTORS IN THIS COUNTRY TO CONTINUE REPRESSION."

THE GUERRILLA LEADER, KNOWN AS "ESTEBAN," SAID: "WE ARE WILLING TO NEGOTIATE WITH THE GOVERNMENT A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE WAR FROM HERE [SAN SALVADOR], WHILE WE CONTINUE TO HOLD THESE TERRITORIES (IN SAN SALVADOR)." HE ADDED: "WE WOULD HAVE TO ASK ARMY CHIEFS IF THESE ARE THE SO-CALLED UNDELIMITED BORDER AREAS BORDERING HONDURAS."

THE SALVADORAN ARMY HAS REPEATEDLY CHARGED THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) WITH SEEKING REFUGE IN "UNDELIMITED BORDER AREAS" IN DISPUTE WITH HONDURAS.

GUARDADO WAS INTERVIEWED NEAR A CLINIC IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR. HE WAS SURROUNDED BY PEOPLE WHO COMPLAINED TO THE PRESS OF THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE'S "INDISCRIMINATE" BOMBINGS.

"WE HAVE BEEN FORCED TO LEAVE OUR HOMES. WE DO NOT KNOW WHAT TO DO. WE ASK YOU (THE PRESS) TO REPORT THAT THE AIR FORCE IS BOMBING THESE NEIGHBORHOODS," A MAN WHO WAS CARRYING A WHITE FLAG AND SAYING GOOD-BYE TO HIS NEIGHBORS SAID.

THE GUERRILLAS PRESENTED TO THE PRESS TWO SOLDIERS WHO WERE DETAINED ON 15 NOVEMBER AS SOLDIERS TRIED TO EXPEL REBELS FROM MEJICANOS, A DENSELY POPULATED NEIGHBORHOOD IN SAN SALVADOR. THE SOLDIERS, APPROXIMATELY 25 YEARS OLD, IDENTIFIED THEMSELVES AS JOSE FRANCISCO RAMIREZ AND SANTOS LOPEZ. "WE WERE CAPTURED YESTERDAY. WE WERE TREATED WELL AND HAVE BEEN FED. WE DO NOT CONSIDER OURSELVES PRISONERS OF WAR," RAMIREZ SAID. LOPEZ SAID HE HAD ENTERED THE MEJICANOS AREA WITH 45 OTHER SOLDIERS, BUT "ALL OF THEM LEFT."

DEV-MUC3-0767 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI STATED TODAY HIS GOVERNMENT IS WILLING TO CONTINUE THE DIALOGUE WITH THE GUERRILLAS, BUT ONLY IF IT DESISTS FROM VIOLENCE AND JOINS THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.

"WE WILL NOT LEND OURSELVES TO ANY GAME WITH THE GUERRILLAS. WHILE SPEAKING OF PEACE, THEY PREPARED THIS ACTION" (THE OFFENSIVE), CRISTIANI STATED, NOTING THAT THE REBELS "ARE GOING TO ANY LENGTH TO TRY TO ACHIEVE POWER THROUGH VIOLENT MEANS."

"IF HOSTILITIES DO NOT CEASE ON THE PART OF THE GUERRILLAS, THERE WILL NOT BE ANY DIALOGUE. THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT LEND ITSELF TO THIS GAME," HE INSISTED.

THE PRESIDENT STATED AT A NEWS CONFERENCE THAT THE ARMY "HAS CONTROLLED" NATIONAL TERRITORY, ALTHOUGH HE ADMITTED THAT IN SOME PLACES, ESPECIALLY IN NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE CAPITAL, CLASHES ARE STILL TAKING PLACE WITH THE REBELS.

CRISTIANI STATED THAT COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS "IS VERY DISTURBED AND TERMED THE REBELS CYNICAL," BECAUSE WHILE THEY SPOKE OF PEACE THEY WERE PREPARING THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED ON SATURDAY.

THE PRESIDENT AGAIN DENIED THAT THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE IS INDISCRIMINATELY BOMBING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. HE SAID THAT ONLY TWICE HAVE BOMBS BEEN USED, THE FIRST TIME IN AN OPEN FIELD OF THE UNIVERSITY OF EL SALVADOR WHERE MORTARS WERE POSITIONED, AND AGAIN LAST NIGHT IN THE VICINITY OUTSIDE THE AIR FORCE GARRISONS.

CRISTIANI STATED THAT THE GUERRILLAS USED BOMBS LAST NIGHT AGAINST THE AIR FORCE IN EASTERN SAN SALVADOR AND WERE REPELLED BY AIRCRAFT WHICH DROPPED BOMBS.

THE PRESIDENT STRESSED THAT THE ARMY HAS NOT EVICTED THE GUERRILLAS FROM POSITIONS IN THE NORTHWESTERN NEIGHBORHOODS OF SAN SALVADOR SO AS "NOT TO AFFECT THE CIVILIAN POPULATION."

HE ADDED THAT FRANCE AND GUATEMALA HAVE OFFERED TO DONATE MEDICINE FOR THE THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS WHO HAVE HAD TO LEAVE THEIR HOMES AS A RESULT OF THE INTENSE FIGHTING BETWEEN THE ARMY AND GUERRILLAS SINCE THE OFFENSIVE BEGAN, CAUSING APPROXIMATELY 1,000 DEATHS.

DEV-MUC3-0768 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CRISTIANI] FIRST, I WOULD LIKE TO THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE. BRIEFLY, BEFORE BEGINNING THE QUESTION AND ANSWER SESSION, WE WOULD LIKE TO SAY BEFORE THE INTERNATIONAL PRESS THAT WE CONDEMN IN THE STRONGEST TERMS THE MURDERS OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THEIR COOK, AND HER DAUGHTER EARLY THIS MORNING AT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY, UCA. WE FEEL THAT THESE INCIDENTS FURTHER COMPLICATE OUR COUNTRY'S CRITICAL SITUATION. GROUPS OR MINDS WANT TO HAMPER THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, ESPECIALLY THE PEACE PROCESS THAT THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC HAS TRIED TO ADVANCE AND WILL CONTINUE TO PURSUE.

FROM THE START WE ORDERED AN INVESTIGATION BECAUSE WE BELIEVE THAT NOW THAT THE PEOPLE AND ALL OF THE COUNTRY'S INSTITUTIONS HAVE SUPPORTED THE PEACE PROCESS, IT IS NO LONGER POSSIBLE TO CONTINUE HAVING THESE SAVAGE INCIDENTS TAKE PLACE THAT ARE AIMED AT BLOCKING THIS PROCESS. WE HAVE MADE PRELIMINARY INVESTIGATIONS THAT MERELY TELL US HOW THINGS HAPPENED. WE HAVE ALREADY TAKEN SOME PROCEDURAL STEPS, SUCH AS [WORD INDISTINCT] WHERE THE IMPACT WAS FELT AND WHERE THE CRIMES WERE PERPETRATED. IN SUM, WE DID THE THINGS NORMALLY DONE AT THE START OF THESE KINDS OF INVESTIGATIONS.

THERE IS A POSSIBLE WITNESS TO THESE CRIMES, BUT, UNFORTUNATELY, HE HAS NOT BEEN LOCATED SO THAT HE CAN BE QUESTIONED BY THE INVESTIGATORS. THEY WILL CERTAINLY MAKE EVERY EFFORT TO LOCATE HIM SO THAT HE CAN PROVIDE INFORMATION THAT WILL CLARIFY THIS REGRETTABLE INCIDENT.

I SUPPOSE THE JESUITS' PROVINCIAL WILL HOST A NEWS CONFERENCE. YOU HAVE MANY OF THE DETAILS, SO WE ARE GOING TO SKIP THEM. THE ONLY THINGS WE HAVE FOUND ARE FINGERPRINTS THAT ARE BEING STUDIED AND SHELL CASINGS FROM AK-47 AND M-16 RIFLES. WE WILL SUBMIT THEM FOR BALLISTIC TESTS. WE WILL ALSO CONDUCT FORENSIC TESTS, WHICH WILL BEGIN SOON. ANOTHER IMPORTANT DETAIL IS THAT INSIDE THE BUILDING THERE WAS A ROOM OR LIBRARY WITH VIDEO CASSETTES. IT WAS LIKE A STUDIO. THIS ROOM LOOKED LIKE IT HAD BEEN BURNED AFTER BEING RANSACKED. ALL THESE THINGS AND OTHER DETAILS HAVE BEEN REPORTED AND SUBMITTED TO THE INVESTIGATORS. WE ALSO TALKED TO THE JESUITS' PROVINCIAL AND TOLD HIM THAT WE WERE DETERMINED TO GET TO THE BOTTOM OF THIS. WE ASKED HIM FOR HIS HELP, AND HE EXPRESSED HIS READINESS TO ASSIST IN THE INVESTIGATION. WE ARE GRATEFUL FOR THIS HELP BECAUSE IN THE PAST COOPERATION WITH THE AUTHORITIES HAS NOT ALWAYS BEEN FORTHCOMING.

WE HOPE THAT WITH THIS HELP AND WITH THE REMARKS BY MSGR ARTURO RIVERA Y DAMAS, WITH WHOM WE ALSO SPOKE THIS MORNING, THIS CASE WILL NOT BE POLITICIZED AND JUSTICE CAN BE SERVED, AVOIDING REACHING HASTY OR BIASED CONCLUSIONS BY ANY OF GROUP OR PARTY. WE THINK AND AGREE WITH MSGR RIVERA Y DAMAS THAT THIS IS HOW A SERIOUS INVESTIGATION SHOULD BE CONDUCTED. WE HOPE THAT THIS INVESTIGATION WILL LEAD US TO THE HEART OF THE MATTER. REGARDLESS OF WHO THE PERPETRATORS ARE, WE WANT PUNISHMENT FOR THOSE ATTEMPTING TO HINDER THE PROCESS OF PEACE AND DEMOCRACY IN EL SALVADOR.

AND SO WE BEGIN THE QUESTIONS. PERHAPS MR SANDOVAL OR ANA MARIA MAY WANTO HELP US TO PUT SOME ORDER [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI] FIRST, THE GOVERNMENT COMMUNIQUE REPEATS ECO [MEXICAN NEWS AGENCY] ECO REPORTS, WHICH MENTION UNKNOWN TERRORISTS. REGARDLESS OF THE SIDE THAT IS INVOLVED, THIS IS THE WAY TO DESCRIBE THESE ACTIONS. THESE ARE TERRORIST ACTIONS BECAUSE OF THEIR OVERALL CONTEXT, NO MATTER WHO [WORDS INDISTINCT]. LET ME REPEAT: WE HAVE COMMENTS BY CHURCH OFFICIALS WHO WERE GIVING VERSIONS THAT HAVE NOT BEEN CORROBORATED. WE HAVE BEEN TOLD THERE WERE SEVERAL PERSONS WEARING UNIFORMS, TO CITE THESE VERSIONS VERBATIM. I DO NOT WANT TO EXCUSE OR ACCUSE ANYONE, BUT I FEEL THAT IS NOT A CATEGORICAL PROOF. TODAY, MANY PEOPLE WHO DO NOT BELONG TO THE ARMED FORCES ARE WEARING UNIFORMS.

LET ME REPEAT: ONE CANNOT SAY ONE THING OR ANOTHER, BUT I DO THINK THIS MUST BE INVESTIGATED. IF MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES ARE FOUND TO BE INVOLVED, THEY WILL FEEL THE FULL WEIGHT OF THE LAW. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0769 (U NEBRASKA)

PARIS (FRANCE), 16 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF SIX MEMBERS OF HIS ORDER, INCLUDING IGNACIO ELLACURIA, RECTOR OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY (UCA), "ARE THE SAME ONES WHO KILLED MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO, ARCHBISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR."

"I DO NOT WANT TO ACCUSE ANYONE, BUT IT IS OBVIOUS WHERE THE FACTS ARE POINTING," JOSE MARIA TOJEIRA [JESUIT PROVINCIAL SUPERVISOR] STATED AT A NEWS CONFERENCE HELD THIS AFTERNOON IN THE UCA CHAPEL, ONLY A FEW METERS FROM WHERE THE JESUIT PRIESTS AND TWO DOMESTICS WERE KILLED THIS MORNING.

THE BODIES OF ELLACURIA AND HIS JESUIT COMPANIONS IGNACIO MARTIN BARO, SEGUNDO MONTES, JUAN RAMON MORENO, ARMANDO LOPEZ, AND JOAQUIN LOPEZ, AS WELL AS DOMESTIC ELBA RAMOS AND HER 15-YEAR-OLD DAUGHTER, WERE RIDDLED WITH BULLETS, WHILE SOME ALSO HAD THEIR SKILLS CRUSHED.

THE DEATH OF THE PRIESTS, FIVE OF THEM SPANIARDS, WHO WERE ALWAYS IN FAVOR OF A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE CRISIS, HAS INCREASED THE FEAR AND DESPERATION FELT BY THE SALVADORANS SINCE THE PAST WEEKEND, WHEN VIOLENT FIGHTING BROKE OUT BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND SOLDIERS IN THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR.

THE PRIESTS WERE KILLED BY SOME 30 MEN WEARING OLIVE DRAB UNIFORMS WHO BROKE INTO THE PLACE, ACCORDING TO WITNESSES WHO WERE THERE, TOJEIRA EXPLAINED.

THE PRIEST RECALLED THAT OVER THE WEEKEND THE GOVERNMENT RADIO NETWORK "LAUNCHED FIERCE ATTACKS AGAINST THE [WORD INDISTINCT], SAYING THAT A FEW PRIESTS HAD TO BE KILLED IN THIS COUNTRY OR THAT THEY HAD TO BE PLACED IN FRONT OF THE CATHEDRAL SO THAT THE PEOPLE COULD KILL THEM BY SPITTING AT THEM," TOJERA NOTED.

ALSO, HE ADDED THAT ON MONDAY ARMED FORCES MEMBERS RAIDED THE HOMES OF ELLACURIA AND COMPANIONS. "ON THAT OCCASION THEY WERE QUITE CORRECT, ACCORDING TO WHAT FATHER ELLACURIA TOLD ME," ADDED TOJEIRA, WHO WAS QUITE UPSET DURING THE NEWS CONFERENCE.

"APPARENTLY THE MEN SAID THEY HAD REPORTS THAT THERE WERE WEAPONS IN THE RESIDENCES. OF COURSE THEY FOUND NOTHING, AND FATHER ELLACURIA INVITED THEM TO RETURN ON TUESDAY AND GO THROUGH THE UCA CAMPUS, BUT THEY DID NOT DO SO."

ALSO, TOJEIRA CONFIRMED THAT ON WEDNESDAY AFTERNOON AND EVENING THERE WAS TIGHT SECURITY IN THE VICINITY OF THE UCA IN THE SOUTHERN PART OF THE CAPITAL.

"I DO NOT KNOW IF THE SOLDIERS LEFT THE PLACE LATER, BUT UP UNTIL 2200 ON WEDNESDAY, HOURS BEFORE THE HORRIBLE MASSACRE, THE SOLDIERS WERE THERE," TOJEIRA ADDED.

"THESE ARE THE FACTS. THEREFORE, WE SHARE THE OPINION OF ARCHBISHOP ARTURO RIVERA -- THAT THE ONES RESPONSIBLE ARE THE SAME ONES WHO ASSASSINATED MSGR ROMERO," HE ADDED.

DEV-MUC3-0770 (U NEBRASKA)

GUATEMALA CITY, 9 NOV 89 (PRENSA LIBRE) -- [TEXT] IN AN ANALYSIS OF THE VIOLENCE DURING THE MONTH OF SEPTEMBER, THE INFORMATION OFFICE OF THE BUSINESS SECTOR (OFISEM) POINTS OUT THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOT BEEN ABLE TO PROVIDE AN ATMOSPHERE OF SECURITY FOR THE PEOPLE SO THAT THE ECONOMY CAN MOVE IN A MANNER FAVORABLE FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE COUNTRY.

THE STATISTICS ON THE SEPTEMBER VIOLENCE -- TAKEN FROM THE MEDIA -- SHOW THERE IS A SLIGHT IMPROVEMENT IN SOME ASPECTS, BUT THE PREVAILING SITUATION IS OF GREAT CONCERN, THE BUSINESSMEN ADD.

IN A COMPARISON OF THE STATISTICS FOR AUGUST AND SEPTEMBER, IT IS NOTED THAT 142 MURDERS WERE REPORTED IN SEPTEMBER WHILE 126 WERE REPORTED IN AUGUST. OFISEM ALSO REPORTS THAT 17 KIDNAP CASES WERE REPORTED IN SEPTEMBER, AGAINST 19 CASES IN AUGUST. AS FOR MISSING PERSONS, THERE WERE 12 REPORTED IN SEPTEMBER AND 19 IN AUGUST.

THE REPORT ADDS THERE WERE 26 CASES OF ASSAULT IN SEPTEMBER, AGAINST 71 CASES IN AUGUST, WHILE THERE WERE 41 CRIMINAL ATTACKS IN SEPTEMBER AND 57 IN AUGUST. CONCERNING ACTIONS BY SUBVERSIVE GROUPS, OFISEM ADDS ONE SUCH ACTION WAS REPORTED IN SEPTEMBER, AND 12 IN AUGUST. FIVE CASES OF NARCOTICS TRAFFICKING WERE REPORTED IN AUGUST, AND ONLY ONE IN SEPTEMBER.

OFICEM ONCE AGAIN URGES THE AUTHORITIES TO INCREASE THEIR ACTIVITIES TO PROTECT THE SECURITY OF THE GUATEMALANS, WHO DESERVE TO LIVE IN PEACE IN AN ATMOSPHERE THAT IS CONDUCIVE FOR THE PROGRESS OF GUATEMALA.

DEV-MUC3-0771 (U NEBRASKA)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [REPORT] [COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF] [TEXT] SALVADORAN PEOPLE: AFTER 5 DAYS OF COMBAT, CONFRONTING THIS ARMED AGGRESSION BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORISTS, [WORDS INDISTINCT] I WANT TO INFORM YOU OF THE SITUATION THROUGHOUT THE NATION:

IN THE WESTERN AREA, THERE ARE NO PROBLEMS. IN THE EASTERN AREA, THERE ARE STILL PROBLEMS. IN SAN MIGUEL CITY, THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE COMMAND HAS BEEN OPERATING IN A PROFESSIONAL MANNER, AND IT HAS AVOIDED HARMING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION; THEREFORE, THERE ARE TERRORISTS IN THE [NAMES INDISTINCT] NEIGHBORHOODS. ALSO IN USULUTAN LAST NIGHT AND EARLY THIS MORNING, [WORDS INDISTINCT] BUT AT PRESENT ONLY SOME EXPLOSIONS AND SOME SPORADIC FIRING ARE HEARD IN THE VICINITY OF THE CITY OF USULUTAN. IN ZACATECOLUCA YESTERDAY WE MANAGED TO CONTROL THE POPULATION COMPLETELY. WE DISLODGED THE TERRORISTS FROM THE 27 SEPTEMBER NEIGHBORHOOD.

WE HAVE HAD SERIOUS PROBLEMS IN THE CAPITAL CITY. THE FMLN HAS WAGED ITS GREATEST EFFORTS HERE. THEY ARE [WORD INDISTINCT] TERRORISTS, AND THEY SHOULD BE CONSIDERED AS SUCH. IN SOME NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE NORTHERN AREA, THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] MEJICANOS, [WORDS INDISTINCT] AS OF SUNDAY, 12 NOVEMBER. IN SOME [WORDS INDISTINCT] AS IT WAS YESTERDAY. ALTHOUGH IT IS TRUE [WORDS INDISTINCT] OF THE CAPITAL CITY. IN MEJICANOS, IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD, [WORDS INDISTINCT] NORTH OF THE GUADALUPE AND SOYAPANGO NEIGHBORHOODS, [WORDS INDISTINCT] REPARTO SANTA MARTA, AND ALTOS DEL [WORD INDISTINCT]. IN THIS AREA, THE ARMED FORCES HAVE CARRIED OUT ACTIONS TO DEFEND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO NEUTRALIZE THIS GENOCIDE [WORDS INDISTINCT].

ON THE NATIONAL LEVEL, I WOULD LIKE TO ANNOUNCE SOME PARTIAL RESULTS. THE ARMED FORCES HAVE SUSTAINED THE FOLLOWING: 177 DEAD AND 251 WOUNDED.

AMONG THE TERRORISTS THERE ARE 655 DEAD AND 491 WOUNDED. WE HAVE CAPTURED 92 FMLN MEMBERS, AND 6 FMLN TERRORISTS HAVE TURNED THEMSELVES IN. AS FOR THE CIVILIANS, WE REGRET 47 PERSONS HAVE DIED, AND 153 HAVE BEEN WOUNDED.

THE ARMED FORCES HAVE SEIZED FROM THE FMLN TERRORISTS 324 RIFLES, 75 GRENADE AND ROCKET LAUNCHERS, 26 MORTARS, 8 MACHINEGUNS, 15 SUBMACHINEGUNS, AND 40 WEAPONS OF OTHER TYPES. FOUR ARSENALS HAVE ALSO [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN MEJICANOS, WHERE THE TERRORISTS HAD A CONSIDERABLE QUANTITY OF AMMUNITION AND EXPLOSIVES.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: YOU MUST HAVE CONFIDENCE IN YOUR ARMED FORCES AND IN YOUR GOVERNMENT BECAUSE WE ARE WORKING JOINTLY. OUR COMMANDER IN CHIEF IS UP TO DATE ON THE SITUATION, AND [WORDS INDISTINCT], AND WE ARE WORKING TOGETHER. THE ARMED FORCES IS WORKING IN A VERY PROFESSIONAL MANNER. YOU MUST UNDERSTAND THAT WE CANNOT RESOLVE THIS SITUATION BY ENDANGERING THE LIVES OF INNOCENT PEOPLE. THAT IS WHY IT TAKES LONGER FOR THE ARMED FORCES TO DO THINGS.

ON BEHALF OF THE ARMED FORCES, WE WANT TO THANK YOU, OUR PEOPLE, FOR YOUR SUPPORT, AS YOU HAVE BEEN PROVIDING US WITH PLENTY OF INFORMATION, SUPPORTING OUR TROOPS IN THE VARIOUS COMBAT AREAS, AND-- MOST IMPORTANT OF ALL--CONDEMNING AND REJECTING THIS TERRORIST ATTACK. THAT IS THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] OF THE FMLN.

WE ARE ALL WORKING, STRUGGLING TO MAINTAIN A DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM, TO MAINTAIN FREEDOM [WORD INDISTINCT], AND ACHIEVE PEACE. I ALSO WANT TO INFORM YOU THAT AFTER VISITING THIS AFTERNOON THE VARIOUS AREAS WHERE WE ARE [WORD INDISTINCT], THE MORALE OF OUR TROOPS AND OFFICERS IS VERY HIGH. AND THERE IS A REASON FOR THIS, BECAUSE THEY ARE FIGHTING TO DEFEND YOU.

[WORD INDISTINCT] THE FMLN TERRORISTS HAVE A VERY LOW MORALE, [WORDS INDISTINCT] MANY, BECAUSE THEY ARE NOW AWARE OF THEIR CASUALTIES AND [WORDS INDISTINCT].

I WANT TO AVAIL MYSELF OF THIS OPPORTUNITY AND ON BEHALF OF THE ARMED FORCES, TO STRONGLY CONDEMN THOSE WHO THIS MORNING MASSACRED SIX JESUIT PRIESTS. WE REGRET AS WELL THE DEATHS OF OTHER CIVILIANS, INNOCENT PEOPLE WHO HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH THIS CONFLICT. WE ALSO REGRET THE DEATHS AMONG OUR ARMED FORCES.

IT IS ALSO IMPORTANT TO MENTION THAT THE GOVERNMENT, THE PEOPLE, AND THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL COMMAND ARE PROUD OF THE PROFESSIONAL WORK BEING DONE AT THE VARIOUS GARRISONS OF OUR ARMED FORCES.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, ON BEHALF OF THE ARMED FORCES, WE ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT. YOU MUST CONTINUE GOING TO WORK AND CONTINUE WORKING. IN CONCLUSION, I WANT TO THANK THE PEOPLE ONCE AGAIN FOR THEIR MORAL AND MATERIAL SUPPORT OF THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES AT SUCH A DIFFICULT TIME.

DEV-MUC3-0772 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [REPORT] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] [TEXT] SIX DAYS AFTER HAVING INITIATED OUR OFFENSIVE IN THE CAPITAL CITY AND THE ENTIRE COUNTRY, THERE HAS BEEN AN OVERWHELMING TREND TOWARD THE CONSOLIDATION AND BROADENING OF FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] POSITIONS IN IMPORTANT CITIES AND TOWNS IN THE COUNTRY, WHICH HAVE PLAYED LEADING ROLES BECAUSE THE PEOPLE HAVE SUPPORTED AND JOINED THE STRUGGLE.

TODAY WE COMPLETED AN ARCH OF FREEDOM IN SAN SALVADOR BY EXTENDING AND CONNECTING SEVERAL AREAS UNDER OUR CONTROL, AFTER REPELLING AND SWAMPING THE GOVERNMENT'S SPECIAL BATTALIONS IN FIVE COUNTERATTACKS SUPPORTED BY ARMORED VEHICLES AND AERIAL BOMBINGS.

OUR FIGHTERS DISPLAYED SINGULAR HEROISM DURING THE OCCUPATION OF THE CUSCATANCINGO HEADQUARTERS AND THE COMMANDS IN MEJICANOS AND CIUDAD DELGADO, WHERE WE CAPTURED A LARGE ARSENAL OF WEAPONS AND AMMUNITION, AND DURING CLASHES IN [NAME INDISTINCT], SOYAPANGO, CIUDAD MERLIOT, AND [NAME INDISTINCT].

THE FMLN ALSO HAS FORCES ALONG THE LEADING ROUTES TO THE CAPITAL CITY; THESE FORCES HARASS AND HINDER ARMY DEPLOYMENTS ON THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAY, AND ON THE SAN SALVADOR-SANTA TECLA HIGHWAY.

WE NOW HIGHLIGHT OUR FORCES' FEATS: COMPANIES FORMED BY POPULAR FORCES HAVE EXTENDED THEIR CONTROL OVER NEW AREAS AND CITIES IN SAN MIGUEL AND USULUTAN, WHERE WEAPONS HAVE BEEN SEIZED AND PRISONERS OF WAR TAKEN. WE STRESS OUR PERMANENT HARASSMENT OF ENEMY FORCES IN ZACATECOLUCA, CHALATENANGO, SANTA ANA, APOPA, SAN MARTIN, SAN MARCOS, NUEVA CONCEPCION, SANTA ELENA, AND OTHER TOWNS.

TRANSPORTATION HAS BEEN PARALYZED SINCE THE FMLN DECLARED A STOPPAGE, AND MOST OF THE COUNTRY IS WITHOUT ELECTRICITY DUE TO SABOTAGE. THE CRITICAL DEADLINE THE HIGH COMMAND SET FOR ITSELF TO RECOVER OUR POSITIONS HAS PASSED, AND OUR FORCES HAVE ASSAULTED HEADQUARTERS IN CONTROLLED AREAS AND HAVE REQUISITIONED WEAPONS AND AMMUNITION.

HUNDREDS OF YOUTHS CONTINUE TO JOIN OUR ARMY. WITHOUT POPULAR SUPPORT THE FMLN WOULD NOT HAVE ACHIEVED POLITICAL-MILITARY VICTORIES OF SUCH DIMENSIONS AS TO TAKE THE ENEMY BY SURPRISE AND EARN THE WORLD'S ADMIRATION.

IN THE PAST 2 DAYS THE FMLN HAS INFLICTED DOZENS OF CASUALTIES AMONG THE ARMY'S OFFICERS AND TROOPS, AND IT HAS TAKEN FIVE PRISONERS OF WAR, AMONG WHOM ARE A CAPTAIN AND A LIEUTENANT, WHOSE PHYSICAL AND MENTAL WELL BEING HAS BEEN RESPECTED. THE FMLN HAS SEIZED 63 RIFLES, 4 MACHINEGUNS, 3 GRENADE LAUNCHERS, 5 PRC-77 RADIOS, [WORDS INDISTINCT], AND THOUSANDS OF ROUNDS OF AMMUNITION FROM THE OCCUPIED HEADQUARTERS AND COMMANDS.

WE CALL ON ALL THE PEOPLE TO JOIN THE UPRISING [WORD INDISTINCT] AGAINST THE FASCIST GENOCIDE. WE ASK THE OFFICERS AND TROOPS NOT TO CONTINUE SERVING IN AN ARMY THAT IS BEHAVING LIKE A FOREIGN OCCUPATION ARMY, [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE CIVILIAN POPULATION, EXECUTING PRIESTS, AND MASSACRING LABOR LEADERS.

IN THE CITIES AND COUNTRYSIDE, A SEA OF GUERRILLAS [BREAK IN RECEPTION PREVENTS COMPLETION OF ITEM].

DEV-MUC3-0773 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE ARE IN CONTACT WITH SAN SALVADOR AND WE ARE RECEIVING MORE REPORTS ON THE PERSECUTION UNLEASHED AGAINST THE RELIGIOUS GROUPS IN SAN SALVADOR.

WE REMIND YOU THAT A FEW WEEKS AGO COLONEL FRANCISCO ELENA FUENTES AND COLONEL INOCENTE ORLANDO MONTANO LAUNCHED A CAMPAIGN AGAINST THE LUTHERAN AND OTHER CHURCHES THROUGHOUT EL SALVADOR. NOW THIS CAMPAIGN, ORCHESTRATED BY COL ELENA FUENTES, CHIEF OF THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE'S DEATH SQUADS, HAS HEIGHTENED. NOT ONLY HAVE JESUIT PRIESTS BEEN MURDERED, BUT THIS MORNING THE NATIONAL GUARD ARRESTED TWO PRIESTS AND SEVERAL MISSIONARIES, INCLUDING A U.S. CITIZEN. WE REPEAT: TWO PRIESTS AND SEVERAL MISSIONARIES HAVE BEEN ARRESTED INCLUDING A U.S. CITIZEN. THESE PEOPLE WERE ARRESTED BY THE NATIONAL GUARD. WE CALL ON ALL THE [WORD INDISTINCT] AROUND THE WORLD; WE CALL ON ALL THE LATIN AMERICAN RELIGIOUS SECTORS TO MOBILIZE. TWO PRIESTS AND SEVERAL MISSIONARIES WERE ARRESTED THIS MORNING BY THE NATIONAL GUARD IN SAN SALVADOR. AMONG THE ARRESTED PERSONS IS A U.S. CITIZEN.

RADIO VENCEREMOS IS IN CONTACT WITH SAN SALVADOR TO GATHER MORE DETAILED INFORMATION REGARDING THE WHEREABOUTS OF THE TWO PRIESTS AND SEVERAL MISSIONARIES, INCLUDING A U.S. CITIZEN, WHO WERE ARRESTED.

THE PERSECUTION AGAINST THE CHURCH CONTINUES BY ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] AND THE LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO THE 1966 GRADUATES OF THE CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] MILITARY CLIQUE. RADIO VENCEREMOS CALLS ON ALL THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, ESPECIALLY THE CATHOLIC UNIVERSITIES AROUND THE WORLD, THE LATIN AMERICAN COMMUNITY, TO MOBILIZE, OCCUPY SALVADORAN EMBASSIES, DEMONSTRATE IN FRONT OF SALVADORAN EMBASSIES AROUND THE WORLD AND DEMAND THE RELEASE OF THE PRIESTS WHO WERE ARRESTED THIS MORNING BY THE NATIONAL GUARD. [WORDS INDISTINCT] 1 MINUTE FOR THE RELIGIOUS COMMUNITY AROUND THE WORLD TO SPEAK OUT AND MOBILIZE TO PRESSURE PRESIDENT CRISTIANI. THIS COULD SAVE THE LIVES OF THE PERSONS ARRESTED THIS MORNING BY THE NATIONAL GUARD, A BLOODTHIRSTY GUARD THAT IS RELIVING THE LAST DAYS OF THE SOMOZIST GUARD. THE KILLING OF PRIESTS AND NOW THE ARREST OF TWO PRIESTS AND SEVERAL MISSIONARIES FURTHER CONFIRMS THAT THE REGIME IS ON THE VERGE OF COLLAPSING, THAT IT IS DESPERATE AND NO LONGER CARES ABOUT THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, PRESSURE, OR REQUESTS FOR AN END TO THE BOMBINGS AND BLOODSHED. THIS MORNING'S RESPONSE HAS BEEN THE ARREST OF TWO PRIESTS AND SEVERAL MISSIONARIES.

DEV-MUC3-0774 (U NEBRASKA)

NO CITY, NO DATE -- [STATEMENT] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] ACTIONS SUCH AS THESE, ACCOMPANIED BY ORCHESTRATED SLANDEROUS CAMPAIGNS, SCARE AWAY INVESTMENTS FROM OUR COUNTRY AND THE HUMANITARIAN AID THAT WE NEED SO MUCH. DR CUSTODIO, THE SAME AS NORIEGA, CONTINUES TO DECEIVE THE PEOPLE AND EXPLOIT THEM TO FURTHER PERSONAL INTERESTS AND INTERNATIONAL COMMUNISM. AS A BUREAUCRAT, (ALTHOUGH HE TRIES TO COVER THIS UP), CUSTODIO OWNS MANY MATERIAL GOODS AND FOREIGN BANK ACCOUNTS, AND AS IF THIS WERE NOT ENOUGH, HE IS FUELING THE BONFIRE OF VIOLENCE IN OUR COUNTRY ONLY TO RUN AWAY WHEN THE FIRE GIVES WAY TO CHAOS AND ANARCHY AMONG THE PEOPLE. HE WILL LEAVE THE COUNTRY WITH HIS INTERNATIONAL CONTACTS AND FEEL SATISFIED FOR WHAT HE HAS DONE.

PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA [SUBHEAD]

CODEH HAS DONE NOTHING FOR PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA. QUITE THE CONTRARY, IT HAS DISCREDITED DEMOCRATIC COUNTRIES AND SUPPORTED THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT OF DANIEL ORTEGA, WHO IS NOW DOING ALL HE CAN TO BOYCOTT FREE ELECTIONS TO WHICH THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE ARE ENTITLED TO, AND TO MURDER THOSE WHO LAID DOWN THEIR ARMS AND ARE RETURNING TO THE COUNTRY IN SEARCH OF PEACE, DEMOCRACY, AND LIBERTY.

CODEH HAS DONE NOTHING TO PROMOTE PEACE AND RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, BECAUSE IT IS SUPPORTING AND PROMOTING THE RECRUITMENT, TRAINING, AND ACTIONS OF GUERRILLA GROUPS, WHICH ARE DESTABILIZING AND SOWING VIOLENCE AMONG DEMOCRATIC PEOPLES.

THE EVIDENCE IS CLEAR. CODEH BELIEVES THAT THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT IS THE BEST ONE IN CENTRAL AMERICA. THE FSLN [SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], WITH CUBA'S SUPPORT, IS CHANNELLING ARMS TO THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT OF EL SALVADOR TO MURDER INNOCENT SALVADORAN PEOPLE. ALL THIS IS TAKING PLACE WITH THE APPROVAL OF DR CUSTODIO AND HIS FINANCING SOURCES, WHICH REALIZE THAT THEIR STRATEGIC, IDEOLOGICAL, ECONOMIC, AND POLITICAL GOALS ARE COMING TRUE.

CONCLUSION [SUBHEAD]

IN CONCLUSION: WHAT CAN THE HONDURAN PEOPLE EXPECT FROM DR CUSTODIO AND CODEH WHEN THEY WOULD RATHER DESTROY HONDURAS AND ITS PEOPLE TO INGRATIATE THEMSELVES WITH THE COMMUNISTS?

WHAT CAN BE EXPECTED FROM A HUMAN RIGHTS "LEADER" WHO IS CONSTANTLY DENOUNCING CONDEMNATIONS AND ATTACKS AND DEFINES HIMSELF AS A PERSECUTED PERSON, AND WHO MANIPULATES PUBLIC OPINION TO GAIN NOTORIETY WHILE CREATING FEAR AND TERROR AMONG THE HONDURAN PEOPLE?

WHAT FUTURE CAN HONDURAS EXPECT WHEN THE ALLEGED HUMAN RIGHTS DEFENDER SPECIALIZES IN DISCREDITING THE HONDURAN PEOPLE ABROAD?

WHAT CAN THE HONDURAN PEOPLE EXPECT WHEN CODEH COLLABORATES WITH AND SUPPORTS THE ARMING OF THE SANDINISTS, SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS, AND DICTATOR NORIEGA?

DR CUSTODIO IS NOT BEING PERSECUTED FOR POLITICAL REASONS, HE IS NO HUMAN RIGHTS LEADER, AND HE HAS NOT BEEN CONDEMNED TO DEATH. HE IS SIMPLY A MAN WHO HAS CHOSEN THE WRONG PATH. WHILE COMMUNISM BEHIND THE IRON CURTAIN, WHICH IS OVER 70 YEARS OLD, IS EMBRACING DEMOCRACY AS A WAY OF LIFE (HUNGARY, POLAND), HE INTENDS TO REPLACE DEMOCRACY FOR COMMUNISM AND LIBERTY FOR SLAVERY IN HONDURAS.

DR CUSTODIO HAS SIMPLY MADE A MISTAKE AND HE STAYS ON HIS PATH THROUGH DECEIT AND LIES.

DOWN WITH THE HONDURAN MARXIST-LENINIST TRAITORS!

STOP INTERNATIONAL COMMUNISM!

STOP THE MANIPULATION OF THE HONDURAN PEOPLE!

DEMOCRATS WILL NOT ALLOW THE ENSLAVEMENT AND MURDER OF THE PEOPLES!

LET US STOP THOSE WHO MANIPULATE HUMAN RIGHTS OF OUR HONDURAS.

FREE HONDURAS MOVEMENT

DEV-MUC3-0775 (U NEBRASKA)

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE RECENTLY HEARD U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER ON A SALVADORAN TELEVISION NEWSCAST. HE SAID NO ONE KNEW EXACTLY WHO HAD PLANNED THE MURDER OF FATHER IGNACIO ELLACURIA AND THE OTHER JESUIT PRIESTS WHO WERE ASSASSINATED EARLY YESTERDAY MORNING.

RADIO VENCEREMOS TELLS WILLIAM WALKER THAT HIS CYNICISM IS BEYOND THE LIMIT. WILLIAM WALKER KNOWS PERFECTLY WELL WHICH GENERAL STAFF OFFICE ISSUED THE ORDER TO ASSASSINATE THE JESUIT PRIESTS.

WILLIAM WALKER KNOWS THAT ON THE NIGHT OF 11 NOVEMBER RADIO CUSCATLAN URGED THE PEOPLE TO ASSASSINATE IGNACIO ELLACURIA, RUBEN ZAMORA, AND DOCTOR GUILLERMO UNGO. THE WHOLE WORLD.... [CORRECTS HIMSELF] THE INTERNATIONAL MEDIA HAS FEATURED THE RECORDING IN WHICH RADIO CUSCATLAN -- THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF'S RADIO, MEANING THE RADIO CONTROLLED BY THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF, THE RADIO IN WHICH NOT A SINGLE WORD, NOT A SINGLE COMMA GOES OUT WITHOUT THE APPROVAL OF THE CENSORS WHICH HAVE BEEN IMPOSED ON RADIO CUSCATLAN - - [WORDS INDISTINCT] DEATH.

THEREFORE, WILLIAM WALKER KNOWS PERFECTLY WELL WHERE THE ORDER CAME FROM; HE KNOWS THE EXACT TIME THAT 40 UNIFORMED MEN LEFT IN [WORDS INDISTINCT] CURFEW, A FEW BLOCKS FROM COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE'S OFFICE. WILLIAM WALKER'S CYNICISM WENT BEYOND THE LIMIT WHEN HE SAID THAT HE DOES NOT KNOW [WORDS INDISTINCT] OR WHO PLANNED IGNACIO ELLACURIA'S ASSASSINATION.

WILLIAM WALKER IS DOING A HISTORICAL IMITATION OF THE FILIBUSTER WHO CAME TO CENTRAL AMERICA IN 1856 TO SUBJUGATE OUR PEOPLE AND BECOME PRESIDENT OF A CENTRAL AMERICAN NATION, MEANING NICARAGUA, WHO DECREED THAT ENGLISH BE THE OFFICIAL LANGUAGE, AND THAT THE U.S. FLAG BECOME THE OCCUPATION FORCES' FLAG. WILIAM WALKER IS RE- EDITING A SHAMEFUL CHAPTER IN CENTRAL AMERICA'S HISTORY. WILLIAM WALKER, THE U.S. AMBASSADOR IN OUR HOMELAND, IS RE-EDITING -- IN THE FORM OF A CARICATURE -- A HISTORICAL EVENT WHICH OCCURRED IN THE 19TH CENTURY. HOWEVER, WE WANT TO TELL SOMETHING TO THE NEW WILLIAM WALKER, WHO HAS BEEN FEATURED IN PRESS AND TELEVISION NEWS REPORTS GIVING FIGURES WHICH DIFFER EVEN FROM THOSE GIVEN BY COL PONCE; THE NEW WILLIAM WALKER, WHO THINKS HE IS PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND IS BETTER THAN CRISTIANI AND COL PONCE, SO HE GIVES INVENTED FIGURES ON GUERRILLA CASUALTIES; THE NEW WILLIAM WALKER, WHO EVALUATES THE NATION'S POLITICAL AND MILITARY SITUATION, EVEN BEFORE CRISTIANI AND PONCE DO SO, EVEN CONTRADICTING COL PONCE'S FIGURES. WILLIAM WALKER SAID 40 MEMBERS OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WERE CAPTURED, YET THE BLEARY-EYED COL PONCE LAST NIGHT TALKED ABOUT 9 FMLN MEMBERS. WHERE, THEN, ARE THE REST OF THE CAPTURED FMLN FIGHTERS?

HUMANITARIAN GROUPS SHOULD PAY ATTENTION TO THAT CONTRADICTION BETWEEN PRESIDENT WILLIAM WALKER AND HIS SUBORDINATE, COL PONCE. RED CROSS INTERNATIONAL, GREEN CROSS, AND AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL MUST DEMAND THAT WILLIAM WALKER SAY WHERE THE CAPTURED GUERRILLA FIGHTERS ARE, BECAUSE COL PONCE ONLY MENTIONS NINE FIGHTERS. COL PONCE TALKS ABOUT NINE AND THE OTHER ONE TALKS ABOUT DOZENS. THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY MUST PAY CLOSE ATTENTION TO THE CONTRADICTION BETWEEN PRESIDENT WILLIAM WALKER AND HIS SUBORDINATE, COL PONCE. WHERE ARE THE OTHER CAPTURED FIGHTERS? MOST OF THEM WERE SURELY CIVILIANS WHO HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH THE CONFLICT. THEY MUST HAVE BEEN CAUGHT IN THE WAR ZONES AND THEN PRESENTED TO THE MEDIA AS DEAD GUERRILLA FIGHTERS.

WE DEMAND, BEFORE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, THAT AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER CLEARLY SAY HOW COL PONCE COULD HAVE BEEN MISTAKEN WHEN ADMITTING THAT ONLY NINE GUERRILLA FIGHTERS WERE CAPTURED -- WHILE THE U.S. AMBASSADOR PERSONALLY REVEALED THE FIGURES THAT SHOULD HAVE BEEN REVEALED BY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI A LONG TIME AGO -- EVEN IF THEY WERE IMAGINARY FIGURES. WILLIAM WALKER MUST ANSWER THIS QUESTION: WHERE ARE THE GUERRILLA FIGHTERS?

DEV-MUC3-0777 (PRC)

HAVANA (CUBA), 17 NOV 89 (RADIO REBELDE NETWORK) -- [COMMENTARY] [ORLANDO CONTRERAS] [TEXT] FIGHTING CONTINUES TODAY IN SAN SALVADOR, AND FOR THE FIRST TIME, THE TRIUMPHALIST TONE OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY BEGINS TO CHANGE. AN AP CABLE WE RECEIVED THIS MORNING IN OUR NEWSROOM SAYS THE FOLLOWING: THE ARMED FORCES HAVE ACKNOWLEDGED THEY HAVE SERIOUS PROBLEMS IN VARIOUS SUBURBS OF THIS CAPITAL. THIS IS WHAT THE AP CABLE SAYS TEXTUALLY IN ITS HEADLINE.

IN ADDITION TO THIS SITUATION, THERE IS ANOTHER FACT IN THE BATTLEFIELD TO WHICH THE NEWS AGENCIES HAVE NOT PAID MUCH ATTENTION, WHICH IS ALSO A REFLECTION OF THE TYPE OF COMBAT THAT THE SALVADORAN FORCES ARE FIGHTING. AP ITSELF SAYS THE FOLLOWING: THE WAR BECAME DIRTY WITH THE MURDER OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND TWO WOMEN BY UNIDENTIFIED TERRORISTS WHO ACTED DURING THE CURFEW. FURTHERMORE, THE CABLE SAYS THAT THE CANADIAN EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR REPORTED THAT 12 WORKERS FROM THE LUTHERAN CHURCH WERE ARRESTED BY UNIFORMED SECURITY INDIVIDUALS IN DOWNTOWN SAN SALVADOR. AT THE BEGINNING, THE CABLE SAID THAT THE SIX PRIESTS HAD BEEN MURDERED BY UNIDENTIFIED TERRORISTS. LATER, THEY ARE IDENTIFIED AS UNIFORMED INDIVIDUALS.

AMONG THE PRIESTS MURDERED WAS FATHER IGNACIO ELLACURIA, RECTOR OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY AND DIRECTOR OF A MAGAZINE WHICH REFLECTED THE PEOPLES' THOUGHTS, NOT ONLY IN EL SALVADOR BUT ALSO IN THE REST OF CENTRAL AMERICA. NONE OF THESE PRIESTS BELONGED TO THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. FURTHERMORE, ELLACURIA HIMSELF ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS EXPRESSED OPINIONS WHICH DID NOT CONCUR WITH THOSE OF THE FMLN. HOWEVER, HE FELT THAT A SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN PROBLEM COULD NOT EXCLUDE THE PEOPLE'S INCLUSION OF THE FMLN. THE ASSASSINS WHO ACTED UNDER THE PROTECTION OF THE CURFEW ARE FROM THE SALVADORAN ARMY, THEY ARE NOT UNIDENTIFIED TERRORISTS, LIKE THE AP CABLE SAYS. THEY ARE ASSASSINS OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY, THE SAME ARMY WHICH HAS ALL THE SUPPORT OF THE U.S. GOVERNMENT. IN THIS, WE CAN ALSO SEE THE DOUBLE STANDARD OF THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION. ON THE ONE HAND, ALL ITS PUBLICITY APPARATUS SAYS TO THE WORLD THAT WASHINGTON IS IN FAVOR OF DEMOCRACY AND RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS. HOWEVER, IN PRACTICE, IT SUPPORTS THE ASSASSINS OF PRIESTS AND SUPPLIES BOMBS AND ROCKETS SO THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMY -- WHICH HAS PLANES AND HELICOPTERS PROVIDED BY THE UNITED STATES -- CAN BOMB THE SALVADORAN CIVILIAN POPULATION.

THESE ARE THE FACTS. THIS IS THE TRUTH THAT YANKEE PROPAGANDA IS HIDING AND MANIPULATING.

DEV-MUC3-0778 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] THIS MORNING, AND WITH A STUPID LOOK ON HIS FACE, U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER ASKED WHO HAD KILLED FATHER IGNACIO ELLACURIA. HE SAID HE DID NOT KNOW WHO HAD DONE THIS. WELL THEN, MR WILLIAM WALKER, AND MONITORS AT THE U.S. EMBASSY, GOOD MORNING; RADIO VENCEREMOS GREETS YOU. WE ARE ASKING YOU TO TAKE DOWN WHAT WE ARE GOING TO SAY AND TAKE IT IMMEDIATELY TO WILLIAM WALKER'S OFFICE.

GOOD MORNING U.S. EMBASSY MONITORS, TELL WILLIAM WALTER -- WE DO NOT KNOW IF HE IS FROM TENNESSEE LIKE THE OTHER FILIBUSTER -- THAT RADIO VENCEREMOS IS GIVING HIM A CLUE SO THAT HE CAN FIND OUT WHO KILLED FATHER ELLACURIA. TELL WILLIAM WALKLER TO FIND OUT WHO ARRESTED TWO PRIESTS AND SEVERAL MISSIONARIES, INCLUDING A U.S. CITIZEN THIS MORNING.

AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER, THIS MORNING YOU ASKED WHO HAD MURDERED FATHER IGNACIO ELLACURIA; RADIO VENCEREMOS WILL GIVE YOU A CLUE. FIND OUT WHO ORDERED THIS MORNING'S ARREST OF TWO PRIESTS. U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER, IF YOU HAVE A DROP OF DECENCY LEFT IN YOU, SPEAK UP, SAY WHAT YOU KNOW. TELL US WHERE THE 40 MEN IN UNIFORM LEFT FROM. U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER FROM TENNESSEE, THAT IS, IF YOU ARE FROM TENNESSEE LIKE THE OTHER FILIBUSTER -- RADIO VENCEREMOS IS GIVING YOU A CLUE SO THAT YOU WILL FIND AN ANSWER TO THE QUESTION YOU CANDIDLY ASKED ON TELEVISION THIS MORNING. YOU SAID THAT YOU DID NOT KNOW WHO HAD ORDERED THE DEATH OF ONE OF THE MOST INTELLIGENT MEN IN EL SALVADOR, NOT BORN IN EL SALVADOR BUT MORE SALVADORAN THAN COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE.

WE REPEAT, MR AMBASSADOR TO EL SALVADOR, THE FOLLOWING IS OUR CLUE: FIND OUT WHO ORDERED THE ARREST OF THE PRIESTS AND MISSIONARIES, INCLUDING A U.S. CITIZEN. FIND OUT IMMEDIATELY, AND YOU BETTER MOVE QUICKLY, OTHERWISE THEY COULD BE KILLED. THERE LIES YOUR ANSWER. ASK WHETHER THE TWO PRIESTS WERE ARRESTED BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] OR THE ARMED FORCES. WE INSIST, IF THERE IS A SINGLE DROP OF DECENCY LEFT IN YOU, CHECK THE ELENA FUENTES STATEMENTS AGAINST THE CHURCH MONITORED A FEW DAYS AGO.

MR AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER, IF THERE IS A SINGLE DROP OF DECENCY LEFT IN YOU, CHECK THE RECORDINGS THE U.S. EMBASSY HAS OF RADIO CUSCATLAN AND LISTEN TO WHAT THEY SAID ABOUT FATHER IGNACIO ELLACURIA, MSGR RIVERA Y DAMAS, AND MSGR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ ON THE NIGHT OF 11 NOVEMBER AND EARLIER.

GENTLEMEN AT THE U.S. EMBASSY WHO ARE MONITORING US, HELP THE AMBASSADOR. GO TO YOUR FILES, FIND THE RADIO CUSCATLAN RECORDINGS AND TAKE THEM TO THE AMBASSADOR'S OFFICE. MONITORS AT THE EMBASSY, HELP THAT ABSENTMINDED AMBASSADOR. MONITORS AT THE EMBASSY, GIVE HIM A HAND; IT SEEM THAT THE AMBASSADOR'S MEMORY IS FAILING HIM. MONITORS, YOU WHO ARE SO EFFICIENT, WE ASK YOU TO HELP THE AMBASSADOR REGAIN HIS MEMORY. TAKE HIM COL ELENA FUENTE'S RECORDING ACCUSING THE CHURCH OF HAVING TIES WITH THE FMLN. TAKE HIM COL MONTANO'S STATEMENTS, TAKE HIM COL ZEPEDA'S STATEMENTS, TAKE HIM ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON'S STATEMENTS, ACCUSING FATHER IGNACIO ELLACURIA OF BEING THE DIRECTOR OF THE WAR IN EL SALVADOR. HELP US U.S. EMBASSY MONITORS BECAUSE IT SEEMS THAT MR WILLIAM WALKER HAS A VERY SHORT MEMORY.

DEV-MUC3-0780 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [REPORTER] COMRADE VILLALOBOS [MEMBER OF THE GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN)] REFERRED TO THE BOMBINGS AND THE KILLING OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS. THIS IS THE QUESTION HE WAS ASKED: IN THE PAST FEW HOURS, SEVERAL GOVERNMENTS AND HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS HAVE PRESSURED THE GOVERNMENT TO STOP THE BOMBINGS AND THE BLOODSHED IN OUR HOMELAND. HOWEVER, DESPITE THIS INTERNATIONAL PRESSURE, THE JESUIT PRIESTS WERE KILLED IN SAN SALVADOR. THEREFORE, WHAT IS THE INTENTION BEHIND THE BOMBINGS? WHAT INTENTION DID THE ARMED FORCES' GENERAL STAFF HAVE IN KILLING THE JESUITS? COMMANDER VILLALOBOS REPLIED:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [VILLALOBOS] FIRST, IT MUST BE SAID THAT THE KILLING OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS BY THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT WAS A HARSH BLOW TO THE POSSIBILITIES FOR AN EFFECTIVE DEMOCRACY IN OUR COUNTRY. THE JESUIT PRIESTS ARE A SECTOR OF SALVADORAN SOCIETY THAT HAS MADE AND CONTINUES TO MAKE GREAT CONTRIBUTIONS TO OUR PEOPLE'S EDUCATION. THEY TAUGHT US HOW TO DEBATE, THE NEED TO REASON THINGS OUT, AND THE NEED TO HAVE POLITICAL PLURALISM.

HOWEVER, IT IS EVIDENT THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, THE [WORD INDISTINCT] SECTORS, AND MR. CRISTIANI CANNOT STAND INTELLIGENT PEOPLE, THE DEBATES, THE ANALYSES, AND THE PEOPLE'S REASONING. THIS IS WHY THEY COMMITTED THIS CRIME.

THE RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS CRIME BECOMES EVIDENT, NOT ONLY BASED ON DIRECT CIRCUMSTANCES SUCH AS THE FACT THAT IT WAS CARRIED OUT BY UNIFORMED MEN DURING THE CURFEW PERIOD AND THAT A FEW DAYS BEFORE THE CRIME A GROUP OF MILITARY MEN CHECKED OUT THE PLACE WHERE THEY WERE GOING TO COMMIT THE CRIME -- CLEARLY INTENDING TO PREPARE A PLAN -- BUT BECAUSE OF ACCUSATIONS AGAINST THE JESUITS MADE OVER THE NATIONAL NETWORK. WE MUST ALSO BEAR IN MIND THAT THIS CRIME WAS A POLITICAL MISTAKE MADE BY THE DICTATORSHIP. IT WAS A MISCALCULATION ON THE PART OF THOSE WHO MADE THAT DECISION.

WE HAVE ALREADY MENTIONED THAT THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN UNABLE TO STOP THE FMLN. THEY COULD NOT STOP THE FMLN PLAN. ONCE WE BEGAN TO IMPLEMENT THE PLAN [1-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] A VERY CRITICAL SITUATION.

WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THIS CRITICAL SITUATION, THEY TOOK THE WRONG STEP. THE DAY BEFORE THE CRIME THE ARMED FORCES BEGAN A STRATEGY TO WEAR OUT THE FMLN, LOGISTICALLY. WE MUST NOT IGNORE THE FACT THAT THE ARMED FORCES' CALCULATIONS WERE BASED ON THE ASSUMPTION THAT THE FMLN FORCES WOULD BECOME EXHAUSTED. WE WOULD HAVE MADE A SERIOUS MISTAKE IF WE HAD BEGUN THIS PLAN WITHOUT FORESEEING ALL THESE CIRCUMSTANCES. HOWEVER, THE ARMED FORCES BASED THEIR CALCULATIONS ON OUR POSSIBLE EXHAUSTION.

CONSEQUENTLY, BASED ON THOSE CALCULATIONS, THEY FIGURED THAT THEY HAD 3 OR 4 DAYS TO LAUNCH A COUNTERATTACK. SO, THE DAY PRIOR TO THE KILLING OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THEY LAUNCHED SEVERAL OFFENSIVES -- I RATHER CALL THEM COUNTEROFFENSIVES -- TO TRY TO DISLODGE US FROM OUR POSITIONS. THEIR TACTIC WAS TO MAKE US WASTE AMMUNITION. THEY WERE NOT REALLY TRYING TO MAKE US ABANDON OUR POSITIONS YET.

HOWEVER, OUR FIGHTERS, IN ADDITION TO SAVING OUR AMMUNITION, HAVE THE MATERIAL AND HUMAN RESOURCES SO THEY INFLICTED MANY CASUALTIES ON THE ARMED FORCES AND WORE THEM OUT. BUT IT SEEMS THAT THE ARMED FORCES DID NOT REALIZE THAT AND FELT THAT THEY COULD LAUNCH A BIG COUNTERATTACK TO ANNIHILATE THE FMLN FORCES. BASED ON THAT, THEY CAME UP WITH A PLAN THAT WAS NOT ONLY MILITARY BUT POLITICAL. [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE U.S. AMBASSADOR, THE U.S. ADVISERS, THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION, AND WHO KNOWS WHO ELSE WERE INFORMED ABOUT THIS PLAN. THEY MADE THE WRONG INTERPRETATION OF THE CALLS MADE BY THE INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS AND OTHER HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS ON THE NEED TO HAVE A TRUCE TO EVACUATE CIVILIANS. THEY THOUGHT THAT WE MADE THESE CALLS AND BASED ON THAT, THEY FELT THAT THEY COULD PROCEED TO A COUNTEROFFENSIVE.

BASED ON THAT, LET US ANALYZE THE PROPAGANDA AND INFORMATION DISSEMINATED ON THE DAY PRIOR TO THE KILLING OF THE JESUITS. THE U.S. AMBASSADOR HIMSELF EXPLAINED A WAR REPORT AND GAVE AN UPDATE ON THE SITUATION. THUS, THEY THOUGHT THAT THE FMLN WAS GOING TO SUFFER A GREAT POLITICAL AND MILITARY DEFEAT IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS. THEY HAD AN OVERALL PLAN. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0781 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 -- [INTERVIEW WITH VILLALOBOS, MEMBER OF THE GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [VILLALOBOS] [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE ARMY CARRIED OUT A LARGE BOMB ATTACK ON NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR IN AN EFFORT TO WEAKEN OUR POSITIONS. [WORDS INDISTINCT] THEY THOUGHT THEY WERE GOING TO HAVE A VICTORY THERE. BUT IT JUST SO HAPPENS THAT, ASIDE FROM ALL THE PROPAGANDA THEY USED AND THE PLAN TO WEAKEN US MILITARILY, THE ARMED FORCES ATTACKED UNION OFFICES AND THE HOMES OF LEADERS OF POPULAR MOVEMENTS IN VARIOUS SECTORS. APPARENTLY, EVERYONE HAD GONE INTO HIDING AND THEY ONLY FOUND THE WIFE OF A UNIVERSITY LEADER AND THEY KILLED HER. THEY ALSO FOUND THE JESUITS. IT SEEMS THAT IN VIEW OF RECENT TALKS WITH CRISTIANI, FATHER ELLACURIA HAD BECOME VERY TRUSTING. HE THOUGHT THAT NOTHING WOULD HAPPEN TO THEM. [30-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] THIS SITUATION SO THEY DID NOT PROTECT THEMSELVES IN THE FACE OF THE DANGER OF A POSSIBLE ACTION SUCH AS THIS CRIME.

ON THE SAME NIGHT WHEN THE ENTIRE NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR AREA WAS BEING BOMBED, THE JESUITS WERE KILLED. WHAT WAS THEIR INTENTION? THEY THOUGHT THEY WERE TO OBTAIN A MILITARY VICTORY AND SET OUT TO CARRY OUT A WITCH HUNT. THEY SET OUT TO KILL ALL OPPOSITION MEMBERS THAT ONE NIGHT, WITH THE IDEA THAT THEY WERE GOING TO WIPE OUT THE FMLN, MILITARILY. BASED ON THAT ASSUMPTION, THEY DECIDED TO CARRY OUT THIS ACTION TO GUARANTEE FOR THEMSELVES A FEW MORE YEARS OF STABILITY THROUGH THE PEACE OF CEMETERIES, REGARDLESS OF THE CONSEQUENCES.

WHAT REALLY HAPPENED? THE DAY AFTER THEY COMMITTED THE CRIME, THEY LAUNCHED THEIR OFFENSIVE TO ANNIHILATE THE FMLN. THEY THOUGHT THIS WAS GOING TO BE THEIR DECISIVE DAY, BUT THE OFFENSIVE FAILED. THEIR ATTACK WAS REPELLED, THEY SUSTAINED MANY CASUALTIES, AND LOSS MUCH MATERIEL. THEIR TROOPS WERE FURTHER BEATEN AND THEY DID NOT OBTAIN ANY EFFECTIVE MILITARY RESULTS.

CONSEQUENTLY, THEIR COUNTEROFFENSIVE WAS REJECTED AND THE BLOW THEY THOUGHT THEY WERE GOING TO DEAL TO THE LEADERS OF THE POPULAR MOVEMENT FAILED, ON THE ONE HAND BECAUSE SOME OF THESE LEADERS WERE HIDING AND ON THE OTHER BECAUSE THEY COMMITTED AN HORRENDOUS CRIME AND IT BACKFIRED. IT WAS A CRIME [WORD INDISTINCT] BY THE GENERAL STAFF AND MR. CRISTIANI KNEW ABOUT IT. CRISTIANI CLEARLY [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND PROBABLY EVEN THE U.S. EMBASSY COULD BE INVOLVED IN THIS. THEY THOUGHT THAT BY KILLING ALL OPPOSITION MEMBERS, THEY WERE GOING TO ACHIEVE DEFINITE PEACE IN EL SALVADOR. THIS IS VERY CLEAR. BUT THIS ACTION BACKFIRED. IT WAS A PAINFUL INCIDENT, BUT IT IS AN INCIDENT THAT IS GOING TO BACKFIRE FOR THE GOVERNMENT. IT IS GOING TO RESULT IN GREAT ISOLATION FOR THE REGIME, AT A MOMENT WHEN THE FMLN IS STRONGER. AT A MOMENT WHEN THE FMLN HAS A POLITICAL, MILITARY, AND STRATEGIC ADVANTAGE.

THE MURDER OF THE JESUITS IS SUICIDE FOR THE REGIME. I REALLY DO NOT UNDERSTAND IT. THEY MADE A VERY SERIOUS MISTAKE. IN ADDITION, THEY CONFIRMED A TRUTH WE HAVE BEEN MAINTAINING: THEY ARE FASCISTS AND ASSASSINS. THEY MUST LEAVE POWER. THEY HAVE CREATED A SITUATION IN WHICH THE POSSIBILITY FOR AN FMLN VICTORY IS GREAT. THEY HAVE CREATED A SITUATION IN WHICH THE DISAPPEARANCE OF THE MOST CONSERVATIVE OLIGARCHIC SECTORS OF THE SALVADORAN SOCIETY WILL BE CAUSED BY THEIR OWN MISTAKES. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0782 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 17 NOV 89 (INTERPRESS AGENCY [IPS]) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN OPPOSITION POLITICAL PARTIES AND THE PEOPLE'S ORGANIZATIONS TODAY PROPOSED THE CREATION OF A SALVATION JUNTA THAT WOULD INCLUDE THE ARMY AND THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], HUMBERTO CENTENO -- LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION NATIONAL UNION OF SALVADORAN WORKERS [UNTS] -- HAS ANNOUNCED. IN STATEMENTS TO IPS, CENTENO SAID THE FMLN HAS ALREADY SAID IT IS WILLING TO JOIN THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL LIFE, AND THAT IT IS WILLING TO BE A PART OF A SALVATION JUNTA AS A SOLUTION TO THE NATIONAL CRISIS.

THE UNTS' PROPOSAL WAS SUPPORTED BY FIDEL CHAVEZ MENA, CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC] NATIONAL SECRETARY AND PRESIDENT OF THE LATIN AMERICAN CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC ORGANIZATION, IN STATEMENTS TO THE PRESS. CHAVEZ MENA, WHO WAS THE PDC PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE IN THE PAST ELECTIONS, SAID THAT ONE OF THE WAYS TO SOLVE THE CIVIL WAR PROBLEM WOULD BE FOR THE GOVERNMENT TO RECTIFY ITS STAND AND INITIATE NEW NEGOTIATIONS. WE SHOULD ALL SIT DOWN TO FIND A SOLUTION, HE TOLD NEWSMEN, ADDING THAT NEITHER SIDE WILL ACHIEVE A MILITARY VICTORY.

MEANWHILE, CENTENO STATED THAT THE BOMBINGS IN DENSELY POPULATED AREAS AND THE MURDER OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS ARE FACTORS THAT ARE WEARING OUT THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND. ACCORDING TO THE LABOR LEADER, NONE OF THE SOCIAL FORCES WITH ANY REPRESENTATIVE FORCE SUPPORT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND HIS GOVERNMENT.

ALTHOUGH THERE IS NOT A GENERAL CONSENSUS, THE POLITICAL AND LABOR GROUPS HAVE SAID THEY ARE IN FAVOR OF A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION AND THE RESUMPTION OF A DIALOGUE WITH THE PRESENCE OF THE OAS AND THE UNITED NATIONS AS WELL AS THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS AS GUARANTORS OF THE AGREEMENTS. HOWEVER, THE PETITION MIGHT NOT BE RECEIVED WELL BY A GOVERNMENT THAT IS APPARENTLY NOT WILLING TO NEGOTIATE A CEASE-FIRE WITH THE REBELS WHO CONTINUE OCCUPYING THE NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE NORTHERN AREA OF THE CAPITAL CITY.

DEV-MUC3-0784 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATEMENT] [GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] WE CONDEMN GUATEMALAN INTERFERENCE IN EL SALVADOR.

THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY [URNG] GENERAL COMMAND EXPRESSES ITS PROFOUND SOLIDARITY AND ADMIRATION FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THEIR VANGUARD FORCES, THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], WHO WITH GREAT HEROISM AND DETERMINATION, ARE WRITING ONE OF THE MOST GLORIOUS PAGES IN SALVADORAN HISTORY.

WITH DEEP INDIGNATION, WE HAVE SEEN HOW THE MEMBERS OF LA TANDONA, [MEMBERS OF THE 1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] AND THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] GOVERNMENT HEADED BY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI HAVE DECIDED TO CONDUCT AND MAINTAIN MASSIVE BOMBINGS AGAINST THE DEFENSELESS CIVILIAN POPULATION, THUS SOWING DEATH, SLAUGHTERING, AND DESTROYING, IN VIEW OF THEIR INABILITY TO DEFEAT, DISLODGE, OR CONTAIN THE HEROIC FMLN FIGHTERS.

CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT AND THE SALVADORAN ARMY HAVE LOST CONTROL OVER THEIR ACTIONS BECAUSE OF THEIR DESPERATION OVER THE FMLN'S VICTORIOUS ADVANCE. THE FMLN FORCES HAVE NOT ONLY MAINTAINED THEIR POSITIONS, BUT HAVE ALSO INCREASED THEM IN SAN SALVADOR AND THROUGHOUT THE REMAINING SALVADORAN TERRITORY.

ACTING OUT OF REVENGE, CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT AND THE SALVADORAN ARMY BEGAN A SERIES OF CRIMINAL ACTIONS AIMED AT ALL THOSE WHO HAVE IDENTIFIED THEMSELVES WITH THE FAIR CAUSES OF THE SALVADORAN MAJORITY. AS A RESULT, EARLY ON THE MORNING OF 16 NOVEMBER, SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND TWO HUMBLE WOMEN WHO WORKED WITH THEM WERE BRUTALLY MURDERED.

WE SHARE THE ENORMOUS PAIN OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THAT OF THE JESUIT COMMUNITIES. WE ADD OUR PROTEST TO THE VOICES OF ALL THOSE WHO HAVE PROTESTED AGAINST SUCH A VILE MURDER.

THE URNG GENERAL COMMAND VIGOROUSLY CONDEMNS THOSE ACTIONS AND CALLS ON THE GUATEMALAN PEOPLE AND ON ALL POLITICAL, SOCIAL, DEMOCRATIC, AND RELIGIOUS ORGANIZATIONS TO EXPRESS THEMSELVES AGAINST THOSE BARBARIC AND GENOCIDAL ACTIONS, WHICH CAN ONLY BE COMPARED TO THE ACTIONS CARRIED OUT BY THE UNITED STATES IN VIETNAM AND THE NAZIS DURING WORLD WAR II.

IN OUR STATEMENT ISSUED ON 13 NOVEMBER, WE REPORTED THE INTERVENTIONIST PLANS OF THE GUATEMALAN ARMY AGAINST OUR FRATERNAL NATION, EL SALVADOR. ACCORDING TO REPORTS RELEASED BY PRESS AGENCIES ON 15 NOVEMBER, 126 GUATEMALAN ARMY MEN BELONGING TO SPECIAL TROOPS CALLED SAIBILES, WHO CHARACTERIZED THEMSELVES FOR THEIR PATHOLOGIC SAVAGERY, WERE DEPLOYED. [SENTENCE AS HEARD] PRESIDENT CEREZO, THE CHIEF OF THE GUATEMALAN GENERAL STAFF, AND THE GUATEMALAN ARMY OFFICIAL SPOKESMAN HAVE ALREADY PUBLICLY EXPRESSED THEIR SOLIDARITY AND SUPPORT FOR CRISTIANI.

WE VIGOROUSLY CONDEMN THE INTERFERENCE OF THE GUATEMALAN ARMY AGAINST THE GLORIOUS SALVADORAN PEOPLE. WE CALL ON ALL GUATEMALAN GROUPS TO PROTEST THAT INTERFERENCE. WE WILL MAKE THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMY PAY A VERY HIGH PRICE FOR THIS AGGRESSION AGAINST THE FRATERNAL SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

WE WARN THE WORLD THAT A GENOCIDE LARGER THAN THE ONE WHICH HAS ALREADY OCCURRED IS BEING CONDUCTED IN EL SALVADOR NOW. WE ARE SURE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WILL DEFEAT ALL THEIR ENEMIES; THAT THEY WILL BE THE WINNERS OF THIS HISTORIC STRUGGLE, AND THAT THEY WILL ACHIEVE THEIR GOALS.

THE BLOOD THAT HAS BEEN SHED WILL TURN INTO NEW LIFE. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WILL UNDOUBTEDLY ACHIEVE THEIR GOALS OF FREEDOM, DEMOCRACY, AND PEACE.

GUATEMALA, 17 NOVEMBER 1989

URNG GENERAL COMMAND

[SIGNED] COMMANDER ROLANDO MORAN

COMMANDER GASPAR ILOM

COMMANDER PABLO MONSANTO

CARLOS GONZALEZ, PGT [GUATEMALAN LABOR PARTY] SECRETARY GENERAL

DEV-MUC3-0786 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 17 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] SALVADORAN PEOPLE: WE HAVE POWERFUL REASONS FOR ENSURING THAT JUSTICE WILL BE SERVED IN THIS REGRETTABLE INCIDENT IN WHICH FATHER ELLACURIA, OTHER PRIESTS, AND CIVILIANS WERE KILLED. WE WANT TO TELL THOSE WHO ARE TRYING TO DRAW PREMATURE CONCLUSIONS TO ABSTAIN FROM DOING SO; WE URGE YOU TO HEED THE COMMUNITY OF JESUS AND THE ARCHBISHOPRIC OF SAN SALVADOR'S CALLS THAT THIS CASE NOT BE POLITICIZED OR USED TO GENERATE FURTHER VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY.

WE BELIEVE THAT AN INVESTIGATION MUST BE CONDUCTED; WE ARE COMMITTED TO CONDUCTING AN IN-DEPTH INVESTIGATION TO PUNISH THE PERPETRATORS OF THIS SAVAGE ACTION REGARDLESS OF WHO IS INVOLVED. THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC WILL REQUEST HELP TO ENSURE THAT THE SALVADORAN CRIME INVESTIGATION COMMISSION WILL BE ADVISED BY EXPERTS IN ORDER TO GET TO THE ROOT OF THIS REGRETTABLE INCIDENT AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. WE WILL ASK THE UNITED STATES, GREAT BRITAIN, AND SPAIN TO HELP US. I MENTION SPAIN BECAUSE SOME OF THOSE WHO WERE ASSASSINATED ARE CITIZENS OF THAT COUNTRY.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: WE BELIEVE THAT THE TIME HAS COME TO CONDUCT AN INVESTIGATION AND ENSURE THAT JUSTICE IS SERVED IN REPREHENSIBLE ACTIONS LIKE THIS ONE INSTEAD OF POLITICIZING THEM AND GENERATING FURTHER VIOLENCE.

THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND THE ARMED FORCES WILL NEVER ALLOW A RETURN TO THE PAST; A RETURN TO THOSE DRAMATIC AND REGRETTABLE TIMES IN THE COUNTRY WHEN GROUPS WANTED TO FUTHER THEIR CAUSE THROUGH VIOLENT ACTS SUCH AS THIS ONE. WE WILL NOT ALLOW THIS TO HAPPEN AND WILL PURSUE SUCH GROUPS TO ENSURE THAT THEY FEEL THE FULL FORCE OF THE LAW.

DEV-MUC3-0787 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 17 NOV 89 (CADENA REVOLUCIONARIA NACIONAL) -- [REPORT] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] ON THE 7TH DAY OF THE OFFENSIVE, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HAS TAKEN A STRATEGIC TURN IN THE WAR, AS WE BEGIN TO STRUGGLE FOR POWER IN A NEW AND DEFINITE SCENARIO OF OPERATIONS IN THE CITIES, WITH THE INSURRECTIONAL PARTICIPATION OF THE PEOPLE SEEKING TO ACHIEVE PEACE AND DEMOCRACY. THE FIGHTING WAGED IN SAN SALVADOR, SAN MIGUEL, USULUTAN, ZACATECOLUCA, SANTA ANA, AND OTHER PARTS IN THE COUNTRY HAVE BEEN POSSIBLE THANKS TO THE LEADING ROLE PLAYED BY THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE SUPPORTED AND JOINED THE STRUGGLE.

THE 7 DAYS OF OUR OFFENSIVE HAVE EXPOSED THE MILITARY FASCIST DICTATORSHIP TO THE EYES OF THE WORLD. THE DICTATORSHIP HAS REMOVED ITS CIVILIAN MASK, AND IT HAS SHOWN ITS BARBARIC NATURE AS IT BOMBED CITIES AND MURDERED JESUIT PRIESTS, WHO WERE MEMBERS OF A NATIONAL CONSCIENCE THAT IS SEEKING SOCIAL CHANGES AND PEACE IN EL SALVADOR.

THESE CRIMES COMMITTED BY CRISTIANI AND COLONEL PONCE [CHAIRMAN OF THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF] DEFINITELY ISOLATE THEM FROM THE REST OF THE WORLD, WHICH CONDEMNS THEM AND RECALLS THE LAST DAYS OF SOMOZA. IN THE MEANTIME, THE U.S. CONGRESS DISCUSSES CUTTING MILITARY AID TO THE REGIME. THE 7 DAYS OF OUR OFFENSIVE HAVE LED TO IRREVERSIBLE ACHIEVEMENTS. THE REGIME HAS BEEN DEFEATED IN THE POLITICAL FIELD AND FATALY WOUNDED IN THE MILITARY FIELD.

IN 7 DAYS OF COMBAT IN THE CAPITAL CITY, THE HIGH COMMAND LOST ITS LAST DEFENSIVE LINE. OUR FORCES ARE HITTING HARD AT THEIR TIRED HEART. VICTORY IS A FACT THAT NO ONE CAN ALTER.

IN THE OFFENSIVE, WE KILLED OR WOUNDED AN ESTIMATED 827 TROOPS AND OFFICERS. WE SEIZED 127 LONG WEAPONS, 21 MACHINEGUNS AND SUPPORT WEAPONS, AS WELL AS ABOUT 80,000 ROUNDS OF AMMUNITION OF VARIOUS CALIBERS. WE HAVE CONFIRMED REPORTS THAT WE HAVE DAMAGED 11 AIRCRAFT AND DESTROYED 27 ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS.

THE HUMILIATING DEFEAT OF THE HIGH COMMAND IS EVIDENT IN A DEPRESSED COL PONCE, WHO NO LONGER SPEAKS OF THE GUERRILLAS IN POCKETS ALONG THE BORDER. INSTEAD, HE SPEAKS IN FRONT OF A MAP OF THE CAPITAL CITY, POINTING OUT THE PRESENCE AND ADVANCE OF THE FMLN.

VARIOUS POLITICAL AND SOCIAL GROUPS OF EL SALVADOR HAVE INITIATED EFFORTS ON THE INTERNATIONAL LEVEL TO ACHIEVE A CONSENSUS IN ORDER TO FORM A NEW GOVERNMENT THAT WILL PUT AN END TO THE WAR AND BRING ABOUT THE DEMOCRATIZATION OF THE COUNTRY. THE FMLN LOOKS FAVORABLY ON THESE EFFORTS, AND IT HAS ALREADY ACTIVELY JOINED THESE NATIONAL SECTORS WHO ARE OPPOSED TO THE GENOCIDE BEING CARRIED OUT BY THE HIGH COMMAND IN A SUICIDAL ATTEMPT TO PRESERVE THE WAR THAT IT HAS TURNED INTO A BUSINESS DEAL.

THE GENERAL COMMAND RECOGNIZES THE HEROISM OF OUR FIGHTERS AND CALLS ON THEM TO CONTINUE ADVANCING ALONG WITH OUR REBELS IN THE FINAL CHAPTER OF THIS HISTORY.

[SIGNED] THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND, 17 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0788 (PRC)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 17 NOV 89 (LA REPUBLICA) -- [TEXT] PRD [DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTIONARY PARTY] COMMUNIQUE:

TWENTY YEARS AFTER THE LATIN AMERICAN CHURCH MET IN MEDELLIN AND DECIDED TO WORK FOR THE NEEDY, DEATH SQUADS IN EL SALVADOR HAVE MURDERED IGNACIO ELLACURIA, A PRIEST, TEACHER, AND A SOCIAL FIGHTER, ALONG WITH SEVEN OTHER PRIESTS AND FAITHFUL. A WAR THAT BEGAN WITH THE MARTYRDOM OF ARCHBISHOP OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO IS NOW TAKING THE LIVES OF HUNDREDS OF VICTIMS WHO ARE KILLED IN INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS AND ATTACKS ON THE POPULATION.

THE CRIME COMMITTED TODAY WAS SPONSORED BY THE SAME ONES WHO ARE NOW PLANNING GENERAL MANUEL ANTONIO NORIEGA'S MURDER. THERE IS ONLY A DIFFERENCE OF TIME AND PLACE. INSTEAD OF BOMBING DENSELY POPULATED NEIGHBORHOODS, THESE PEOPLE ARE RESORTING TO ATTACKS ON CERTAIN FIGURES AND LEADERS.

BECAUSE OF THE ENORMOUS SIZE OF THE LATIN AMERICAN CRISIS, IT IS EVIDENT THAT THE CHURCH CANNOT ESCAPE THE DEMAND THAT MODERN TIMES IMPOSE ON ALL GROUPS OF DECIDING WHETHER TO BE ON THE SIDE OF PATRIOTIC AND LIBERTARIAN CAUSES OR TO BECOME ACCOMPLICES OF LOCAL AND FOREIGN OPPRESSORS.

LIKE MSGR ROMERO, FATHER ELLACURIA AND HIS COMPANIONS IN MARTYRDOM REPRESENT THE CHURCH THAT IS BORN FROM THE HOMELAND AND THAT STRUGGLES ALONG WITH THE PEOPLE. PANAMANIAN GENERAL OMAR TORRIJOS ALSO DECIDED TO WORK ALONG WITH THE PEOPLE FROM INSIDE THE ARMED FORCES. THESE MARTYRS DESERVE THE SAME SOLIDARITY THEY GAVE TO THE LATIN AMERICAN CAUSE OF NATIONAL LIBERATION, BECAUSE THEY CHALLENGED THE OLIGARCHY, IMPERIALISM, AND EVEN THE REACTIONARY GROUPS OF THEIR OWN CHURCH.

NOW, WHEN ALL THE WEIGHT OF THE LATIN AMERICAN CRISIS AND FOREIGN AGGRESSION FALLS UPON THE SALVADORAN AND PANAMANIAN PEOPLES; NOW THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE MASSIVELY REPRESSED; AND NOW THAT THE GOVERNMENT IN WASHINGTON ORDERS THE CIA TO ATTACK GEN NORIEGA, THOSE WHO STRUGGLE IN EL SALVADOR AND THOSE WHO PATRIOTICALLY RESIST ARE IN FACT DOING SO FOR ALL OF LATIN AMERICA.

THUS, IGNACIO ELLACURIA'S AND HIS PARTNERS' SACRIFICE, AS WELL AS THE PREVIOUS SACRIFICE OF MSGR ROMERO AND THAT OF GEN NORIEGA, WILL BEAR FRUITS OF LIBERATION, JUSTICE, AND SOVEREIGNTY.

THESE FRUITS WILL BE PLENTIFUL AND MORE DELICIOUS IF ALL THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN NEXT TO AND LEARNED FROM THESE PEOPLE CONTINUE STRUGGLING WITH THEIR EXAMPLE IN MIND. THE SACRIFICE THEY HAVE MADE FOR ALL OF US DESERVES PRAISE AND SOLIDARITY. WE OFFER THEM THAT PRAISE AND SOLIDARITY BY REAFFIRMING OUR COMMITMENT TO WORK AND STRUGGLE FOR THE DEFINITIVE LIBERATION OF OUR OWN PEOPLE.

[SIGNED] CARLOS DUQUE, PRESIDENT

NATIONAL EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE

DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTIONARY PARTY

PANAMA, 16 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0791 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 17 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, IN PROGRESS] [TEXT] ...HAVE CONTROLLED THE TERRORIST ACTIONS OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. ON 17 NOVEMBER, THE ARMED FORCES MADE GREAT ADVANCES, AND WE CAN NOW SAY THAT THE AREA OF ZACAMIL HAS BEEN TOTALLY RECOVERED. THE CIVILIAN RESIDENTS OF THAT SECTOR HAVE SUFFERED VERY MUCH. LIKEWISE, THE ARMED FORCES CONTROL OTHER AREAS IN MEJICANOS MUNICIPALITY. THERE ARE ONLY SOME SMALL POCKETS IN CIUDAD DELGADO AND SOME SECTORS OF SOYAPANGO MUNICIPALITY WHERE THERE ARE STILL SOME CLASHES.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, IT IS REGRETTABLE THAT THE FMLN INSISTS ON CONTINUING WITH THESE DESTRUCTIVE ACTIONS THAT MAKE INNOCENT PEOPLE, WHO ONLY WANT TO BE WITH THEIR FAMILIES AND LIVE IN PEACE, GO THROUGH SOME TRULY DRAMATIC MOMENTS. HOWEVER, WE MUST HAVE FULL CONFIDENCE THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE GOING TO DEFINITELY CONTROL ALL OF THESE FMLN TERRORISTS. THAT IS THE SCOPE OF THE ARMED FORCES ADVANCE, SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

WE TRUST THAT EACH DAY WE WILL CONTINUE ADVANCING UNTIL WE HAVE FULL CONTROL, IN THE LEAST AMOUNT OF TIME POSSIBLE, ALWAYS RESPECTING THE LIVES OF THOSE CIVILIANS IN DANGER. IN A COWARDLY MANNER, THE FMLN HIDES BEHIND THESE INNOCENT CIVILIANS AND USES THEM AS SHIELDS.

WE ALSO WANT TO TELL YOU, SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND PARTICULARLY THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN FORCED IN ANY MANNER TO ABANDON THEIR HOMES THAT, THROUGH THE EMERGENCY COMMISSION, THE GOVERNMENT IS OFFERING BASIC SERVICES, AS BEST IT CAN, TO THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN TEMPORARILY DISPLACED FROM THEIR HOMES.

WE BELIEVE THAT WITH THE HELP OF ALL THE FRIENDLY COUNTRIES WHO ARE ALREADY BEGINNING TO HELP AND SEND AID, [CHANGES THOUGHT] FOR EXAMPLE, THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. WE HAVE ALSO BEEN TOLD THAT TOMORROW THE KING OF SPAIN IS SENDING A PLANE LOADED WITH MEDICATION. ANOTHER PLANE IS BRINGING 55,000 TONS OF MEDICATIONS FROM THE ORDER OF MALTA. THE SALVADORAN-AMERICAN FOUNDATION IS SENDING A VERY GENEROUS DONATION OF 200 FIELD TENTS TO BE USED TO PROVIDE PROTECTION FOR MANY FAMILIES FROM THE INCLEMENCY OF THE WEATHER. THERE IS ALSO THE ROTARY CLUB, AND THERE IS EVEN A COMMUNITY IN THE UNITED STATES CALLED COOPERATION CALIFORNIA THAT IS SENDING 3,000 TONS OF CORN.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AS YOU HAVE OBSERVED, AID IS ON ITS WAY. WE WANT TO TELL THOSE WHO ARE IN SUCH SITUATIONS, IN ONE WAY OR ANOTHER, TO REMAIN CALM, TO LISTEN TO THE INFORMATION AND INSTRUCTIONS THAT ARE CONTINUOUSLY BEING GIVEN OVER THE NATIONAL RADIO NETWORK, AND TO COOPERATE AND HELP SO THAT THE DISTRIBUTION OF FOOD AND MEDICATIONS CAN BE DONE IN THE BEST ORDERLY MANNER. WE FEEL THAT WHAT THE COUNTRY HAD IN STORAGE AND WHAT THESE GENEROUS COUNTRIES AND ORGANIZATIONS ARE DONATING WILL BE SUFFICIENT TO ATTEND TO THE PEOPLE WHO ARE BEING MOMENTARILY AFFECTED.

THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC IS ALSO MAKING EFFORTS TO HAVE A RECONSTRUCTION FUND. WE KNOW THAT MANY HOMES HAVE BEEN DAMAGED. THE TERRORISTS HAVE OPENED HUGE HOLES IN ORDER TO MOVE IN BETWEEN THESE HOUSES. THIS COWARDLY ATTACK BY THE FMLN HAS BROUGHT ABOUT MUCH DESTRUCTION. ONCE THE SITUATION HAS BEEN NORMALIZED, WE WANT TO BE ABLE TO GIVE YOU FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE SO THAT YOU CAN REBUILD YOUR HOMES AND RETURN TO NORMALCY AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0792 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 17 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] AND SO, TODAY WE RECEIVED A RESOLUTION FROM THE GUATEMALAN CONGRESS, WHERE THE GUATEMALAN CHRISTIAN DEMOCRACY, UCN [UNION OF THE NATIONAL CENTER], AND THE MLN [NATIONAL LIBERATION MOVEMENT], IN SUM, ALL THE POLITICAL FORCES JOINED IN CONDEMNING VIOLENCE AND THE FMLN, AND SUPPORTING OUR COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONALITY WHICH IS WHAT THE PEOPLE WANT. SALVADORAN BROTHERS, THIS SUPPORT MUST SERVE TO MOTIVATE US TO CREATE A UNITED FRONT, REJECT THE FMLN'S TERRORIST VIOLENCE, AND SEEK THE PEACE OUR COUNTRY WANTS AND NEEDS.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WE ARE SURE THIS WILL BE OVER SOON. IN TIMES LIKE THESE, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAVE ALWAYS REACTED IN A POSITIVE MANNER. SOLIDARITY EXISTS AMONG ALL SALVADORANS TO SEEK AND HELP THE NEEDIEST. THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS READY TO DO EVERYTHING WITHIN ITS POWER TO ACHIEVE TOTAL NORMALIZATION AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. IN ADDITION, IT IS JUST TO RECOGNIZE THE MILITARY CHIEFS AND OFFICERS AND, ESPECIALLY, THE SOLDIERS WHO HAVE BEEN DEFENDING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE FOR MANY DAYS, TRYING TO OUST THE FMLN HORDES FROM SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER CITIES WHERE THEY SOUGHT TO SOW TERROR.

WE BELIEVE THAT THOSE MILITARY CHIEFS AND OFFICERS MUST FEEL THE SUPPORT FROM ALL THE PEOPLE AND, PRIMARILY, OUR RECOGNITION OF THEIR BRAVERY AND TOTAL DEDICATION TO THEIR FATHERLAND AND PEOPLE, WHO ARE NOW SEEKING PEACE AND CALM. AS FOR US, MILITARY CHIEFS, OFFICERS, SOLDIERS: OUR HIGHEST RECOGNITION AND GRATITUDE. HISTORY WILL REWARD YOU AND SAY THE GLORIOUS ARMED FORCES AND THEIR UNITS FOUND THE ROAD FOR ERADICATING VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY. SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THROUGH THE NATIONAL RADIO NETWORK AND DIFFERENT LOCAL NEWS MEDIA, YOU HAVE LEARNED WHAT IS HAPPENING. WE WILL BE GIVING YOU THE INFORMATION YOU NEED. WE ALSO WANT TO ASK YOU TODAY, JUST AS YOU SAW ALMOST TOTAL NORMALCY -- BUSES ON THE STREETS, PEOPLE GOING TO WORK -- TO CONTINUE DOING YOUR PART SO THAT TRANQUILLITY WILL PREVAIL AS SOON AS POSSIBLE. TO ALL, THANK YOU. MAY GOD BLESS YOU.

DEV-MUC3-0796 (PRC)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 18 NOV 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [TEXT] [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH NORMAN LACAYO, NICARAGUAN CHARGE D'AFFAIRES IN EL SALVADOR BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [LACAYO, IN PROGRESS] ...GOVERNMENT AGAINST OUR EMBASSY WORSENED. THIS CAMPAIGN WAS INITIATED AT THE HIGHEST LEVELS OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. ON VARIOUS OCCASIONS OVER THE PAST 8 DAYS, TELEVISION, PRESS, AND RADIO HAVE SYSTEMATICALLY BROADCAST STATEMENTS BY EL SALVADOR'S TOP MILITARY AND POLITICAL AUTHORITIES, PRESIDENT CRISTIANI, VICE PRESIDENT MERINO, AND THE HEAD OF ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE], ETC, BLAMING NICARAGUA FOR WHAT IS HAPPENING IN EL SALVADOR.

THIS CAMPAIGN HAS BEEN SYSTEMATIC AND IT HAS ENCOURAGED TERRORIST GROUPS TO THREATEN THE LIVES AND SAFETY OF NICARAGUA'S DIPLOMATIC REPRESENTATIVES. OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS, I HAVE RECEIVED MANY DEATH THREATS FROM EXTREMIST SECTORS AND, I REPEAT, THIS LED THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT TO THE DECISION TO EVACUATE US.

THIS DOES NOT MEAN THAT DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES ARE BROKEN. IT IS A PRECAUTIONARY MEASURE TO ENSURE THE ENTIRE MISSION'S PHYSICAL SAFETY. WE REQUESTED DIPLOMATIC PROTECTION FROM THE MEXICAN GOVERNMENT AND RECEIVED A POSITIVE RESPONSE. WE WENT TODAY FROM THE RESIDENCE OF THE MEXICAN AMBASSADOR IN EL SALVADOR TO THE AIRPORT, AND FROM THERE TO MANAGUA.

IF YOU HAVE ANY QUESTIONS, I WILL BE GLAD TO ANSWER THEM.

[REPORTER] A QUESTION FROM RADIO SANDINO. FIRST OF ALL, SINCE YOU GOT A FIRST- HAND VIEW, WHAT IS THE CURRENT SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR; SECOND, IS THIS A PROVISIONAL MEASURE OR WILL IT BE EXTENDED; HOW LONG WILL THIS MEASURE LAST?

[LACAYO] I CANNOT SAY HOW LONG IT WILL LAST. THAT IS UP TO THE GOVERNMENT, AND IT WILL DEPEND ON THE INTERNAL SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY. REGARDING YOUR FIRST QUESTION, THE SITUATION IS DIFFICULT. ON A MILITARY LEVEL, THE WAR CONTINUES; THERE IS A GOOD DEAL OF MISINFORMATION BY THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND MANY INTERNATIONAL NEWS AGENCIES. THE TRUTH IS THAT THE BATTLE CONTINUES, THERE HAS BEEN CONSIDERABLE PHYSICAL DESTRUCTION IN MANY TOWNS AND NEIGHBORHOODS ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR. YOU KNOW WHICH TOWNS ARE INCLUDED: ZACAMIL, CIUDAD DELGADO, SOYAPANGO, ETC. THIS IS THE RESULT OF THE INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS BY THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE.

[REPORTER] THERE IS A REPORT THAT SOMOZIST GUARDS ARE FIGHTING WITH THE SALVADORAN ARMY. IS THERE ANYTHING TO THIS?

[LACAYO] THERE ARE RUMORS TO THAT EFFECT. SOME INSURGENT RADIO STATIONS HAVE REPORTED IT, AND THEY HAVE ALSO MENTIONED TROOPS FROM OTHER CENTRAL AMERICAN GOVERNMENTS.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] YES, BUT NOT WITH THE PERSISTENCE THAT PREVAILS NOW.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] OF COURSE. MANY TELEPHONE CALLS, SURVEILLACE BY SUSPICIOUS INDIVIDUALS AND VEHICLES AT THE RESIDENCE THROUGHOUT THE DAY, AND ESPECIALLY DIRECT THREATS BY TELEPHONE.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] I WOULD IMAGINE THEY ARE SALVADORAN RIGHTWING EXTREMISTS, BETTER KNOWN AS DEATH SQUADS. THEY BEGAN TO SELECTIVELY SHOOT PEOPLE. THERE IS THE CASE OF MRS NORMA GIROLA DE HERRERA, PRESIDENT OF THE WOMENS INSTITUTE, A VERY PROGRESSIVE INSTITUTION. MRS HERERA WAS VERY WELL KNOWN, AND SHE WAS MURDERED UNDER CIRCUMSTANCES VERY SIMILAR TO THOSE OF THE ASSASINATION OF THE JESUITS; ON THE SAME DAY.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO[ I DO NOT HAVE ANY MORE INFORMATION BECAUSE OF THE CITY'S MILITARIZATION. A STATE OF SIEGE HAS BEEN IMPLEMENTED, THE CIRCULATION OF VEHICLES IS MINIMAL, COMMUNICATION IS SPARSE, TELEPHONES ARE TAPPED.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] YES, THAT HAS BEEN PROVEN.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] THEY ARE WAGING A WAR WHICH CONSISTS AT TIMES OF MAINTAINING POSITIONS, AT OTHER TIMES OF MOBILIZING. ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS CONTROLLED AREAS CEASED TO BE CONTROLLED BUT THE WAR CONTINUES.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] NO, I DO NOT KNOW. THE GOVERNMENT DID THAT DIRECTLY THROUGH THE FOREIGN MINISTRY.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] NO, BECAUSE WE DID NOT KNOW. HOWEVER, THE TRUTH IS THAT WE NEVER HAD PROTECTION. WE NEVER HAD POLICE PROTECTION AT THE RESIDENCE ALTHOUGH IT WAS REQUESTED THROUGH THE FOREIGN MINISTRY. THE EMBASSY HAD TWO POLICEMEN, BUT DURING THIS PERIOD THEY LEFT AND THE EMBASSY IS WITHOUT POLICE PROTECTION.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] THAT HAS BEEN SAID ABOUT GUATEMALA AND HONDURAS.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LACAYO] AS A REPORT AND IN THE PRESS.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT] [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0798 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 18 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, ATTENTION. WE HAVE A LAST MINUTE REPORT. THE REPORT IS COMING FROM THE CAPITAL CITY. HEAVY CLASHES ARE CONTINUING THIS MORNING IN VARIOUS PARTS OF NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

CLASHES ARE CONTINUING IN THE NORTHEASTERN NEIGHBORHOODS OF SAN SALVADOR, AND HEAVY FIGHTING IS TAKING PLACE IN CIUDAD DELGADO. THE ENEMY TROOPS ARE SUPPORTED BY ARMORED VEHICLES, HELICOPTERS, AND A [WORD INDISTINCT] SMALL PLANE, BUT OUR COMRADES ARE MAINTAINING THEIR POSITIONS IN CIUDAD DELGADO.

THIS IS A LAST MINUTE REPORT. HEAVY FIGHTING IS CURRENTLY TAKING PLACE IN THE SAN SALVADOR NORTHEASTERN NEIGHBORHOODS. THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] IS DETERMINED TO WIN. CIUDAD DELGADO CONTINUES FIGHTING. THERE ARE ALSO HEAVY CLASHES IN MEJICANOS.

ATTENTION. HEAVY CLASHES ARE NOT JUST TAKING PLACE IN SAN SALVADOR. CLASHES ALSO CONTINUE IN SAN MIGUEL CITY. THE FMLN POSITIONS IN SAN MIGUEL CONTINUE TO BE STRONG. WE CONTINUE TO ADVANCE IN SAN MIGUEL CITY.

THE REPORT COMING FROM SAN MIGUEL STATES THAT CLASHES CONTINUE AT THIS TIME. CIUDAD DELGADO AND SAN MIGUEL ARE BOTH CENTERS OF POPULAR FIGHTING.

RADIO VENCEREMOS IS RECEIVING LAST MINUTE REPORTS. TODAY, SATURDAY 18 NOVEMBER, WE ARE RECEIVING A REPORT SAYING THAT AT 0500, OUR FIGHTERS BEGAN A COUNTERATTACK ON POSITIONS OF THE ARMED FORCES ENGINEERS MILITARY DETACHMENT, DEMIFA. THE DEMIFA POSITION WAS ATTACKED, AND THE CLASHES HAVE SPREAD TO [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND THE DEMIFA HEADQUARTERS. [PASSAGE INDISTINCT]

IN ADDITION, A STEEL FACTORY IN ZACATECOLUCA WAS SABOTAGED AFTER DISLODGING THE [WORD INDISTINCT] DEMIFA TROOPS.

WE REPEAT. THE FMLN BEGAN A COUNTERATTACK ON THE DEMIFA HEADQUARTERS IN ZACATECOLUCA AT 0500 TODAY. THE CLASHES IN ZACATECOLUCA CITY, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT HAVE SPREAD NORTH, WEST, AND EAST OF THE DEMIFA HEADQUARTERS.

AT 0500, THE FMLN FORCES BEGAN TO MOVE IN THE DEMIFA HEADQUARTERS, ATTACKING IT WITH RIFLE AND ARTILLERY FIRE AND MACHINEGUNS. IN ZACATECOLUCA, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT, OUR FORCES TOOK CONTROL OF THE ENTIRE STEEL FACTORY. AFTER DISLODGING THE ENEMY TROOPS, OUR FORCES SET THE FACTORY ON FIRE. THE FACTORY IS OWNED BY ONE OF THE OLIGARCHIC FAMILIES THAT FINANCE THE DEATH SQUADS.

THE REPORTS WE HAVE JUST READ TO YOU, WHICH CAME FROM SAN SALVADOR, ZACATECOLUCA, AND SAN MIGUEL -- THREE VERY IMPORTANT SALVADORAN CITIES -- INDICATE THAT FIGHTING HAS INCREASED TODAY. AT THIS TIME, THE AIR FORCE IS BOMBING FMLN POSITIONS IN CIUDAD DELGADO, NORTHEASTERN SAN SALVADOR. THE AIR FORCE IS NOW CONDUCTING AN INDISCRIMINATE ATTACK IN DENSELY POPULATED AREAS.

DEV-MUC3-0801 (PRC)

MADRID (SPAIN), 18 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT SEEMS READY TO CARRY OUT THE INVESTIGATION REQUESTED BY THE SPANISH GOVERNMENT TO CLARIFY LAST THURSDAY'S MURDER OF EIGHT PEOPLE, SIX OF THEM JESUITS, OF WHOM FIVE WERE SPANIARDS. GOOD EVENING SPECIAL CORRESPONDENT GLORIA DEL CAMPO IN SAN SALVADOR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [DEL CAMPO] GOOD EVENING. SPANISH UNDER SECRETARY FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS INOCENCIO ARIAS HAD A 40-MINUTE MEETING WITH PRESIDENT OF EL SALVADOR ALFREDO CRISTIANI, AND ALSO HAD A SEPARATE MEETING WITH THE DEPUTY FOREIGN MINISTER IN THE ABSENCE OF THE MINISTER.

ACCORDING TO INOCENCIO ARIAS, CRISTIANI WAS VERY CORDIAL AND ABSOLUTELY PREPARED TO LAUNCH AN INVESTIGATION AND HE SAID THE HE WANTS SPAIN, THE UNITED STATES, AND GREAT BRITAIN TO MAKE UP THE COMMISSION WHICH WILL INVESTIGATE THE MURDER OF THE SIX JESUITS AND THE TWO WOMEN WHO WORKED AT THE RESIDENCE OF THE JESUITS. ALTHOUGH IT IS STILL NOT KNOWN WHEN THE INVESTIGATION WILL START, CRISTIANI SAID IT WILL BE SOON AND THAT THE INVESTIGATION WILL BE RAPID, SERIOUS, AND IN-DEPTH. IT IS NOT KNOWN EITHER WHICH OFFICIALS OR EXPERTS WILL BE INVOLVED OR HOW LONG IT WILL LAST. CRISTIANI ALSO SAID THAT THE ARMED FORCES STAFF WANTS TO CLARIFY THE MATTER AND THAT HE DID NOT RULE OUT UNCONTROLLED ELEMENTS IN THE ARMY AS HAVING BEEN RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MURDERERS IN THIS MASSACRE. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0802 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 18 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] GUILLERMO UNGO, VICE PRESIDENT OF THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL AND MAIN LEADER OF THE SALVADORAN CIVILIAN LEFT, WILL MEET WITH THE PRESIDENTS OF VENEZUELA AND FRANCE AND THE PRIME MINISTER OF SPAIN IN THE NEXT FEW DAYS. UNGO LEFT EL SALVADOR TODAY.

SPOKESMEN OF THE NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MNR), WHOSE SECRETARY GENERAL IS UNGO, TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT THE LEFTIST LEADER WILL MEET WITH CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ, FRANCOIS MITTERRAND, AND FELIPE GONZALEZ AND ASK THEM TO WORK FOR A CEASE-FIRE IN EL SALVADOR. UNGO WILL ALSO ASK FOR THE "IMMEDIATE" RESUMPTION OF THE PEACE TALKS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN).

THE GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS HAD BEEN SCHEDULED TO HOLD A THIRD ROUND OF NEGOTIATIONS IN CARACAS ON 20 NOVEMBER, BUT AFTER THE ASSASSINATION OF 10 LABOR LEADERS THE FMLN ANNOUNCED LAST WEEK IT WOULD NOT ATTEND.

SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI TOLD ACAN-EFE TODAY THAT "WE WILL NOT GO TO A MEETING WHERE THE OTHER SIDE IS NOT PRESENT."

UNGO LEFT FOR PANAMA TODAY AFTER HAVING TAKEN REFUGE IN THE VENEZUELAN EMBASSY IN EL SALVADOR 6 DAYS AGO BECAUSE HE WAS THE TARGET OF DEATH THREATS OVER AN OFFICIAL RADIO NETWORK. THE SALVADORAN SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC LEADER WILL ALSO ATTEND A SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL MEETING IN GENEVA NEXT WEEK.

AN MNR SPOKESMAN SAID UNGO "PLANS TO RETURN TO EL SALVADOR IN ABOUT 10 DAYS."

MEANWHILE, MNR ASSISTANT SECRETARY HECTOR OQUELI COLINDRES, WHO ALSO LEFT EL SALVADOR TODAY, WILL MEET WITH REPRESENTATIVES OF THE COSTA RICAN GOVERNMENT IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS TO DISCUSS THE SALVADORAN SITUATION AND ASK FOR PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS' MEDIATION.

DEV-MUC3-0806 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 18 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE ARMED FORCES OF EL SALVADOR HEREBY REPORT TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THE MILITARY SITUATION THROUGHOUT THE NATIONAL TERRITORY.

METROPOLITAN AREA: IN THE CAPITAL CITY, ARMY TROOPS CONTROL THE AREAS OF CUSCATANCINGO AND MEJICANOS, PARTICULARLY THE ZACAMIL, REGALADO, AND EL SOL NEIGHBORHOODS, WHERE THE ARMY IS CONSTANTLY PATROLLING THE AREA TO PREVENT NEW SUBVERSIVE ATTACKS. IN CIUDAD DELGADO, ARMED FORCES PERSONNEL ARE FIGHTING SMALL GROUPS OF EXTREMISTS WHO HAVE HIDDEN IN SEVERAL HOMES IN LOMAS DEL RIO AND SAN SEBASTIAN NEIGHBORHOODS, WHERE THERE ARE STILL SOME TERRORISTS WHO WILL BE EXPELLED IN A FEW HOURS.

LIKEWISE, ARMY TROOPS ARE CONDUCTING COUNTERINSURGENCY OPERATIONS IN GUADADALUPE, SUYAPA, AND LOS SANTOS NEIGHBORHOODS, SOYAPANGO MUNICIPALITY, WHERE THERE WAS SOME FIGHTING YESTERDAY AND THIS MORNING. THE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES INFLICTED ON THE ENEMY IS NOT AVAILABLE YET. THE ARMY IS CONTROLLING THE SITUATION IN THE AMATEPEC AND CIUDAD CREDISA NEIGHBORHOODS AND IN SANTA MARTA NO 2, WHERE THERE STILL IS A SLIGHT PROBLEM. AT NOON TODAY TROOPS FOUGHT THE TERRORISTS IN THE NORTHERN PART OF MEJICANOS, BUT THERE ARE NO REPORTS ON CASUALTIES YET. THE REBELS ARE FLEEING THE SANTA MARTA NEIGHBORHOOD AND OTHER NEARBY AREAS.

WESTERN ZONE: THE 2D INFANTRY BRIGADE, TOGETHER WITH MILITARY DETACHMENTS NO 6 AND NO 7, CONTROL THE WESTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY. THIS INCLUDES SANTA ANA, SONSONATE, AND AHUACHAPAN DEPARTMENTS WHERE THERE IS NO MAJOR PROBLEM. THERE HAVE BEEN SOME CLASHES AND ENCOUNTERS, BUT THESE HAVE BEEN UNIMPORTANT AND WITHOUT ANY SERIOUS CONSEQUENCES FOR THE CIVILIAN AND MILITARY POPULATION.

EASTERN ZONE: THE 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE, HEADQUARTERED IN SAN MIGUEL CITY, REPORTED THIS MORNING THAT THEIR TROOPS WERE FIGHTING SMALL REBEL GROUPS IN FRANCISCO GAVIRIA, 15 SEPTEMBER, EL MOLINO, AND LOPEZ NEIGHBORHOODS. BRIGADE OFFICERS SAID THEY EXPECT TO HAVE FULL CONTROL IN A FEW HOURS. THEY ALSO SAID THAT AT LEAST 15 REBELS WERE BURIED IN COMMON GRAVES ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN MIGUEL CITY, WHERE THEY WERE ABANDONED BY THEIR COMRADES WHO YESTERDAY AFTERNOON BEGAN TO FLEE AS A RESULT OF THE ARMY'S CONSTANT ACTIONS IN THAT AREA OF THE COUNTRY. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0807 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 18 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE REPORT ADDS THAT THE SITUATION IN MORAZAN AND LA UNION DEPARTMENTS IS UNDER THE CONTROL OF MILITARY DETACHMENTS NO 3 AND NO 4, WHICH ARE CURRENTLY CARRYING OUT COMBING OPERATIONS IN THE AREAS UNDER THEIR RESPONSIBILITY. IN ADDITION, THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE HAS REPORTED THAT 56 REBELS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND APPROXIMATELY 60 OTHERS HAVE BEEN WOUNDED SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THE FAILED FINAL OFFENSIVE CALLED "TO THE HILT." THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE ADDS THAT JOINT COUNTERINSURGENCY OPERATIONS ARE BEING CARRIED OUT WITH ATONAL BATTALION TROOPS.

IN THE LAST 48 HOURS, THE ARMED FORCES HAVE CONFISCATED 10 AK-47 RIFLES, 6 M-16 MACHIGUNES, 2 UZI MACHINEGUNS, 1 MP-5 SUBMACHINEGUN, LARGE QUANTITIES OF AMMUNITION, AND MATERIEL TO MAKE EXPLOSIVES.

SIMILARLY, THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE REPORTS THAT HARASSMENT OPERATIONS WERE CARRIED OUT THIS MORNING NEAR A CEMETERY, CHULA VISTA NEIGHBORHOOD, AND EL NANZAL HILL ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF THE AFOREMENTIONED CITY.

PARACENTRAL AREA: THE 5TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, ALONG WITH ITS MILITARY DETACHMENT NO 2 AND ENGINEERS MILITARY DETACHMENT, HAS ITS AREAS OF RESPONSIBILITY UNDER CONTROL, ESPECIALLY IN SAN VICENTE, SENSUNTEPEQUE, ILOBASCO, AND OTHER MUNICIPALITIES IN CABANAS AND LA PAZ DEPARTMENTS.

UP UNTIL NOW, THERE HAVE BEEN ONLY SMALL CLASHES IN NORTHERN ZACATECOLUCA CITY AND IN AREAS SURROUNDING THE ZACATECOLUCA STADIUM AND HOSPITAL. SEVERAL HARASSMENT OPERATIONS AND THE BURNING OF A STEEL FACTORY TOOK PLACE EARLY THIS MORNING IN THOSE AREAS, BUT NO CASUALTIES HAVE BEEN REPORTED.

MEMBERS OF THE ENGINEERS MILITARY DETACHMENT ARE COMBING THE AFOREMENTIONED AREAS IN ORDER TO COMPLETELY DISLODGE THE TERRORIST GROUPS THAT ARE STILL CIRCULATING IN THE AREA.

NUMBER OF FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] CASUALTIES UP UNTIL THIS MORNING:

THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF CONFIRM THAT 784 TERRORISTS HAVE BEEN KILLED, AND 527 HAVE BEEN WOUNDED. THE ARMED FORCES ALSO REPORT THAT 129 REBELS HAVE BEEN ARRESTED AND THAT 36 OTHERS SHOWED UP AT VARIOUS ARMY POSTS LOCATED THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.

THE ARMED FORCES CASUALTIES INCLUDE 208 ARMY MEMBERS KILLED AND 427 WOUNDED. AS FOR WEAPONS CONFISCATED, THE ARMY SAYS IT HAS CONFISCATED 370 RIFLES, 82 GRENADE LAUNCHERS, 26 MORTARS, 18 MACHINEGUNS, 17 SUBMACHINEGUNS, LARGE QUANTITIES OF AMMUNITION, HANDGUNS, AND LARGE AMOUNTS OF EXPLOSIVE MATERIEL.

THE ARMY HAS FOUND MORE WEAPONS IN ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD:

TODAY, ARMY TROOPS PATROLLING ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD IN NORTHWESTERN SAN SALVADOR FOUND 47 M-16 RIFLES, 35,000 CARTRIDGES, 49 CARTRIDGE CLIPS, AND VARIOUS EXPLOSIVES. THE WEAPONS WERE HIDDEN INSIDE A MEDIUM-SIZE TRUCK FOUND DURING A SEARCH OPERATION CONDUCTED AT NOON TODAY NEAR ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD. AT PRESENT, ARMED FORCES MEMBERS MAINTAIN TOTAL CONTROL OVER THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD AND OTHER SURROUNDING AREAS.

THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES THANK THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE FOR THEIR VALUABLE COOPERATION AND THEIR SUPPORT FOR THE VARIOUS ARMY GROUPS THAT ARE DETERMINED TO DISLODGE THE TERRORIST GROUPS LOCATED IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE COUNTRY, ESPECIALLY IN SAN SALVADOR.

SIMILARLY, THE ARMED FORCES CONGRATULATE OUR GLORIOUS CHIEFS, OFFICERS, AND TROOPS, WHO TENACIOUSLY, BRAVELY, AND HEROICALLY DEFEND OUR PEOPLE AND HOMELAND FROM THE GENOCIDE IMPOSED BY THE FMLN HORDES.

IN ADDITION, THE ARMED FORCES WARN THE TERRORISTS WHO STILL PERSIST IN THEIR BLIND STRUGGLE AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THAT ITS FIRM AND IMPLACABLE ADVANCE WILL CONTINUE. THE ARMED FORCES ASK THOSE TERRORISTS TO SURRENDER AND TURN THEMSELVES IN TO SPARE THE HONEST POPULATION FROM EVEN MORE SUFFERING. THE ARMED FORCES WILL BE BENEVOLENT WITH THOSE WHO SURRENDER.

THE ARMED FORCES REITERATE THEIR UNYIELDING WILLINGNESS TO CONTINUE STRUGGLING IN DEFENSE OF NATIONAL SOVEREIGNTY AND THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS TO PRESERVE THE FREEDOM OF ALL SALVADORANS.

SAN SALVADOR, 18 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0808 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 18 NOV 89 (AFP) -- [EXCERPT] THE CAPITAL FELL INTO DARKNESS SATURDAY NIGHT AS ELECTRICAL SERVICE THROUGHOUT SAN SALVADOR WAS CUT AND THE COUNTRY ENTERED THE EIGHTH DAY OF A NATIONWIDE REBEL OFFENSIVE.

INSURGENTS FROM THE LEFTIST FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) STILL HELD KEY POSITIONS AROUND THE CAPITAL, FENDING OFF FIERCE SALVADORAN AIR AND ARTILLERY ATTACKS.

THE POWER OUTAGE, WHICH HAD AFFECTED CERTAIN ZONES OF THE CITY AND SURROUNDING SUBURBS BUT NOT THE ENTIRE CITY OVER THE PAST WEEK OF FIGHTING, CAME AMID UNCONFIRMED REPORTS THAT THE ARMY WAS PREPARING A MAJOR COUNTER-OFFENSIVE TO DRIVE THE REBELS FROM THE SAN SALVADOR METROPOLITAN AREA.

GOVERNMENT SOLDIERS BLOCKED ALL ACCESS TO THE REBEL-HELD NORTHERN AND EASTERN SECTORS OF THE CAPITAL.

THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS CONTINUED TO FLEE THE COMBAT ZONES, WHERE A NUMBER HAVE BEEN KILLED IN THE CROSS-FIRE SINCE THE LEFTIST FMLN LAUNCHED ITS ATTACK NOVEMBER 11 -- THE BOLDEST OFFENSIVE OF THE 10-YEAR CIVIL WAR.

INSURGENTS WHO THURSDAY HAD EVACUATED THE DISTRICT OF ZACAMIL -- DEVASTATED BY THE ARMED FORCES' AERIAL FIREBOMBINGS -- REGROUPED IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE, AN AREA NORTH OF THE CAPITAL, ACCORDING TO PRESS REPORTS.

FIGHTING WAS REPORTEDLY ALSO RAGING IN APOPA, 12 KILOMETERS (7.5 MILES) NORTH OF THE CAPITAL ON THE MAJOR NORTHERN ROUTE.

IN THE CITY OF SAN MIGUEL, 140 KILOMETERS (87 MILES) EAST OF THE CAPITAL, THE REBELS SHOT DOWN A GOVERNMENT A-37 COMBAT PLANE, JOURNALISTS THERE SAID. THIS CONFIRMED EARLIER FMLN RADIO REPORTS THAT THE GUERRILLAS HAD SHOT DOWN AN ARMY DRAGON FLY A-37 AS IT WAS BOMBING REBEL-OCCUPIED SECTIONS OF THE CITY.

AUTHORITIES ESTIMATED THAT MORE THAN 2,000 PEOPLE HAD BEEN KILLED OR INJURED IN THE CONFLICT.

JOAO BAENA SOARES, SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE ORGANIZATION OF AMERICAN STATES (OAS), WAS TO ARRIVE HERE SUNDAY WITH AN OAS DELEGATION SEEKING A CEASE-FIRE.

DEV-MUC3-0809 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] CIN REPORTS THE FOLLOWING TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE:

1. THE ARMED FORCES HAS ABSOLUTE CONTROL OVER NATIONAL TERRITORY IN SAN MIGUEL, ZACATECOLUCA, USULUTAN, SANTA ANA, AND SAN SALVADOR. THE SITUATION IS UNDER CONTROL; ONLY A FEW SNIPERS REMAIN IN BUILDINGS AND TREES.

2. CITIZENS WHO ARE STILL STILL SEEKING REFUGE IN THEIR WORK PLACES ARE ADVISED TO RETURN TO THEIR RESPECTIVE HOMES BEFORE 1800 WHEN THE CURFEW BEGINS.

3. PARENTS ARE ADVISED TO MAINTAIN CALM IN THEIR HOMES AND ENSURE THAT THEIR CHILDREN DO NOT LEAVE HOME UNTIL ORDER HAS BEEN FULLY RESTORED.

4. THE PRESS, RADIO, AND TELEVISION ARE WARNED THAT IF THEY BROADCAST ANY INFORMATION TO PUBLIC WHICH HAS NOT BEEN CONFIRMED BY THE CIN, THEY COULD FACE PENALITES; THEIR FACILITIES COULD BE INDEFINITELY CLOSED.

5. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE MUST REALIZE THAT THE SECURITY CORPS, NATIONAL GUARD, TREASURY POLICE, NATIONAL POLICE, AND RAPID DEPLOYMENT BATTALIONS SUCH AS THE ATLCATL, ATONAL, ARCE, BELLOSO, AND BRACAMONTE, AND BRIGADES BELONGING TO OUR GLORIOUS ARMED FORCES HAVE SUCCESSFULLY DEFEATED FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] MURDERERS TO ENSURE THE FREEDOM AND TRANQUILLITY OF OUR SALVADORAN BROTHERS. WARLIKE OPERATIONS LAUNCHED IN ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD, WHICH INVOLVED GROUND AND AIR FORCES, WERE NECESSARY BECAUSE OF THE VIOLENCE AND CRUELTY SHOWN BY THE TERRORIST MURDERERS AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

6. ALL BASIC AND VITAL SERVICES IN THE COUNTRY, SUCH AS WATER AND ELECTRICITY, ARE BEING PROVIDED NORMALLY AND ARE UNDER ARMED FORCES CONTROL.

7. WITH GREAT SATISFACTION, WE REPORT TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES HAVE RECEIVED EXPRESSIONS OF SUPPORT FROM NEARLY ALL PROFESSIONAL UNIONS AND BUSINESS GROUPS. THEY HAVE AGREED TO RESUME DAILY ACTIVITIES TO SUPPORT PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S EFFORTS TO BRING ABOUT PEACE AND PROGRESS.

DEV-MUC3-0810 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 19 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) COMMANDER ROBERTO ROCA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] COMMANDER ROBERTO ROCA, THE REPERCUSSIONS OF THE JESUITS' [WORDS INDISTINCT] WERE NOT LONG IN COMING. ONE OF THE MOST SIGNIFICANT ONES WAS THE EDITORIAL OF AN IMPORTANT U.S. NEWSPAPER, THE NEW YORK TIMES, ON 18 NOVEMBER. THE EDITORIAL SAYS, AMONG OTHER THINGS, THAT IF PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI DOES NOT ORDER A QUICK, THOROUGH, AND GENUINE INVESTIGATION TO CATCH THE ASSASSINS, HE MIGHT LOSE THE UNITED STATES' ECONOMIC AID.

THE EDITORIAL ALSO STATES THE DEMOCRATS IN CONGRESS HAVE SAID THAT THE MILITARY AID SHOULD BE SUSPENDED IF EL SALVADOR CANNOT CONTROL AND PUNISH THE DEATH SQUADS. THEY ADD THAT IF HE DOES NOT HEED THE WARNING, THE NEXT STATEMENT MIGHT BE ISSUED BY BOTH PARTIES. WHAT ARE THE IMPLICATIONS OF THIS IMPORTANT STATEMENT BY AN INFLUENTIAL U.S. NEWSPAPER FOR CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT AND THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES?

[ROCA] ACTUALLY, THE NEW YORK TIMES STATES THE FEELING PERVADING THE ENTIRE UNITED STATES. IT IS A WAY OF CONFIRMING THAT THE FASCIST GROUPS PREVAIL WITHIN THE GOVERNMENT AND ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE], AND THEY ARE DECIDING THE REGIME'S POLICIES. POLITICAL OPINION IN THE UNITED STATES HAS UNDOUBTEDLY BEEN SHAKEN BY THIS MASSACRE PLANNED BY ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT.

WE BELIEVE THAT U.S. POLITICIANS WILL PROGRESSIVELY COME TO SUPPORT THE U.S. PEOPLE'S FEELINGS AND WILL DEMAND THAT CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT ORDER THE INVESTIGATION. WE KNOW THAT THIS WILL NOT BE EASY IN EL SALVADOR, BECAUSE, AS THE EDITORIAL POINTS OUT, SIMILAR ASSASSINATIONS HAVE BEEN PERPETRATED INNUMERABLE TIMES. THESE CASES HAVE BEEN SURROUNDED BY ABSOLUTE SECRECY; NO CULPRITS ARE FOUND; AND WITNESSES HAVE TESTIFIED MANY TIMES THAT THE ACTIONS WERE CARRIED OUT BY ARMED FORCES MEMBERS, EITHER DRESSED AS CIVILIANS OR IN UNIFORM. HOWEVER, THE POLICY OF THE ARMED FORCES AND THE GOVERNMENT PROTECTS THE CULPRITS.

WE BELIEVE THAT THIS CIVILIAN ASSASSINATION, MEANING THE ASSASSINATION OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THE FACT THAT PRACTICALLY ALL THE LEADERS OF THE LABOR MOVEMENT WERE SOUGHT OUT THAT SAME NIGHT TO BE KILLED, PLUS THE FACT THAT THE KILLING OF THE COOPERATIVE MEMBERS WAS CARRIED OUT WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE GREAT BATTLES BEING FOUGHT IN EL SALVADOR'S URBAN AREAS, WILL EVENTUALLY CONVINCE U.S. POLITICIANS THAT THE GOVERNMENT THEY HAVE BEEN SUPPORTING IS CLEARLY A FASCIST GOVERNMENT WHICH HAS ABSOLUTELY NO INTEREST IN ANY KIND OF DEMOCRATIC CONSOLIDATION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0811 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 19 NOV 89 -- [INTERVIEW WITH FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) COMMANDER ROBERTO ROCA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [ROCA] REAL LIFE IS MAKING IT EVIDENT THAT IN EL SALVADOR WE MUST FIND A DEMOCRATIC SOLUTION TO THE TERRIBLE CRISIS BEING ENDURED -- TO THE WAR. THIS DEMOCRATIC SOLUTION MEANS ISOLATING AND EXCLUDING THE FASCISTS FROM POWER BECAUSE THEY ARE AGAINST DEMOCRACY.

MR CRISTIANI CANNOT SAY UNDER THESE CIRCUMSTANCES THAT HE SHARES NO RESPONSIBILITY IN THE MURDER OF THE JESUITS. IN THE FRAMEWORK OF HIS FRUSTRATED ATTEMPT TO STOP THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE, HE UNLEASHED THE DOGS OF WAR -- ALL THE FASCIST ELEMENTS -- SO THAT THEY WOULD COMMIT ALL THE OUTRAGES THEY HAVE COMMITTED. THIS INCLUDES THE FASCIST ELEMENTS IN THE AIR FORCE AND THEIR INDISCRIMINATE BOMBING OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION, AS WELL AS THE DEATH SQUADS, WHO WERE UNLEASHED SO THEY WOULD MURDER PEOPLE WHO BEST EXPRESS THE DEMOCRATIC FEELINGS OF THE PEOPLE AND, AS IN THE CASE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, TO ELIMINATE A VALUABLE SECTOR OF THE SALVADORAN INTELLIGENTSIA AT THE SERVICE OF DEMOCRACY AND SOCIAL JUSTICE.

AS WE ALL KNOW, THE JESUITS HAD CONTINUOUSLY DENOUNCED THE UNJUST SYSTEM IN EL SALVADOR AND HAD CALLED FOR CLEARING UP ALL CRIMES. THE FASCISTS, IN THEIR HATRED, PUT AN END TO THE LIVES OF THESE JESUITS BELIEVING THAT THEY CAN HIDE THE SUN WITH ONE FINGER. THE INDIGNATION OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WILL BE INCREASINGLY BACKED BY THE U.S. PEOPLE AS A RESULT OF THEIR INDIGNATION AND BY U.S. POLITICIANS WHO HAVE BECOME AWARE OF THE FACT THAT IT IS NECESSARY TO PUT AN END TO FASCIST OUTRAGES IN EL SALVADOR. THE FASCISTS REPRESENT A BARRIER THAT MUST BE DESTROYED AND DEFEATED TO HAVE DEMOCRACY IN EL SALVADOR.

[REPORTER] COMMANDER, IF THE UNITED STATES DECIDED TO CUT OFF MILITARY AND ECONOMIC AID TO THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT, WHAT IMPACT WOULD THIS HAVE ON THE ARMED FORCES?

[ROCA] WE HAVE SAID ON MANY OCCASIONS THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES WOULD HAVE LOST THE WAR SOME TIME AGO WERE IT NOT FOR U.S. SUPPORT AND FINANCING. AS WE HAVE STATED IN ALL OUR PROPOSALS FOR A POLITICAL SOLUTION, OUR OBJECTIVE IS NEITHER THE DESTRUCTION NOR THE ELIMINATION OF THE ARMED FORCES. WHAT WE WANT IS FOR THE ARMED FORCES TO GET RID OF THE FASCIST ELEMENTS THAT HAVE TURNED IT INTO A TOOL THAT ACTS AGAINST THE PEOPLE AND DEMOCRACY.

WE BELIEVE THAT SENSIBLE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES OFFICERS, THOSE WHO HAVE NOT LOST THEIR HEADS, MUST TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION [WORDS INDISTINCT] INDISCRIMINATE BOMBING, THE POLITICAL DEFEAT OF THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT, AND THE MILITARY DEFEAT OF THE METHODS AND TACTICS [WORDS INDISTINCT]. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0812 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH SALVADOR SAMAYOA, MEMBER OF THE POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC COMMISSION OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT-DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTIONARY FRONT, FMLN-FDR, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [SAMAYOA] THEREFORE, THE WESTERN EUROPEAN PRESS, POLITICAL PARTIES, LABOR UNIONS, AND GENERAL PUBLIC ARE VERY STRONGLY REJECTING CRISTIANI'S REGIME. THE CONGRESSES AND PARLIAMENTS OF MANY WESTERN EUROPEAN COUNTRIES ARE SAYING THAT THE COOPERATION THE SALVADORAN REGIME RECEIVES SHOULD BE REEVALUATED.

[REPORTER] COMRADE SALVADOR SAMAYOA, THE GOVERNMENT NETWORK IS REPORTING THAT U.S. AID TO CRISTIANI WILL CONTINUE. THE COLONELS HAVE ALSO SAID THAT THE FMLN CANNOT DEFEAT THE ARMED FORCES BECAUSE THE LATTER HAS MILITARY AND ECONOMIC AID FROM THE U.S. GOVERNMENT. RETURNING TO THIS POINT, COMRADE SAMAYOA, WHAT IS YOUR VIEW? WHAT OPTIONS DOES THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAVE CONCERNING EL SALVADOR, AND WHAT IMPACT HAS THE NEW SITUATION HAD ON U.S. POLICY TOWARD EL SALVADOR?

[SAMAYOA] AS I SAID, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT MUST TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION THAT A NEW INTERNAL SITUATION OF GENERALIZED POPULAR, POLITICAL, AND SOCIAL DISCONTENT IS TAKING SHAPE, AND THAT FROM THIS MOMENT ON ITS POLICY IN EL SALVADOR WILL UNDERGO ISOLATION AND WILL BE REJECTED BY THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, AND EVEN BY VERY IMPORTANT SECTORS WITHIN THE HOUSE AND SENATE.

SO FAR, THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION HAS STUBBORNLY CONTINUED PROVIDING AID AND SUPPORT TO A REGIME THAT IS OBVIOUSLY CRIMINAL AND GENOCIDAL, AND THAT POLICY IS [WORDS INDISTINCT] CURRENTLY A VERY STRONG DEBATE IN THE UNITED STATES. THE OPTIONS AVAILABLE TO THE U.S. GOVERNMENT ARE TO SINK WITH THE CRISTIANI REGIME, WHICH IS OBVIOUSLY MOVING TOWARD DEFEAT AND MILITARY AND POLITICAL DESTRUCTION DESPITE ALL THE PROPAGANDA IT HAS MADE, OR TO CHANGE ITS OPINION WHILE THERE IS STILL TIME. THE ALTERNATIVE OF A CHANGE OF GOVERNMENT, A REPLACEMENT OF CRISTIANI'S REGIME OR THE MILITARY HIERARCHY, IS ALREADY UNDER DISCUSSION. THESE, THEREFORE, ARE THE TWO ALTERNATIVES AVAILABLE TO THE UNITED STATES: EITHER CHANGE ITS POLICY IN TIME AND REPLACE CRISTIANI, OR THE GOVERNMENT WILL SINK BECAUSE ITS PROPAGANDA IS NOT WORKING.

THE U.S. AMBASSADOR HAS MADE A FOOL OF HIMSELF. HE SAID THE GUERRILLAS HAD 1,500 MEN IN SAN SALVADOR, AND HE HAS LISTED CASUALTY FIGURES ACCORDING TO WHICH THE FMLN SUFFERED OVER 500 DEATHS, OVER 400 WOUNDED, AND OTHERS CAPTURED. ACCORDING TO THE FIGURES QUOTED BY THE U.S. AMBASSADOR, WHO PROVIDES GOVERNMENT WAR BULLETINS AND HAS ALMOST BECOME THE SALVADORAN DEFENSE MINISTER, THE FMLN ONLY HAS 200 MEN LEFT IN SAN SALVADOR.

WHAT I FIND INEXPLICABLE IS THE GOVERNMENT'S NEED TO USE 40 OR 50 WAR PLANES AND HELICOPTERS, ALONG WITH ITS ARTILLERY AND ELITE BATTALIONS, TO BOMB AND DESTROY CITIES, ESPECIALLY SAN SALVADOR. THAT IS WHY THEIR PROPAGANDA HAS BACKFIRED ON THEM. IN THE UNITED STATES THE PRESS AND GENERAL PUBLIC KNOW FULL WELL THAT THE FMLN OFFENSIVE IS IN FULL FORCE AND IS MOVING FORWARD, AND THAT THE U.S. POLICY IS REACHING THE POINT OF TOTAL FAILURE.

[REPORTER] TO CONCLUDE, COMRADE SAMAYOA, WHAT IS YOUR MESSAGE ON RADIO VENCEREMOS TO THE COMRADES WHO HAVE MAINTAINED THEIR POSITIONS IN SAN SALVADOR, SAN MIGUEL, ZACATECOLUCA, USULUTAN, AND VARIOUS POINTS OF THE NATIONAL TERRITORY? WHAT IS YOUR MESSAGE TO THE FIGHTERS AND THE PEOPLE?

[SAMAYOA] TO ALL THE COMRADES WHO ARE FIGHTING IN TRENCHES THROUGHOUT THE LENGTH AND BREADTH OF OUR COUNTRY, I MUST SAY THAT THE AFFECTION AND ADMIRATION YOU HAVE GENERATED THROUGHOUT THE WORLD, THE SOLIDARITY WITH YOUR STRUGGLE, AND THE SURPRISING STRENGTH AND HEROISM YOU HAVE DISPLAYED ARE NOW RECEIVING SUPPORT FROM ALMOST ALL OF THE COUNTRIES OF THE WORLD. THEREFORE, OUR STRUGGLE NOT ONLY IS NOT ALONE, BUT IT HAS NOW ACHIEVED MAXIMUM SUPPORT OF ALL TYPES: POLITICAL, MATERIAL, ECONOMIC. SOLIDARITY HAS MULTIPLIED HUNDREDFOLD OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS, AND IT WILL BE AN INEXHAUSTIBLE SOURCE OF SUPPORT THAT WILL CONTRIBUTE TO COMPLETING THE FASCIST REGIME'S DESTRUCTION. THE PEOPLE OF THE WORLD ADMIRE THE STRUGGLE THE COMRADES AND FIGHTERS IN ALL THE CITIES IN THIS COUNTRY ARE WAGING, AND THEY VERY CLEARLY UNDERSTAND THAT THE STRUGGLE IS FOR A JUST CAUSE AND AGAINST A COMPLETELY ILLEGITIMATE, FASCIST, AND CRIMINAL REGIME.

THE COMRADES CAN REST ASSURED OF THIS INTERNATIONAL SUPPORT, WHICH IS CURRENTLY VERY GREAT. IT IS IMPRESSIVE TO SEE ALL OF THE AFFECTION AND ADMIRATION THAT OUR FIGHTERS ARE RECEIVING FROM ALL OVER THE WORLD.

[REPORTER] THANK YOU VERY MUCH, SALVADOR. OUR GREETINGS TO ALL THE OTHER COMRADES.

[SAMAYOA] THANK YOU, [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.

DEV-MUC3-0814 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 19 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH SALVADOR SAMAYOA, MEMBER OF THE POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC COMMISSION OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT-DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTIONARY FRONT, FMLN-FDR, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] COMRADE SALVADOR SAMAYOA, WE HAVE HEARD REPORTS ON STATEMENTS BY THE U.S. AMBASSADOR IN SAN SALVADOR, WILLIAM WALKER, WHO SAID THAT DESPITE THE BOMBINGS HIS GOVERNMENT, THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION, WILL CONTINUE GIVING MILITARY AID AND SUPPORT TO THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT. HOWEVER, IT SEEMS THE SITUATION HAS CHANGED FOLLOWING THE ASSASSINATION OF THE JESUITS. AT THIS MOMENT, HOW DOES THE UNITED STATES PERCEIVE THE NEW SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR?

[SAMAYOA] AT THE LEVEL OF THE U.S. PEOPLE, THERE IS A TOTAL REPUDIATION OF THE FASCIST CRIMINAL GOVERNMENT AND OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES BECAUSE OF THE BOMBINGS -- WHICH HAVE BECOME A TRUE GENOCIDE -- IN VARIOUS DENSELY POPULATED CITIES AND NEIGHBORHOODS IN EL SALVADOR, AS WELL AS BECAUSE OF THE ASSASSINATIONS PERPETRATED BY THE SALVADORAN ARMY AGAINST THE JESUIT PRIESTS AT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY [UCA]. THERE HAVE BEEN VERY RADICAL DEMONSTRATIONS EXPRESSING MUCH INDIGNATION BY VARIOUS U.S. SOCIAL SECTORS. MOREOVER, IN SOME OF THOSE DEMONSTRATIONS, THE POLICE BARRICADES WERE BROKEN. IMPORTANT U.S. POLITICAL PERSONALITIES SUCH AS JESSE JACKSON, ONE OF THE MOST PRESTIGIOUS LEADERS IN THE UNITED STATES, PARTICIPATED IN THE DEMONSTRATIONS. THERE HAVE ALSO BEEN DEMONSTRATIONS IN BOSTON, CHICAGO, NEW YORK, SAN FRANCISCO, AND LOS ANGELES. IN AT LEAST 20 CITIES IN THE UNITED STATES PEOPLE HAVE EXPRESSED ALL THEIR REPUDIATION AND INDIGNATION OVER THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND THE U.S. POLICY IN EL SALVADOR.

SINCE THE ASSASSINATION OF THE UCA PRIESTS, A LARGE NUMBER OF IMPORTANT U.S. SENATORS AND REPRESENTATIVES ARE SAYING THAT U.S. MILITARY AID TO THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES AND GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE CUT AND SUSPENDED. SENATOR KENNEDY IN PARTICULAR MADE A VERY STRONG STATEMENT, SAYING THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES' ATTITUDE SIMPLY EXPRESSES THE FAILURE OF 10 YEARS OF U.S. POLICY -- WHICH HAS BEEN SPENT FEEDING, TRAINING, ARMING, AND FINANCING AN ARMED FORCE THAT CARRIES OUT ASSASSINATIONS. IN ADDITION TO SENATOR KENNEDY, THERE ARE MANY U.S. SENATORS AND CONGRESSMEN WHO ARE REQUESTING THE TOTAL SUSPENSION OF MILITARY AID TO EL SALVADOR. AT THIS TIME, THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES HAVE THE HIGHEST LEVEL OF REPUDIATION IN THE UNITED STATES IN THE PAST 10 YEARS. HOWEVER, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT, [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE STATE DEPARTMENT, AND THE WHITE HOUSE CONTINUE SUPPORTING THE [SALVADORAN] CRIMINAL REGIME AND GIVING IT FURTHER EMERGENCY AID.

[REPORTER] COMRADE, YESTERDAY WE LEARNED ABOUT ARTICLES PUBLISHED IN THE MAIN U.S. NEWSPAPERS THE NEW YORK TIMES AND THE WASHINGTON POST, WHICH STRONGLY QUESTION THE GOVERNMENT, SPECIFICALLY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI, THE CHIEF OF THE FASCIST DICTATORSHIP. WHAT IS THE SITUATION OF THE CRISTIANI SPEECH AND HIS ALLEGED LEGITIMACY, NOT ONLY IN THE UNITED STATES BUT ALSO AT THE LEVEL OF THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITY?

[SAMAYOA] THE ALLEGED LEGITIMACY OF CRISTIANI COLLAPSED. IN THE UNITED STATES, THEY SAID CRISTIANI WAS [WORDS INDISTINCT] HAD GOOD INTENTIONS, BUT THE RIGHT-WING [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND THE DEATH SQUADS DID NOT LET HIM WORK. THE SPEECH FAILED BECAUSE IT IS NOW CLEAR THAT AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES, CRISTIANI IS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE GENOCIDE IN SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER DEPARTMENTS IN THE COUNTRY [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THE MEDIA HAVE ALSO REPORTED THE ARREST OF U.S. RELIGIOUS MEN AND OF SWISS, FRENCH, SPANISH, AND JAPANESE CITIZENS. THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS A GOVERNMENT ACCUSING EVERYONE OF COOPERATING WITH THE GUERRILLAS, AND THIS HAS CAUSED A TOTAL LOSS OF THE GOVERNMENT'S PRESTIGE. EDITORIALS ON 18 NOVEMBER IN THE MAIN U.S. NEWSPAPERS [WORDS INDISTINCT] CRISTIANI IS NOT MORE THAN [WORDS INDISTINCT]. AT EMBASSIES AND CONSULATES IN MOST COUNTRIES IN WESTERN EUROPE -- IN ITALY, SPAIN, THE FRG, FRANCE, SWEDEN, DENMARK AND EVERYWHERE -- THERE HAVE BEEN DEMONSTRATIONS CALLED BY LABOR UNIONS, POLITICAL PARTIES, AND PEOPLE'S MOVEMENTS IN THOSE COUNTRIES TO EXPRESS REPUDIATION. IN LONDON, ONE OF THE MOST PRESTIGIOUS HUMAN RIGHTS ORGANIZATIONS, AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL, URGED EVERYONE TO STAGE DEMONSTRATIONS IN FRONT OF ALL SALVADORAN EMBASSIES AND CONSULATES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0815 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FMLN'S ROBERTO ROCA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [ROCA] THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE HAS NOT BEEN DEFEATED AND CANNOT BE DEFEATED. INTERNATIONAL REPORTS INDICATE THAT THE REVOLUTIONARY FORCES HAVE BECOME STRONG IN THE CITY, THAT THEY ARE MAKING TACTICAL MOVEMENTS, AND THAT IN SPITE OF THE BARBARISM WITH WHICH THE ARMED FORCES HAS BEEN OPERATING, THE GUERRILLAS MAINTAIN ALL OF THEIR OPERATIONAL CAPABILITIES.

THE SITUATION CANNOT DEFEAT US. THERE MUST BE A SOLUTION, AND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE INCREASINGLY, AND IN DIFFERENT WAYS, BECOMING INVOLVED IN THE REVOLUTIONARY PROCESS TO DEFEAT THE FASCISTS AND THE GENOCIDAL TACTICS THEY ARE USING.

WE BELIEVE THAT WHAT IS HAPPENING IS HAVING AN IMPACT ON INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC OPINION, AND THIS UNDOUBTEDLY WILL HAVE AN EFFECT ON THE ARMED FORCES AND COULD RESULT IN AN EFFORT TO SAVE THE INSTITUTION.

WE BELIEVE THAT IN THE ARMED FORCES THERE ARE OFFICERS AND SOLDIERS WHO REJECT FASCISM. THERE HAVE BEEN MANY DESERTIONS IN THE ARMY FILES. MANY ORDERS ARE BEING DISOBEYED, ORDERS OF A GENOCIDAL NATURE USUALLY. THIS IS THE STARTING POINT OF AN EVENT THAT WILL STUN POLITICAL OPINION IN EL SALVADOR.

WE BELIEVE THAT IF THIS SAVAGE KILLING OF PEOPLE DOES NOT STOP, THE MILITARY INSTITUTION WILL BE SIGNING ITS OWN DEATH SENTENCE. THE PEOPLE CANNOT TOLERATE A MILITARY THAT FUNCTIONS UNDER A MOST SAVAGE AND DESPOTIC REGIME, AND THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT IS IN HOT WATER, WE COULD SAY.

THE REVOLUTIONARY OFFENSIVE, AS I HAVE NOTED, IS BEING DEVELOPED. WE HAVE SOLID POSITIONS IN FOUR OF EL SALVADOR'S MAIN CITIES, AND AS WE HAVE SAID BEFORE: NO ONE IS GOING TO PUSH US OUT. VICTORY FOR DEMOCRACY HAS BEEN ASSURED. THE WORLD WILL BACK US IN THE FACE OF THE SAVAGE GENOCIDE BY THE GOVERNMENT FORCES, ESPECIALLY BY THE FASCIST MILITARY ELEMENTS IN EL SALVADOR.

[REPORTER] TO CONCLUDE, COMMANDER, THE FUNERAL RITES FOR THE THE PRIESTS WHO WERE MURDERED IN SAN SALVADOR ARE TAKING PLACE AT THIS MOMENT, AROUND NOON TIME, AND ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND HIS WIFE ARE ATTENDING THIS CEREMONY. DO YOU HAVE ANY MESSAGE FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, FOR THE STUDENTS FROM THE CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY, FOR THE CHRISTIAN PEOPLE, FOR THE PEOPLE IN GENERAL, WHO ARE MOURNING THE DEATH OF THESE WORTHY JESUITS?

[ROCA] WE HAVE ALREADY EXPRESSED, AND I WILL REITERATE IT NOW, THE DEEP SORROW OF THE FMLN MILITANTS AND THE PEOPLE IN GENERAL OVER THE LOSS OF THESE WORTHY JESUIT PRIESTS WHO HAVE BEEN CONSISTENT STRUGGLERS FOR DEMOCRACY AND PEACE IN EL SALVADOR. WE SHARE THE FEELINGS OF THE SALVADORAN RELIGIOUS COMMUNITY.

I WOULD LIKE TO NOTE THAT THE PRESENCE OF CRISTIANI AT THE BURIAL FOR THE JESUIT PRIESTS CALLS FOR A NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL OUTCRY IN DEMAND FOR PUNISHMENT FOR THE PERSONS RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS ATROCIOUS ASSASSINATION.

CRISTIANI CANNOT GO TO THAT BURIAL AND DO NOTHING ABOUT PEOPLE TO WHOM HE OPENED DOORS SO THAT THEY COULD COMMIT THESE KILLINGS. EVERYBODY MUST DEMAND THAT CRISTIANI RESPOND TO THE PEOPLE'S INDIGNATION BY PUNISHING THE PERSONS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CRIME. CRISTIANI CANNOT SPEAK ABOUT HAVING MORAL AUTHORITY FOR ATTENDING THAT BURIAL UNLESS HE PUNISHES THE PEOPLE WHO ARE RESPONSIBLE. IT IS NOT ENOUGH TO PUNISH THE ASSASSINS. THERE MUST BE A THOROUGH INVESTIGATION OF THE WAVE OF CRIME THAT HAS BEEN UNLEASHED IN EL SALVADOR. THE MOST NOTORIOUS CRIME HAS BEEN THE KILLING OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, BUT IN THE PAST 8 DAYS MANY COMMON PEOPLE AND COMMUNITY LEADERS HAVE ALSO BEEN MURDERED. THE BOMBING HAS BEEN INTENSE. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE ENDURING MUCH PAIN AND THEY DEMAND THAT THE PEOPLE RESPONSIBLE FOR IT BE PUNISHED.

WE AGAIN REITERATE THE PAIN OF THE PEOPLE OVER THE DEATH OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS. WE BELIEVE THAT THE CATHOLIC CHURCH MUST BRAVELY AND LOUDLY DEMAND JUSTICE IN THE FACE OF THESE CRIMES.

DEV-MUC3-0818 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE FOLLOWING IS AN UPDATED REPORT OF THE MILITARY SITUATION.

THE ARMED FORCES INFORM THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THAT THE AREAS IN SAN SALVADOR WHERE ARMY TROOPS ARE CURRENTLY CONDUCTING COUNTERINSURGENCY OPERATIONS ARE THE GUADALUPE AND LOS SANTOS NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE SOYOPANGO MUNICIPALITY, AND SAN SEBASTIAN [WORD INDISTINCT] AT CIUDAD DELGADO. THE ARMED FORCES EXPECT TO EXPEL THE REMAINING SMALL REBEL REDOUBTS FROM THESE AREAS IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS. THERE WERE HARRASSMENT ACTIONS IN APOPA THIS MORNING, BUT NO CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED. THE ARMY CONTROLS THE MEJICANOS AND ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOODS.

THE ARMED FORCES CONTROL THE SITUATION IN THE WESTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY. THE SITUATION IN THE EASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY IS ALSO UNDER CONTROL, EXCEPT FOR A FEW TERRORIST GROUPS CURRENTLY BEING EXPELLED FROM THE CITY OF SAN MIGUEL.

THE ARMED FORCES JOINT COMMAND STAFF REPORTS THAT 840 TERRORISTS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND 558 HAVE BEEN WOUNDED AS OF TODAY. THE ARMY HAS SUFFERED THE LOSS OF 220 SOLDIERS, WHO HEROICALLY OFFERED THEIR LIVES TO DEFEND THE FATHERLAND FROM COMMUNISM. ALSO, 457 SOLDIERS HAVE BEEN WOUNDED.

THE FOLLOWING WAR MATERIEL HAS BEEN CONFICATED: 446 RIFLES OF DIFFERENT CALIBERS, 87 GRENADE LAUNCHERS, [WORDS INDISTINCT], 22 MACHINEGUNS, 18 SUBMACHINEGUNS, AND A LARGE AMOUNT OF AMMUNITION AND OTHER WAR MATERIEL.

DEV-MUC3-0819 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [GENERAL RAFAEL HUMBERTO LARIOS, SALVADORAN DEFENSE AND PUBLIC SECURITY MINISTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THIS IS OUR RESPONSIBILITY, THIS IS OUR MISSION, AND WE ARE WILLING TO GIVE OUR LIVES IN SACRIFICE, AS HAS BEEN PROVEN BY THE MANY HEROIC SOLDIERS WHO ARE DYING IN THIS STRUGGLE TO DEFEND JUSTICE, PEACE, DEMOCRACY, AND THE WELL-BEING OF THESE PEOPLE WHOM WE LOVE SO MUCH, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

ARMED FORCES, DO NOT FEAR THE ENEMY. GO FORWARD WITH YOUR RESOLVE AND SPIRIT. OUR FAITH IN GOD AND OUR CHRISTIAN PRINCIPLES GIVE US THE TRUTH AND THE STRENGTH TO CONTINUE DESTROYING THE FORCES THAT ARE TRYING TO WIPE OUT OUR HISTORY, TRADITION, VALUES, AND CITIZENS' PRINCIPLES.

FOR EACH OFFICER AND SOLDIER LOST IN THE STRUGGLE, THERE IS NO OTHER MISSION BUT TO DEFEAT THE ENEMY, TO DESTROY THE TERRORISTS' PLANS, AND TO ONCE AND FOR ALL WIPE OUT THIS MANEUVER, THIS ATTEMPT TO DESTROY THE INSTITUTIONALITY OF EL SALVADOR.

THIS IS A TIMELY OCCASION, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, TO SAY THAT THE ARMED FORCES AS AN INSTITUTION AT SOCIETY'S SERVICE DEEPLY REGRET AND HAVE BEEN DISMAYED BY THE INCIDENTS AT THE JOSE SIMEON CANAS CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY. WE CONDEMN, POINT AT, AND DEEPLY REJECT THESE IRRATIONAL AND VIOLENT ACTIONS, WHICH ARE AIMED AGAINST SALVADORAN INTELLECTUALS. WE, LIKE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, ALSO POINT TO, QUESTION, AND TOTALLY REJECT THESE ACTIONS WHICH ONLY BRING MOURNING AND GRIEF AND, FURTHERMORE -- AS THE TERRORIST FORCES HAVE DONE ON OTHER OCCASIONS -- CREATE CONFUSION, DECEIT, AND FURTHER TORMENT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WHO HAVE ALREADY SUFFERED SO MUCH.

THE ARMED FORCES CONVEY THEIR DEEPEST CONDOLENCES TO THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL JESUIT COMMUNITY, AND WE ARE WILLING -- AS THE GOVERNMENT HAS POINTED OUT -- TO CARRY OUT THOROUGH INVESTIGATIONS, SO THAT SOONER OR LATER WE WILL FIND THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS SITUATION AND APPLY TO THEM THE PUNISHMENT THEY DESERVE FOR SUCH IRRATIONAL, VIOLENT ACTIONS THAT ONLY BRING GRIEF, TEARS, AND BLOOD TO OUR SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, I BELIEVE THE TIME HAS COME TO FURTHER DEMONSTRATE OUR STOICISM. I BELIEVE THIS IS THE TIME TO DEFINE, IN A TRUE CITIZEN'S SPIRIT, OUR RESOLVE TO DEFEAT, OUR RESOLVE TO WIN. WITHIN A SHORT WHILE, A FEW HOURS, OR A FEW DAYS, WE WILL JOIN THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO CELEBRATE THE VICTORY OF DEMOCRACY, JUSTICE, AND PEACE OVER THE IRRATIONAL VIOLENCE UNLEASHED BY THE FMLN.

THIS MAY ALSO BE A TIMELY OPPORTUNITY TO POINT TO THE TERRORIST FORCES THAT ARE STILL TRYING TO HURT OUR CIVILIAN POPULATION, TO TELL THEM THAT THEIR CAUSE, THE CAUSE OF VIOLENCE, IRRATIONALITY, AND DISRESPECT FOR THE PEOPLE'S WILL, IS LOST. TO THIS EFFECT, THE ARMED FORCES ARE URGING THE TERRORIST FORCES TO SURRENDER, TO LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS, TO STOP THE VIOLENCE, AND TO JOIN CIVILIAN LIFE IN SOCIETY, IN PEACE AND HARMONY, SO THAT WE ALSO -- AS THE ARMED FORCES AND AS AN INSTITUTION -- CAN RESPECT THEIR LIVES AND INCORPORATE THEM INTO SOCIETY, AND SO THAT TOGETHER -- TODAY, TOMORROW, AND ALWAYS -- WE CAN BUILD A COUNTRY FULL OF LOVE, WELL- BEING, PEACE, AND FAITH IN GOD.

DEV-MUC3-0821 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE ARMED FORCES MAINTAIN CONTROL IN THE CAPITAL. AFTER 6 [NUMBER AS HEARD] DAYS OF INTENSE BATTLES BETWEEN THE ARMY AND THE TERRORIST CRIMINALS OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES HAVE SHOWN THEIR PROFESSIONALISM BY ACHIEVING TOTAL CONTROL IN THE CAPITAL. THE LOCATIONS WHERE THERE WERE THE BIGGEST PROBLEMS -- THE SLOPES OF SAN JACINTO HILL IN THE SOUTH AND SOYAPANGO, CIUDAD DELGADO, MEJICANOS, AND ZACAMIL -- HAVE BEEN RETAKEN BY THE ARMY DURING THE WEEKEND. EVEN THOUGH THE ARMY HAD DISLODGED THE MARXIST - LENINISTS FROM MEJICANOS, CIVILIAN ACCESS TO THAT AREA HAS NOT BEEN PERMITTED BECAUSE THE GUERRILLAS MINED THE ENTRANCES TO SEVERAL NEIGHBORHOODS AND SEVERAL HOUSES OF PEOPLE WHO DID NOT COOPERATE WITH THEM. IN CIUDAD DELGADO, ARMED FORCES SOLDIERS FOUGHT SMALL GROUPS OF GUERRILLAS WHO HAD HIDDEN IN HOUSES AND WHO PUT UP SOME RESISTANCE, WHICH WAS QUICKLY CONTROLLED BY THE ARMED FORCES. THE ARMED FORCES MAINTAIN ABSOLUTE CONTROL OVER AMATEPEC AND CIUDAD CREDISA NEIGHBORHOODS.

ONWARD BRAVE SOLDIERS. CONTINUE FIGHTING TO KEEP OUR FATHERLAND FREE WITH GUARANTEES FOR ALL HONEST SALVADORANS.

DEV-MUC3-0822 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL, WHICH HAS BEEN THE SCENE OF FIERCE FIGHTING BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN ARMY AND GUERRILLAS OVER THE PAST WEEK, IS SLOWLY RETURNING TO NORMAL. FOR THE FIRST TIME IN 9 DAYS MANY BUSINESSES AND WORKPLACES OPENED THEIR DOORS AND MANY BUSES WERE OPERATING. AFTER MANY DAYS IN WHICH MOST VEHICLES ON THE STREETS WERE AMBULANCES, OFFICIAL OR MILITARY VEHICLES, AND VEHICLES BELONGING TO NEWSMEN, THE CAPITAL AWAKENED TODAY TO HEAVY TRAFFIC WITH BUSES, TAXIS, TRUCKS, AND PRIVATE VEHICLES.

THE 24-HOUR "CURFEW" DECREED BY THE ARMED FORCES IN THE DENSELY POPULATED NEIGHBORHOODS OF AYUTUXTEPEQUE, CUSCATANCINGO, AND MEJICANOS IN THE NORTHWESTERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR WAS SUSPENDED, SALVADORAN PRESIDENT AFLREDO CRISTIANI ANNOUNCED ON TELEVISION LAST NIGHT.

THE "STATE OF SIEGE" AND "CURFEW," HOWEVER, WILL REMAIN IN EFFECT, FROM 1800 IN THE EVENING UNTIL 0600 IN THE MORNING.

IN TWO OUTLYING NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE CAPITAL, GUERRILLA REDOUBTS AND SOLDIERS HAVE CONTINUED TO CLASH, PARTICULARLY IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS OF APOPA, CIUDAD DELGADO, AND SOYAPANGO.

PRIVATE VEHICLES CANNOT OPERATE IN MUCH OF MEJICANOS NEIGHBORHOOD, ONE OF THE MAIN GUERRILLA BASTIONS LAST WEEK, AS A RESULT OF THE TRENCHES DUG BY THE REBELS AND DEBRIS PILED ON THE STREETS FROM DESTROYED BUILDINGS AND HOMES.

THE SITUATION IS ALSO RETURNING TO NORMAL IN SOME PARTS OF THE INTERIOR, EXCEPT FOR SOME CITIES SUCH AS SAN MIGUEL IN THE EAST AND ZACATECOLUCA IN THE SOUTH WHERE THERE IS STILL FIERCE FIGHTING IN WHICH ELITE ARMY UNITS ARE INVOLVED.

IN THE CAPITAL CITY, THE RED CROSS AND OTHER HUMANTARIAN ASSISTANCE ORGANIZATIONS ARE BEGINNING THE TASKS OF CLEANING UP THE RUBBLE AND REBUILDING THOUSANDS OF HOMES AFFECTED BY THE FIGHTING AND BOMBING, ACCORDING TO THE PRELIMINARY ASSESSMENTS. INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS SOURCES SAID THAT SOME 50,000 PERSONS HAVE HAD TO ABANDON THEIR HOMES AND ARE LODGED IN CHURCHES, STADIUMS, SCHOOLS, AND OTHER BUILDINGS SET UP AS TEMPORARY LODGINGS.

INTERNATIONAL EMERGENCY ASSISTANCE HAS ALSO BEGUN TO ARRIVE BRINGING FIRST AID FOR THE MANY CIVILIANS WHO WERE WOUNDED AND ARE BEING TREATED IN THE HOSPITALS WHERE HUNDREDS OF THE MORE THAN 1,000 WHO WERE TREATED LAST WEEK REMAIN, ACCORDING TO SALVADORAN HOSPITAL SOURCES.

PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANO REPORTED ON A RADIO AND TELEVISION NETWORK THAT "A FEW REDOUBTS" GUERRILLA REDOUBTS REMAIN, THAT THE ARMED FORCES HAVE CONTINUED TO ADVANCE, AND THAT "THE SITUATION WILL BE TOTALLY CONTROLLED SOON."

HE SAID THAT THE WAR VICTIMS WILL BE GIVEN ECONOMIC ASSISTANCE AND THAT HIS CABINET WILL IMPLEMENT "RECONSTRUCTION PROGRAMS," WITH WHICH HE INVITED THE PRIVATE SECTOR TO COOPERATE.

THE STATE RADIO IS CELEBRATING THE "DEFEAT OF THE RED HORDES" OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) IN A TONE OF RESOUNDING VICTORY, CONSTANTLY RENDERING TRIBUTE TO THE LEADERS AND SOLDIERS OF THE BATTALIONS THAT HAVE PARTICIPATED IN EXPELLING THE GUERRILLAS FROM THE CAPITAL AND OTHER CITIES.

"THE TERRORISTS FLED IN DISARRAY," ACCORDING TO THE STATE RADIO, WHICH COMMENTED ON THE MILITARY SITUATION THAT CIRCLES CLOSE TO THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] INTERPRETED AS A "TACTICAL WITHDRAWAL."

THE FIGHTING AND BOMBINGS IN THE CAPITAL AND OTHER PARTS OF THE COUNTRY HAVE LEFT A TOLL OF MORE THAN 1,000 DEAD, HUNDREDS WOUNDED, AND TENS OF THOUSANDS HOMELESS.

DEV-MUC3-0823 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] A FRIEND OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THE FIRST TO ARRIVE ON THE SCENE, SAID THAT HE COUNTED SOME 500 OR 600 BULLET HOLES. HE SAID THAT THESE SHOTS WERE FIRED FROM SOME DISTANCE, WITH A MACHINEGUN SET UP ON A TRIPOD. THE PRIESTS WERE ALSO LATER SHOT IN A GARDEN NEARBY. ACCORDING TO INFORMATION THAT THE SOCIETY OF JESUS RECEIVED FOLLOWING THEIR OWN RECONSTRUCTION OF THE CRIME, WHICH THEY HAVE RELEASED TO THE AUTHORITIES INVESTIGATING THE CASE, THE KILLERS, APPROXIMATELY 30 MEN IN UNIFORM, ARRIVED SHORTLY BEFORE 0230. THEY MACHINEGUNNED THE HOUSE BEFORE ENTERING, DRAGGED THE PRIESTS OUT, PUT THEM IN FRONT OF A WALL THAT IS STILL STAINED WITH BLOOD, AND SHOT THEM. THE PRIESTS WERE ALSO SHOT IN THE HEAD WITH A LONG-RANGE WEAPON; HOWEVER, THESE SHOTS WERE FIRED FROM SOME DISTANCE. A LAWYER, HELPING IN THE INVESTIGATION OF THIS CASE AND WHO HAS ASKED TO REMAIN UNIDENTIFIED, SAID THAT THIS WAS DETERMINED BECAUSE THERE WERE NO GUNPOWDER MARKS ON THE VICTIMS.

AT THE TIME THE CRIME WAS CARRIED OUT, A CURFEW WAS BEING OBSERVED THROUGHOUT THE CITY. [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND THE HOUSE WHERE THE PRIESTS LIVED WAS SURROUNDED BY SOLDIERS. TOGETHER WITH THIS INFORMATION, GATHERED BY SEVERAL INSTITUTIONS AND PROMINENT PERSONS TO PROVE THAT THE MURDER WAS CARRIED OUT BY SOLDIERS, WE MUST STRESS THAT THE HOUSE WAS ALSO SEARCHED BY THE SOLDIERS 2 DAYS BEFORE THE CRIME WAS COMMITTED. A JESUIT PRIEST WHO WAS DESCRIBING THE SCENE SAID THAT ONLY THE AREA PREVIOUSLY SEARCHED BY THE SOLDIERS WAS DESTROYED. HE SAID THAT THE LIBRARY WAS BURNED AND THE ROOMS HAD BEEN RANSACKED. ACCORDING TO THE PRIEST, $5,000 THAT FATHER IGNACIO ELLACURIA HAD RECEIVED IN BARCELONA -- PART OF AN AWARD GIVEN THE UNIVERSITY -- WERE TAKEN FROM ONE OF THE ROOMS.

THE USE OF LONG-RANGE WEAPONS WOULD ALSO EXPLAIN WHY THE BRAINS OF THE DEAD WERE SCATTERED ABOUT. THIS WAS SEEN BY THE FIRST PERSONS WHO ARRIVED ON THE SCENE. OTHERS SAID THAT THE BODIES WERE DESTROYED BECAUSE AK-47 AND M-16 ASSAULT RIFLES WERE USED IN THE ATTACK. THE BODIES WERE SO UTTERLY DESTROYED THAT EMBALMING WAS NOT POSSIBLE. THIS WAS REPORTED TO ACAN-EFE BY SOCIETY OF JESUS SUPERIOR JOSE MARIA TOJEIRA.

REGARDING THE TWO MURDERED WOMEN, THE COOK ELBA JULIA RAMOS AND HER 15-YEAR-OLD DAUGHTER MARISELA, ALL INDICATES THAT THEY WERE MACHINEGUNNED IN THE SMALL ROOM WHERE THEY SLEPT. THERE WAS SO MUCH BLOOD THAT IT SEEPED UNDER THE DOOR, AND A VERTEBRA AND PIECES OF A SKULL CAN STILL BE SEEN UNDER A SOFA IN THE SMALL ROOM. THE PRELIMINARY INVESTIGATIONS SEEM TO INDICATE THAT THE VICTIMS WERE NOT TORTURED AS EARLIER REPORTS HAD STATED.

MEANWHILE, SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI REPORTEDLY SAID YESTERDAY THAT THE ARMED FORCES HIGH COMMAND HAS NOT RULED OUT THE POSSIBILITY THAT THE KILLERS OF THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS COULD HAVE BEEN SOLDIERS. THEY HAVE NOT RULED OUT THE POSSIBILITY THAT SOLDIERS COULD HAVE KILLED THE PRIESTS, AND THEY ARE DETERMINED TO INVESTIGATE THE INCIDENT AND PUNISH THE RESPONSIBLE PARTIES. THIS WAS SAID BY THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT IN STATEMENTS TO ACAN-EFE AND OTHER FOREIGN NEWS AGENCIES. CRISTIANI, WHO INSISTED ON THE NEED TO AVOID UNFOUNDED CONCLUSIONS, ADDED THAT THE MILITARY DOES NOT THINK IT WILL BE AFFECTED BY SOMETHING DONE BY INDIVIDUAL MEMBERS OF THE INSTITUTION.

WE CAN CLEARLY SEE NOW THAT THERE ARE SOME CONTRADICTIONS. AT THIS MOMENT THERE ARE THREE POSITIONS. THERE IS THE POSITION OF U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER -- HE IS LIKE AN OSTRICH WITH ITS HEAD BURIED IN THE SAND. THERE IS PROOF THAT RULES OUT ALL DOUBT. HOW CAN 40 MEN IN UNIFORM BE IN A MILITARIZED AREA FOR 60 MINUTES AND NOT HEAR SHOTS BEING FIRED AND BOMBS EXPLODING? WHY DID THE ARMY NOT SEND IN TROOPS TO FIND OUT WHAT HAPPENED ONLY A FEW BLOCKS FROM COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE'S OFFICE? THE 40 MEN WERE IN THE AREA FOR A WHOLE HOUR. THEY HAD ALREADY SEARCHED FATHER ELLACURIA'S HOME.

OUR QUESTION FOR WILLIAM WALKER: IF THIS WAS NOT DONE BY THE ARMED FORCES, THEN WHY WERE THEY THERE SEARCHING THE PREMISES FOR A WHOLE HOUR AND EVEN STEALING $5,000? THEY SEARCHED DRAWER BY DRAWER. THE DISORDER THEY LEFT BEHIND WAS QUITE EVIDENT IN THE CLIPS SHOWN ON TELEVISION. THEY SEARCHED THE AREA FOR AN HOUR TO SEE WHAT THEY, THE MURDERERS, COULD FIND TO STEAL. HOWEVER, AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER SAYS THAT HE DOES NOT KNOW IF THE ARMY COMMITTED THE CRIME. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0824 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] AS WE SAID EARLIER, THERE ARE THREE POSITIONS. THIS PROVES THAT THERE ARE CONTRADICTIONS SURROUNDING THIS CASE. THERE IS WILLIAM WALKER, ACTING LIKE AN OSTRICH WITH HIS HEAD STUCK IN THE GROUND. AND THERE IS CRISTIANI'S POSITION -- THE DEATH SQUAD MEMBER WHO WEARS A TIE, WHO [WORDS INDISTINCT] AFTER THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY [WORDS INDISTINCT], AND WHO SAID THAT RASH JUDGMENT SHOULD NOT BE PASSED AND THAT NO ONE SHOULD BE IN A HURRY TO ACCUSE THE GOVERNMENT OR ANYONE ELSE. AND THERE IS ALSO THE GENERAL STAFF AND DEFENSE MINISTRY POSITION BLAMING THE FMLN. WHY? IF IT IS TRUE THAT THERE IS A CIVILIAN GOVERNMENT IN EL SALVADOR, THEN WHY CAN THE DEFENSE MINISTER APPEAR BEFORE THE TELEVISION CAMERAS CONTRADICTING CRISTIANI, GOING AGAINST WHAT CRISTIANI HAD SAID? WHO GIVES THE ORDERS HERE, LARIOS OR CRISTIANI? IF CRISTIANI GIVES THE ORDERS, THEN THE DEFENSE MINISTER MUST OBEY CRISTIANI AND REFRAIN FROM MAKING ACCUSATIONS BEFORE A SERIOUS INVESTIGATION IS HELD. HOWEVER, THIS IS NOT THE CASE.

THIS FURTHER PROVES WHAT WE HAVE BEEN SAYING. THE CIVILIAN MASK FELL ON SATURDAY. THE DEFENSE MINISTRY HOLDS THE REAL POWER IN THE COUNTRY. THE DEFENSE MINISTRY CENSORS THE PRESS. THE SOLDIERS ARE THE ONES CENSORING THE TELEVISION STATIONS, AND NOT THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] FOLLOWERS OR OTHER CIVILIANS. THE GENERAL STAFF, THE SOLDIERS, ARE GAGGING THE PRESS, IMPOSING THE STATE OF SIEGE, GIVING THE FINAL ORDERS. IT IS IMPORTANT TO LOOK INTO THIS CLOSELY BECAUSE GEN LARIOS, IN AN EMPTY SPEECH -- WE HEARD HIM DELIVER A RHETORICAL AND EMPTY SPEECH -- ACCUSED THE FMLN OF KILLING THE PRIESTS AND SAID THAT THE ARMY CONTROLS THE COUNTRY. WE POINT OUT THESE CONTRADICTIONS [WORDS INDISTINCT].

BY SAYING THAT THEY DID NOT DO IT, THAT THE ARMED FORCES DID NOT DO IT, THE DEFENSE MINISTER ADMITTED THAT HE DID IT, THAT HE IS ONE OF THE KILLERS. THAT IS WHAT GEN LARIOS IS SAYING, THAT IS WHAT HE SAID IN HIS PUBLIC STATEMENT. [WORDS INDISTINCT] NO DOUBT, AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY HAS [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE DO NOT BELIEVE IN THE GOVERNMENT'S INVESTIGATIONS BECAUSE WE HAVE PAST EXAMPLES OF IT. WE HAVE MONSIGNOR ROMERO'S CASE AND WE HAVE THE CASE OF THE REVOLUTIONARY DEMOCRATIC FRONT LEADERS, WHO, A FEW YEARS AGO, WERE ARRESTED IN BROAD DAYLIGHT DURING A POLICE OPERATION. HOWEVER, NOT A SINGLE SOLDIER HAS BEEN PUNISHED. WE DO NOT BELIEVE IN CRISTIANI'S JUSTICE. THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY IS PUTTING ON THE PRESSURE AND CRISTIANI WILL HAVE TO DO SOMETHING. HE WILL PROBABLY PUT UP SOME ACT. THE U.S. CONGRESS ALSO HAS ITS EYES ON EL SALVADOR. THEY ARE DEBATING THE ISSUE OF AID TO EL SALVADOR. THERE IS SOMETHING ELSE THE U.S. CONGRESS MUST THINK ABOUT. THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE SAID THAT IT IS PLEASED WITH THE WAY CRISTIANI ACTED IN THE FACE OF THE FMLN OFFENSIVE. THIS MEANS THAT THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE HAS APPROVED THE DROPPING OF WHITE PHOSPHORUS OVER ZACAMIL AND THE DESTRUCTION OF 500 HOMES. THIS MEANS THAT THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF STATE HAS APPROVED THE KILLING OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, AND ALSO THE MASSACRE OF SEVERAL SALVADORAN CITIZENS WHO WERE TAKEN FROM THEIR HOMES AND KILLED ON THE SAME BLACK NIGHT WHEN THE JESUIT PRIESTS WERE KILLED.

DEV-MUC3-0826 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 20 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] HERE IS A VERY IMPORTANT POINT THAT U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER SHOULD TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION. AMBASSADOR WALKER SEEMS TO BE A VERY BAD INVESTIGATOR, AS HE IS STILL IN THE DARK AS REGARDS THE COWARDLY MURDER OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS. AFTER THE FUNERAL OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THE U.S. AMBASSADOR STILL EXPRESSED DOUBTS REGARDING THE AUTHORS OF THIS CRIME.

WELL, WE HAVE RECEIVED A REPORT STATING THAT THE MURDERERS OF THE JESUITS FIRED MORE THAN 500 SHOTS AND STAYED IN THE RESIDENCE OF THE SLAIN PRIESTS FOR 1 HOUR. IN OTHER WORDS, 40 MEN IN THE UNIFORM OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY WERE A FEW BLOCKS FROM THE GENERAL STAFF PARTICIPATING IN SHOOTING THAT LASTED SEVERAL MINUTES, AND REMAINED IN THERE FOR 1 HOUR, IN AN AREA UNDER THE ARMY'S CONTROL, IN AN AREA UNDER THE CONTROL OF THE GENERAL STAFF.

WE HAVE A QUESTION FOR THE U.S. AMBASSADOR. HOW COULD 40 MEN IN SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES UNIFORMS, AND WITH POLICE AND ARMY PATROLS ONLY A FEW METERS AWAY FROM THE JESUITS' RESIDENCE, REMAIN IN THAT PLACE FOR 1 HOUR IF THEY WERE NOT MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES?

AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER, IF YOU STILL HAVE ANY SHAME, TELL THE WORLD AND ANSWER THIS QUESTION: IF THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF DID NOT KILL THE JESUIT PRIESTS, HOW COULD THE MURDERERS -- AS THIS INTERNATIONAL DISPATCH SAYS -- REMAIN IN THE RESIDENCE FOR 1 HOUR AFTER THE HEAVY SHOOTING, AFTER KILLING THE PRIESTS WITH MACHINEGUNS IN TRIPODS, AS THE CABLE SAYS?

WE WILL READ THIS DISPATCH WHICH IS BEING READ ALL OVER THE WORLD. MAYBE WILLIAM WALKER DOES NOT EVEN READ INTERNATIONAL DISPATCHES, BECAUSE HE CYNICALLY SAID AFTER THE PRIESTS' FUNERAL THAT HE HAD NO EVIDENCE OR INDICATION THAT THE CRIME WAS COMMITTED BY THE ARMED FORCES. WELL, AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER, WE WILL READ THIS DISPATCH TO YOU:

THE [WORD INDISTINCT] IN UNIFORM WHO KILLED SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND TWO COMPANIONS IN SAN SALVADOR ON THURSDAY FIRED MORE THAN 500 SHOTS AND REMAINED AT THE SCENE OF THE CRIME FOR ALMOST 1 HOUR. WE REPEAT: THEY WERE IN THE PRIESTS' RESIDENCE FOR ALMOST 1 HOUR, ACCORDING TO PRIVATE INVESTIGATIONS CONDUCTED BY VARIOUS INSTITUTIONS.

A FEW HOURS BEFORE THE FUNERAL, THE SCENE OF THE CRIME REVEALS SOME OF THE CIRCUMSTANCES CONCERNING THE MACHINEGUNNING OF THE PRIESTS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0827 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 21 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE THREE SPANISH MEMBERS OF THE INTERNATIONAL PEACE BRIGADES, FREED TODAY BY THE SALVADORAN NATIONAL GUARD, SAID THAT THE AUTHORITIES ORDERED THEM TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY BECAUSE THEY WERE SUSPECTED OF COLLABORATING WITH "TERRORIST DELINQUENTS."

"WE ARE BEING THROWN OUT OF THE COUNTRY," SAID FRANCES RIERA, ONE OF THE SPANIARDS DETAINED THIS MORNING TOGETHER WITH HIS FELLOW COUNTRYMEN ESTHER DOMENECH AND LUIS PEREZ, A GUATEMALAN UNDER REFUGE AT THE EPISCOPAL CHURCH, AND ANOTHER THREE FOREIGNERS -- A COLOMBIAN, A CANADIAN, AND AN AMERICAN.

RIERA SAID THEY WERE DETAINED AT 1005 GMT, WHILE THE CITY WAS "UNDER CURFEW" AND UNDER A "STATE OF SIEGE," AND THAT NATIONAL GUARD MEMBERS "KNOCKED ON THE DOOR, ENTERED, SEPARATED US, TOOK THE FOREIGNERS ASIDE, AND DELIVERED US AN ANTICOMMUNIST HARANGUE."

"THEY TOLD US THEY WERE ARRESTING US FOR OUR OWN PROTECTION BECAUSE FOREIGNERS WERE BEING THREATENED BY TERRORIST DELINQUENTS. AT THE NATIONAL GUARD WE WERE MADE TO SIGN A STATEMENT IN WHICH WE APPEAR AS SUSPECTS OF COLLABORATING WITH TERRORIST DELINQUENTS," RIERA ADDED.

THE THREE SPANIARDS ARE AT THE SPANISH EMBASSY, AFTER AMBASSADOR FRANCISCO CADIZ IMMEDIATELY WENT INTO ACTION TO GET THEM FREED.

A TOTAL OF 15 PEOPLE WERE DETAINED, NINE OF THEM SALVADORANS, AND WE "KNOW NOTHING OF THEIR WHEREABOUTS," RIERA SAID. HE ADDED THAT THEY HAD REMAINED IN DETENTION FOR OVER 1 HOUR, STRESSING THAT "WE WERE NEVER MISTREATED NOR WERE WE ASKED ANY QUESTIONS."

RIERA SAID THAT THERE ARE MORE THAN 135 PEOPLE AT THE EPISCOPAL CHURCH WHO WERE LEFT HOMELESS BY THE WAR, AND MORE ARE EXPECTED TODAY.

"PEOPLE HAVE TO REMAIN THERE (AT THE EPISCOPAL CHURCH) BECAUSE THEY HAVE NO PLACE TO GO. THERE ARE NO PLACES LEFT AFTER THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE BOMBINGS," RIERA STRESSED.

HE ADDED THAT THE CHURCH "HAS EVIDENCE THAT WHOLE NEIGHBORHOODS WERE SET ON FIRE."

RIERA REPORTED THAT AT THE END OF AUGUST "ARMED MEN, DRESSED IN MILITARY UNIFORMS," ENTERED HIS HOME AND "INTIMIDATED US."

THE THREE FREED SPANIARDS WILL RETURN AS SOON AS POSSIBLE TO MADRID, VIA GUATEMALA, A SPOKESMAN FOR THE SPANISH EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR REPORTED.

DEV-MUC3-0829 (PRC)

WASHINGTON DC (UNITED STATES), 21 NOV 89 (MOSCOW TASS) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH HAS SAID THAT THE UNITED STATES INTENDS TO CONTINUE MILITARY AND ECONOMIC AID TO EL SALVADOR, THE SCENE OF FIERCE CLASHES RECENTLY BETWEEN SALVADOREAN INSURGENTS AND THE PRO-AMERICAN REGIME'S ARMY.

SPEAKING AT THE ANDREWS AIR FORCE BASE, MARYLAND, ON MONDAY, THE PRESIDENT STRONGLY CRITICISED THE PREVAILING CONGRESSIONAL SENTIMENTS IN FAVOUR OF THE TERMINATION OF AID TO THE SALVADOREAN GOVERNMENT.

"THIS CONCEPT OF THE CONGRESS, OF SOME MEMBERS -- TALKING ABOUT CUTTING OFF AID TO EL SALVADOR IS ABSOLUTELY UNACCEPTABLE TO ME AS PRESIDENT." HE SAID.

"WE SUPPORT PRESIDENT CRISTIANI AND HIS EFFORTS TO RESTORE ORDER," BUSH SAID.

THE PRESIDENT ACCUSED THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FIGHTING FOR NATIONAL INDEPENDENCE AND DEMOCRACY, OF BEING FINANCED BY "MARXISTS". MEANWHILE THE VOLUME OF WASHINGTON'S MILITARY AND ECONOMIC AID TO THE SALVADOREAN REGIME IS KNOWN TO EXCEED 1.5 MILLION DOLLARS.

"TO CONTINUE TO HAVE A HANDFUL OF COUNTRIES AROUND -- A VERY SMALL HANDFUL -- SUPPORTING THE OUTDATED CONCEPT OF MARXIST GUERRILLAS, IS UNACCEPTABLE TO THE UNITED STATES," THE PRESIDENT SAID. "AND I AM TO TELL THE CONGRESS OF THE UNITED STATES THAT I WILL NOT ACCEPT, AS PRESIDENT, A CUT OFF OF AID TO EL SALVADOR," HE SAID.

THE PRESIDENT SAID "WE CANNOT CONDONE KILLING" IN EL SALVADOR, IGNORING THE FACT THAT THE NOTORIOUS "DEATH SQUADS", PARAMILITARY EXTREME RIGHT-WING FORMATIONS, HAVE KILLED SCORES OF THOUSANDS OF CIVILIANS IN THE PAST FEW YEARS. CIVILIANS, SUSPECTED OF LINKS WITH GUERRILLAS, ARE IMMEDIATELY EXECUTED, THE AMERICAN PRESS HAS REPORTED.

ACCORDING TO THE ASSOCIATED PRESS, THERE ARE 55 AMERICAN MILITARY ADVISERS IN EL SALVADOR, SOME OF THEM INVOLVED IN TERRORISTIC "DEATH SQUAD" OPERATIONS, AS WELL AS MANY U.S. SECRET SERVICE EMPLOYEES.

DEV-MUC3-0831 (PRC)

CLANDESTINE, 21 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE SEEN DISPATCHES RELEASED BY U.S. NEWS AGENCIES REPORTING THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HAS TAKEN HOSTAGES. THE FMLN DOES NOT TAKE HOSTAGES; OUR ACTIONS ARE NOT AGAINST FOREIGNERS. THEREFORE, NO HOSTAGES HAVE BEEN TAKEN. THE FMLN ENSURES THE SAFETY OF ALL FOREIGNERS WHO MAY BE TRAPPED IN THE AREAS OF CONFLICT AREAS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY. THE FMLN DOES NOT TAKE HOSTAGES, IT IS NOT THE WAY THE FMLN OPERATES. THEREFORE, ONCE AND FOR ALL WE WISH TO STATE THAT THERE ARE NO FOREIGNERS BEING HELD HOSTAGE BY THE FMLN. THE FMLN DOES NOT TAKE HOSTAGES. THEREFORE, THE INFORMATION BEING RELEASED BY THE U.S. NEWS AGENCIES IS NOT TRUE. THE FMLN DOES NOT TAKE HOSTAGES. THERE IS NO REASON WHY WE SHOULD TAKE HOSTAGES, WE ARE NOT TERRORISTS. WE DO NOT HOLD FOREIGNERS HOSTAGE AS SOME U.S. NEWS AGENCIES ARE REPORTING.

WE WILL BE RELEASING A COMMUNIQUE ON THIS MATTER SHORTLY. HOWEVER, WE WISH TO STATE THAT THE FMLN DOES NOT TAKE HOSTAGES. THE FOREIGN DISPATCHES RELEASED ARE GROUNDLESS. THE DISPATCHES STATE THAT THE FMLN IS HOLDING FOREIGNERS HOSTAGE. THAT IS NOT TRUE; WE DO NOT TAKE HOSTAGES, IT IS NOT OUR POLICY. WE ARE CLARIFYING THIS FOR THE DIPLOMATIC CORPS AND INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY. WE DO NOT WANT THEM TO BE CAUGHT OFF GUARD BY THE INFORMATION BEING RELEASED BY FOREIGN NEWS AGENCIES.

THERE ARE NO HOSTAGES, TAKING HOSTAGES IS NOT OUR POLICY. IF A FOREIGN CITIZEN -- U.S. CITIZEN OR ANY OTHER FOREIGNER -- IS TRAPPED IN AREAS OF CONFLICT, THE FMLN WILL ENSURE HIS SAFETY. OUR FIGHTERS HAVE BEEN ORDERED TO PROTECT THE PHYSICAL INTEGRITY OF ANY CITIZEN AFFECTED BY THE CURRENT SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR.

WE WISH TO BE VERY CLEAR THAT THERE ARE NO HOSTAGES, IT IS NOT THE FMLN POLICY TO HOLD HOSTAGES.

DEV-MUC3-0832 (PRC)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 21 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] WE BRIEFLY INTERRUPT OUR SCHEDULED PROGRAM TO BRING YOU A LAST MINUTE REPORT.

ACCORDING TO AFP, RELIABLE EYEWITNESSES HAVE REPORTED THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS THIS MORNING OCCUPIED THE SHERATON HOTEL LOCATED IN ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, NORTHEASTERN SAN SALVADOR. OAS SECRETARY GENERAL JOAO BAENA SOARES IS CURRENTLY STAYING AT THE SHERATON HOTEL. FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] REBELS REPORTEDLY POSITIONED THEMSELVES ON THE ROOF OF THE HOTEL WHERE SECRETARY GENERAL BAENA SOARES IS STAYING SHORTLY BEFORE 0830 [1430 GMT]. ACCORDING TO A RELIABLE SOURCE, AT 0830 THE REBELS HAD NOT CAPTURED BAENA SOARES. THE SOURCE ADDED THAT BAENA SOARES' PERSONAL BODYGUARDS WERE KILLED IN THE CLASHES THAT CONTINUE AROUND THE HOTEL. IT WAS ALSO LEARNED THAT HELICOPTERS WERE BOMBING THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, WHERE THE REBELS RAISED BARRICADES EARLY THIS MORNING WITH THE APPARENT INTENTION OF ISOLATING THE AREA.

AN UNIDENTIFIED AND NERVOUS- SOUNDING PERSON, WHO MANNED THE SHERATON HOTEL SWITCHBOARD EARLY THIS MORNING, TOLD A REPORTER THAT HE COULD NOT TRANSFER ANY CALLS AND HUNG UP ABRUPTLY. SINCE 0630 [1230 GMT], THE TELEPHONES AT THE SHERATON HOTEL ARE NOT BEING ANSWERED.

DEV-MUC3-0833 (PRC)

MEXICO CITY (MEXICO), 21 NOV 89 (RED NACIONAL 13 IMEVISION TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] IMEVISION CORRESPONDENT FOR CENTRAL AMERICA EPIGMENIO IBARRA WAS DETAINED BY THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES FOR A FEW HOURS AFTER BEING IN A CAR ACCIDENT IN MERLIOT NEIGHBORHOOD. IBARRA WAS RELEASED LAST NIGHT AND TAKEN TO A HOSPITAL WERE HE IS BEING TAKEN CARE OF. OUR REPORTS STATE THAT HIS CONDITION IS STABLE.

EPIGMENIO IBARRA, KNOWN FOR HIS IMPORTANT AND OUTSTANDING INCURSIONS INTO THE SALVADORAN BATTLEFIELD, HAS BEEN THE VICTIM OF FREQUENT SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ATTACKS.

WE, THE IMEVISION WORKERS, REPUDIATE THIS ATTACK ON EPIGMENIO IBARRA, WHO WAS ARRESTED AND RELEASED LAST NIGHT.

CLASHES BETWEEN THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] AND THE SALVADORAN ARMY RESUMED YESTERDAY AFTERNOON AFTER A PERIOD OF APPARENT CALM IN EL SALVADOR.

SHOOTING IN ESCALON, SAN BENITO, AND MERLIOT NEIGHBORHOODS WORSENED AFTER THE AIR FORCE BOMBED THE DENSELY POPULATED AREA. CLANDESTINE RADIO VENCEREMOS HAS ASSERTED THAT THE AREAS OCCUPIED BY THE REBELS DURING THE LAST FEW DAYS CONTINUE UNDER THEIR CONTROL.

THERE IS HEAVY FIGHTING BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND THE GOVERNMENT FORCES IN ZACATECOLUCA DEPARTMENT, AND NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR IS UNDER FMLN CONTROL.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [FMLN COMMANDER JORGE MELENDEZ] WE TRUST THAT DESPITE THE ENORMOUS BLOODSHED, THE WAY IN WHICH THE ARMY IS FACING OUR ATTACKS REAFFIRMS THE ABSOLUTE JUSTICE AND LEGITIMACY OF OUR STRUGGLE. [END RECORDING]

THE ARMY HAS BEEN UNABLE TO ADVANCE DUE TO THE THE GUERRILLA TACTICS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED ARMY MEMBER] AT PRESENT, OUR MEN ARE ENTERING THE AREA AND COMBING THE AREA BLOCK BY BLOCK, BECAUSE WE HAVE TOO MANY CIVILIANS IN THIS AREA. [END RECORDING]

THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS HAVE SOUGHT REFUGE IN CHURCHES AND RED CROSS BUILDINGS.

OAS SECRETARY GENERAL JOAO BAENA SOARES HAS VISITED THE AREAS MOST AFFFECTED BY THE FIGHTING. IN WASHINGTON, PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH REFUSED TO WITHDRAW THE U.S. AID FOR SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT.

MEANWHILE, SALVADORAN FOREIGN MINISTER JOSE MANUEL PACAS HAS REJECTED ALL POSSIBILITIES OF A DIALOGUE WITH THE FMLN REBELS. IN VENEZUELA, IT WAS REPORTED THAT THE ROUND OF TALKS BETWEEN THE GUERRILLA MOVEMENT AND THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT SCHEDULED TO BE HELD THIS WEEK WAS SUSPENDED FOR AN INDEFINITE PERIOD.

DEV-MUC3-0837 (PRC)

HAVANA (CUBA), 21 NOV 89 (TELE REBELDE NETWORK) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FERNANDO CASTRO, A MEMBER OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT WHO RESIDES IN CUBA, BY JOURNALIST ROBERTO AGUDO] [TEXT] [AGUDO] WELL, WE BELIEVE THAT TODAY IT IS PARTICULARLY IMPORTANT TO HEAR THE REMARKS OF COMRADE CASTRO OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] IN THIS PROGRAM. I CONSIDER IT PARTICULARLY IMPORTANT BECAUSE THE LATEST REPORTS WE ARE RECEIVING STATE THAT THE GUERRILLAS ARE CARRYING OUT A TACTICAL RETREAT, A TACTICAL REDEPLOYMENT. I WOULD LIKE TO ASK YOU, CASTRO, WHAT THE OBJECTIVES BEHIND THIS TACTICAL RETREAT OR REDEPLOYMENT OF THE GUERRILLA MOVEMENT ARE.

[CASTRO) FOLLOWING 10 DAYS OF FIGHTING IN VARIOUS PLACES IN THE COUNTRY, ESPECIALLY IN SAN SALVADOR, WHERE THE REGIME CONDUCTED CRIMINAL BOMBINGS, GOING AS FAR AS USING PHOSPHOROUS BOMBS, AND TO AVOID FURTHER LOSS OF CIVILIAN LIVES, THAT IS, OF PEOPLE DIRECTLY INVOLVED IN THE FIGHTING, THE FMLN HAS DECIDED TO CARRY OUT A TACTICAL RETREAT IN ORDER TO CONCENTRATE ITS FORCES TO CONTINUE TO STRIKE IN OTHER PLACES AGAINST THE ENEMY: THE SALVADORAN ARMY.

[AGUDO] CASTRO, DOES THIS MEAN THAT THE POLITICAL-MILITARY MANEUVER HAS ALREADY ENDED?

[CASTRO] NO. THE POLITICAL-MILITARY MANEUVER CONTINUES. THE OBJECTIVE IS TO OPEN AREAS FOR NEGOTIATIONS AND, IF POSSIBLE, TO CREATE CONDITIONS THAT WOULD BE CONDUCIVE TO DISLODGING THAT CRIMINAL GOVERNMENT WHICH IS TODAY MAKING OUR PEOPLE SUFFER.

[AGUDO] AFTER NEARLY 10 DAYS OF FIGHTING, DOES THE FMLN CONSIDER THAT THE OPERATION HAS ACHIEVED ITS POLITICAL OBJECTIVE?

[CASTRO] WE BELIEVE THAT THIS OPERATION HAS ACHIEVED SEVERAL OBJECTIVES. IN THE FIRST PLACE, WE HAVE SHOWN THE SALVADORAN ARMY AND THE WORLD OUR POLITICAL, MILITARY AND DIPLOMATIC CAPABILITIES. THE ENEMY CLAIMED THAT WE ARE WEAK. THEY EVEN STATED THAT IT WOULD BE IMPOSSIBLE FOR THE FMLN TO HOLD A POSITION IN SAN SALVADOR FOR 1 DAY. WE HAVE HELD MORE THAN 10 POSITIONS FOR 10 DAYS AND THEY HAD TO USE ALL OF THE SOPHISTICATED WEAPONS DELIVERED TO THEM BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT TO FORCE US TO RETREAT, TO CARRY OUT A TACTICAL MANEUVER IN ORDER TO AVOID MORE DEATHS AND TO BE ABLE TO CONTINUE TO TAKE ACTIONS IN OTHER AREAS OF THE COUNTRY, INCLUDING THE CAPITAL ITSELF.

[AGUDO] WE ARE CONCERNED ABOUT ONE THING: THERE IS A GROUP OF GUERRILLA FIGHTERS, OF REBEL FORCES THAT ARE RETREATING FROM THE CAPITAL. ISN'T THE SALVADORAN ARMY IN A POSITION TO SURROUND THEM, TO ANNIHILATE THEM?

[CASTRO] NO. IT IS IMPOSSIBLE FOR THE ARMY TO SURROUND OR TO ANNIHILATE OUR COMRADES. WE HAVE DEMONSTRATED OUR GREAT MANEUVERING SKILLS IN THE COURSE OF THIS WAR. WE HAVE TIME AND AGAIN BROKEN SIEGES, AND IT IS IMPOSSIBLE FOR THEM TO ANNIHILATE US. I REPEAT, WE HAVE JUST RETREATED IN ORDER TO RELOCATE OUR FORCES IN PLACES THAT WOULD ENABLE US TO DEAL EVEN HARDER BLOWS TO THE ENEMY. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0841 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 22 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE EL DESPERTAR REFUGEE CENTER IN SAN SALVADOR, MANAGED BY JESUITS, WAS EVACUATED TODAY BECAUSE IT WAS HIT BY A MISSILE FIRED BY A MILITARY PLANE LAST NIGHT, RELIGIOUS AND DIPLOMATIC SOURCES HAVE SAID.

SPANISH CITIZEN JOSE MARIA TOJEIRA, SUPERIOR OF THE JESUITS IN CENTRAL AMERICA, TOLD ACAN - EFE THAT A ROCKET HIT EL DESPERTAR BUT THAT NONE OF THE 4 PRIESTS AND APPROXIMATELY 100 REFUGEES, WHO HAVE BEEN THERE SINCE LAST WEEK'S BLOODY CONFRONTATIONS, WAS HURT.

THE 4 JESUITS, INCLUDING DIRECTOR RICHARD HOWARD, A U.S. CITIZEN, WERE TRAPPED WITH THE REFUGEES AT EL DESPERTAR FOR 24 HOURS BECAUSE OF CLASHES IN THE SECTOR BETWEEN THE ARMED FORCES AND GUERRILLAS. THE LATTER YESTERDAY BROKE INTO THE HOTEL WHERE OAS SECRETARY GENERAL JOAO BAENA SOARES WAS STAYING.

A SOURCE OF THE SPANISH EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR TOLD ACAN - EFE THAT HE HAD TO CONVINCE THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMY TO STOP THE AIR STRIKES AGAINST EL DESPERTAR, LOCATED IN SAN ANTONIO ABAD IN THE CAPITAL'S NORTHWEST.

BECAUSE OF THE FIGHTING AROUND THE SHERATON HOTEL, TWO OTHER JESUITS YESTERDAY WERE TRAPPED AT THE SACRED HEART SECONDARY SCHOOL, WHERE SEVERAL DOZENS OF PEOPLE HAVE SOUGHT REFUGE, THE ORDER'S SUPERIOR FOR CENTRAL AMERICA TOLD ACAN - EFE.

ACCORDING TO TOJEIRA, THE EVACUATION OF THE REFUGEES WAS DISCUSSED WITH SALVADORAN ARCHBISHOP ARTURO RIVERA DAMAS. THE REFUGEES WERE TAKEN TO PLACES CONSIDERED SAFER.

THE JESUITS REGRETTED THAT THE AIR FORCE FIRED AGAINST THIS REFUGEE CENTER, WHICH THEY HAVE BEEN MANAGING FOR 6 YEARS, WHEN THE WAR IN EL SALVADOR INCREASED ITS TEMPO.

JESUITS IGNACIO ELLACURIA, IGNACIO MARTIN BARO, SEGUNDO MONTES, AMANDO LOPEZ, JUAN RAMON MORENO, AND JOAQUIN LOPEZ, THE FIRST FIVE SPANIARDS AND THE LAST A SALVADORAN, WERE KILLED IN SAN SALVADOR ON 16 NOVEMBER.

DEV-MUC3-0847 (PRC)

TAIPEI (ROC), 23 NOV 89 (CNA) -- [TEXT] THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA [ROC] WEDNESDAY EXPRESSED ITS REGRETS OVER THE EL SALVADORAN SITUATION THAT HAS RESULTED FROM MILITARY ATTACKS LAUNCHED BY LEFT-WING GUERRILLAS.

CHEN YU-CHU, SPOKESMAN FOR THE MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS [MOFA], SAID THAT WITH THE ASSISTANCE OF SUCH COMMUNIST COUNTRIES AS CUBA AND NICARAGUA, THE LEFT-WING GUERRILLAS HAD LAUNCHED LARGE-SCALE MILITARY ATTACKS ON SAN SALVADOR, THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL, AND OTHER MAJOR CITIES IN AN ATTEMPT TO FORCIBLY SUBVERT THE LEGITIMATE GOVERNMENT. THE ATTACKS KILLED MANY UNARMED CIVILIANS.

CHEN POINTED OUT THAT THE ATROCITIES COMMITTED BY THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS HAD BEEN STRONGLY CONDEMNED BY PEOPLE ALL OVER THE WORLD.

"I ALSO REGRET AND CONDEMN THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS' BRUTAL ACTION," THE FOREIGN MINISTRY SPOKESMAN SAID.

"WE BELIEVE THAT UNDER THE ABLE LEADERSHIP OF SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO FELEX CRISTIANI, PEACE, SECURITY AND PROSPERITY WILL BE RESTORED SOON IN EL SALVADOR," CHEN SAID.

MEANWHILE, THE MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS DENIED A FOREIGN WIRE REPORT THAT THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR HAD BEEN OCCUPIED BY SALVADORAN LEFTIST GUERRILLAS. ALL EMBASSY STAFF MEMBERS ARE SAFE, THE MINISTRY SAID.

THE AMERICAN CABLE NEWS NETWORK (CNN) REPORTED IN ITS TV NEWS CASTS THAT THE ROC EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR HAS BEEN OCCUPIED BY THE GUERRILLAS. THE CNN REPORT CAUSED DEEP CONCERN AT THE MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS, WHICH IMMEDIATELY CABLED ITS OVERSEAS MISSIONS TO TRY TO CONTACT THE ROC EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR.

THE MIAMI OFFICE OF THE COORDINATION COUNCIL FOR NORTH AMERICAN AFFAIRS WAS FINALLY ABLE TO CONTACT CHINESE AMBASSADOR TO SAN SALVADOR SHEN JEN-PIAO.

ACCORDING TO AMBASSADOR SHEN'S REPORT, THE ROC EMBASSY IN SAN SALVADOR HAS NOT BEEN OCCUPIED BY THE GUERRILLAS AND ALL STAFF MEMBERS WERE SAFE. HOWEVER, THE AREA AROUND THE EMBASSY, THE AMBASSADORIAL RESIDENCY AND THE STAFF HOUSING AREA HAD BECOME A BATTLE FIELD AND THE ONLY ACCESS TO THE OUTSIDE WAS BY TELEPHONE, MOFA SAID.

MOFA SAID THAT AMBASSADOR SHEN HAD ORDERED ALL STAFF MEMBERS TO STAY AT HOME AND WAIT FOR FURTHER INSTRUCTIONS.

DEV-MUC3-0849 (PRC)

SAN SALVADOR, 22 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, ATTENTION, SALVADORAN PEOPLE; ATTENTION, ATTENTION, SALVADORAN PEOPLE: THE NATIONAL INFORMATION CENTER, CIN, REPORTS THAT THE TERRORIST DELINQUENTS ARE SPREADING FALSE RUMORS THAT YOU SHOULD LEAVE YOUR HOUSE BECAUSE THAT IS A MEASURE ADOPTED BY THE ARMED FORCES -- WITH THE INTENTION OF EXERTING PSYCHOLOGICAL PRESSURE ON THE POPULATION.

HOWEVER, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE OFFICIALLY NOTIFIED THAT THOSE ARE FALSE RUMORS BEING SPREAD BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. THE ARMED FORCES ARE HERE TO PROTECT THE CITIZENRY, AND NO ONE HAS BEEN ASKED TO LEAVE HIS PLACE OF RESIDENCE.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, YOUR COURAGEOUS AND HEROIC ARMED FORCES ARE HERE TO CONTINUE DEFENDING YOU FROM THAT COWARDLY AND SAVAGE FMLN AGGRESSION. CITIZEN, DO NOT LEAVE YOUR HOUSE, BECAUSE THE FMLN CAN TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THIS AND USE YOU AS A SHIELD TO CARRY OUT MORE CRIMES AGAINST YOU.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, YOUR TRUST IN THE ARMED FORCES ENCOURAGES US TO CONTINUE DEFENDING YOU FROM THOSE FMLN DELINQUENTS. SALVADORANS, DO NOT LEAVE YOUR HOUSE BECAUSE IT COULD BE LOOTED BY THE FMLN HORDES. DO NOT HEED THE FALSE RUMORS BRING SPREAD BY THE TERRORISTS.

THE CIN KEEPS YOU INFORMED ON WHAT IS REALLY TAKING PLACE. THE FMLN RESORTS TO LIES WHEN ITS PLANS ARE COUNTERED BY OUR GLORIOUS ARMED FORCES' PROFESSIONALISM AND REJECTED BY YOU, COURAGEOUS SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

LONG LIVE THE ARMED FORCES! LONG LIVE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE! LONG LIVE THE REPUBLIC!

DEV-MUC3-0850 (PRC)

SANTIAGO, 22 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] CHILE HAS RESUMED DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH CZECHOESLOVAKIA AS OF WEDNESDAY, 22 NOVEMBER [AS HEARD]. THIS INFORMATION WAS RELEASED BY FOREIGN MINISTER HERNAN FELIPE ERRAZURIZ. THE MINISTER ADDED THAT THIS IS THE FOURTH SOCIALIST COUNTRY WITH WHICH CHILE HAS NORMALIZED RELATIONS. HE ALSO EXPLAINED THAT THIS STEP IS PART OF THE PRESIDENT AUGUSTO PINOCHET'S POLICY TO INCREASE THE PRESENCE OF CHILE THROUGHOUT THE WORLD.

THE MINISTER INDICATED THAT THE CHILEAN COMMUNITY IN EL SALAVADOR AND THE MEMBERS OF CHILE'S DIPLOMATIC MISSION THERE ARE FINE, FOLLOWING THE RAID STAGED BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT ON THE SHERATON HOTEL IN EL SALVADOR.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] WHAT INFORMATION DOES THE FOREIGN MINISTRY HAVE ABOUT CHILEAN RESIDENTS IN EL SALVADOR?

[ERRAZURIZ] AS WE REPORTED YESTERDAY, THERE ARE PERMANENT CONTACTS BETWEEN THE MINISTRY AND THE CHILEAN EMBASSY IN EL SALVADOR AND, OBVIOUSLY, WITH THE SALVADORAN AMBASSADOR IN SANTIAGO. BASICALLY, BOTH THE MEMBERS OF THE CHILEAN COMMUNITY AND THE MEMBERS OF THE DIPLOMATIC MISSION ARE FINE. WE HAVE RECEIVED INFORMATION TO THE EFFECT THAT THERE IS CLEAR INVOLVEMENT OF CUBA AND NICARAGUA IN THE RECENT TERRORIST ONSLAUGHT IN EL SALVADOR, AND WE WANT TO EXPRESS OUR SOLIDARITY WITH THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S STRUGGLE TO DEFEND THEIR DEMOCRACY. [END RECORDING]

THE CHILEAN FOREIGN MINISTER EXPLAINED THAT THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT HAS OFFICIALLY DECIDED TO SUSPEND NORMAL MOVEMENT OF PEOPLE ACROSS THE BORDER BETWEEN TACNA AND ARICA. HE ADDED THAT BORDER RESTRICTIONS ALSO APPLY TO BOLIVIA AND ECUADOR.

ERRAZURIZ ADDED THAT THE CHILEAN FOREIGN MINISTRY IS IN TOUCH WITH THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT, THE CHILEAN EMBASSY IN LIMA, AND PERUVIAN CUSTOMS OFFICIALS IN AN EFFORT TO NORMALIZE THE MOVEMENT ACROSS THE CHILEAN-PERUVIAN BORDER.

THE FOREIGN MINISTER CONCLUDED BY SAYING THAT THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT HAS APPOINTED AMBASSADOR SANTIAGO BENADAVA EXECUTIVE SECRETARY OF THE CHILEAN-ARGENTINE COMMISSION FOR PHYSICAL AND ECONOMIC INTEGRATION. SANTIAGO BENADAVA WILL THUS REPLACE GENERAL ENRIQUE MOREL.

DEV-MUC3-0851 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 22 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] MR. WALKER, WHEN WILL YOU TELL YOUR PRESIDENT BUSH TO STOP BEING SO RUDE. HE HAS BEEN TALKING TOO MUCH. [WORDS INDISTINCT] HEAR YOUR OWN PEOPLE SPEAK DEMANDING PEACE. THIS IS NOT RIGHT. IS THIS IS THE DEMOCRACY YOU PEOPLE WANT TO EXIST HERE? BUT YOU PEOPLE ARE WRONG, MR. WALKER. IT WILL BE IMPOSSIBLE HERE BECAUSE THE PEOPLE ARE A VOLCANO IN ERUPTION. WHOEVER PUTS HIS HAND IN THE FIRE WILL GET BURNED, MR. WALKER. STOP STICKING YOUR NOSE INTO SOMEONE ELSE'S BUSINESS. YOU SHOULD RATHER SEND AWAY, ONCE AND FOR ALL, THOSE COUNTRYMEN OF YOURS WHO HAVE BEEN SENT HERE AS ADVISERS. THEY ARE ADVISERS, ALL RIGHT, BUT OF THE DEATH SQUADS. I HAVE JUST ONE PIECE OF ADVICE FOR YOU. UNDERSTAND ONCE AND FOR ALL THAT WHOEVER PUTS HIS HAND IN THE FIRE WILL GET BURNED. THE LAVA OF THIS ERUPTING VOLCANO IS BOILING, MR. WALKER. UNDERSTAND THAT THE PEOPLE WILL NOT TAKE ONE STEP BACK. ALL FOR PEACE.

WE HAVE BEEN READING THE SUMMARY OF OUR NEWS MONITORING. U.S. PENTAGON MILITARY OFFICIALS AND MANY NONMILITARY ANALYSTS ARE SURPRISED OVER WHAT THEY CALL THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT'S OFFENSIVE CAPABILITIES. A REPORT STATES THAT PENTAGON OFFICIALS ARE VERY SURPRISED OVER THE FMLN MANEUVERABILITY AND OFFENSIVE CAPABILITIES. THE FMLN ACTIONS OF THE PAST DAYS HAS SPOILED ALL THE INTELLIGENCE REPORTS THAT SALVADORAN MILITARY MEN SENT TO U.S. OFFICIALS CONTAINING INFORMATION ON THE FMLN MANPOWER-WEAPONS RATIO AND OUR MILITARY ABILITY TO OPERATE.

THE FMLN HAS NEVER LOST ITS MILITARY CAPABILITIES. SOME ANALYSTS VIEW THE SALVADORAN WAR AS A WAR BETWEEN TWO ARMIES. THAT IS A MISTAKE BECAUSE THE SALVADORAN WAR IS NOT A WAR BETWEEN TWO ARMIES. IT CANNOT BE VIEWED AS IF IT WERE A REGULAR WAR SUCH AS THE IRAN-IRAQ WAR. EL SALVADOR IS LIVING THROUGH CONFLICT THAT IS MAINLY SOCIAL IN NATURE, A CONFLICT THAT IS ROOTED IN SOCIAL INJUSTICE. THE FMLN DID NOT EMERGE FROM A MILITARY SCHOOL WITH A REARGUARD IN ANOTHER COUNTRY, BUT IT IS MADE UP OF THE PEOPLE THEMSELVES. FMLN COMBATANTS HAVE LEARNED TO FIGHT IN ACTUAL CLASHES. THEY HAVE GAINED GROUND INCH BY INCH; IT HAS ORGANIZED THE PEOPLE. THE FMLN DOES NOT FORCEFULLY RECRUIT PEOPLE. THEREFORE, IT IS NOT PERIODICALLY RENEWING ITS RANKS AS THE ARMY DOES THROUGH FORCEFUL RECRUITMENT. TO THE FMLN, THE MAIN GOAL IS TO ORGANIZE THE PEOPLE, TO GET AS CLOSE AS IT CAN TO THE PEOPLE.

BECAUSE OF THE ECONOMIC CRISIS, SOCIAL INJUSTICE, AND LACK OF DEMOCRATIC OPPORTUNITIES IN [EL] SALVADOR, THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS HAVE NO OTHER OPTION THAN TO TAKE UP ARMS AND FIGHT TO ACHIEVE BETTER LIVING CONDITIONS IN THE FACE OF THE GOVERNMENT'S BRUTAL REPRESSION, ECONOMIC INJUSTICE, AND UNEMPLOYMENT. TO CHANGE THIS SITUATION, THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS DECIDED TO TAKE UP ARMS AND LEARN TO WAGE WAR BY FIGHTING DAIILY. THAT IS THE HISTORY OF THE FMLN.

THEREFORE, IT CANNOT BE SAID THAT TWO ARMIES ARE FIGHTING EACH OTHER. THE LOGISTICS APPARATUS OF THE FASCIST GOVERNMENT' [ARMED] FORCES IS NOT COMPARABLE TO OUR FORCES. THEY BRING TO OUR COUNTRY TONS OF BOMBS, RIFLES, BOOTS, AND MATERIAL THROUGH PORTS AND MILITARY AIRPORTS. ALTHOUGH THE GOVERNMENTS OF NICARAGUA, CUBA, AND THE USSR COULD HELP THE FMLN, AS MANY ARE SAYING, THE FIREPOWER OF OUR FORCES COULD NEVER BE COMPARED TO THE ARMY'S.

NEVERTHELESS, THE FMLN HAS OPENED IN ALL COUNTRIES, INCLUDING THE [UNITED] STATES, THE NECESSARY WAYS FOR US TO OBTAIN OUR ARMS AND AMMUNITION. WE HAVE THE RIGHT TO THIS. HOW DOES THE FMLN LEARN TO FIGHT-- BY FIGHTING. WE ARE NOW FIGHTING IN CITIES. EVERY MILITARY ANALYST KNOWS HOW DIFFICULT IT IS TO FIGHT IN URBAN AREAS. THE FMLN FIGHTING IN SAN SALVADOR, SAN MIGUEL, ZACATECOLUCA, AND USULUTAN HAS SHOWN THE ORGANIZATION'S TREMENDOUS ABILITY TO WEAR OUT THE ENEMY, TAKE AND HOLD POSITIONS, AND MANEUVER IN THE CITY JUST AS IT HAS DONE IN RURAL AREAS. THE FMLN ABILITY HAS SURPRISED THE MILITARY ANALYSTS AT THE PENTAGON. OUR FRONT HAS ALWAYS HAD THIS ABILITY. BUT NOW WE HAVE CHANGED OUR STRATEGY AND TACTICS TO DEFEAT THE ENEMY PLANS. THE [ARMED] FORCES HAVE A SPECIFIC PLAN REGARDING THE ACTIONS BY PATROLS [WORDS INDISTINCT], SPECIAL OPERATIONS. THE FMLN HAD TO CHANGE ITS STRATEGY TO STRIKE AT THE SMALL FORCES THAT TRIED TO INFILTRATE OUR ZONE UNDER COVER. ONLY THUS COULD WE ANNIHILATE AND DEFEAT THESE FORCES AND THEIR STRATEGY. AND THIS IS WHAT WE DID. THIS IS WHAT MUST BE OBSERVED, HOW THE FMLN HAS CHANGED ITS MILITARY STRATEGY TO FACE THE ONE USED BY THE [ARMED] FORCES. OF COURSE, WE HAVE ACCUMULATED GREAT EXPERIENCE OVER THE YEARS, WHICH WE HAVE APPLIED THESE LAST DAYS IN COMBAT IN [SAN] SALVADOR AND [SAN] MIGUEL. ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS ARE BEING DESTROYED IN STREETS AND AVENUES; HELICOPTERS ARE BEING SHOT DOWN; SOLDIERS ARE BEING TAKEN PRISONER; AND ARMS ARE BEING SEIZED.

MILITARY ANALYSTS ARE WONDERING HOW A GUERRILLA ARMY CAN OPERATE FOR SO LONG IN AN URBAN AREA. IN ADDITION, LOGISTICS MUST BE TAKEN INTO CONSIDERATION. THE [ARMED] FORCES ARE CONSTANTLY GETTING AMMUNITION THROUGH THE ILOPANGO [AIR] BASE. THE FMLN HAS BEEN ABLE TO CARRY OUT THIS OPERATION BECAUSE OF THE PEOPLE'S SUPPORT. THOUSANDS OF CAPITAL RESIDENTS COOPERATED BY KEEPING SILENT WHEN THEY SAW THE GUERRILLA COLUMNS PASS BY. THEY DID NOT WARN THE [ARMED] FORCES. WHY? BECAUSE THE PEOPLE SEE IN THESE GUERRILLA COLUMNS THEIR OWN ARMY.

DEV-MUC3-0853 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 22 NOV 89 (CANAL SEIS TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] GENERAL JUAN RAFAEL BUSTILLO, COMMANDER OF THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE, TODAY DEFENDED THE MILITARY ACTIONS THAT THE ARMY CARRIED OUT DURING THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONA LIBERATION FRONT] OFFENSIVE. THE MILITARY CHIEF SAID THAT IF THERE HAS BEEN DRASTIC ACTION AGAINST THE FMLN REBELS, IT HAS ONLY BEEN TO DEFEND THE CIVILIANS FROM WHAT HE DESCRIBED AS A FOREIGN AGGRESSION. IN THIS WAY, GEN BUSTILLO REPLIED TO STATEMENTS BY SAN SALVADOR ARCHBISHOP ARTURO RIVERA Y DAMAS, WHO SAID THE ARMY'S RESPONSE TO THE FMLN OFFENSIVE IN SAN SALVADOR WAS EXCESSIVE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BUSTILLO] MANY COMMENTS CAN BE MADE BUT WHAT MUST BE ASKED IS WHY DID THE REBELS SEEK THE URBAN AREAS? WHAT IS THEIR JUSTIFICATION? THAT IS THE CONDEMNABLE ASPECT. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THE MEDIA SHOULD NOT BE CONFUSED ABOUT WHETHER WE ACTED STRONGLY AS MSGR RIVERA Y DAMAS SAID. IT IS TRUE WE HAVE BEEN STRONG AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO BE STRONG. BUT WE MUST UNDERSTAND THAT THE TERRORISTS BEGAN THE ACTION, THAT IS HOW THE PROBLEM BEGAN. THAT IS WHAT MUST BE JUDGED AND NOT HOW WE REACTED. [END RECORDING]

GEN BUSTILLO SAID THE MAIN ROLE OF THE AIR FORCE IS THE DEFENSE OF THE FATHERLAND. HE ADDED: THERE IS NO ROOM HERE FOR GUERRILLAS AND MUCH LESS FOR THOSE OF THE FMLN WHO CALL THEMSELVES DEFENDERS OF THE PEOPLE. GEN BUSTILLO SAID THIS FMLN OFFENSIVE WAS NOT PREPARED IN THE LAST FEW DAYS. INSTEAD, HE SAID, IT MUST HAVE BEEN PREPARED AT LEAST 18 MONTHS AGO. HE SAID IT HAS TAKEN TIME TO OUST THE REBELS BECAUSE THE ARMED FORCES HAVE NOT WANTED TO HARM THE CIVILIAN POPULATION, AMONG WHICH THE INSURGENTS HID.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BUSTILLO] IT IS DIFFICULT FOR US TO ANNIHILATE THESE TERRORISTS WHEN THEY TAKE PEOPLE AS HOSTAGES. THAT IS WHY FOR YEARS THEY BEGAN INFILTRATING AND ESTABLISHING THE MEANS TO USE THE PEOPLE AS A COVER. WE CAN SEE THAT WHAT THEY HAVE BEEN DOING IN THE MOUNTAINS AND THE VILLAGES FOR THE PAST 9 YEARS, THEY HAVE NOW CARRIED OUT HERE IN SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER BIG CITIES. THEY HAVE TAKEN COVER BEHIND THE PEOPLE, AND THAT IS WHY IT HAS BEEN VERY HARD AND DIFFICULT FOR US TO ANNIHILATE THEM. WE HAD TO BE CAREFUL SO AS TO CAUSE THE LEAST HARM TO THE PEOPLE. [END RECORDING]

HE ALSO SAID THE SEIZURE OF THE SHERATON HOTEL IS AN ISOLATED INCIDENT THAT ONLY SEEKS INTERNATIONAL ATTENTION. BUSTILLO SAID A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION HAS JUST BEEN A GAME FOR THE REBELS SO NO ONE IN EL SALVADOR SHOULD CONSIDER IT AS A SOLUTION TO A 10-YEAR-OLD WAR THAT HAS LEFT MORE THAN 60,000 DEAD.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BUSTILLO] THE DIALOGUE AND A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION HAVE BEEN A TACTIC USED BY THE FMLN FOR SEVERAL YEARS. WE CAN NOW CLEARLY SEE THAT NEITHER THE PEOPLE, ARMED FORCES, NOR THE POLITICIANS SHOULD CONSIDER THEM AS AN ALTERNATIVE. IT CAN BE CLEARLY SEEN THAT ALL THIS TIME DURING WHICH SOME INDIVIDUALS OF THIS ADMINISTRATION AND THE PREVIOUS ADMINISTRATION HAD BEEN SEEKING A SOLUTION THROUGH DIALOGUE, THE FMLN HAD JUST BEEN PREPARING FOR THIS OFFENSIVE. [END RECORDING]

ASKED WHAT PLANS THE ARMED FORCES HAVE IN THE FACE OF ANOTHER FMLN OFFENSIVE, THE GENERAL WAS EMPHATIC:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BUSTILLO] ANNIHILATE THEM. ANNIHILATE THEM. THAT IS THE ONLY THING WE CAN DO. [END RECORDING]

THE GENERAL MADE THESE STATEMENTS TO THIS NEWSCAST AFTER HE LISTED THE WEAPONS THAT WERE SEIZED AND THE CASUALTIES SUSTAINED BY THE ARMY. BUSTILLO SAID FOUR OFFICERS OF THE PARATROOPERS BATTALION WERE KILLED AND SEVERAL WERE WOUNDED. HE SAID 20 SOLDIERS DIED IN THE MILITARY ACTIONS [TIME FRAME NOT SPECIFIED].

DEV-MUC3-0854 (GTE)

BOGOTA, 23 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] GENERAL MIGUEL ANTONIO GOMEZ PADILLA, NATIONAL POLICE DIRECTOR, REPORTED TODAY THAT PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, NUMBER ONE IN THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, AND ONE OF THE OCHOA BROTHERS, ALSO A KINGPIN IN THE GROUP, ARE APPARENTLEY SURROUNDED AND SHOULD BE CAPTURED ANY TIME.

GENERAL PADILLA TOLD REPORTERS AT 1500 GMT TODAY THAT THE SEARCH FOR SOME OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL LEADERS HAD BEEN INTENSIFIED IN THE PAST 2 DAYS SOMEWHERE IN THE MIDDLE MAGDALENA IN COLOMBIA'S NORTHERN CENTER. HE REFUSED TO IDENTIFY THE PLACE SO AS NOT TO HAMPER THE OPERATIONS.

HE ALSO SAID THAT THE SEARCH IS BEING CONDUCTED BY THE POLICE'S ELITE GROUP, SUPPORTED BY ARMY AND AIR FORCE TROOPS.

GEN PADILLA SAID: "FOR THE PAST 2 DAYS, SPECIAL ELITE POLICE MEMBERS, SUPPORTED BY THE AIR FORCE AND MILITARY UNITS, HAVE CONFRONTED DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN THE SEARCH FOR DRUG TRAFFICKING CAPOS WHO WILL BE CAPTURED LATER."

"AT THIS TIME, WE ARE OPERATING IN A SPECIFIC AREA AGAINST THE MEDELLIN CARTEL." HE ALSO SAID THAT "PABLO ESCOBAR AND ONE OF THE OCHOA BROTHERS" ARE POSSIBLY ENCIRCLED AND THAT THE CLASHES "APPARENTLY HAVE RESULTED IN TWO MEN BEING KILLED AND NUMEROUS OTHERS BEING DETAINED."

THE HIGH-RANKING OFFICER ASKED NEWSMEN FOR TIME "TO COMPLETE THE ACTION AND, POSSIBLY, TO REPORT THAT WE HAVE ACHIEVED VICTORY."

POLICE SOURCES SAID THAT THE OPERATIONS ARE TAKING PLACE IN THE CONCORNA MUNICIPALITY AREA, IN ANTIOQUIA'S MIDDLE MAGDALENA REGION, BETWEEN MEDELLIN AND BOGOTA, SOME 180 KM NORTHWEST OF THE COLOMBIAN CAPITAL, WHERE GUERRILLAS OF THE CAMILIST UNION - NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY (UC-ELN) ARE ALSO ACTIVE.

THE MEDELLIN CARTEL IS REGARDED AS THE WORLD'S MOST IMPORTANT DRUG TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATION AND, ACCORDING TO THE U.S. POLICE, IS RESPONSIBLE FOR 70 PERCENT OF THE COCAINE SMUGGLED INTO THE UNITED STATES.

PABLO ESCOBAR AND JORGE LUIS OCHOA VASQUEZ, THE CARTEL'S NUMBER ONE AND NUMBER TWO MEN, RESPECTIVELY, ARE RANKED AMONG THE WORLD'S 20 RICHEST MEN BY SPECIALIZED U.S. MAGAZINES LIKE "FORBES" AND "FORTUNE," WHICH ESTIMATE THEIR PERSONAL WEALTH AT OVER $3 BILLION.

JORGE LUIS OCHOA HAS TWO BROTHERS WHO ARE ALSO REGARDED AS IMPORTANT DRUG KINGPINS.

DEV-MUC3-0855 (GTE)

BOGOTA, 23 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, HEAD OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, HAS ESCAPED FROM THE COLOMBIAN POLICE TRAP WHICH WAS SET UP 2 DAYS AGO TO CAPTURE HIM, POLICE SOURCES SAID.

ESCOBAR, REGARDED AS THE OPERATIONS CHIEF OF COLOMBIA'S LARGEST COCAINE - EXPORTING GROUP, FLED "VIRTUALLY IN UNDERWEAR," ONE OF THE OFFICERS IN CHARGE OF THE OPERATIONS SAID.

CHIEF OF POLICE GENERAL MIGUEL PADILLA HAD EARLIER REPORTED THAT THE DRUG TRAFFICKER HAD BEEN "SURROUNDED" AND THAT "HIS CAPTURE WAS IMMINENT." PADILLA ALSO SAID HE WAS "ALMOST SURE" THAT THE OPERATION, IN WHICH THE ARMY AND THE AIR FORCE ALSO PARTICIPATED, WOULD YIELD "POSITIVE RESULTS."

THE COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES SURROUNDED AND RAIDED FOUR ESTATES OWNED BY ESCOBAR GAVIRIA IN THE MIDDLE REGION OF THE MAGDALENA RIVER, IN COLOMBIA'S NORTHERN CENTER.

ON THE ESTATES, CALLED "LAS PALMAS," "EL ORO," "LA PAZ," AND "FLORENCIA," 50 BODYGUARDS AND 5 WOMEN WERE DETAINED. TWO UNIDENTIFIED PEOPLE WERE KILLED IN THE ENSUING CLASHES.

THE POLICE SEIZED RIFLES, ISRAELI-MADE UZZI SUBMACHINEGUNS, AND SEVERAL GRENADES.

ACCORDING TO A POLICE SOURCE, THE POLICE ELITE TROOPS HAVE CONTINUED TO COMB THE AREAS NEAR THE RAIDED ESTATES IN AN EFFORT TO TRACK THE ESCAPEES, WHO COULD INCLUDE ONE OF THE THREE OCHOA BROTHERS, WHO ARE THE CARTEL'S HEADS.

THE OPERATIONS ARE BEING CONDUCTED IN THE COCORNA MUNICIPALITY, IN THE MIDDLE MAGDALENA IN ANTIOQUIA, BETWEEN MEDELLIN AND BOGOTA, 180 KM NORTHWEST FROM BOGOTA.

THE MEDELLIN CARTEL IS CONSIDERED RESPONSIBLE FOR 70 PERCENT OF THE COCAINE THAT ENTERS THE UNITED STATES ILLEGALLY.

DEV-MUC3-0857 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 23 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] JUST AS WE REPORTED THIS AFTERNOON, FASCIST CRISTIANI AND PONCE, THE VISIBLE HEAD OF LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO THE 1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] HELD A PECULIAR NEWS CONFERENCE WHICH NOT EVEN THE CUSCATLAN RADIO NETWORK EVEN DARED BROADCAST.

THE NEWS CONFERENCE HAD JUST BEGUN THIS AFTERNOON WITH CRISTIANI AND SOME REPORTERS. PONCE WAS BESIDE HIM. SUDDENLY, AN EXPLOSION OCCURRED WHICH STARTLED BOTH CRISTIANI AND PONCE. THE NERVOUSNESS OF CRISTIANI AND PONCE DID NOT FADE AWAY. THEY WERE SCARED. THE REPORTERS ASKED FOR AN EXPLANATION OF THE EXPLOSION. AFTER STAMMERING FOR A WHILE, PONCE SAID IT WAS A BOMBING BY THE ARMY ON THE SLOPES OF THE [SAN] SALVADOR VOLCANO.

IN THE NEWS CONFERENCE, CRISTIANI REJECTED THE FMLN'S [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] POSITION, WHICH HE DESCRIBED AS A PROPOSAL. BUT THE FMLN HAS MADE NO PROPOSAL. THE FMLN HAS BUT ECHOED THE CLAMOR OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY AND VARIOUS ORGANIZATIONS, ALL OF WHICH DEMAND A CEASE - FIRE IN THE COUNTRY. CONSEQUENTLY, CRISTIANI HAS NOT REJECTED A CEASE - FIRE PROPOSAL, BUT THE POSITION OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY.

DEV-MUC3-0859 (GTE)

NO CITY, NO DATE -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] CRISTIANI EMPHASIZED THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE CAPABLE OF COUNTERING ANY AGGRESSION ON THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. HE ALSO TERMED AS A COMPLETE FAILURE THE TERRORIST OFFENSIVE, WHICH WAS SPURNED BY THE CITIZENRY, ADDING THAT THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY HAD HARSHLY CRITICIZED THE FMLN'S TERRORIST ACTIONS.

[CRISTIANI] "LET US SAY THAT THE ARMED FORCES AND THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT ARE PREPARED TO MILITARILY COUNTER THE AGGRESSION FOR AS LONG AS THE FMLN WANTS TO. THE FMLN DECIDED TO LAUNCH AN OFFENSIVE BECAUSE IT THOUGHT THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE SUPPORTED IT [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE PEOPLE HAVE SPURNED IT ONCE AGAIN. THE ONLY THING THE FMLN HAS MANAGED TO ACHIEVE IS TO EARN THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S SCORN."

"WE WANT TO TALK ABOUT A CEASE-FIRE AND NEGOTIATE A CEASE-FIRE BUT WE BELIEVE THAT THE ENDING OF HOSTILITIES SHOULD BE THE FIRST GESTURE BECAUSE THAT IS THE ONLY WAY WE CAN TALK TO THE FMLN. IF THIS DOES NOT OCCUR, I DO NOT THINK THAT ONE SINGLE SALVADORAN WILL TRUST THE FMLN IN THE LEAST [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE, MEANING THE ARMED FORCES AND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC, DO NOT WANT TO [WORDS INDISTINCT]."

THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT THERE IS A POSSIBILITY THAT THE CURFEW WILL BE MODIFIED, PARTICULARLY IN PLACES WHERE ORDER HAS BEEN COMPLETELY RESTORED. HE ALSO EXPLAINED THAT HIS GOVERNMENT HAS NEVER SOUGHT A MILITARY SOLUTION TO THE ARMED CONFLICT BECAUSE THAT IS CLARIFIED IN THE CONSTITUTION.

CRISTIANI "WE HAVE NEVER SOUGHT A MILITARY SOLUTION. THE FMLN IS THE ONE WHICH HAS OPTED FOR A MILITARY SOLUTION. WE HAVE NOT [WORDS INDISTINCT] GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC WITH WEAPONS AND WE HAVE NOT SOUGHT THE ARMED FORCES TO DO IT. THE FMLN IS THE ONLY ONE TRYING TO SEIZE POWER WITH ITS WEAPONS. THE ARMED FORCES HAS ONLY FULFILLED ITS DUTY, WHICH IS TO COUNTER AN ARMED ACTION."

"FURTHERMORE, WE BELIEVE THAT THIS AGGRESSION IS [WORDS INDISTINCT] NICARAGUA AND CUBA, BECAUSE NICARAGUA AND CUBA [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE FMLN WOULD HAVE NO POSSIBILITY OF [WORDS INDISTINCT] PEACE IN EL SALVADOR."

THE PRESIDENT ASSERTED THAT HIS GOVERNMENT WILL CONTINUE WITH THE DIALOGUE PROCESS BUT IT MUST BE FULLY CONVINCED THAT THE REBEL GROUPS ARE WILLING TO PUT DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND JOIN THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IN A PEACEFUL AND VOLUNTARY WAY. HE EXPLAINED THAT THE GOVERNMENT'S ROLE IN CARACAS, VENEZUELA, WAS LIMITED TO NOTIFYING HIS COUNTERPART, CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ, ABOUT THE SALVADORAN SITUATION AND REASSERTING THE GOVERNMENT'S POSITION GIVEN THE FMLN DELEGATION'S ABSENCE -- WHICH CONFIRMED THEIR LACK OF WILLINGNESS TO ACHIEVE PEACE.

DEV-MUC3-0860 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 23 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] WHENEVER WE HAVE MADE ANY PEACE PROPOSAL, THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT ANSWERS BY SAYING IT'S IMPOSSIBLE TO ACHIEVE PEACE AND THAT OUR PROPOSALS ARE NOT FEASIBLE BECAUSE WE MUST RESPECT THE CONSTITUTION. THAT IS WHAT ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] ALWAYS SAYS. WELL, WE WOULD LIKE TO ASK [U.S. AMBASSADOR] WILLIAM WALKER -- WHO HAS SAID IN THE UNITED STATES THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] PEACE PROPOSALS ARE NOT FEASIBLE BECAUSE THEY VIOLATE THE SALVADORAN CONSTITUTION -- IF THE CONSTITUTION DOES NOT PROHIBIT FOREIGN TROOPS FROM COMING TO OUR COUNTRY WITHOUT THE GOVERNMENT'S APPROVAL? WE WOULD LIKE TO ASK THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY WHY U.S. ARMY SPECIAL FORCES CAME TO EL SALVADOR, AS PRESIDENT BUSH HIMSELF ANNOUNCED? WE SAW THESE SPECIAL FORCES IN THE STREETS OF SAN SALVADOR, VIOLATING THE CONSTITUTION THAT YOU PEOPLE CLAIM TO DEFEND.

WE WANT TO ASK THE PATRIOTIC OFFICIALS: WHY ARE THERE THREE ARMIES RIGHT NOW IN THIS COUNTRY? THERE IS THE FMLN ARMY, THE LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO 1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE CAPT GEN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] ARMY, AND PRESIDENT BUSH'S ARMY. SO, WHAT IS THE ANSWER? WHENEVER WE PROPOSE A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT, WE ARE TOLD IT IS IMPOSSIBLE BECAUSE IT VIOLATES THE CONSTITUTION. HOWEVER, PRESIDENT BUSH VIOLATED THE CONSTITUTION THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY CLAIM TO DEFEND WHEN HE SENT A FOREIGN MILITARY FORCE TO THIS COUNTRY. HE ALSO VIOLATED THE SOVEREIGNTY OF THIS NATION. THEREFORE, GENTLEMEN OF ARENA AND OF THE HIGH COMMAND, THIS LOVE FOR THE CONSTITUTION AND THE LAWS THAT YOU CLAIM TO HAVE IS FALSE.

WE WANT TO ASK COLONEL PONCE: WHY IS THERE A FOREIGN MILITARY FORCE IN OUR COUNTRY RIGHT NOW? DOESN'T THE CONSTITUTION THAT YOUR ARMED FORCES CLAIM TO RESPECT PROHIBIT IT? IN OTHER WORDS, WHEN THE NATION WANTS A POLITICAL SOLUTION FOR THE SAKE OF PEACE, YOU PEOPLE SAY IT IS IMPOSSIBLE BECAUSE WE MUST RESPECT THE CONSTITUTION. HOWEVER, WHEN PRESIDENT BUSH ARROGANTLY ANNOUNCES IN HIS PRESIDENTIAL PLANE THAT HIS FORCES HAVE CARRIED OUT OPERATIONS IN A SAN SALVADOR HOTEL, THEN THE CONSTITUTION IS WORTH NOTHING.

WE WANT TO APPEAL TO THE ARMED FORCES OFFICERS TO THINK ABOUT THIS SITUATION. THERE ARE OFFICERS BEING KILLED ON THE BATTLEFIELDS. FOR EXAMPLE, AN OFFICER FROM THE MORAZAN BATTALION DIED IN ALTOS DE LA CUEVA IN SAN MIGUEL; LIEUTENANTS HAVE BEEN KILLED IN SAN SALVADOR CITY; DOZENS OF LIEUTENANTS HAVE BEEN WOUNDED OR KILLED IN THE LAST 10 DAYS. OFFICERS, YOU KNOW ABOUT THIS. SO WE WANT TO CALL ON THE LIEUTENANTS, THE CAPTAINS, THE PATRIOTIC OFFICERS, TO THINK ABOUT THIS SITUATION. YOU ARE BEING TOLD YOU ARE DEFENDING THE CONSTITUTION. WHAT CONSTITUTION? AFTER ALL, A HERD OF GRINGO RAMBOS IS HERE; AND WITH THEIR YANKEE BOOTS, THEY HAVE TRAMPLED ON THE CONSTITUTION. SO OFFICERS, WHAT ARE YOU DEFENDING? WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT THIS? THIS SITUATION IS UNACCEPTABLE FOR ANY SALVADORAN PATRIOT. OFFICERS, WE KNOW YOU ARE LISTENING TO US IN THE GARRISONS TO FIND OUT WHAT IS HAPPENING, BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT NETWORK IS HIDING THIS INFORMATION FROM YOU. YOU MUST THINK OVER THIS SITUATION, OFFICERS. YOU ARE SHEDDING BLOOD, LOSING ARMS AND LEGS IN THE BATTLEFIELDS, SACRIFICING YOUR LIVES, SEEING HOW THE CAPITAL CITY IS BEING DESTROYED BY THE BOMBINGS, AND YOU ARE TOLD THIS IS BEING DONE TO DEFEND THE CONSTITUTION. HOWEVER, MR BUSH DECIDED TO SEND A HERD OF RAMBOS WHO ARE GOOD FOR NOTHING. AFTER ALL, THEY DID NOTHING, EXCEPT COVER THEIR FACES LIKE COMMON CRIMINALS. SO, OFFICERS, WHAT ARE YOU FIGHTING FOR? WHAT IS AT STAKE HERE? IS IT COMMUNISM, OR THIS OR THAT? IS IT BECAUSE MSGR ROMERO WAS A COMMUNIST AND THEREFORE MURDERED? WAS IT BECAUSE THE JESUITS WERE COMMUNISTS AND THEREFORE MURDERED? NOW IT IS SAID THAT THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY MEMBERS ARE COMMUNISTS. OTHERS SAY THAT THE JOURNALISTS, THE TEACHERS ARE COMMUNISTS; EVERYONE IS A COMMUNIST. IS THIS A NATION OF COMMUNISTS? WHAT IS THIS? WE MUST START TO THINK ABOUT THIS SITUATION AT THIS CRITICAL HOUR FOR THE NATION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0863 (GTE)

TEGUCIGALPA, 24 NOV 89 (EL HERALDO) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [INFORMATION AND PRESS DIRECTORATE OF THE FOREIGN RELATIONS MINISTRY] [TEXT] THE INFORMATION AND PRESS DIRECTORATE OF THE FOREIGN RELATIONS MINISTRY HEREBY PUBLISHES A NOTE SENT TO NICARAGUAN FOREIGN MINISTER MIGUEL D'ESCOTO BY FOREIGN RELATIONS MINISTER CARLOS LOPEZ CONTRERAS. THE TEXT OF THE NOTE READS.

NOTE NO. 122-DSM

TEGUCIGALPA, 23 NOVEMBER 1989

HIS EXCELLENCY

MR MIGUEL D'ESCOTO BROCKMANN

FOREIGN MINISTER

MANAGUA, NICARAGUA

MR MINISTER:

MY GOVERNMENT HAS NOTED WITH GREAT CONCERN THE CONCENTRATION OF NICARAGUAN TROOPS AT VARIOUS POINTS OF THE BORDER WITH HONDURAS, AS WELL AS THE ANNOUNCEMENTS MADE BY NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT SPOKESMEN ABOUT BEGINNING MILITARY ACTIONS AGAINST THEIR ARMED OPPOSITION, REGARDLESS OF LOCATION.

TAKING INTO CONSIDERATION THE DANGER REPRESENTED BY THE CONCENTRATION OF TROOPS AT THE BORDER, MY GOVERNMENT HEREBY WARNS THAT IT IS A VIOLATION OF INTERNATIONAL LAW, PARTICULARLY TO INTER-AMERICAN LAW, TO RESORT TO THREATS OR THE USE OF FORCE AND TO VIOLATE THE SOVERIGNTY AND TERRITORIAL INTEGRITY OF OTHER STATES.

AS YOUR GOVERNMENT IS FULLY AWARE OF -- AND THIS HAS BEEN VERIFIED BY ON-SITE INSPECTIONS BY THE INTERNATIONAL COMMISSION OF SUPPORT AND VERIFICATION (CIAV) -- APPROXIMATELY 15,000 HONDURANS LIVE IN THE BORDER SECTOR CURRENTLY THREATENED BY THE SANDINIST PEOPLE'S ARMY AND ARTILLERY. THE SECURITY OF THOSE CITIZENS IS THE PRIMARY RESPONSIBILITY OF MY GOVERNMENT. HOWEVER, IN THAT SECTOR THERE ARE CAMPS OF DISARMED FORMER COMBATANTS FROM THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE [RN]. MANY OF THEM ARE WAR CRIPPLED AND THEIR RELATIVES, MOST OF WHOM ARE CHILDREN, WOMEN, AND THE ELDERLY.

TO CARRY OUT INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS AGAINST THE HONDURAN CIVILIAN POPULATION AND TO VIOLATE THAT SECTOR OF HONDURAN TERRITORY WOULD BE A BARBARIC ACTION AGAINST HUMANITY. IF YOU ARE REFERRING TO AN ALLEGED RIGHT TO CARY OUT MILITARY ACTIONS AGAINST YOUR ARMED OPPOSITION "NO MATTER WHERE THEY ARE," I REMIND YOU THAT THIS WOULD BE AN INTENTIONAL MASSACRE, BECAUSE MOST OF THE PEOPLE IN THAT AREA ARE CIVILIANS AND THE REST ARE DISARMED FORMER COMBATANTS. THIS SITUATION HAS BEEN VERIFIED BY THE CIAV.

THEREFORE, MY GOVERNMENT DEMANDS THE IMMEDIATE WITHDRAWAL OF THE NICARAGUAN TROOPS CONCENTRATED IN THE BORDER AREAS WITH HONDURAS. UP UNTIL THIS TIME, THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT HAS NOT INCREASED THE NUMBER OF TROOPS WHO REGULARLY COMPOSE THE BORDER SECURITY FORCES.

NEVERTHELESS, MY GOVERNMENT IS NOT GIVING UP ITS RIGHT TO REPEL ANY ACTION THAT VIOLATES HONDURAN SOVEREIGNTY AND TERRITORIAL INTEGRITY AND TO CARRY OUT THE CONSULTATIONS IT DEEMS NECESSARY, TO ADOPT THE INDIVIDUAL OR COLLECTIVE DEFENSE MEASURES THE SITUATION REQUIRES.

MY GOVERNMENT ALSO WANTS TO STATE THAT IT VIEWS WITH ASTONISHMENT THE PROPOSAL PRESENTED BY THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT TO THE COUNTERREVOLUTION -- DURING THE TALKS PROMOTED BY THE CIAV IN THE UNITED STATES -- IN THE SENSE THAT THE NICARAGUAN INTERNAL ARMED CONFLICT BE SOLVED BY WITHDRAWING THE ARMED OPPOSITION TO HONDURAS. THIS PROPOSAL CLEARLY VIOLATES THE ESQUIPULAS II AGREEMENT AND THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED AT THE TELA SUMMIT, WHICH CONTAIN PROVISIONS FOR DEMOCRATIZATION, NATIONAL RECONCILIATION, DEMOBILIZATION, AND REPATRIATION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0865 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 24 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] ATTORNEY GENERAL MAURICIO COLORADO, INVESTIGATING THE MURDER OF THE SIX JESUITS IN EL SALVADOR, SAID TODAY THAT THE DECLARATIONS MADE SO FAR, AMONG THEM THOSE MADE BY LUCIA BARRERA CERNA, ONE OF THE MAIN WITNESSES, "ARE NOT CONCLUSIVE, NOR HAVE THEY SHED ANY LIGHT" ON THE IDENTITY OF THE KILLERS."

THE JESUITS, FIVE SPANIARDS AND ONE SALVADORAN, WERE MURDERED 9 DAYS AGO BY A GROUP OF MEN WEARING MILITARY UNIFORMS DURING A "CURFEW" DECREED BY THE GOVERNMENT AS A RESULT OF THE REBEL OFFENSIVE THAT BEGAN ON 11 NOVEMBER.

LUCIA BARRERA, WHO TESTIFIED BEFORE COLORADO, A GOVERNMENT COMMISSION INVESTIGATING THE MURDERS, AND SEVERAL DIPLOMATS, AMONG THEM SPANISH AMBASSADOR FRANCISCO CADIZ, SAID THAT THE MURDERERS NUMBERED BETWEEN 30 AND 40 UNIDENTIFIED MEN WEARING MILITARY UNIFORMS. COLORADO SAID IN A NEWS CONFERENCE THAT "THERE ARE SEVERAL WITNESSES, NONE OF WHICH HAS SHED MUCH LIGHT ON THE CASE. THEIR DECLARATIONS ARE NOT CONCLUSIVE REGARDING THIS SAD AND REGRETTABLE EVENT." HE STRESSED "THAT IT WOULD BE RASH TO SAY THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMY DID IT."

ACCORDING TO COLORADO, NEITHER FBI AGENTS FROM THE UNITED STATES, NOR SCOTLAND YARD AGENTS FROM GREAT BRITAIN, NOR THE SPANISH GOVERNMENT'S DELEGATES -- AS REQUESTED BY SALVDORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI WHEN HE PROMISED TO INVESTIGATE THE CASE EXHAUSTIVELY -- HAVE ARRIVED IN EL SALVADOR.

HE SAID THAT THE COURT WILL SUBPOENA MARIA JULIA HERNANDEZ, DIRECTOR OF THE SAN SALVADORAN ARCHBISHOPRIC'S LEGAL AID OFFICE, "TO DECLARE WHAT SHE KNOWS, WHO TOLD HER WHAT, AND TO SAY IF SHE WAS AT THE SCENE."

THE ARCHBISHOPRIC'S LEGAL AID OFFICE, A HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATION, HAS PROMISED TO CONDUCT AN INVESTIGATION JOINTLY WITH THE JESUITS.

THE ATTORNEY GENERAL SAID THAT "WE ARE INVESTIGATING ALL CLUES," WHEN ASKED BY REPORTERS IF HE WOULD INTERROGATE THE SOLDIERS WHO WERE PATROLLING THE UNIVERSITY AREA WHERE THE MURDERS TOOK PLACE ON 16 NOVEMBER.

MEANWHILE, JOSE MARIA TOJEIRA, JESUIT SUPERIOR IN CENTRAL AMERICA, SAID THAT THE MAIN WITNESS TO THE MURDERS IS "SAFE AND SOUND" ABROAD, POSSIBLY IN THE UNITED STATES.

ACCORDING TO TOJEIRA, THE WITNESS, WHO WAS INTERROGATED REPEATEDLY, WAS KEPT UNDER STRICT SECURITY. HE STRESSED THAT SHE LEFT FOR AN UNKNOWN DESTINATION AND THAT SHE "IS AT EASE BECAUSE SHE HAS TOLD THE TRUTH."

JESUIT SUPERIOR TOJEIRA AND ARTURO RIVERA Y DAMAS, ARCHBISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR, HAVE ASSERTED THAT THERE IS A STRONG BELIEF THAT THE MURDERERS OF THE JESUITS WERE EITHER MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES OR PERSONS CLOSELY LINKED TO THEM.

WHEN ASKED ABOUT THIS BELIEF, THE ATTORNEY GENERAL REPLIED, "I DO NOT HAVE THAT INFORMATION. HOWEVER, IT WOULD BE RASH TO SAY THAT THE ARMY DID IT."

DEV-MUC3-0866 (GTE)

SEOUL (ROK), 22 NOV 89 (HANGYORE SINMUN) -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] AT A TIME WHEN THE WORLD'S ATTENTION IS RIVETED ON THE DEMOCRATIZATION MOVEMENT IN EASTERN EUROPE, WE HEAR A GLOOMY NEWS REPORT THAT THE PROTRACTED CIVIL WAR BETWEEN EL SALVADOR'S GOVERNMENTAL TROOPS RECEIVING U.S. ASSISTANCE AND LEFTIST GUERRILLAS HAS RECENTLY ONCE AGAIN INTENSIFIED, AND HAS TAKEN MANY LIVES.

THE SOVIET UNION IS NOW PRODDING THE COUNTRIES IN EASTERN EUROPE, WHICH WERE ONCE KNOWN AS SOVIET SATELLITES, TO DEMOCRATIZE AND TO REFORM THEIR STATE SYSTEMS; WHY DOES THE UNITED STATES INCREASE ITS MILITARY AID TO EL SALVADOR AND CAUSE THE CIVIL WAR TO INTENSIFY?

LIKE MANY CENTRAL AND SOUTH AMERICAN COUNTRIES BEFORE THEY BECAME DEMOCRATIZED, THE POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR IS SUCH THAT IT IS PLAGUED BY AN EXTREME FORM OF THE GAP BETWEEN RICH AND POOR, BY MILITARY DICTATORSHIP, BY RIGHT-WING TERRORISM, AND BY ABUSE OF HUMAN RIGHTS TO THE POINT WHERE IT COULD BE ENGULFED BY REVOLUTION AT ANY TIME. HOW CAN A COUNTRY WHERE MORE THAN 2.5 MILLION OUT OF A POPULATION OF 5.4 MILLION ARE ON THE BORDER OF STARVATION, AND WHERE ROUGHLY 20 PERCENT OF THE POPULATION ENJOYS 66 PERCENT OF THE COUNTRY'S GROSS NATIONAL PRODUCT, BE IN PEACE?

AFTER A LARGE-SCALE PEASANT UPRISING IN 1930, THE LEFTIST FORCES IN THIS COUNTRY FORMED A UNIFIED GUERRILLA ORGANIZATION IN 1980 AND BEGAN THE ARMED STRUGGLE IN EARNEST.

THE OLIGARCHIC RULING CLASS, WHICH IS SAID TO CONSIST OF 15 TO 240 FAMILIES WITH HIGH INCOME, LAUNCHED A "CLEAN-UP OPERATION" AGAINST GUERRILLAS IN COLLUSION WITH THE MILITARY, AND OPENLY MASSACRED THE LEADERS OF WORKERS AND PEASANTS BY ORGANIZING AN EXTREME RIGHT-WING ASSASSINATION GROUP CALLED THE "DEATH SQUAD." THEY EVEN WENT SO FAR AS TO ASSASSINATE INTELLECTUALS AND CLERGYMEN WHO CHAMPIONED SOCIAL REFORM AND HUMAN RIGHTS.

FILMS SUCH AS "ROMERO" AND "SALVADOR" THAT HAVE BEEN SHOWN IN OUR COUNTRY IN RECENT MONTHS ARE CLEAR EVIDENCE OF THE BRUTALITY COMMITTED BY SUCH AN ASSASSINATION GROUP. THIS GROUP WAS UNQUESTIONABLY BEHIND THE RECENT ASSASSINATIONS IN WHICH 10 LABOR UNION LEADERS WERE MERCILESSLY MASSACRED AND ANOTHER 8, INCLUDING A JESUIT PRIEST, WERE BRUTALLY KILLED.

THE PROBLEM IS THAT THE UNITED STATES LURKS BEHIND THE MILITARY AND RIGHT-WING FORCES THAT ARE BENT ON SUPPRESSING THOSE WHO CALL FOR SOCIAL REFORM AND RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS, NOT STOPPING AT A "CLEANING UP" OF THE LEFTIST GUERRILLAS. WHILE SENDING A GROUP OF MILITARY ADVISERS TO EL SALVADOR TO HELP THE GOVERNMENT TROOPS MOP UP THE GUERRILLAS, THE UNITED STATES IS NOW ALSO SUPPLYING THE COUNTRY WITH WEAPONS, INCLUDING ASSAULT HELICOPTERS, WORTH U.S. $103 MILLION.

HOW LONG WILL THE UNITED STATES RETAIN ITS OLD POLICY OF IGNORING SOCIAL REFORM AND DEMOCRATIZATION IN A NEIGHBORING COUNTRY AND OF GIVING MILITARY AID TO ITS INCOMPETENT GOVERNMENT IN ORDER TO DEFEND ITS OWN INTERESTS? WITH OUR EYES ON THE DEMOCRATIZATION MOVEMENT IN EAST EUROPE, WE ARE COMPELLED TO THINK ONCE AGAIN OF THE DEMOCRATIZATION IN CENTRAL AND SOUTH AMERICA, AND OF THE OUTSIDE INTERVENTION THERE BLOCKING THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.

DRAWING A LESSON FROM THE DEFEAT IT SUFFERED IN VIETNAM AND IN IRAN, THE UNITED STATES SHOULD CEASE INTERFERING IN THE INTERNAL AFFAIRS OF OTHER COUNTRIES.

DEV-MUC3-0868 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 24 NOV 89 (DIARIO LATINO) -- [TEXT] "THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] USED TUPAC AMARU, VIETNAMESE, SANDINIST, AND OTHER GUERRILLA WARFARE OFFENSIVE TACTICS IN ITS OFFENSIVE," [COLONEL RENE EMILIO] PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINTS CHIEFS OF STAFF OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, STATED 23 NOVEMBER. HE REPORTED THAT THE FMLN OFFENSIVE RESULTED IN 1,484 GUERRILLAS AND 284 SOLDIERS KILLED. THE OFFICER SAID THAT GUERRILLAS WERE ENGAGED IN A TACTICAL-TYPE DIALOGUE BY ATTENDING THE MEETINGS WITH THE GOVERNMENT WHILE PREPARING FOR THE OFFENSIVE. AMONG THE WEAPONS SEIZED, WE FOUND RUSTED WEAPONS AND AMMUNITION, INDICATING THEY HAD BEEN BURIED FOR A LONG TIME. WE ALSO FOUND DOCUMENTS AND MEDICINES WITH OLDT EXPIRATION DATES."

HE SAID THAT THE ARMED FORCES LEARNED ON 9 NOVEMBER ABOUT THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE FMLN ON 11 NOVEMBER, BUT IT WAS TOO LATE TO ACT. THAT IS WHY THE ARMED FORCES ACTED WITH CAUTION WHEN IT BEGAN, BECAUSE THE FMLN WANTED A FAR-REACHING REACTION, SOMETHING WHICH WOULD HAVE ENTAILED HUGE DAMAGE TO CIVILIANS, AND SO THE GUERRILLAS' INTENTIONS FAILED.

THE TUPAC AMARU TACTIC EMPLOYED CONSISTED IN DIGGING LARGE DITCHES, AND SO THE GUERRILLAS FORCED THE PEOPLE TO DIG THEM, COL PONCE SAID.

REGARDING THE BOMBINGS HEARD EAST OF THE CAPITAL DURING THE NEWS CONFERENCE, COL PONCE SAID IT WAS A OPERATION TO PURSUE "A GROUP OF TERRORISTS WHO HAD BEEN LOCATED IN THE LOS CASTILLOS, SAN FRANCISCO, AND EL PROGRESO CANTONS. HOWEVER, ONLY THE FIRST CANTON WAS SHELLED BECAUSE IT HAD BEEN EVACUATED, WHICH WAS NOT THE CASE IN THE OTHER TWO CANTONS.

DEV-MUC3-0869 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 25 NOV 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES TODAY REPORTED THAT A PLANE LOADED WITH WEAPONS FOR GUERRILLAS COMING FROM NICARAGUA CRASHED AT DAWN TODAY IN A TOWN OF USULUTAN DEPARMENT, KILLING THREE CREWMEN WHILE A FOURTH COMMITTED "SUICIDE."

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) POINTED OUT THAT THE PLANE CRASHED AT 0025 LOCAL TIME (0625 GMT) IN A TOWN IN EL TRANSITO, EASTERN USULUTAN DEPARTMENT. ACCORDING TO COPREFA, THREE CREWMEN DIED DURING THE ACCIDENT AND A FOURTH SURVIVED, BUT COMMITTED SUICIDE AFTERWARD. THE ARMED FORCES DID NOT IDENTIFY THE CREWMEN, STATING ONLY THAT THEY WERE WEARING CAMOUFLAGE UNIFORMS.

THE MILITARY SOURCE REPORTED THAT THE PLANE, A WHITE AND BLUE, RED-STRIPED TWO-MOTOR "CESSNA" BELONGS TO A COMPANY CALLED "SETA" HEADQUARTERED IN NICARAGUA.

THE COPREFA REPORT, WHICH IS BASED ON THE FLIGHT SCHEDULE, STATES THAT THE PLANE LEFT MANAGUA (NICARAGUA) AND WAS TO HAVE LANDED IN AMATECAMPO, LA PAZ DEPARTMENT, BUT SUFFERED AN ACCIDENT IN "PIEDRA PACHA" NEAR EL TRANSITO.

COPREFA REPORTS THAT THE PLANE WAS CARRYING 24 "SAM-7" SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILES, A "REDEYE" MISSILE, A 75- MM ANTITANK GUN, AND 21 ROUNDS OF AMMUNITION FOR NONRECOILLESS 75- MM CANNON.

SALVADORAN ARMY TROOPS SURROUNDED THE AREA OF THE ACCIDENT AND SEIZED THE WEAPONS, THE SOURCE REPORTED.

ON VARIOUS OCCASIONS THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES HAVE ACCUSED THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT OF HELPING THE FARABUNNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) LOGISTICALLY AND WITH WEAPONS.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES, THE OFFENSIVE THAT THE FMLN BEGAN ON 11 NOVEMBER, WHICH HAS YIELDED 2,000 DEAD AND THOUSANDS OF WOUNDED, WAS SUPPORTED BY NICARAGUA AND CUBA, WHICH SUPPLIED MOST OF THE WEAPONS.

DEV-MUC3-0870 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 25 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [BULLETIN] [ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE] [TEXT] A CESSNA PLANE TRANSPORTING WEAPONS FROM MANAGUA CRASHED TODAY AT 0525 ON A SMALL LANDING STRIP IN PIEDRA PACHA CANTON, EL TRANSITO, 6 KM EAST OF USULUTAN. THE PLANE WAS CARRYING THE FOLLOWING WEAPONS FOR THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT TERRORISTS: 24 SAM-7, SOVIET-MADE SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILES; 21 GRENADES FOR 75-MM CANNONS; A 75-MM ANTI-TANK CANNON; A U.S.-MADE SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILE KNOWN AS THE RED-EYE; AND OTHER EQUIPMENT.

THE PLANE, A WHITE AND BLUE TWIN-ENGINE CRAFT WITH RED STRIPES, WAS BEING FLOWN BY SANDINISTS. FOUR PERSONS, DRESSED IN CAMOUFLAGE WEAR, WERE KILLED AT THE SITE OF THE ACCIDENT. SOME DOCUMENTS THAT ARE BEING ANALYZED BY MILITARY INTELLIGENCE WERE ALSO FOUND AT THE SCENE. AMONG THE DOCUMENTS IS THE FLIGHT PLAN THAT SHOWS THAT THE PLANE DEPARTED FROM MANAGUA, NICARAGUA, AND ITS DESTINATION WAS EL SALVADOR. THIS PLANE WAS TO HAVE LANDED AT THE AMATICAMPO LANDING STRIP, ALONG THE LA PAZ DEPARTMENT COASTLINE.

THE INFORMATION ADDS THAT THE PLANE BELONGED TO ZETA COMPANY -- OFFICES LOCATED ACROSS FROM THE CESAR AUGUSTO SANDINO AIRPORT IN MANAGUA -- AND THAT IT DEPARTED EARLY THIS MORNING FROM MANAGUA. THE AUTHORITIES ARE INVESTIGATING MORE DETAILS REGARDING THIS INCIDENT, WHICH PROVES NICARAGUA'S INTERFERENCE IN EL SALVADOR'S DOMESTIC AFFAIRS.

DEV-MUC3-0871 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 26 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN] [TEXT] IN VIEW OF THE INTENSIFICATION OF THE COUNTRY'S ARMED CONFLICT AND THE ARMED FORCES' ATTITUDE, THE FMLN REPORTS THE FOLLOWING:

1. THAT THE GOVERNMENT, FAR FROM SUSPENDING, HAS INTENSIFIED BOMBINGS AND ARTILLERY ATTACKS. IT IS NOW EVEN USING 105-MM OBUS HOWITZERS IN DENSELY POPULATED AREAS. WE ARE INFORMING THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY THAT SUCH BOMBINGS HAVE YIELDED THOUSANDS OF REFUGEES AND DESTROYED THOUSANDS OF HOMES BELONGING TO HUMBLE FAMILIES IN SAN SALVADOR, SAN MIGUEL, USULUTAN, AND ZACATECOLUCA. IN REJECTING A CEASE-FIRE, THE GOVERNMENT HAS TURNED ITS BACK ON THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY.

2. THAT IN VIEW OF THE RUMORS THAT THE FMLN IS PLANNING TO ATTACK U.S. CITIZENS [7-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] TO NOT ATTACK U.S. PERSONNEL AND INSTALLATIONS. THAT POLICY WAS EVIDENT DURING THE SHERATON HOTEL INCIDENT IN WHICH, ALTHOUGH OUR FORCES ENJOYED AN ADVANTAGE OVER THE GREEN BERETS TRAPPED IN THAT HOTEL, AND DESPITE THE PREVAILING TENSION, THEY RIGOROUSLY ADHERED TO THAT POLICY WITH DISCIPLINE.

3. THE FMLN DOES NOT ADVOCATE CAPTURING PRISONERS OR CARRYING OUT INDISCRIMINATE ARMED ACTIONS.

4. WE ALSO ALERT THE ENTIRE NATION AND INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY ABOUT THE GENERALIZED REPRESSION BEING UNLEASHED BY THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] GOVERNMENT. THAT PARTY, BY TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THE STATE OF SIEGE AND THE MARTIAL LAW, HAS HASTILY APPROVED THE ANTITERRORIST LAW AS AN INSTRUMENT TO INSTITUTIONALIZE TERROR. THIS LAW SEEKS TO ELIMINATE THE POLITICAL OPPORTUNITIES THAT OUR PEOPLE HAVE ACHIEVED, ALL FORMS OF OPPOSITION, AND TO CONSOLIDATE A FASCIST REGIME. THIS HAS BEEN THE HISTORIC PROJECT OF ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON AND LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO THE 1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] WHO NOW CONTROLS THE ENTIRE MILITARY LEADERSHIP.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

COMMANDERS FRANCISCO JOVEL, SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, JORGE SHAFIK HANDAL, EDUARDO SANCHO, AND JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS.

DEV-MUC3-0872 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 26 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THIS AIRCRAFT, I REPEAT, WAS CARRYING VERY SOPHISTICATED ARMAMENTS. IT CARRIED 24 SOVIET-MADE SURFACE-TO-AIR-MISSILES, ONE 75-MM RECOILLESS CANNON, GRENADES FOR THAT CANNON, AND IT ALSO HAD DOCUMENTS AND MANUALS EXPLAINING ITS USAGE.

WE CAN NO LONGER CONTINUE DOING NOTHING IN VIEW OF THIS GENOCIDAL, INTERVENTIONIST ACTION, AND MORE THAN ANYTHING, A TRAITOROUS ACTION BY DANIEL ORTEGA. THAT IS WHY WE RESOLVED ON 25 NOVEMBER, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, TO MAKE THE PROPER CHARGES AGAINST ORTEGA AND HIS GOVERNMENT BEFORE THE UN SECURITY COUNCIL AND THE OAS SECURITY COUNCIL.

SECOND, WE WILL SUSPEND RELATIONS, BE THEY DIPLOMATIC, COMMERCIAL, OR OF ANY SORT WITH NICARAGUA. WE WILL WITHDRAW OUR MISSION FROM NICARAGUA.

THIRD, AT THE NEXT PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT, EL SALVADOR WILL NOT GO TO NICARAGUA. RIGHT NOW, IT WILL ASK THE OTHER THREE DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTS OF THE AREA TO TRANSFER THE SITE OF THAT MEETING TO ANOTHER FRATERNAL CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRY. WE WILL DEMAND THERE, BEFORE THE CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES THAT THEY TRULY HONOR THE ESQUIPULAS PACT AND CONDEMN DANIEL ORTEGA FOR SUPPORTING THE FMLN

WE CAN APPRECIATE, VERY FRANKLY, WHAT THE FMLN IS. THEY ARE NOTHING MORE THAN THE PUPPETS OF THE COMMUNIST AGGRESSION. MR CASTRO AND MR ORTEGA ARE RESISTING ALL OF THE CHANGES THAT ARE TAKING PLACE IN THE SOVIET UNION AND IN ALL OF THE COUNTRIES BEHIND THE IRON CURTAIN WHICH ARE ATTEMPTING TO DEMOCRATIZE THEMSELVES AND GIVE THEIR PEOPLE LIBERTY. THEY ARE THE ONLY TWO WHO SEEK TO CONTINUE TO REMAIN IN POWER THROUGH THE RIFLE AND BY WAR.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WE CANNOT PERMIT OUR COUNTRY, OUR SMALL EL SALVADOR, OR OUR NOBLE SALVADORAN PEOPLE TO BE THE VICTIMS OF THAT COMMUNIST AGGRESSION WHICH DANIEL ORTEGA AND FIDEL CASTRO SEEK TO LAUNCH.

IN THAT SENSE, SALVADORAN PEOPLE, IN VIEW OF THIS NEW SITUATION, WE WANT YOU TO REFLECT ON THAT ARTIFICIAL CEASE-FIRE WHICH THE FMLN LAUNCHED A FEW DAYS AGO. WHAT IS THE FMLN UP TO WITH THAT CEASE-FIRE? IT MADE THAT PROPOSAL AFTER IT WAS REMOVED FROM THE CITY THAT IT HAD ATTACKED. THE PEOPLE WERE RESUMING THEIR NORMAL ACTIVITIES AND EVERYTHING WAS UNDER THE CONTROL OF THE ARMED FORCES IN THOSE AREAS. WHY DID THEY CALL FOR A CEASE-FIRE WHEN THEY HAD ALREADY BEEN DEFEATED IN THE OFFENSIVE BY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WHO HAD REPUDIATED THEIR TERRORIST ACTIONS? THEY HAD NO REAL OBJECTIVE AHEAD, OTHER THAN TO CONTINUE TO DESTROY, TO ASSASSINATE, AND TO CONTINUE TO GENERATE TERRORIST ACTIONS HERE IN OUR COUNTRY.

THEREFORE, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT CANNOT PERMIT ITSELF TO FALL INTO ANOTHER TRAP OF THE FMLN. IF THEY WENT TO MEXICO AND COSTA RICA WITH A SINCERE DESIRE FOR PEACE, AS THEY TRIED TO MAKE US BELIEVE, WE REALIZE TODAY THAT THOSE ACTIONS WERE JUST ANOTHER FARCE. THIS AGGRESSION WAS NOT PLANNED IN 2 OR 3 DAYS. THIS AGGRESSION HAD BEEN PLANNED SEVERAL MONTHS BACK. KNOWING THAT THEY WERE GOING TO ATTACK THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THEY HAD THE GALL TO ATTEND AND MAKE THE ENTIRE WORLD BELIEVE THAT THEY REALLY WANTED PEACE. THEREFORE, WE CANNOT, I REPEAT SALVADORAN PEOPLE, FALL INTO ANOTHER TRAP OF THE FMLN. THEY HAVE NO RIGHT TO DEMAND TERRITORIAL RIGHTS IN OUR COUNTRY WHEN THEY ARE A BAND OF TERRORISTS AND ARE PUPPETS OF ORTEGA AND CASTRO. LET US SEE IF THE PEOPLE WHO RECEIVE SUPPORT, AS THEY ARE, WILL OWE ORTEGA AND CASTRO FAVORS. IF THEY SUCCEED, THEY WILL OWE LOYALTY NOT TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, BUT TO COMMUNIST DICTATORS SUCH AS DANIEL ORTEGA AND FIDEL CASTRO. THAT IS WHY THE GOVERNMENT HAS ESTABLSIHED A CLEAR POSITION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0874 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 26 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] WE WANT PEACE BADLY AND ARE CONVINCED THAT YOU SALVADORANS ALSO WANT PEACE AND VIEW IT AS A MAJOR GOAL TO BE ACHIEVED. WE ALSO MUST BE COURAGEOUS AND ENDURE THE FMLN AGGRESSION AS WE, PARTICULARLY, YOU HAVE IN THE PAST DAYS.

WE ARE WILLING TO SOLVE THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT THROUGH A DIALOGUE PROCESS. HOWEVER, WE CAN NO LONGER TRUST LIARS AND CYNICS WHO HAVE TAKEN ADVANTAGE OF THE PEOPLE'S DESIRE FOR PEACE AND OPPORTUNITIES GIVEN TO THEM IN AN ATTEMPT TO SIMPLY GAIN GROUND AND TIME TO REARM THEMSELVES TO ATTACK, KILL, AND DESTROY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

THIS IS WHY TODAY WE DEMAND THAT THE FMLN END ALL THEIR HOSTILITIES. THE VERIFICATION TEAM ONUCA [UNITED NATIONS OBSERVER GROUP IN CENTRAL AMERICA] MAY COME HERE IF THEY WANT TO, TO ENSURE THAT THE FMLN ENDS THEIR HOSTILITES AND FINDS A WAY TO INCORPORATE ITSELF TO THE SALVADORAN POLITICAL PROCESS. HOWEVER, WE WILL NEVER AGAIN ALLOW OURSELVES TO FALL INTO THE TRAP SET UP BY FMLN CYNICS WHO HAVE DECEIVED THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, BECAUSE THEY ARE NOT LOOKING AFTER YOUR INTERESTS, BUT THOSE OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNISM THAT ORTEGA AND FIDEL CASTRO ARE SENDING OUR WAY.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: WE MUST ASK YOU TO TRUST YOUR GOVERNMENT AND ARMED FORCES. IT MATTERS NOT WHAT DANIEL ORTEGA PLANS TO DO OR WHAT WEAPONS HE SENDS THEM BECAUSE THE ARMED FORCES WILL BE READY TO REPEL ANY ATTACK OR ANY IRRATIONAL ACTION THAT THE FMLN MIGHT LAUNCH.

YOU MUST REST ASSURED AND REALIZE THAT WE ARE WAGING A STRUGGLE FOR THE SAKE OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE; TO DEFEND OUR COUNTRY FROM AGGRESSIONS, WHICH REGARDLESS OF THEIR ORIGIN, SHOULD NOT HINDER THE FREEDOM OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

WE MUST BE CONFIDENT THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ARE A PROFESSIONAL ARMED FORCES THAT HAVE SUCCESSFULLY RESISTED, REPELLED, AND REMOVED THIS AGGRESSION THROUGH A PROFESSIONALISM THAT MUST STAND AS AN EXAMPLE ALL OVER THE WORLD TODAY.

ALTHOUGH THE FMLN HAS HIDDEN BEHIND YOU, AS COWARDS DO, THE ARMED FORCES HAVE GRADUALLY AND CAREFULLY DEALT A BLOW TO THEM WHILE SAFEGUARDING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S INTERESTS. THE ONLY DESTRUCTORS HERE ARE THE FMLN FOLLOWERS; THE ONLY TERRORISTS HERE ARE FMLN FOLLOWERS. WE CANNOT ALLOW THIS TO CONTINUE IN OUR COUNTRY.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: I DO NOT WANT TO ALARM YOU. I WANT US TO GRADUALLY UNDERSTAND, AS EACH PIECE OF THIS PUZZLE FALLS INTO ITS PLACE, WHAT THE FMLN REALLY IS: A PUPPET OF INTERNATIONAL COMMUNISM THAT IS ONLY SEEKING TO SUBJUGATE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, TAKE AWAY THEIR FREEDOMS, AND SINK THEM INTO DESTITUTION, AS ORTEGA HAS DONE TO THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE.

OUR NICARAGUAN POLICY HAS AT NO TIME BEEN AGAINST THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE; OUR POLICY IS ONLY AGAINST THAT ANTIDEMOCRATIC DICTATOR CALLED ORTEGA WHO WANTS TO SPREAD DESTRUCTION AND DEATH TO OTHER COUNTRIES TO SATISFY HIS OWN GOALS OF CONSOLIDATING A TOTALITARIAN GOVERNMENT IN NICARAGUA.

WE MUST BE ALERT TO ALL THE UPCOMING INFORMATION REGARDING THE NORMALIZATION OF THE SITUATION IN OUR COUNTRY AND REST ASSURED THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT WILL ALSO HELP THE PEOPLE, WHO HAVE IN ONE WAY OR ANOTHER SUFFERED FROM THE FMLN AGGRESSION, WITH MEDICINE, FOOD, AND ESPECIALLY, THIS IS NEARLY FINALIZED, AID TO RECONSTRUCT THOSE HOMES THAT WERE DAMAGED BY THIS SAVAGE AND IRRATIONAL FMLN ACTION.

SALVADORAN PEOPLE: THANK YOU VERY MUCH; GOD BLESS YOU ALL.

DEV-MUC3-0876 (GTE)

LIMA, 24 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] A 2-MONTH-OLD LABOR CONFLICT INVOLVING [WORDS INDISTINCT] WORKERS, WHICH IN THE PAST FEW DAYS HAS CAUSED STREET VIOLENCE IN LIMA, HAS BECOME ONE OF THE MAIN SOURCES OF CONCERN FOR THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT.

THE STRIKE, WHICH WAS DECREED BY THE INTERSECTORIAL CONFEDERATION OF PUBLIC EMPLOYEES (CITE), IS BEING OBSERVED BY 300,000 PUBLIC SERVANTS, WHO MAKE UP 50 PERCENT OF CITE MEMBERS. THE STRIKERS DEMAND SALARY IMPROVEMENTS, THE REINSTATEMENT OF 250 DISMISSED WORKERS, AND THE OFFICIAL RECOGNITION OF THE CITE.

RULING AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE (APRA) SECRETARY GENERAL LUIZ ALVA CASTRO, WHO IS ALSO THE APRA PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, REPORTED THAT TODAY HE MET WITH PRIME MINISTER GUILLERMO LARCO COX IN SEARCH FOR A SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEM.

ALVA SAID THAT "THERE IS GOOD WILL" TO FIND A SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT, WHICH HAS AFFECTED LARGE SECTORS OF THE POPULATION, WHO MAKE USE OF HEALTH, EDUCATION, JUSTICE, TRANSPORTATION, AND COMMUNICATION SERVICES. THE STRIKE HAS ALSO AFFECTED THE STATE, WHICH HAS FAILED TO COLLECT 70 PERCENT OF TAXES BECAUSE OF THE STRIKE BY THE TAX COLLECTORS.

ALVA CASTRO SAID THAT THE PRIME MINISTER TOLD HIM THAT THERE WILL BE NO PROBLEM IN RECOGNIZING THE CITE, PROVIDED THAT THIS ORGANIZATION MEETS THE APPROPRIATE LEGAL REQUIREMENTS.

THERE WERE INCIDENTS IN LIMA ON 23 NOVEMBER, WHEN GROUPS OF CITE MEMBERS DEMONSTRATED IN DOWNTOWN LIMA AND WERE REPRESSED BY THE POLICE. DURING THE INCIDENTS, BOMBS WERE DETONATED, TIRES WERE BURNED, AND THE POLICE SHOT IN THE AIR. AT LEAST [9] PERSONS DIED DURING THE INCIDENTS LAST WEEK.

A UNION SOURCE TODAY SAID THAT A 15-DAY STRIKE BY 3,500 WORKERS OF THE STATE-RUN MINERO PERU COMPANY HAS CAUSED DAILY LOSSES OF $800,000.

ACCORDING TO THE LABOR MINISTRY, THE STRIKES HAVE COST THE PRIVATE SECTOR 13 MILLION HOURS OF LABOR,

IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT THE MINING SECTOR LOST $80 MILLION DURING 18 DAYS OF STRIKE IN AUGUST AND SEPTEMBER, WHILE THE FISHING SECTOR HAS LOST $150 MILLION BECAUSE OF A STRIKE THAT THE WORKERS OF THE SECTOR BEGAN 55 DAYS AGO.

DEV-MUC3-0877 (GTE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] I AM GOING TO TELL YOU SOMETHING, AND I AM GOING TO SPEAK TO YOU FROM THE HEART. ABOUT 15 DAYS AGO, I HEARD THE NEWS THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT, THE SALVADORAN ARMY, WAS BOMBING NEIGHBORHOODS AND CITIES IN EL SALVADOR, THAT IT WAS MURDERING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. I LATER HEARD THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMY HAD MURDERED SIX JESUIT PRIESTS, AMONG THEM A PRIEST WHO HAD BEEN DEAN OF THE CATHOLIC UNIVERSITY HERE IN NICARAGUA. IT WAS THEN THAT I BEGAN TO THINK AND ASKED MYSELF: HOW CAN I WELCOME THE PRESIDENT OF EL SALVADOR HERE IN NICARAGUA WHEN THE CENTRAL AMERICAN SUMMIT IS HELD? WHAT A PROBLEM. A REAL PROBLEM. HOW COULD I WELCOME IN NICARAGUA THE REPRESENTATIVE OF A GOVERNMENT THAT KILLS PRIESTS AND BISHOPS, THAT KILLED MONSIGNOR ROMERO; A GOVERNMENT THAT KILLS CLERGYMEN, THAT HAS KILLED NUNS AND MEMBERS OF OTHER CHURCHES, CATHOLICS AND EVANGELISTS; A GOVERNMENT THAT KILLS WORKERS, PEASANTS, LABORERS, AND LEADERS OF POLITICAL PARTIES, THAT HAS KILLED MORE THAN 600 CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY LEADERS. THEY WERE KILLED BY ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLIC ALLIANCE], THE RULING PARTY IN EL SALVADOR, AND THE SALVADORAN ARMY, WHICH IS THE SAME THING. I KEPT ASKING MYSELF: HOW CAN I WELCOME THEM IN NICARAGUA? IT WOULD BE LIKE WELCOMING SOMOZA. ALL I COULD COME UP WITH WAS TO FIND AN EXCUSE NOT TO HOLD THE MEETING. IT WOULD HAVE BEEN TERRIBLE FOR THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE TO HAVE TO WELCOME AND HAVE AS A GUEST THE REPRESENTATIVE OF A GOVERNMENT THAT KILLS PRIESTS, NUNS, WORKERS, LABORERS, PEASANTS, INTELLECTUALS, PROFESSIONALS, AND WORKERS. THEREFORE, THIS NEWS MADE ME HAPPY. IT MADE ME HAPPY BECAUSE WE HAVE AVOIDED THE PROBLEM OF HAVING TO WELCOME, IN NICARAGUA, THE PRESIDENT OF THAT GOVERNMENT OF INTERNATIONAL KILLERS AND COMMON CRIMINALS. [APPLAUSE]

THE TRUTH IS THAT WE SHOULD FEEL PROUD. AS A NICARAGUAN I FEEL PROUD THAT THAT MURDEROUS GOVERNMENT HAS BROKEN RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA. THAT IS SOMETHING TO BE PROUD OF, BECAUSE IT MEANS THAT THEY KNOW PERFECTLY WELL THAT WE ARE ON THE SIDE OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, ON THE SIDE OF THE SALVADORAN PEASANT, ON THE SIDE OF THE SALVADORAN WORKER, ON THE SIDE OF THE SALVADORAN CHURCH AND PRIESTS, THAT WE ARE ON THE SIDE OF PEACE, JUSTICE, AND DEMOCRACY IN EL SALVADOR, AND THAT WE OPPOSE TYRANNY IN EL SALVADOR.

I CAN SEE THAT THE TIME HAS COME FOR ME TO SPEAK CLEARLY TO YOU. I BELIEVE THAT IT IS NECESSARY TO SPEAK CLEARLY BECAUSE DIPLOMATIC JARGON CAN SOMETIMES CONFUSE THINGS. IT IS TIME THAT WE SPEAK CLEARLY. THE LEAST THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT CAN DO IN RESPONSE TO THE ATTITUDE ASSUMED BY THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS TO ASK AND DEMAND OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY AND THE WORLD THAT IT BREAK RELATIONS WITH THAT MURDEROUS AND CRIMINAL GOVERNMENT UNTIL THOSE WHO KILLED THE PRIESTS HAVE BEEN PUNISHED, UNTIL THOSE WHO ARE KILLING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE HAVE BEEN PUNISHED. [APPLAUSE] THAT IS WHAT WE ARE GOING TO DEMAND. THAT IS GOING TO BE OUR ANSWER.

THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY IS UNEASY BECAUSE OF WHAT IS HAPPENING IN EL SALVADOR. CRISTIANI IS NO TAME DOVE. HE HAS BECOME AN ACCOMPLICE AND INSTRUMENT OF THIS POLICY OF DEATH IMPLEMENTED BY THE ARMY, BY MEN LIKE [COLONEL RENE EMILIO] PONCE AND [GENERAL JUAN RAFAEL] BUSTILLO. THEY ARE MURDEROUS GUARDSMEN JUST LIKE THOSE YOU KNEW, THE SOMOZIST GUARDSMEN. BUSTILLO, PONCE, AND A FEW OTHERS ARE JUST LIKE THAT. HOWEVER, NOT ALL OF THEM ARE LIKE THAT. THERE ARE SOME HONEST SOLDIERS IN EL SALVADOR, SOLDIERS WITH HONEST POSITIONS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0878 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 26 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] A FEW DAYS AFTER THE START OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] OFFENSIVE, THE RESULTS ARE COMPLETELY POSITIVE. FIRST OF ALL, WE ARE SEEING THE TOTAL POLITICAL DEFEAT OF THE DEMOCRACY AND COUNTERINSURGENCY PLAN BECAUSE THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN UNMASKED AS A FASCIST DICTATORSHIP.

THE U.S. COUNTERINSURGENCY MODEL TRIED TO LEGITIMIZE, THROUGH AN ELECTORAL PROCESS, A QUOTE, DEMOCRATIC, UNQUOTE, GOVERNMENT WHICH WOULD LEAVE THE GROWING POPULAR INSURGENCY IN EL SALVADOR WITH NO REASON TO EXIST. THAT MODEL HAS OVERWHELMINGLY FAILED BECAUSE, INSTEAD OF AN EVEN TIMIDLY DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT, WHAT HAS BEEN INSTALLED IS A REGIME THAT DOES NOT EVEN TOLERATE THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY, WHICH IT VIEWS AS A GREAT TRAITOR TO THE FATHERLAND. A REGIME HAS BEEN ESTABLISHED WHICH DOES NOT PERMIT THE MOST MINIMAL OPPORTUNITIES FOR THE FREE EXPRESSION OF THOUGHT. IT DOES NOT TOLERATE THE EXISTENCE OF AN OBJECTIVE AND INDEPENDENT NEWSCAST, SUCH AS THAT OF TELEVISION CANAL DOCE. IT IS A REGIME WHICH DEMANDS THAT THE HIGHEST LEADERS OF THE CHURCH LEAVE THE COUNTRY BECAUSE IT DOES NOT GUARANTEE THEIR SECURITY. IT IS A REGIME THAT ISSUES TOTALLY UNDEMOCRATIC LAWS AND CLOSES ALL POLITICAL OPPORTUNITIES. IN SHORT, IT IS A REGIME IN A STATE OF EMERGENCY. IT IS A FASCIST REGIME WITH ALL ITS COMPONENTS. THAT IS THE FINAL RESULT OF THE U.S. EFFORTS TO ESTABLISH A COUNTERINSURGENT DEMOCRATIC REGIME IN EL SALVADOR. THE LITTLE LEGITIMACY THAT THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AT ONE POINT ENJOYED WAS DESTROYED WHEN IT HAD TO COVER UP AND PERMIT THE ASSASSINATION OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS TO GO UNPUNISHED, AND WHEN IT INDISCRIMINATELY BOMBED THE MORE DENSELY POPULATED AREAS OF THE COUNTRY.

A FEW DAYS OF THE OFFENSIVE HAVE BEEN ENOUGH TO TEAR DOWN THE FOUNDATIONS OF THE ERRONEOUS U.S. POLICY IN OUR COUNTRY. AND THE VALIDITY OF THAT POLICY HAS BEGUN TO BE SERIOUSLY QUESTIONED IN THE UNITED STATES.

A SECOND GREAT ACHIEVEMENT OF THESE FIRST WEEKS OF THE OFFENSIVE HAS BEEN A RADICAL CHANGE IN THE THEATERS OF OPERATION. WE HAVE PLACED THE WAR IN ITS FINAL PHASE, IN ITS PHASE OF STRATEGIC DEFINITION. THERE HAS BEEN AN ABRUPT CHANGE IN WHAT HAD APPEARED TO BE AN ENDLESS WAR AND AN UNBREAKABLE BALANCE OF FORCES. THE TRANSFER OF THE THEATERS OF OPERATION TO THE CITIES HAS RESULTED IN A STRATEGIC SIEGE OF THE CITIES, WHICH ARE THE WEAK SPOTS OF THE POLITICAL, ECONOMIC, AND SOCIAL POWER. IN TURN, AS WE HAVE PREVIOUSLY POINTED OUT, THIS HAS BROUGHT ABOUT AN ACCELERATED POLITICAL BREAKDOWN OF THE REGIME. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0879 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE ENEMY IS LEFT LIKE THAT, HANGING FROM A THREAD -- A STRATEGIC THREAD WHICH CAN BREAK AT ANY MOMENT AND RESULT IN A MILITARY SETBACK FOR THE ARMY. THE PHENOMENON WHICH ENSUED AFTER THE MASSES JOINED THE OFFENSIVE IN ITS EARLY STAGES FORCED THE ENEMY TO INDISCRIMINATELY USE THE AIR FORCE TO PREVENT A GENERAL UPRISING AND TO CURTAIL THE INSURRECTION. NEVERTHELESS, THE EFFORT EXERTED TO LAUNCH A NATIONWIDE OFFENSIVE HAS BEEN BASED ON A LARGE-SCALE PEASANT AND SUBURBAN INSURRECTION PROCESS. OUR RANKS WERE CONSIDERABLY INCREASED TO RENDER THE OFFENSIVE EFFECTIVE, AND THIS WAS POSSIBLE THANKS TO THE PEOPLE'S GREAT INTEREST IN FIGHTING IN THE CITIES AND SPEEDING UP THE OUTCOME OF THE WAR. THE PEOPLE ALSO JOINED OUR RANKS DURING THE FIGHTING WHICH OCCURRED IN THE CITIES.

FURTHERMORE, THE GERM OF A NEW SOCIAL EXPLOSION HAS BEEN CREATED BY THE GOVERNMENT ITSELF, WITH ITS INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS AND REPRESSION. EVEN THOUGH SOME PEOPLE MAY BLAME THE FMLN FOR THE ARMY'S BRUTAL REACTION, FEW CAN FEEL ANY SYMPATHY FOR THOSE WHO HAVE BOMBED THEM. THIS HAS CREATED A SOCIAL SITUATION WHICH GUARANTEES THE CONTINUITY OF THE FMLN'S OFFENSIVE UNTIL VICTORY IS ACHIEVED. ALL THE PEOPLE DISPLACED BY THE BOMBINGS ARE DISSATISFIED PEOPLE WHO WILL JOIN THE STRUGGLE SOONER OR LATER.

WE REMEMBER THE PHENOMENON OF THE DISPLACED PEOPLE AND REFUGEES CAUSED BY THE BOMBINGS IN THE SALVADORAN COUNTRYSIDE. THE BRUTAL ATTITUDE OF THE ARMY AND AIR FORCE HAS LEGITIMIZED THE ARMED STRUGGLE. THE OTHER PARTY, MEANING THE ENEMY, HAD TO GRAB ALL THE RESOURCES OF A CONVENTIONAL WAR: AIRPLANES, HELICOPTERS, AND HEAVY ARTILLERY. THIS LEGITIMIZES THE PEOPLE'S ARMED STRUGGLE AND SELF-DEFENSE.

A THIRD GREAT ACHIEVEMENT OF THE NATIONAL AND STRATEGIC EFFORT EXERTED AGAINST FASCISM HAS BEEN THE LIBERATION OF LARGE ZONES OF THE NATIONAL TERRITORY. A NEW, EMERGING POWER NOW CONTROLS EIGHT DEPARTMENTS OF THE COUNTRY. THE ARMY IS SPREAD THIN AND IT HAD TO ABANDON THE ZONES WHERE IT CANNOT KEEP ITS MEN -- COMPROMISED AS IT IS IN THE STRATEGIC DEFENSE OF THE CITIES. THIS PUTS THE ARMY THROUGHOUT THE NATIONAL TERRITORY IN A SITUATION RESEMBLING A CLOTH WITH MANY HOLES, STRETCHED TO THE LIMIT AND THREATENING TO RIP AT ANY POINT. THE TEAR CAN OCCUR WHEN LEAST EXPECTED. LARGE GROUPS OF PEOPLE ARE NOW IN THOSE LIBERATED TERRITORIES, ENGAGED IN A RECONSTRUCTION EFFORT AND ORGANIZING A REARGUARD FOR THE MARCH ON THE CITIES.

THERE IS A FOURTH ELEMENT TO CONSIDER: ONE OF THE FIRST AND MOST IMPORTANT ACHIEVEMENTS IS THE FACT THAT THERE IS NOW A BETTER BALANCE FOR NEGOTIATIONS. ALL OF THE GOVERNMENT'S DEMANDS AND PROPOSALS AT THE NEGOTIATION TABLE ARE COMPLETELY NULL AND VOID. THE PRETENSE OF DEMANDING THE FMLN'S SURRENDER IS UNTIMELY GIVEN SUCH A SHOW OF STRENGTH. NO ONE IN THE WORLD WOULD NOW BE WILLING TO BET ON THAT POSITION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0880 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THERE IS NO LONGER ROOM FOR THE IDEA OF DIALOGUE WITHOUT NEGOTIATION. NOW WE MUST NEGOTIATE IN EARNEST. THAT DEMAND HAS BEEN MADE BY SEVERAL GOVERNMENTS AND INTERNATIONAL FORUMS, AND EVEN BY SOME INFLUENTIAL SECTORS IN THE UNITED STATES. YET CRISTIANI HAS OPPOSED THIS UNIVERSAL CURRENT. CRISTIANI'S TACTICAL, PROPAGANDISTIC, AND DELAYING MOVES AROUND THE NEGOTIATIONS TABLE WILL NO LONGER HAVE A CHANCE TO SUCCEED. ON THE OTHER HAND, IT WILL NOW BE AN INDISPENSABLE CONDITION THAT DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION BE EXPANDED AND THAT THE REAL DECISIONMAKERS BE THE ONES WHO SIT AT THE NEGOTIATING TABLE.

FINALLY, FOLLOWING THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE FMLN, THE ANALYSTS, ESPECIALLY IN THE UNITED STATES, HAVE ADMITTED THAT THERE IS A NEED TO CARRY OUT AN IN-DEPTH STUDY OF THE VALUE OF THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S POLICY TOWARD EL SALVADOR. THE DEBATE ON THE CONDITIONING, AND EVEN THE TOTAL SUSPENSION, OF MILITARY AID TO THE SALVADORAN ARMY IS VERY INTENSE, AND IT HAS ALREADY SHAKEN THE FOUNDATIONS OF BIPARTISANSHIP REGARDING U.S. SUPPORT FOR THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT. YOU WILL RECALL THAT THE DEBATE HAS NOT CONTINUED BECAUSE THE U.S. CONGRESS HAS DECLARED A RECESS; HOWEVER, IT WILL SOON BECOME THE CENTER OF THE U.S. CONGRESS' DEBATES.

IN SUMMARY, WE COULD SAY THAT THE ENEMY HAS LOST GROUND AND LEGITIMACY, AND THE BASIS FOR ITS SUPPORT, THE U.S. AID, IS BEING SERIOUSLY THREATENED. IN ADDITION, THE ARMY HAS BEEN REDUCED TO THE STRATEGIC DEFENSE OF AN IMPORTANT CENTER, THE CAPITAL CITY. THEREFORE, IT IS ONLY LOGICAL TO SAY THAT TODAY WE SAW A VERY WORRIED, EVEN DESPERATE, CRISTIANI. CRISTIANI'S SPEECH ON THE RADIO AND TELEVISION NETWORK SHOWS AN ATTEMPT TO RETOUCH THE PICTURE. CRISTIANI TRIED TO LOWER THE LEVEL OF THE WATER THAT HAS REACHED HIS NECK BY DIVERTING THE WORLD'S ATTENTION FROM THE BOMBINGS AND THE DEATHS OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS TO NICARAGUA. IN THIS DESPERATE EFFORT, ALL THAT CRISTIANI HAS DONE IS TO TAKE THE WAR TO OTHER AND MORE DANGEROUS LEVELS. HE IS ATTEMPTING TO REGIONALIZE THE WAR, AND THIS WILL UNDOUBTEDLY ISOLATE HIM EVEN MORE FROM THE WORLD.

THE OUTCOME OF THIS SITUATION DEPENDS ON ALL THESE FACTORS THAT CAN ACCELERATE THE DECOMPOSITION OF FASCISM IN THE COUNTRY. HOWEVER, THEY DEPEND MOSTLY ON THE VIGOR AND STRENGTH THAT ALL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE PLACE ON THIS ONGOING AND IRREVERSIBLE STRUGGLE.

DEV-MUC3-0882 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 27 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION. PAY CLOSE ATTENTION. ATTENTION. PAY CLOSE ATTENTION. AS WE HAVE ALREADY REPORTED, U.S. OFFICIALS, IMPORTANT PERSONS, AND POLITICIANS IN THE UNITED STATES HAVE ISSUED STATEMENTS AFFIRMING THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ARE DIRECTLY LINKED TO THE CASE OF THE MURDERED JESUITS. THE TESTIMONY GIVEN BY THE LADY WHO WITNESSED THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY CRIME HAS CAUSED POLITICAL UPHEAVAL THAT IS ALSO BEING FELT IN THE CORRIDORS OF THE U.S. CONGRESS, THE WHITE HOUSE, AND THE PENTAGON.

EVEN ELLIOTT ABRAMS, FORMER ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INTER-AMERICAN AFFAIRS, HAS STATED ON THE FACE THE NATION TELEVISION PROGRAM ON 27 NOVEMBER, THAT THE MURDER OF THE SIX JESUITS, A WOMAN, AND HER DAUGHTER WAS AN ACTION BY THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES AND NOT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. ABRAMS, A FORMER REAGAN ADMINISTRATION OFFICIAL, STATED: BASED ON 10 YEARS EXPERIENCE ON THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT, I PRESUME THAT THE DEATH OF THE PRIESTS WAS NOT THE WORK OF LEFTIST GUERRILLAS, BUT AN ACTION BY FORCES OF THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION. WE DO NOT HAVE A RECORD OF GUERRILLAS TAKING THIS SORT OF ACTION, SAID ELLIOT ABRAMS. HE ADDED THAT, IN THE PAST, MANY MILITARY OFFICERS HAVE BEEN ASSOCIATED WITH THE SO-CALLED DEATH SQUADS AND THE RIGHTIST SECTOR IN EL SALVADOR. THESE WERE THE STATEMENTS BY ELLIOT ABRAMS. VOA HAS REPORTED THE STATEMENTS BY THE WOMAN WHO WITNESSED THE CRIME. AT THIS TIME IN THE UNITED STATES, THE SALVADORAN TOP MILITARY COMMAND, COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, AND PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI ARE BEING POINTED OUT AS THE PERSONS DIRECTLY RESPONSIBLE FOR THIS ABOMINABLE CRIME.

IN RELATION TO THIS, WE WANT TO DENOUNCE THE FOLLOWING TO THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, THE PEOPLE OF THE UNITED STATES, AND THE INTERNATIONAL MEDIA. OVER THE PAST FEW HOURS, THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION HAS TRIED TO DIVERT THE ATTENTION OF THE UNITED STATES THAT IS PRESENTLY CENTERED ON THE CASE OF THE MURDERED JESUITS AND THE INVOLVEMENT OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IN THIS CRIME. WE DENOUNCE THE ARREST OF U.S. CITIZEN JENNIFER CAZOLO AS PART OF A SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES PLAN TO ATTEMPT TO DIVERT THE ATTENTION OF INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC OPINION FROM THE JESUITS' CASE. WE ALSO DENOUNCE THE ARREST OF JENNIFER CAZOLO AS A REPRESSIVE ACT. ALSO, THE ARMED FORCES IS TRYING TO LINK HUMANITARIAN AID FOR EL SALVADOR, HUMAN RIGHTS, AND U.S.-BASED ORGANIZATIONS TO THE FMLN. IT IS TRYING TO LINK THESE ORGANIZATIONS AND THESE PERSONS TO THE FMLN.

THE FMLN COMPLETELY DENIES THAT IT HAS ANY LINK WITH U.S. CITIZEN JENNIFER CAZOLO. WE DENOUNCE THIS ACCUSATION AS A CLUMSY SET UP BY THE ARMED FORCES COMMAND, WHICH IS TRYING -- WE REPEAT -- TRYING TO REPRESS THESE HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS AND FOREIGNERS. THIS IS A SET UP BY THE ARMED FORCES TO REPRESS FOREIGN CITIZENS AND -- WE REPEAT -- IT IS A SMOKE SCREEN TO DIVERT U.S. ATTENTION FROM THE CASE THAT IS PRESENTLY ON THE TABLE. IT IS A SET UP TO NOT ATTEND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY'S DEMAND FOR JUSTICE IN THE CASE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS.

IF ELLIOT ABRAMS, FORMER SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INTER-AMERICAN AFFAIRS, WHO KNOWS SO MUCH ABOUT EL SALVADOR, SAYS THAT IT WAS NOT THE FMLN AND THAT THE CRIME WAS COMMITTED BY MILITARY UNITS AND PERSONS LINKED TO THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION, HIS STATEMENTS WILL HAVE STRONG REPERCUSSIONS IN THE UNITED STATES. THE ARMED FORCES COMMAND AND THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION ARE TRYING TO DO ALL THEY CAN TO THROW A SMOKESCREEN HERE AND THERE TO TRY TO DIVERT THE ATTENTION OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY AND, ESPECIALLY, THE PEOPLE OF THE UNITED STATES.

IN CONCLUSION, WE REAFIRM: WE DENY THE ARMED FORCES' ACCUSATIONS AGAINST U.S. CITIZEN JENNIFER CAZOLO. WE STATE THAT THE ACCUSATION IS A CLUMSY SET UP TO HIDE AND NOT RESPOND TO THE QUESTION EVERYONE IS ASKING -- WHERE ARE THE MURDERERS OF THE JESUITS? BEHIND THE CLUMSY SET UP WITH REGARD TO THE U.S. CITIZEN, WE ALSO SEE THAT THEY INTEND TO CONTINUE TO REPRESS HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS AND DIFFERENT SECTORS THAT HAVE EXPRESSED SOLIDARITY WITH EL SALVADOR. IN SHORT, ALL THIS SET UP ATTEMPTS TO DO IS THROW A HUGE SMOKESCREEN TO REPRESS THESE ORGANIZATIONS AND FOREIGNERS.

DEV-MUC3-0883 (GTE)

SANTIAGO, 27 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [EXCERPTS] THE RADIO MINERIA SANTIAGO STAFF CONTINUES TO EVALUATE THE SUBSTANTIAL DAMAGE CAUSED BY A TERRORIST ATTACK AT THE OFFICES OF RADIO MINERIA.

ERNANI VALDA, THE DIRECTOR OF THE RADIO STATION, HAS REPORTED THAT SO FAR THE DAMAGE IS ESTIMATED AT 2.5 MILLION PESOS.

THE BOMB WAS PLACED IN THE OFFICE OF POLITICAL COMMENTATOR GERMAN GAMONAL, WHO IS ALSO THE PRESS DIRECTOR. FIVE PEOPLE WERE WORKING AT THE OFFICES WHEN THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED; ONE OF THEM WAS INJURED.

WE SPOKE WITH REPORTER HERMOGENES CARRILLO, WHO ARRIVED AT THE RADIO STATION OFFICES AFTER THE ATTACK.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CARRILLO] ONE PERSON SUFFERED MINOR INJURIES AND THE OFFICES OF RADIO MINERIA WERE SUBSTANTIALLY DAMAGED DURING THE BOMB ATTACK HERE AT THE INTERSECTION OF PROVIDENCIA AND TOBALABA STREETS THIS MORNING AT 0510. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

THE RADIO STATION WAS OFF THE AIR FOR 45 MINUTES, DURING WHICH TIME CARABINEROS PERSONNEL INSPECTED THE SITE TO CONFIRM THAT THERE WERE NO OTHER BOMBS.

GOPE [SPECIAL OPERATIONS GROUP] PERSONNEL ARRIVED LATER. ACCORDING TO THEIR SPECIALIZED PERSONNEL THE BOMB CONTAINED TRONEX [EXPANSION UNKNOWN], AND IT HAD BEEN PLACED BY ONE OF THE WINDOWS ON PROVIDENCIA STREET.

AT LEAST TWO OR THREE PEOPLE WERE INVOLVED IN THE ATTACK. THEY SOMEHOW CLIMBED TO THE SECOND FLOOR, PLACED THE BOMB, LIT THE FUSE, AND FLED.

NO WARNING WAS RECEIVED NOR HAS ANY SUBVERSIVE MOVEMENT CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS ATTACK SO FAR.

WE HAVE RECEIVED TELEPHONE CALLS FROM OUR LISTENERS ACROSS THE COUNTRY. WE HAVE ALSO RECEIVED IMPORTANT POLITICAL PERSONALITIES, INCLUDING PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE HERNAN BUCHI AND INTERIOR MINISTER CARLOS CACERES.

AMONG OTHERS, WE HAVE RECEIVED A CALL FROM OSORNO FROM [PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE] FRANCISCO JAVIER ERRAZURIZ AND ANOTHER CALL FROM SANTIAGO FROM RICARDO LAGOS.

THIS IS ALL WE CAN REPORT FOR NOW. THE COST HAS NOT YET BEEN ESTIMATED, BUT IT WILL BE SUBSTANTIAL.

THIS WAS A REPORT BY RADIO MINERIA FOR RADIO NACIONAL DE CHILE. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0884 (GTE)

BOGOTA, 27 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] POLICE SOURCES HAVE DESCRIBED THE ANNONYMOUS TELEPHONE CALL TO RADIO CADENA CARACOL BLAMING "THE EXTRADITABLES" DRUG TRAFFICKING GROUP FOR THE EXPLOSION ON BOARD AN AVIANCA BOEING 727 AS "LACKING CREDIBILITY." THE PLANE WAS ON A FLIGHT FROM BOGOTA TO CALI WITH 107 PERSONS ABOARD. THE ANNONYMOUS CALLER SAID THAT "THE EXTRADITABLES" HAD PLANTED A BOMB ON THAT PLANE BECAUSE "FIVE INFORMERS" WERE ABOARD.

HOWEVER, POLICE SOURCES CONSULTED BY EFE WERE SKEPTICAL, DESCRIBING WHAT THE ANNONYMOUS CALLER HAD SAID AS LACKING CREDIBILITY. ANOTHER POLICE SOURCE TOLD EFE THAT THE ANNONYMOUS PHONE CALL BLAMING "THE EXTRADITABLES" FOR THE EXPLOSION SOUNDED MORE LIKE A JOKE IN BAD TASTE. HE ADDED THAT THE CALL DOES NOT FOLLOW THE NORMAL PATTERN USED BY THAT GROUP WHEN CLAIMING RESPONSIBILITY FOR ITS ACTIONS. THE GROUP USUALLY SENDS COMMUNIQUES TO THE MEDIA. THESE COMMUNIQUES ARE WRITTEN ON PAPER WITH THE GROUP'S LETTERHEAD AND ARE DULY SIGNED, AND AT TIMES INCLUDE THE FINGERPRINTS OF THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR SENDING THE COMMUNIQUE.

A SPOKESPERSON AT EL DORADO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT IN BOGOTA, FROM WHERE THE PLANE TOOK OFF, SAID THAT IT WAS PRACTICALLY IMPOSSIBLE FOR SOMEONE TO HAVE EVADED THE STRICT SECURITY AT THE AIRPORT. THE SOURCE ADDED THAT THE PASSENGERS AND THE LUGGAGE UNDERWENT ROUTINE BUT RIGOROUS SECURITY CHECKS. THESE SECURITY CHECKS INCLUDE HAND CHECKS AND THE USE OF ELECTRONIC EQUIPMENT AND EXPLOSIVES-DETECTING DOGS. THE SOURCE ADDED THAT NOTHING UNUSUAL WAS NOTICED.

"THE EXTRADITABLES" IS AN ARMED GROUP UNDER THE MEDELLIN CARTEL THAT FOR THE PAST 6 YEARS HAS BEEN FIGHTING AGAINST THE EXTRADITION OF COLOMBIANS TO THE UNITED STATES. UP TO NOW THE CRIMES THAT THE GROUP HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR, AND OTHERS FOR WHICH IT IS BLAMED, HAVE ALL FALLEN UNDER THE CATEGORY OF SELECTIVE MURDERS BUT NEVER AN INDISCRIMINATE ATTACK LIKE DESTROYING A PLANE.

CIVIL AERONAUTICS DIRECTORATE SOURCES SAID THAT THE BLACK BOX HAS BEEN FOUND AND THAT ITS CONTENTS WILL PROBABLY REVEAL WHAT HAPPENED.

THE SOURCES ADDED THAT 8 HOURS AFTER THE TRAGEDY, THERE ARE STILL NO CLUES THAT WOULD ALLOW THEM TO BE ABSOLUTELY SURE WHETHER THIS WAS AN ATTACK OR AN ACCIDENT.

MOST OF THE PASSENGERS ON BOARD THE PLANE WERE GOVERNMENT AND PRIVATE BUSINESSMEN WHO WERE TRAVELING FROM BOGOTA TO CALI, IN THE SOUTHEASTERN SECTOR OF THE COUNTRY, FOR BUSINESS PURPOSES.

DEV-MUC3-0885 (GTE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 27 NOV 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PILOT MAURICIO QUIROS GARCIA BY LUIS CABRERA] [TEXT] [CABRERA] THE ALLEGED NICARAGUAN PILOT THAT WAS KILLED IN EL SALVADOR IS ALIVE AND WELL, IN MANAGUA, TALKING WITH US. THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT SAID MAURICIO QUIROS GARCIA WAS KILLED IN AN ALLEGED TRANSSHIPMENT OF WEAPONS LAST SATURDAY, 25 NOVEMBER WHEN A CESSNA PLANE CRASHED. MAURICIO QUIROS GARCIA, 36-YEARS-OLD, IS HERE, NEXT TO ME. HE IS MARRIED AND HAS CHILDREN. GOOD EVENING, MAURICIO.

[QUIROS GARCIA] GOOD EVENING. I AM SO SURPRISED AND ASTONISHED OVER THIS REPORT, THAT I REALLY DO NOT KNOW HOW TO EXPLAIN HOW I FELT WHEN I WAS CALLED. AT FIRST, I THOUGHT IT WAS A JOKE. HOWEVER, AFTER RECEIVING SEVERAL TELEPHONE CALLS FROM SEVERAL NEWSMEN, I STARTED TO THINK SERIOUSLY ABOUT THIS. I WANT TO CLARIFY AND EXPLAIN THAT THIS REPORT IS TOTALLY FALSE.

[CABRERA] MAURICIO, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT SAYS YOU ARE A FORMER PILOT OF THE SANDINIST AIR FORCE, FAS. IS THAT TRUE?

[QUIROS GARCIA] THAT IS TRUE. I WAS IN THE FAS FOR 2 YEARS, AND NOW, I HAVE BEEN WORKING WITH AERONICA FOR THE LAST 8 YEARS.

[CABRERA] WHAT TYPES OF FLIGHTS DO YOU MAKE? TO WHERE DO YOU FLY AND FROM WHERE?

[QUIROS GARCIA] THEY ARE INTERNATIONAL FLIGHTS. I AM THE CAPTAIN OF A BOEING 727. WE FLY TO PANAMA CITY; SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA; MEXICO CITY, AND GUATEMALA CITY.

[CABRERA] WHERE DID YOU GO TO SCHOOL?

[QUIROS GARCIA] IN MEXICO.

[CABRERA] WERE YOU EVER INVOLVED WITH THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], ARE YOU FAMILIAR WITH ANY TYPE OF WEAPONS? THE REPORTS MENTION SOPHISTICATED EQUIPMENT. DID YOU JUST UNLOAD ALL THAT IN EL SALVADOR, AND TURNED AROUND SO QUICKLY, THAT YOU WERE IN SEVERAL PLACES ON SATURDAY?

[QUIROS GARCIA] I DO NOT HAVE THE SLIGHTEST NOTION ABOUT SOPHISTICATED WEAPONS, OR ANYTHING ELSE. MY JOB IS TO PILOT A PLANE, AND THAT IS WHAT I DO; I PILOT THE AERONICA PLANE AND THAT IS IT.

[CABRERA] MAURICIO, DO YOU KNOW THE FMLN WELL?

[QUIROS GARCIA] NO, I DO NOT KNOW ANYONE FROM THE FMLN. I HAVE NO RELATIONS WITH ANYONE LINKED AT ALL TO THE FMLN.

[CABRERA] SO WHY SHOULD ANYONE WANT TO REPORT THAT YOU WERE KILLED EARLY IN THE MORNING IN USULUTAN DEPARTMENT?

[QUIROS GARCIA] WELL, AS I SAID BEFORE, THAT REPORT HAS SURPRISED ME. FRANKLY SPEAKING, I DO NOT KNOW. THIS SHOWS THAT CERTAIN GOVERNMENTS SOMETIMES ISSUE TOTALLY FALSE REPORTS IN ORDER TO HIDE OR, I DO NOT KNOW [CHANGES THOUGHT] THAT REPORT IS TOTALLY FALSE. THAT IS ALL I CAN SAY. AS YOU CAN SEE, I AM VERY CONCERNED, AND JUST AS SURPRISED AS YOU ARE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0886 (GTE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 27 NOV 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [SPEECH] [NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA, IN PROGRESS] [TEXT] EL SALVADOR HAS CARRIED OUT A CONSTANT AND PERMANENT AGGRESSION AGAINST NICARAGUA AND NICARAGUA HAS NEVER SUGGESTED BREAKING RELATIONS WITH EL SALVADOR. NICARAGUA HAS NOT EVEN THOUGHT ABOUT BREAKING RELATIONS WITH HONDURAS. ON THE CONTRARY, WE HAVE ALWAYS TRIED TO FOLLOW A POLICY OF NEGOTIATIONS TO SOLVE PROBLEMS. I DO NOT BELIEVE IN FOOLING OURSELVES. THE REAL PROBLEM HERE IS THAT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS MADE A COMMITMENT, AND THAT COMMITMENT MUST BE FULFILLED. THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS MADE A COMMITMENT TO MOBILIZE THE CONTRAS; THAT COMMITMENT MUST BE FULFILLED. THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS ALSO COMMITTED THEMSELVES TO RESPECTING HUMAN RIGHTS IN CENTRAL AMERICA, AND THAT COMMITMENT MUST ALSO BE FULFILLED. EL SALVADOR MUST FULFILL THAT COMMITMENT. THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS NOT RESPECTING HUMAN RIGHTS IN EL SALVADOR, THEY ARE KILLING PEOPLE IN EL SALVADOR, THEY HAVE BOMBED THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THEY HAVE KILLED THE JESUIT PRIESTS.

IN LIGHT OF ALL THIS, THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT MUST EXPRESS ITS SOLIDARITY WITH THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE; THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE THE ONES WHO ARE SUFFERING. WE CANNOT BE IN SOLIDARITY WITH AN ARMY THAT IS KILLING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. LET US WAIT AND SEE HOW MANY GOVERNMENTS WILL SUPPORT THAT ARMY WHICH IS KILLING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AN ARMY THAT IS BOMBING THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AN ARMY THAT HAS KILLED THE JESUIT PRIESTS. LET US WAIT AND SEE HOW MANY GOVERNMENTS WILL SUPPORT THE ARMY. I ASSURE YOU THAT MOST OF THE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD, ALL THE PEOPLES OF THE WORLD WILL EXPRESS THEIR SUPPORT FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

SHORTLY BEFORE COMING HERE THIS EVENING, I WAS WATCHING THE NEWS VIA SATELLITE, AND I SAW PROTEST DEMOSTRATIONS IN THE UNITED STATES. THE PEOPLE ARE PROTESTING THE KILLING OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS AND THE BOMBINGS IN EL SALVADOR. CHRISTIANS, CATHOLICS, CLERGYMEN, AND PRIESTS ARE PROTESTING IN THE UNITED STATES [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THEREFORE, OUR POSITION IS QUITE CLEAR. WE DO NOT RENOUNCE THE PEACE AGREEMENTS. WE CONTINUE TO DEFEND THEM, AND WE WILL DEMAND THAT THE AGREEMENTS BE FULFILLED. WE ARE GOING TO DEMAND THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT RESPECT THOSE AGREEMENTS AND RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS. WHAT IS NEEDED IN EL SALVADOR IS A CEASE-FIRE. A REAL CEASE-FIRE AND NEGOTIATIONS ARE NEEDED IN EL SALVADOR TO REACH AN AGREEMENT THAT WILL ALLOW PEACE AND DEMOCRACY IN EL SALVADOR. NO ONE CAN BE HAPPY WITH THAT KIND OF A DEMOCRATIC REGIME -- LIKE THE U.S. GOVERNMENT AND THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT DESCRIBE IT. THAT GOVERNMENT IS KNOWN FOR KILLING PEOPLE, FOR KILLING CLERGYMEN. HUMAN RIGHTS MUST BE RESPECTED IN EL SALVADOR.

I AM GRATEFUL TO ALL THE COMRADES WHO CAME FROM THE VARIOUS REGIONS TO BE HERE TONIGHT TO ATTEND THIS MEETING DURING WHICH, IN ADDITION TO DISCUSSING SEVERAL MATTERS OF INTEREST FOR ALL THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE, WE ALSO HONORED OUR EVANGELISTIC BROTHERS WHO HAVE WORKED HERE IN NICARAGUA FOR THE PAST 7 YEARS AND GAVE POSTHUMOUS RECOGNITION TO OUR JESUIT BROTHERS, THE PRIESTS BRUTALLY MURDERED IN EL SALVADOR. [WORDS INDISTINCT] WE ARE DETERMINED TO CONTINUE WORKING WITH THE CHRISTIAN PEOPLE, THE PREACHERS OF THE GOSPEL, THE EVANGELISTS AND ALL THE CHURCHES IN OUR COUNTRY, FOR A NICARAGUA IN PEACE AND DEMOCRACY. ONCE AGAIN I WISH TO REITERATE: BETWEEN CHRISTIANITY AND REVOLUTION, THERE IS NO CONTRADICTION.

DEV-MUC3-0887 (GTE)

MOSCOW (USSR), 27 NOV 89 (RADIO PEACE AND PROGRESS) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS REJETED THE PROPOSAL FOR AN IMMEDIATE CEASE-FIRE THAT THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN], ACCORDING TO MAURICIO SANDOVAL, SALVADORAN MINISTER OF CULTURE AND COMMUNICATIONS. SANDOVAL WAS INTERVIEWED BY THE U.S. NEWS AGENCY UPI.

THE SALVADORAN PATRIOTS MADE THIS PROPOSAL IN RESPONSE TO THE OAS RECOMMENDATION REGARDING THE SALVADORAN SITUATION. THE RECOMMENDATION CALLS FOR AN IMMEDIATE RETURN TO NEGOTIATIONS. BISHOP GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ OFFERED HIS GOOD OFFICES. VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ HAS ALSO JOINED THE GROUP OF PEOPLE WHO ARE TRYING TO STOP THE VIOLENCE IN EL SALVADOR. ON TUESDAY, 21 NOVEMBER, PEREZ MET WITH OFFICIALS OF THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION, NAMELY JUSTICE MINISTER OSCAR SANTAMARIA AND MINISTER OF PRESIDENCY JUAN PADELA.

ACCORDING TO CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ, HE ALSO TALKED WITH HIS SALVADORAN COUNTERPART ALFREDO CRISTIANI ON THE PHONE. IN THE COURSE OF THIS TALK HE OFFERED TO HOST A CARACAS MEETING BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE REBELS.

IT WOULD SEEM THAT BECAUSE OF THE NEGATIVE ATTITUDE OF CRISTIANI'S ADMINISTRATION, ALL THESE EFFORTS HAVE NOT YIELDED THE EXPECTED FRUITS. THE FACT IS THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS TRYING TO WORSEN THE TERROR. WITH THIS IN MIND, THE GOVERNMENT IS DRAFTING A LAW TO PUNISH THE OPPOSITION. AS A PREVENTIVE MEASURE, CONGRESS HAS ALREADY APPROVED ANTITERRORIST BILLS. THESE BILLS ALLOW THE ARREST OF PEOPLE ON SUSPICION OF ANTIGOVERNMENT ACTIVITIES.

A SALVADORAN DEPUTY HAS LABELED THESE BILLS UNCONSTITUTIONAL AND CONTRARY TO HUMAN RIGHTS. MEANWHILE, THESE BILLS HAVE ENCOURAGED THE ACURSED DEATH SQUADS. AMERICAS WATCH, A HUMAN RIGHTS ORGANIZATION, HAS REPORTED AN INCREASE OF [WORD INDISTINCT], ARRESTS OF AND THREATS AGAINST FOREIGNERS WHO WORK FOR RELIGIOUS AND HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS IN EL SALVADOR.

THE SALVADORAN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION BELIEVES THAT THE CRUSADE AGAINST FOREIGN MISSIONARIES IS ENCOURAGED BY THE ULTRARIGHTISTS WHO ARE OPERATING UNDER THE PROTECTION OF THE GOVERNMENT. THE GOVERNMENT GUARANTEES THE REACTIONARIES THEIR IMPUNITY.

DEATH SQUADS, WORKING CLOSELY WITH REACTIONARY MILITARY MEN AND THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION, ARE MOST CERTAINLY TO BLAME FOR THE RECENT DISGRACEFUL MURDER OF SIX PRIESTS IN EL SALVADOR, ACCORDING TO THE U.S. PUBLICATION THE BOSTON GLOBE. THE PAPER STATES THAT THIS IS OBVIOUS TO ALL AND THAT THE SALVADORAN REGIME AND THE YANKEE GOVERNMENT ARE THE ONLY ONES THAT REFUSE TO ADMIT IT.

FROM THEIR POINT OF VIEW THIS ATTITUDE IS REASONABLE. WASHINGTON'S POLICY TOWARD EL SALVADOR IS BASED ON THE ULTRARIGTHWING FORCES [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THE BOSTON GLOBE ADDS THAT EVERY YEAR THE TAXPAYERS TAKE OUT OF THEIR POCKETS $500 MILLION TO FINANCE THE ASSISTANCE THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT GIVES TO EL SALVADOR. SOME OF THIS MONEY GOES TO THE DEATH SQUADS WHICH ARE GUILTY OF THOUSANDS OF MURDERS COMMITED AMID HELLISH TORTURES. IT IS A SIGNIFICANT PIECE OF INFORMATION.

THE THING IS THAT U.S. OFFICIALS PREFER TO LASH OUT AT THE FICTITIOUS SHIPMENTS OF SOVIET WEAPONS TO EL SALVADOR, FICTITIOUS BECAUSE THERE HAVE BEEN NONE AT ALL. ON THE OTHER HAND, THE USE THAT SUCCESSIVE SALVADORAN REGIMES HAVE MADE OF U.S. AID, HAS ALWAYS BEEN DOWNPLAYED. HOWEVER, IT IS OBVIOUS THAT WITHOUT THE HEFTY U.S. SUBSIDIES, THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT WOULD HAVE BEEN RESOLVED A LONG TIME AGO AND THE NEARLY 100,000 SALVADORANS WHO HAVE DIED IN THE STRUGGLE, WOULD STILL BE ALIVE.

DEV-MUC3-0888 (GTE)

MOSCOW (USSR), 22 NOV 89 -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO SOME SOURCES, IN THE PAST FEW DAYS MORE THAN 1,000 PEOPLE HAVE DIED IN EL SALVADOR AFTER THE INTENSIFICATION OF THE FIGHT BETWEEN GOVERNMENT FORCES AND THE GUERRILLAS. MIKHAIL MAYOROV FILED THIS REPORT:

THE HORRIFYING REPORTS PUBLISHED BY THE NEW YORK TIMES GIVE AN APPROPRIATE IDEA OF THE TRAGEDY IN EL SALVADOR, WHERE A CIVIL WAR IS RAVAGING THE COUNTRY. ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR, WHERE THE FIGHT IS BEING WAGED, THE PEOPLE ARE FORCED TO BURN DEAD BODIES RIGHT IN FRONT OF THEIR HOUSES.

THE VICTIMS ARE NOT ONLY SOLDIERS AND GUERRILLAS, WHO ARE DIRECTLY INVOLVED IN THE CONFLICT, BUT ALSO CIVILIANS, WHOSE HOUSES ARE HIT BY BOMBS AND PROJECTILES. THE CIVILIANS ARE CONSTANTLY THREATENED BY THE BULLIES OF THE SO-CALLED DEATH SQUADS, WHO MURDERED SIX CATHOLIC PRIESTS AT THE SAN SALVADOR UNIVERSITY CAMPUS.

THE SALVADORAN SITUATION, WHICH HAS CAUSED SERIOUS CONCERN, CANNOT BE REGARDED AS SOMETHING WHICH IS COMMONLY REFERRED TO AS [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THE INTERDEPENDENCE OF THE WORLD NOW SEEMS TO BE STRONGER THAN EVER. WE HAVE FINALLY UNDERSTOOD THE MEANING OF THE OLD SAYING THAT THERE IS NO ISOLATED TRAGEDY. WE FEEL INCREASINGLY RESPONSIBLE FOR WHAT IS HAPPENING IN THE SO-CALLED HOT SPOTS OF THE PLANET.

OBVIOUSLY, THE FIRST THING TO BE DONE TO NORMALIZE THE SITUATION IS TO STEM THE DIRECT AND INDIRECT FLOW OF MILITARY SUPPLIES TO BOTH SIDES.

MOSCOW HAS ALREADY TAKEN THIS POSITION. HOWEVER, U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH HAS TERMED INADMISSIBLE THE POSSIBILITY OF HALTING THE AID TO THE GOVERNMENT OF ALFREDO CRISTIANI.

IF WE COMPARE THE SALVADORAN AND THE AFGHAN SITUATIONS, WHY DOES THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION SO BITTERLY REPPROACHED US FOR HELPING THE NAJIBULLAH REGIME?

WE HAVE UNFORTUNATELY NOT YET ADOPTED GENERAL CRITERIA.

OUR FOREIGN POLICY IS CONSISTENT, MAYOROV SAYS. IN MY OPINION, SOVIET DIPLOMACY HAS A MORE FLEXIBLE ATTITUDE TOWARD THE CURRENT SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR. THE SOVIET GOVERNMENT HAS ABANDONED ITS CONSERVATIVE STAND, WHICH MADE US SUPPORT JUST ONE SIDE. IN THE FINAL ANALYSIS, THE WAR IS A TRAGEDY FOR ALL THE PEOPLE, AND THE MAGNITUDE OF THE TRAGEDY GROWS AS THE CONFLICT BECOMES MORE SERIOUS.

THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT WILL REFLECT THE WILLINGNESS THAT MOSCOW AND WASHINGTON HAVE TO HELP A SMALL NATION, WHICH IS TIRED OF A LONG-STANDING CONFLICT, FIND A WAY TOWARDS PEACE.

ALL OF US ARE WAITING FOR THE SOVIET-U.S. SUMMIT WHICH WILL BE HELD OFF THE COAST OF MALTA. IT IS DIFFICULT TO IMAGINE THE ISSUES THAT WILL BE ON THE AGENDA BECAUSE THE MEETING WILL BE UNOFFICIAL [AS HEARD].

THERE ARE MANY ISSUES THAT MAY BE ADDRESSED IN A BILATERAL SUMMIT. IT IS HIGHLY DESIRABLE, HOWEVER, THAT BOTH SIDES REACH AN UNDERSTANDING AND THAT THEY IDENTIFY THE POSSIBILITIES OF COOPERATION FOR THE RESOLUTION OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PROBLEM.

DEV-MUC3-0890 (GTE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 28 NOV 89 (PL) -- [TEXT] HEAVY CLASHES ARE STILL TAKING PLACE IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR FOLLOWING A NIGHT OF FIERCE COMBAT, WHICH CONFIRMS PREDICTIONS ON THE INTENSIFICATION OF THE WAR THIS WEEK.

PRESS REPORTS RELEASED FROM SAN SALVADOR AT NOON TODAY REPORT THE CONTINUATION OF CLASHES BETWEEN THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] AND THE ARMED FORCES, BASICALLY IN NEIGHBORHOODS IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

AYUTUXTEPEQUE, SOYAPANGO, ZACAMIL, AND SAN RAMON, ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADO, SEEM TO HAVE BEEN OCCUPIED AGAIN BY GUERRILLA COLUMNS, WHICH CONTROLLED THOSE NEIGHBORHOODS DURING THE FIRST DAYS OF THE NATIONAL OFFENSIVE WHICH BEGAN ON 11 NOVEMBER.

IN ITS MOST RECENT NEWSCAST, THE FMLN'S RADIO VENCEREMOS REPORTED THE AIR FORCE HEAVILY BOMBED AYUTUXTEPEQUE, A DENSELY POPULATED NEIGHBORHOOD, AND CONFIRMED THE CLASHES TAKING PLACE IN SOYAPANGO.

THE SOURCE REPORTED THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ELITE TROOPS, AND EVEN INFANTRY BRIGADES FROM MILITARY DETACHMENTS TRADITIONALY STATIONED IN THE COUNTRYSIDE, HAVE BEEN DEPLOYED TO SAN SALVADOR IN AN ATTEMPT TO REPEL THE REBELS' ACTIONS.

ACCORDING TO THE GUERRILLA REPORTS, DESPITE THE CONTINUOUS BOMBINGS, CLASHES ARE TAKING PLACE AT THIS TIME IN THE CAPITAL OF SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT, IN THE EASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY. SEVERAL SECTORS OF THE PANAMERICAN HIGHWAY, ESPECIALLY IN EASTERN SAN SALVADOR, REMAIN UNDER THE FMLN CONTROL, RADIO VENCEREMOS REPORTED.

THE CENTRAL AMERICAN MEDIA TODAY WARNED ABOUT THE SERIOUSNESS OF THE INCIDENTS IN SAN SALVADOR THIS MORNING, WHEN GROUPS OF UNIDENTIFIED MEN MACHINEGUNNED FORMER SUPREME COURT PRESIDENT FRANCISCO GUERRERO, A WELL- KNOWN LEADER OF THE RIGHTWING NATIONAL CONCILIATION PARTY. SOURCES CONSULTED IN SAN SALVADOR, WHICH PREFER NOT TO BE IDENTIFIED, SAID IT IS A FACT THE FAR RIGHTWING IS LINKED TO THIS CRIME. THE SAME SOURCES MAINTAINED THAT THE RECENT ANNOUNCEMENT ON THE SUSPENSION OF DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH MANAGUA, MADE BY PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI, CAUSED DISAGREEMENTS AMONG THE GOVERNMENT BRANCHES AND AMONG THE VARIOUS PARTIES.

DEV-MUC3-0891 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 28 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE RECEIVED A REPORT ADVISING US THAT AT 0200 [0800 GMT] TODAY, FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] FORCES ATTACKED A GROUP OF PARATROOPERS AT THE INSA [EXPANSION UNKNOWN] FACTORY IN SOYAPANGO. THE REPORT ALSO ADDS THAT SINCE EARLY THIS MORNING, FIGHTING HAS BEEN GOING ON IN GUADALUPE NEIGHBORHOOD, ALSO IN SOYAPANGO. REPORTS FROM OTHER AREAS OF SAN SALVADOR SPEAK OF HEAVY CLASHES SINCE EARLY THIS MORNING. THE REPORT STATES THAT AT 0200 TODAY, FMLN UNITS ATTACKED TWO 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE COBRA BATTALION COMPANIES IN SAN SALVADOR. THE TROOPS WERE IN EL CARMEN HILL, AYUTUXTEPEQUE JURISDICTION. THE REPORT ADDS THAT THE FMLN INFLICTED TWO DEAD AND THREE WOUNDED, INCLUDING A SERGEANT AND A CORPORAL. THIS MEANS THAT THE 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE IS ALREADY IN SAN SALVADOR. THIS IS THE WAY THINGS ARE IN SAN SALVADOR: SONSONATE TROOPS, 5TH INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS, AND 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS ARE IN SAN SALVADOR. THIS IS PROOF OF HOW BAD THE ENEMY IS DOING.

THE REPORT ADDS THAT SINCE THIS MORNING, FIGHTING AGAINST ATLACATL BATTALION TROOPS WAS REPORTED IN THE AREA AROUND EL CARMEN HILL. THE ATLACATL BATTALION TROOPS WERE GOING TO REINFORCE THE COWARDLY 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS, WHO HAVE LEFT CHALATENANGO AND ARE NOW IN SAN SALVADOR. THE FIGHTING ENDED AT 0930 [1530 GMT].

WE REPEAT: AT 0200 TODAY, FMLN UNITS ATTACKED A GROUP OF PARATROOPERS AT THE INSA FACTORY IN SOYAPANGO. FIGHTING WAS ALSO REPORTED IN SAN JACINTO, MEJICANOS, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, SOYAPANGO, SANTA EDUVIGES, ESCANDIA NEIGHBORHOOD, EL CARMEN NEIGHBORHOOD, AND OTHER AREAS OF SAN SALVADOR. WE ARE WAITING FOR MORE REPORTS BECAUSE WE HAVE LEARNED THAT FIGHTING HAS RESUMED IN THE CAPITAL CITY.

TO ADD TO THE REPORT WE HAVE RECEIVED FROM SAN SALVADOR, WE WISH TO STATE THAT HEAVY FIGHTING OCCURRED THIS MORNING IN GUADALUPE NEIGHBORHOOD, SOYAPANGO. AT 0600 [1200 GMT], NATIONAL GUARD TROOPS WERE AMBUSHED AT KM 11 ON THE NORTHERN TRUNK ROAD. THE NATIONAL GUARD SUFFERED DEAD AND WOUNDED DURING THAT AMBUSH. WE WILL HAVE MORE INFORMATION ON THIS AMBUSH LATER.

DEV-MUC3-0892 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 28 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [BEGIN RECORDING] [COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF] THIS AGAIN PROVES THE AGGRESSION BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AGAINST POOR PEOPLE, AND AGAINST OUR COUNTRY'S DISTINGUISHED POLITICIANS. THIS IS ADDED TO THE INNOCENT LIVES TAKEN BY THE FMLN FROM THE SALVADORAN POPULATION. I WANT TO TELL YOU WE HAVE A PERSON UNDER ARREST WHO WAS WOUNDED RIGHT WHERE THE ATTACK TOOK PLACE, BY DR. GUERRERO'S BODYGUARD. WE HAVE HIS IDENTITY, HE IS AFFILITATED TO THE FMLN, BUT WE WILL NOT RELEASE HIS NAME WHILE THE INVESTIGATION IS UNDER WAY. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE THE BEST WITNESS TO THE FMLN AGGRESSION AGAINST OUR PEOPLE. [END RECORDING]

[ANNOUNCER] PONCE ALSO SAID THAT THE TERRORISTS CARRY OUT THESE ACTIONS AS PART OF THEIR STRATEGY TO SCARE THE POPULATION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] WE WANT TO SAY THAT CONDITIONS TO ENABLE MARXISM AND THE FMLN TO WIN ARE PRACTICALLY NIL. THE PEOPLE COMPLETELY REJECT THEM. THE FMLN ARE USING THAT LYING AND LOSING VENCEREMOS RADIO STATION TO FOOL THEIR OWN CADRES. IN NICARAGUA, THERE WERE SOME STATIONS THAT WERE IN NETWORK WITH THIS LYING AND LOSING VENCEREMOS RADIO STATION, BROADCASTING FALSE REPORTS ABOUT EL SALVADOR. THIS IS ALSO PART OF THE AGGRESSION. TO ALLOW THEIR SO-CALLED HIGH-RANKING FMLN COMMANDERS TO BE IN NICARAGUA IS ALSO PART OF THE AGGRESSION. NO ONE CAN IGNORE THE AGGRESSION THAT THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN EXERTING FOR A LONG TIME AGAINST THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE.

[UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] HAVING FOUND THESE SOPHISTICATED WEAPONS, DOES IT MEAN YOU MAY EXPECT THE AGGRESSIVE COUNTEROFFENSIVE THESE GROUPS ARE LAUNCHING MAY WIDEN?

[PONCE] DEFINITELY NOT. WE BELIEVE THEIR CADRES ARE DECIMATED. THIS COULD AFFECT MAINLY OUR AIR FORCE; HOWEVER, WE ARE TAKING THE PROPER TACTICAL AND TECHNICAL PREVENTIVE MEASURES. WHAT SHOULD BE VERY CLEAR TO ALL SALVADORANS IS THAT FOR THE FMLN TO ATTAIN POWER, WHICH IS THEIR GOAL, THEY WILL HAVE TO CLIMB OVER THE BODY OF THE LAST ARMED FORCES SOLDIER. [END RECORDING]

[ANNOUNCER] PONCE ALSO SAID THAT THE MISSILES AND OTHER WEAPONS SENT BY ORTEGA FOR THE FMLN ARE AGRESSIONS AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, EXPLAINING THAT IT WAS A NICARAGUAN WHO LIVES IN THIS CAPITAL WHO IDENTIFIED THE MAN WHO PILOTED THE SMALL AIRCRAFT CARRYING THE WEAPONS FOR THE TERRORISTS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] HE SAID THAT IT WAS QUIROS GARCIA. HOWEVER, THAT EVENING HE CALLED BACK AND SAID THAT THE PILOT SHOULD HAVE PART OF HIS THUMB MISSING, AND TO PLEASE CHECK HIM OUT. THE BODY WE HAVE WAS CHECKED AND ONE OF THE THUMBS HAS A PART MISSING. TO US THIS IS IRREFUTABLE PROOF. WE ALL KNOW OF ORTEGA'S CYNCISM. ON THE ONE HAND, HE MADE PROMISES AT ESQUIPULAS II, SIGNING AGREEMENTS HE WAS NOT PREPARED TO IMPLEMENT; HE WOULD NOT DO IT SINCE HE WAS REALLY DOING THESE OTHER THINGS. HE IS THE SAME AS THE FMLN. THE FMLN WAS DISCUSSING PEACE AT A DIALOGUE TABLE WHILE IT WAS PREPARING FOR THIS OFFENSIVE. IT IS A MOCKERY OF THE PEOPLE, BECAUSE THEIR DESIRE FOR PEACE HAS BEEN FOOLED WITH. DOMESTIC AND INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC OPINION HAVE BEEN FOOLED. [END RECORDING]

[ANNOUNCER] FINALLY, PONCE SAID THE SUBVERSIVE GROUPS HAVE LOW MORALE AND ARE DESPERATE, BECAUSE IF DANIEL ORTEGA LOSES THE ELECTIONS, THEY, TOO, WILL LOSE, AND FOREVER. ADDITIONALLY, THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE DO NOT SUPPORT THEIR IRRATIONAL ACTIONS THAT ONLY PRODUCE DEATH AND DESTRUCTION.

DEV-MUC3-0895 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 28 NOV 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT] [TEXT] IN LIGHT OF THE TERRORIST ARMED AGGRESSION LAUNCHED AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WITH THE OPEN SUPPORT AND DIRECTION OF THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT HEADED BY DANIEL ORTEGA ON 11 NOVEMBER, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT ADVISES THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY THAT ON THE DAY THE CURRENT GOVERNMENT ASSUMED OFFICE, IT EXPRESSED ITS FIRM DESIRE TO SEEK, THROUGH THE CIVILIZED PATH OF DIALOGUE, A COMPREHENSIVE SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT BECAUSE THE MARXIST - LENINIST GROUP'S CAUSE BRINGS BLOODSHED TO OUR PEOPLE. IN THIS SENSE, PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT PROMOTED THE PROCESS OF DIALOGUE THAT BEGAN IN MEXICO CITY ON 13, 14, AND 15 SEPTEMBER 1989. AT THAT TIME, GOVERNMENT AND FMLN DELEGATIONS SIGNED AN AGREEMENT COMMITTING THEMSELVES TO SEEK AN END TO HOSTILITIES WITHIN THE SPIRIT OF THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS IN TELA, HONDURAS. BASED ON THE AGREEMENT REACHED IN MEXICO CITY, THE ISSUE TO BE BROACHED DURING THE SECOND ROUND OF TALKS TO BE HELD IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA, ON 16 AND 17 OCTOBER WOULD BE THE END TO HOSTILITIES BASED ON PROPOSALS PRESENTED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN. AT THAT TIME, THE FMLN DID NOT ALLOW THE DISCUSSION OF THE TOPIC PREVIOUSLY AGREED ON AND PRESENTED A SERIES OF PROPOSALS, DELIBERATELY COMPLEX IN FORM AND CONTENT, WITH THE EVIDENT PURPOSE OF PREVENTING THE MAIN AND ONLY TOPIC ON THE AGENDA FROM BEING DISCUSSED.

ON 11 NOVEMBER, THE FMLN LAUNCHED AN AGGRESSION AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AN AGGRESSION THAT WAS OBVIOUSLY PLANNED AT LEAST A FEW MONTHS BEFORE IT WAS LAUNCHED. THIS PROVES THAT WHILE THE FMLN WAS TALKING PEACE AND NEGOTIATIONS AROUND THE NEGOTIATING TABLE, IT WAS, WITH THE POLITICAL, LOGISTICAL, AND MILITARY SUPPORT OF ORTEGA'S GOVERNMENT, PREPARING THE CRIMINAL ATTACK AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THE TERRORIST AGGRESSION TO DATE, CERTAIN THINGS HAVE HAPPENED THAT PROVE THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT'S INVOLVEMENT IN THE GENOCIDE IMPLEMENTED BY THE FMLN TERRORISTS. THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS PROOF THAT THE FMLN IS A PUPPET OF DANIEL ORTEGA'S DEADLY PLANS WHO, FACED WITH AN IMMINENT ELECTORAL DEFEAT AND IN CONJUNCTION WITH FIDEL CASTRO, IS ATTEMPTING TO REGIONALIZE IN CENTRAL AMERICA AN ARMED CONFLICT TO TRY TO SAVE THE SANDINIST REGIME.

IN LIGHT OF THE AFOREMENTIONED AND HAVING ESTABLISHED THE PARTICIPATION OF THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT IN THE TERRORIST AGGRESSION EXPERIENCED BY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AGREED, ON 26 NOVEMBER 1989, TO SUSPEND DIPLOMATIC AND COMMERCIAL RELATIONS WITH THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT AND RECALLED ITS DIPLOMATIC MISSION FOR CONSULTATIONS. IN LIGHT OF THESE SERIOUS ACTIONS WHICH VIOLATE INTERNATIONAL LAW, THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS PRESENTED FORMAL CHARGES BEFORE THE UNITED NATIONS AND THE OAS SO THAT IMMEDIATE AND EFFICIENT MEASURES WILL BE TAKEN TO REPUDIATE THESE TERRORIST ACTIONS AND SO THAT THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT WILL BE DIPLOMATICALLY AND POLITICALLY PRESSURED TO STOP THE AGGRESSION IT HAS UNLEASHED AGAINST EL SALVADOR, AND THUS STOP A POSSIBLE CONFLICT OF UNPREDICTABLE DIMENSIONS.

HOW IS IT POSSIBLE THAT AT A TIME LIKE THIS, WHEN AROUND THE WORLD MOMENTS OF POLITICAL FREEDOM ARE BEING EXPERIENCED IN PLACES LIKE POLAND, THE GDR, CZECHOSLOVAKIA, AND HUNGARY, HERE, IN EL SALVADOR, BECAUSE OF THE FMLN'S IRRATIONAL ACTIONS -- WITH ORTEGA'S SUPPORT -- ATTEMPTS ARE BEING MADE TO DROWN A NATION WHICH, DESPITE 10 YEARS OF WAR, IS TRYING TO CONSOLIDATE A DEMOCRATIC PROCESS?

THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE ARE UNITED DURING THIS HISTORIC TEST TO ACHIEVE PEACE WITHIN THE DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM.

DEV-MUC3-0897 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 29 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, ATTENTION. WE HAVE LAST MINUTE INFORMATION.

ATTENTION. FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] FORCES HAVE BROKEN THE SIEGE THAT THE FASCIST TROOPS WERE MAINTAINING AROUND NORTHWESTERN AND NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR.

ATTENTION. WE HAVE BEEN FIGHTING IN AREAS CLOSE TO THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF HEADQUARTERS. WE REPEAT. WE ARE FIGHTING IN AREAS CLOSE TO THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF HEADQUARTERS. WE ARE FIGHTING IN LA SULTANA NEIGHBORHOOD, ON THE SOUTHERN HIGHWAY AND AROUND THE DEMOCRACIA BUILDING.

OUR UNITS ENTERED THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE NEIGHBORHOOD INHABITED BY HIGH-RANKING MILITARY CHIEFS AND OCCUPIED SEVERAL HOUSES THERE. OUR FORCES FOUND ARSENALS IN SOME OF THE HOUSES AND CLASHED AGAINST ENEMY TROOPS.

OUR FORCES SEIZED MANY WEAPONS INCLUDING RIFLES, MACHINEGUNS, AMMUNITION, AND OTHER WAR MATERIAL. ALL THOSE WEAPONS WERE FOUND IN THE HOUSES OF SEVERAL HIGH-RANKING MILITARY CHIEFS IN THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE NEIGHBORHOOD.

WE ALSO HAVE REPORTS ON CLASHES IN THE AREA OF ANTIGUO CUSCATLAN WHERE MILITARY DETACHMENT NO 6 REINFORCEMENTS REFUSED TO ADVANCE. THE SONSONATE TROOPS REFUSED TO ADVANCE TOWARD OUR POSITIONS IN THE AREA OF ANTIGUO CUSCATLAN.

SIMILARLY, OUR FORCES ARE HOLDING POSITIONS IN SOYAPANGO, MEJICANOS, CUSCATANCINGO, AND AYUTUXTEPEQUE. OUR FORCES ALSO HAVE CONTROL OF THE NORTHERN TRUNK HIGHWAY AND OTHER IMPORTANT ROUTES LEADING TO SAN SALVADOR.

THERE ARE CLASHES AGAINST BRACAMONTE BATTALION TROOPS IN LA SULTANA NEIGHBORHOOD, SAN FRANCISCO, AND ANTIGUO CUSCATLAN. THE ENEMY HAS REACTED IN FOUR DIFFERENT WAYS. THE ENEMY SENT BRACAMONTE BATTALION REINFORCEMENTS IN ONE DIRECTION, BUT THEIR ADVANCE WAS NEUTRALIZED AND HALTED AT THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD. WE REPEAT. THE FIRST HIGH COMMAND RESPONSE TO OUR INCURSION INTO NORTHWESTERN AND WESTERN SAN SALVADOR RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS INCLUDING BRACAMONTE BATTALION REINFORCEMENTS HAS BEEN NEUTRALIZED. OUR FORCES AMBUSHED AND NEUTRALIZED THOSE BRACAMONTE BATTALION REINFORCEMENTS.

A SECOND ENEMY RESPONSE TO OUR INCURSION INTO AND CONTROL OF NORTHWESTERN AND WESTERN SAN SALVADOR MOVED ALONG THE SOUTHERN HIGHWAY AND WAS AMBUSHED WITH RPG-7 ROCKET LAUNCHERS AND THEREFORE NEUTRALIZED. THE ENEMY'S THIRD RESPONSE MOVING THROUGH SANTA TECLA WAS ALSO ATTACKED BY OUR FORCES AND HAS BEEN NEUTRALIZED WITH AN AMBUSH NEAR LA UNIVERSAL AND GUADALUPE GARDENS. THESE ATLACATL BATTALION FORCES WERE ALSO NEUTRALIZED.

WE ARE RECEIVING THIS REPORT FROM SAN SALVADOR. THE HIGH COMMAND'S FIRST AND BELATED RESPONSE INCLUDED FOUR MOVEMENTS, WHICH WERE ALL HALTED BY OUR FORCES. THOSE FOUR HIGH COMMAND DEFENSIVE MOVEMENTS HAVE BEEN ATTACKED AND NEUTRALIZED. BOTH THE BRACAMONTE AND THE ATLACATL BATTALIONS HAVE BEEN NEUTRALIZED. MEANWHILE THE TROOPS COMING FROM SONSONATE REFUSED TO ADVANCE IN SOUTHWESTERN SAN SALVADOR.

CLASHES NOW COVER A LARGE AREA FROM THE HIGHWAY LINKING SANTA TECLA AND SAN SALVADOR AND THROUGH LA MASCOTA, LAS PALMAS, SAN BENITO, MAQUILIGUE, CAMPESTRE, LOMAS VERDES, ESCALON NEIGHBORHOODS, CONTINUING TO THE SAN SALVADOR VOLCANO AND MOVING THROUGH THE ENTIRE NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR INCLUDING AYUTUXTEPEQUE, CUSCATANCINGO, NORTHERN MEJICANOS, AND MEJICANOS ITSELF AND THEN MOVING TO CIUDAD DELGADO, SOYAPANGO, AND THE SOUTHERN SECTION OF THE PAN-AMERICAN HIGHWAY, WHERE OUR UNITS MAINTAIN POSITIONS AND ARE ADVANCING TOWARD ENEMY FORCES. IN OTHER WORDS, AT THIS HOUR THE FMLN HAS FORMED THE LARGEST ARCH OF ATTACKS DURING OUR FORCES' ENTIRE OCCUPATION OF SAN SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0898 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 29 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] WE HAVE LEARNED THAT THE GENERAL STAFF HAS ERECTED A HUMAN WALL, ERECTED BY COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, FOLLOWING THE ARTILLERY ATTACK STAGED BY US AT 0515 THIS MORNING ON THE GENERAL STAFF INSTALLATIONS. IT WAS REPORTED THAT HUNDREDS OF LITTLE SOLDIERS HAVE BEEN PLACED AS CANNON FODDER OUTSIDE THE GENERAL STAFF INSTALLATIONS. THIS GIVES US NEW INTELLIGENCE DATA ON THE MORALE OF COL PONCE, HOW THE CRISIS IS AFFECTING HIM. WITHOUT ANY MILITARY CRITERION, HE HAS PLACED A WALL OF SOLDIERS AROUND THE GENERAL STAFF INSTALATIONS. THIS IS A GOOD PIECE OF INTELLIGENCE GIVEN TO US BY COL PONCE, CONCERNING HIS PHYSICAL STATE AND CONCERNING THE UPSET BEING SUFFERED BY THE STRATEGIC ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF COMMAND.

WE CALL ON THE INHABITANTS OF THE COUNTRY CLUB, THE MAQUILIGUAS, SAN BENITO, AND ESCALON NEIGHBORHOODS TO IMMEDIATELY ABANDON THAT COMBAT ZONE. THE FIGHTING WILL GET WORSE AND THE AIR FORCE WILL BOMB THE FMLN POSITIONS IN SAN BENITO AND ESCALON NEIGHBORHOODS, THEREFORE ITS INHABITANTS ARE URGED TO ABANDON THAT RESIDENTIAL DISTRICT IN SAN SALVADOR.

A REPORT FROM USULUTAN INDICATES AT THIS TIME THAT THE FMLN UNITS ARE ADVANCING AND FIGHTING IN THE SECTOR OF GAVIRIA, EL MANGUITO, AND LOS PILOTOS NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE CITY OF USULUTAN. ALSO, IN THE AREA OF SANTA ELENA THERE IS FIERCE FIGHTING.

YOUR ATTENTION PLEASE. WE HAVE ANOTHER REPORT FROM SAN SALVADOR. IMPORTANT INFORMATION IS BEING RECEIVED FROM LOMAS VERDES. IN THE STRATEGIC ZONE OF LOMAS VERDES IN THE NORTHWESTERN PART OF THE CAPITAL, AN ARMY ARMORED VEHICLE WAS DESTROYED AND ITS 50-CALIBER MACHINEGUN WAS SEIZED, AS WELL AS MANY RIFLES AND MACHINEGUNS FROM THE NATIONAL POLICE AND CAVALRY TROOPS. YOUR ATTENTION TO THIS REPORT FROM SAN SALVADOR. FIGHTING IN THE EXCLUSIVE LOMAS VERDES NEIGHBORHOOD INDICATES THAT AN ARMORED VEHICLE WAS DESTROYED. DURING THE FIGHTING A 50-CALIBER MACHINEGUN WAS SEIZED FROM THE DAMAGED ARMORED VEHICLE. IT IS BEING EMPLACED AND WILL BE USED AGAINST THE AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS AND AIRCRAFT THAT ARE OVERFLYING THE AREA.

SINCE 0000, WHEN THE FIGHTING BEGAN, TO 0940, WHEN WE RECEIVED THE REPORT OF THE FIGHTING IN LOMAS VERDES NEIGHBORHOOD IN THE WESTERN PART OF THE CAPITAL, NEAR ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD, OUR FORCES HAVE DESTROYED AN ARMORED VEHICLE AND SEIZED IN COMBAT TWO M-60 MACHINEGUNS, 8 M-16 RIFLES, 1 M-79 GRENADE LAUNCHER, THREE VRC COMMUNICATION RADIOS, AND A 50-CALIBER MACHINEGUN SEIZED FROM THE ARMORED VEHICLE. THIS OCCURRED DURING THE FIGHTING WITH THE NATIONAL POLICE AND CAVALRY TROOPS, WHICH SUSTAINED 14 CASUALTIES.

DEV-MUC3-0899 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 29 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [EXCERPTS] WE HAVE AN ACAN-EFE REPORT ON THE SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR. THE REPORT READS: THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS TODAY UNLEASHED A NEW OFFENSIVE IN SAN SALVADOR WITH ATTACKS ON MILITARY INSTALLATIONS AND FIERCE CLASHES WITH THE ARMY IN SEVERAL NEIGHBORHOODS IN SAN SALVADOR, WHICH CONTINUE UP UNTIL MID-MORNING ON 29 NOVEMBER. THE ACAN-EFE REPORT ADDS: THE GUERRILLAS' ACTIONS AFFECTED ESCALON, SAN FRANCISCO, AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE THE RESIDENCES OF PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI AND U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER ARE LOCATED.

A LOCAL TELEVISION STATION REPORTED THERE WERE SHOOTOUTS EARLY THIS MORNING ON LA CAPILLA STREET IN SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE THE RESIDENCE OF U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER IS LOCATED. THE FMLN AND THE ARMY ARE ALSO FIGHTING IN MEJICANOS AND CIUDAD DELGADO IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR. THE FMLN IS MAINTAINING POSITIONS ON THE HIGHWAY LINKING SAN SALVADOR TO THE WESTERN SECTOR OF THE COUNTRY. THE FMLN REPORTED THIS MORNING THAT ITS TROOPS AMBUSHED PATROLS FROM THE ARMED FORCES ELITE BATTALIONS. WITNESSES CONFIRMED TO ACAN-EFE THAT THE FMLN TOOK POSITIONS IN ANTIGUO CUSCATLAN, A TOWN SOUTHEAST OF SAN SALVADOR.

THIS HAS BEEN AN ACAN-EFE REPORT ON THE SITUATION IN SAN SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0900 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 29 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] THE FIGHTING IN THE SAN SALVADOR RESIDENTIAL AREAS BRINGS UP SUBSTANTIAL DIFFERENCES IN THE FORM AND CONTENT OF THE WAR IN EL SALVADOR WHEN THE FIGHTING TAKES PLACE IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE POOR AND WHEN THE FIGHTING TAKES PLACE IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE RICH. TODAY, WHEN THE FIGHTING TOOK PLACE IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE CAPITAL CITY, INCLUDING PLACES SUCH AS THE ESCALON, SAN BENITO, SAN FRANCISCO, AND GENERAL ARCE RESIDENTIAL AREAS WHERE U.S. DIPLOMATIC PERSONNEL LIVE, WHERE THE MILITARY OFFICERS AND GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS HAVE THEIR RESIDENCES, WHERE THE SALVADORAN HIGH SOCIETY HAS ITS RESIDENCES, THEN THE REPERCUSSIONS ARE VERY DIFFERENT.

U.S. GOVERNMENT SPOKESMEN REACTED QUICKLY AND WITHOUT DELAY. MARLIN FITZWATER, JAMES BAKER, THE STATE DEPARTMENT, AMBASSADOR WALKER, EVERYONE WAS VERY WORRIED OVER THE FATE OF U.S. PERSONNEL. THEY EXPRESSED ANGRY WORDS AGAINST THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. IF THERE IS SOMEONE IN THE WORLD THAT IS WELL INFORMED OF THE WAR SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR, IT IS PRECISELY THE PENTAGON, THE STATE DEPARTMENT, AND THE U.S. EMBASSY, BECAUSE THEY HAVE FINANCED AND GIVEN ADVICE TO THE SALVADORAN ARMY.

IT IS NOT OUR PRESENCE IN THE SAN SALVADOR RESIDENTIAL AREAS THAT JEOPARDIZES U.S. PERSONNEL. ON THE CONTRARY, IT IS THE U.S. PRESENCE, THE U.S. MEDDLING IN EL SALVADOR THAT IS JEOPARDIZING ITS STAFF. THEY CANNOT ASK US TO GET OUT OF SAN SALVADOR SO THAT THE AMERICANS WILL NOT BE TRAPPED IN THE CROSSFIRE. IT IS THE U.S. INTERVENTION IN THE COUNTRY THAT MUST COME TO AN END, SO THAT WE SALVADORANS WILL BE ABLE TO SETTLE OUR PROBLEMS AMONG OURSELVES. THIS IS OUR LAND, OUR FATHERLAND.

THE WAR WAS IMPOSED BY THE INJUSTICES, THE SLAUGHTERS, THE DICTATORSHIPS, AND TO A GREAT EXTENT, BY THE AMERICANS WHO SPEND $1.4 MILLION DAILY IN THIS WAR. THIS IS A CRUCIAL MOMENT FOR EL SALVADOR. THAT IS WHY WE DEMAND THAT THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION, THAT IS, THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION, THE U.S. CONGRESS, AND THE U.S. PEOPLE CAREFULLY THINK THIS OVER AND ACT SENSIBLY SO THAT WE WILL BE ABLE TO PUT AN END TO THIS WAR. IT IS IMPERATIVE THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT -- THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION -- THINK THIS OVER AND PROMOTE CHANGES IN ITS POLICY TOWARD EL SALVADOR, AND THUS MAKE FEASIBLE A SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT.

WE HAVE PUBLICLY AND OFFICIALLY SAID, AS ONE OF OUR MANY GESTURES OF GOOD WILL, THAT THE FMLN WILL NOT ATTACK U.S. DIPLOMATIC INSTALLATIONS OR PERSONNEL IN EL SALVADOR. IN ADDITION, WE HAVE INSTRUCTED OUR UNITS, OUR FIGHTERS, AND COMMANDO GROUPS NOT TO ATTACK DIPLOMATIC SITES, BECAUSE NATURALLY THEY ARE NOT MILITARY TARGETS FOR THE FMLN. WE HOPE THAT IN THE SAME MANNER, BOTH THE U.S. EMBASSY AS WELL AS THE OTHER DIPLOMATIC REPRESENTATIVES WILL INSTRUCT THEIR SECURITY GUARDS SO THEY WILL NOT BECOME INVOLVED IN THE FIGHTING, THUS PREVENTING CONFUSION THAT WE WOULD ALL REGRET.

THE U.S. GOVERNMENT CAN PLAY A POSITIVE ROLE IN DEFINING THE CONFLICT. THE U.S. CONGRESS AND OTHER INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS, SUCH AS THE UNITED NATIONS AND THE OAS, ARE ALREADY DISCUSSING THE TRUE SITUATION OF OUR COUNTRY. WE BELIEVE THIS IS THE MOMENT TO CHANGE POLICIES. THE U.S. GOVERNMENT CANNOT CONTINUE TO FINANCE AND SUPPORT A REGIME WHICH IS BOMBING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN THE CITIES, A REGIME WHICH MURDERS PRIESTS, WHICH PUBLICLY THREATENS THE BISHOPS. THE U.S. GOVERNMENT MUST USE ITS GOOD JUDGMENT AND CONTRIBUTE TO THE END OF THE WAR, AND NOT CONTINUE TO SUPPORT A FASCIST REGIME THAT IS NOT ACCEPTABLE IN OUR FATHERLAND, EL SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-0903 (GTE)

MOSCOW (USSR), 29 NOV 89 (RADIO PEACE AND PROGRESS) -- [COMMENTARY] [ALEKSEY PAVLOV] [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI ANNOUNCED LAST SUNDAY THAT THE REPUBLIC OF EL SALVADOR HAS BROKEN DIPLOMATIC TIES WITH NICARAGUA. ANALYST ALEKSEY PAVLOV DISCUSSES THIS SUBJECT:

FOR THOSE WHO ARE FAMILIAR WITH CENTRAL AMERICAN ISSUES, THIS NEWS IS NO SURPRISE. GIVEN THE FAILURE OF THE NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS AS WELL AS THE RESUMPTION OF THE WAR, THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION WAS PRESSURED BY CERTAIN U.S. CIRCLES TO BREAK RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA.

THE [WORD INDISTINCT] MEDIA ARE CONDUCTING A CRUSADE TO CONVINCE THE PUBLIC THAT CUBA, NICARAGUA, AND CERTAINLY THE USSR, ARE PROVIDING WEAPONS TO THE [WORD INDISTINCT] REVOLUTIONARIES. THE UNITED STATES CERTAINLY PLAYS AN IMPORTANT ROLE IN THIS CAMPAIGN, AND SO HAS PRESIDENT CRISTIANI BY DECLARING THAT HE WILL NOT ATTEND THE REGIONAL PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT SCHEDULED FOR DECEMBER IN MANAGUA.

APPARENTLY, CRISTIANI NEEDED TO BREAK RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA IN ORDER NOT TO ATTEND TO THE SUMMIT. THIS IS COMPREHENSIBLE BECAUSE THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS ARE SUPPOSED TO DISCUSS THE COMPLIANCE WITH THE TELA AGREEMENTS, THE DISMANTLING OF THE CONTRAS, AND THE CONTINUATION OF PEACE TALKS IN EL SALVADOR. IN FACT, CRISTIANI WAS UNABLE TO JUSTIFY HIS REFUSAL TO ATTEND THIS SUMMIT.

THERE ARE OTHER REASONS WHY CRISTIANI WISHES TO USE THE BREAK WITH NICARAGUA AS A MASK. HE IS TRYING TO DISTRACT PUBLIC ATTENTION FROM THE SALVADORAN ARMY'S HEAVY BOMBINGS OF HEAVILY POPULATED AREAS, INCLUDING THE CAPITAL, AND THE REPRESSION AGAINST SALVADORAN RELIGIOUS AND LABOR ORGANIZATIONS.

IN OTHER TERMS, CRISTIANI WANTS TO CONCEAL THE FACT THAT HE CANNOT CONTROL THE EXCESSES COMMITTED BY HIS GENERALS; THAT IS, THE GENOCIDE THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMY IS PERPETRATING AGAINST ITS OWN PEOPLE. THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION IS ALSO UNABLE TO CONTROL THE DEATH SQUADS WHICH ARE MURDERING PEOPLE WITH IMPUNITY.

IT IS REVEALING THAT SEVERAL DAYS BEFORE CRISTIANI DECLARED THE BREAK OF DIPLOMATIC TIES WITH NICARAGUA, NICARAGUAN EMBASSY STAFF IN SAN SALVADOR WERE EVACUATED HOME IN FACE OF THE DEATH THREATS BY THE DEATH SQUADS. IS THIS MERE COINCIDENCE? OF COURSE NOT. MOST PROBABLY THESE DEATH SQUADS RECEIVED ORDERS TO MAKE SUCH THREATS WITH A VIEW TOWARD THE DIPLOMATIC BREAK.

BY WHAT CAN BE SEEN, THE ACTION OF DEATH SQUADS IS COMMON PRACTICE FOR THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT. HOWEVER, THIS DIPLOMATIC BREAK IS A SERIOUS ACT FOR WHICH CRISTIANI IS LARGELY RESPONSIBLE. HONDURAN PRESIDENT JOSE AZCONA HOYO CONSIDERS THIS ACTION A GREAT DANGER TO PEACE IN THE ISTHMUS. THIS IS AN UNQUESTIONABLE FACT.

DEV-MUC3-0904 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, 30 NOV 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN] [TEXT] REGARDING THE INTERNATIONAL SCANDAL THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS MADE OVER AN ALLEGED SHIPMENT OF SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILES FOUND INSIDE A WRECKED LIGHT AIRCRAFT, THE FMLN EXPRESSES THE FOLLOWING:

1. IN VIEW OF A POSSIBLE INTENSIFICATION OF THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT, IT IS NECESSARY TO NOTE THAT THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES WERE THE FIRST ONES TO ESCALATE THE WAR BY LAUNCHING INDISCRIMINATE ATTACKS AND AIR BOMBINGS AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN DENSELY POPULATED URBAN AREAS. THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES HAD BEEN DOING THIS FOR SEVERAL YEARS IN OUR COUNTRY'S RURAL AREAS. IN VIEW OF THE DAMAGE THAT THIS CAUSES THE POPULATION, SINCE 1987 THE FMLN HAS MADE PROPOSALS TO SCALE DOWN THE WAR AND SUSPEND THE USE OF AIRCRAFT AND AVIATION EQUIPMENT.

THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT'S CHARGES ARE HYPOCRITICAL, AS THE GOVERNMENT ITSELF HAS TURNED AIRCRAFT INTO REAL INSTRUMENTS OF GENOCIDE AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

2. THE POLICY OF THE PREVIOUS U.S. ADMINISTRATION HAS TURNED CENTRAL AMERICA INTO A HUGE ARMS MARKET WHEREBY THOUSANDS OF TONS OF SOVIET AND U.S. WEAPONS, INCLUDING SURFACE-TO AIR MISSILES, HAVE BEEN INTRODUCED INTO THE AREA. THIS HAS CREATED A FLOURISHING BLACK MARKET FOR WEAPONS, WHERE SALVADORAN AND HONDURAN MILITARY MEN AND NICARAGUAN CONTRAS PARTICIPATE AS BIG-TIME SMUGGLERS.

3. THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS BEGUN A CAMPAIGN OF ACCUSATIONS AGAINST THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT WITH THE INTENTION OF PUTTING UP A SMOKE SCREEN TO COVER THE GENOCIDE IT HAS UNLEASHED AND TO DIVERT THE ATTENTION OF THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, WHICH HAS BEEN DEMANDING:

A) THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT STOP THE MASSIVE AND INDISCRIMINATE ATTACKS IN DENSELY POPULATED URBAN AREAS AND THE PERSECUTION AGAINST THE POLITICAL OPPOSITION AND GRASS ROOTS MOVEMENTS;

B) AN INVESTIGATION TO CLEAR UP THE MURDER OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND TWO DOMESTIC WORKERS, ALONG WITH THE PUNISHMENT OF THOSE RESPONSIBLE FOR THESE AND SIMILAR CRIMES; AND,

C) THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT ACCEPT THE CEASE-FIRE IT HAS HERETOFORE REJECTED AND JUSTIFY ITS INTRANSIGENT AND IRRATIONAL POSITION.

4. CRISTIANI'S DECISION TO SUSPEND RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA BASED ON AN ALLEGED SHIPMENT OF MISSILES FOR THE FMLN IS NOT REASONABLE, NOT EVEN BY SAYING THAT THIS REPRESENTS AN ESCALATION OF THE SALVADORAN WAR. IN FACT, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAS ESCALATED THE WAR BY SENDING $4 BILLION IN AID TO STRENGTHEN THE ARMY AND PROVIDE IT WITH A POWERFUL AIR FORCE.

THE JUSTIFICATION HAS ALWAYS BEEN NICARAGUA'S SUPPORT TO THE FMLN, THUS REFUSING TO ADMIT THE INTERNAL CAUSES OF THE CONFLICT AND ALSO KEEPING THE DOORS CLOSED TO ANY NEGOTIATIONS. THIS HAS UNNECESSARILY PROLONGED THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S SUFFERING AND HAS MADE MORE DRAMATIC THEIR LEGITIMATE STRUGGLE FOR A TRUE DEMOCRATIC, PLURALIST, AND NON-ALIGNED GOVERNMENT.

BASED ON THE ABOVE, WE REITERATE:

1. THAT WE CONSIDER ABSOLUTELY LEGITIMATE OUR RIGHT TO OBTAIN ALL TYPES OF WEAPONS TO GUARANTEE OUR DEFENSE AND TO PROTECT OUR PEOPLE FROM THE [WORD INDISTINCT] MILITARY ESCALATION PROMOTED BY THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT WITH THE FIRM SUPPORT OF THE PREVIOUS AND PRESENT U.S. GOVERNMENTS. THIS INCLUDES THE RIGHT TO OBTAIN WEAPONS FROM VARIOUS SOURCES AND TO GUARANTEE THEIR ARRIVAL AT OUR WAR FRONTS THROUGH ANY MEANS AVAILABLE.

2. WE MAINTAIN OUR TOTAL WILLINGNESS TO DE-ESCALATE THE WAR. WE BEGIN BY EXPRESSING THAT WE ARE TOTALLY WILLING TO AGREE ON A CEASE-FIRE WITH INTERNATIONAL SUPERVISION AND TO BEGIN REAL NEGOTIATIONS TO END THE WAR WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF ALL THE NATION'S POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES.

3. WE ARE WILLING TO REFRAIN FROM USING THE SURFACE-TO-AIR MISSILES IF THE AIR FORCE CALLS A COMPLETE HALT TO ITS BOMBINGS, STRAFING, AND MACHINEGUNNING THROUGHOUT THE NATIONAL TERRITORY.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

COMMANDERS JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, EDUARDO SANCHO, SALVADOR SANCHEZ SEREN, AND FRANCISCO JOVEL

EL SALVADOR, 29 NOVEMBER 1989

DEV-MUC3-0905 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THERE IS A TENSE CALM, INTERRUPTED BY SPORADIC SHOOTING, IN THE EXCLUSIVE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD OF THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL TODAY. AT THE SAME TIME, MANY FOREIGNERS ARE LEAVING THE NEIGHBORHOOD, WHICH WAS THE SITE OF HEAVY FIGHTING BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES AND GUERRILLAS YESTERDAY.

AN OFFICIAL OF THE UN OFFICE, WHICH IS LOCATED IN THE AREA OF FIGHTING, TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT "ALL THE PERSONNEL ARE FINE AND WE ARE NOW EVACUATING SOME EMPLOYEES AND FOREIGNERS LIVING IN THE AREA, TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THE CEASE-FIRE" THAT WAS ORDERED BY THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS FOR SEVERAL HOURS.

"WE HAVE NOT SEEN ANY GUERRILLAS. THE SOLDIERS ARE IN THE AREA AND ENTRANCE IS RESTRICTED. THEY ARE ONLY PERMITTING THE EVACUATION," THE OFFICIAL SAID OVER THE TELEPHONE.

A SPOKESMAN OF THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) SAID THIS MORNING THAT THE ELITE COUNTERINSURGENCY BELLOSO AND ATLACATL BATTALIONS AND TROOPS WITH ARTILLERY ARE CARRYING OUT A SPECIAL OPERATION IN ESCALON TO DISLODGE THE REBELS. THE SPOKESMAN SAID THE OPERATION WILL INCLUDE ALL OF NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR. HOWEVER, HE SAID HE COULD NOT PROVIDE FURTHER INFORMATION BECAUSE "WE ARE STILL COMPILING INFORMATION."

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) ON 29 NOVEMBER RESUMED ITS ATTACKS IN SAN SALVADOR, ESPECIALLY IN THE UPPER CLASS NEIGHBORHOODS OF ESCALON, SAN BENITO, AND MAQUILISHUAT AND THE MIDDLE CLASS NEIGHBORHOODS OF JARDIN GUADALUPE, LA CIMA, AND LOMAS DE SAN FRANCISCO.

AFTER SEVERAL HOURS OF FIGHTING IN THE STREETS OF THE NEIGHBORHOODS, THE ARMY SAID IT HAD THE SITUATION UNDER CONTROL. HOWEVER, IT ADMITTED THAT THE REBELS HAD ENTRENCHED THEMSELVES IN ESCALON AND HAD SEIZED "THE RESIDENTS AS HOSTAGES."

THE GUERRILLAS ANNOUNCED LAST NIGHT THAT FROM 0600 TO 1200 (1200 - 1800 GMT) TODAY, 30 NOVEMBER, THEY "WILL UNDERTAKE THE EVACUATION OF FOREIGN PERSONNEL" IN THE ESCALON AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR. THE FMLN SAID THE MEASURE, WHICH IS BEING HEEDED BY THE FOREIGNERS LIVING IN THOSE AREAS, IS TO GUARANTEE THE LIVES OF THE RESIDENTS OF ESCALON.

VARIOUS SOURCES SAID THE REBELS HAVE LEFT ESCALON, BUT THIS INFORMATION HAS YET TO BE CONFIRMED.

DEV-MUC3-0906 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 NOV 89 (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [TEXT] THE CLANDESTINE AND LIAR RADIO STATIONS OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORISTS CONTINUE TO CONDUCT A DISINFORMATION CAMPAIGN AT AN INTERNATIONAL LEVEL WITH THE PURPOSE OF DISTORTING THE TRUTH REGARDING THE AGGRESSION THESE BANDITS HAVE LAUNCHED AGAINST THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

VERY FREQUENTLY THEY BROADCAST REPORTS OF UNIMAGINABLE MILITARY VICTORIES OF THE FMLN. THEIR LIAR RADIO STATIONS SAY THEY HAVE OCCUPIED THE MUNICIPALITIES OF SOYAPANGO, MEJICANOS, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, CIUDAD DELGADO, AND OTHERS, WHICH, DESPITE THE TRAGEDY WE ARE SUFFERING, MAKES PEOPLE BURST OUT LAUGHING BECAUSE EVERYONE KNOWS THESE ARE BIG LIES. THESE CLAIMS ARE ABSOLUTELY FALSE. THE RESIDENTS OF THOSE MUNICIPALITIES ARE GOING TO THEIR JOBS, BUSES ARE OPERATING, AND EVERYDAY ACTIVITIES ARE BEING CONDUCTED IN A NORMAL MANNER.

THE LIAR RADIO STATIONS OF THE FMLN THINK THEY CAN CONFUSE THE PUBLIC OPINION WITH THEIR FALSE INFORMATION. THESE STATIONS ARE USED FOR PROPAGANDISTIC AND DISINFORMATION PURPOSES TO MAKE IT APPEAR AS IF THE FMLN IS WINNING MILITARY VICTORIES, WHICH THEY HAVE NEVER ATTAINED AND WHICH ARE ONLY IN THE MINDS OF ORTEGA'S PUPPETS, WHO BROADCAST FROM MANAGUA.

THE PEOPLE ARE ASKING THEMSELVES: WHERE ARE THE COWARDLY TERRORIST AND MURDEROUS CHIEFS OF THE FMLN, SHAFIK HANDAL, JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, AND OTHER COWARDS, WHO ARE IN MANAGUA ENJOYING A LUXURIOUS LIFE AND GOOD FOOD?

THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE ARE FULLY AWARE OF THE VICTORIOUS ACTIONS OF OUR ARMED FORCES, WHO SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THIS GENOCIDAL AND TERRORIST FMLN OFFENSIVE HAVE FACED THE AGGRESSIVE MERCENARIES BY REDUCING THEM TO SMALL TERRORIST GROUPS, WHICH ARE LOST AND ARE IRRATIONALLY ATTACKING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

THE FMLN HAS RIDICULOUSLY CLAIMED TO COMPLETELY CONTROL CERTAIN MUNICIPALITIES. ALL OF THESE LIES SHOW THAT THE MURDEROUS FMLN LEADERS DO NOT HAVE ANY ARGUMENTS WITH WHICH TO CONCEAL THEIR UNSUCCESSFUL REBEL OFFENSIVE.

THEIR GREATEST FAILURE HAS BEEN THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S REJECTION OF THE REBEL ACTIONS. DESPITE SO MANY THREATS MADE BY THE FMLN TERRORISTS, OUR PEOPLE HAVE NEVER SUPPORTED THEM, LET ALONE AGREED TO ACCEPT THE WEAPONS THAT THE FMLN WERE OFFERING THEM IF THEY JOINED THE REBELLION. THE FMLN AND ITS TERRORIST OFFENSIVE, WHICH WAS CONDUCTED WITH THE WEAPONS THAT DICTATOR ORTEGA HAS GIVEN TO THE FMLN PUPPETS, HAS FAILED, AND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE EXPECT THE NATIONS OF THE FREE WORLD TO CONDEMN THIS GENOCIDAL AGGRESSION OF INTERNATIONAL COMMUNISM.

DEV-MUC3-0907 (GTE)

MOSCOW (USSR), 1 DEC 89 (PRAVDA) -- [COMMENTARY] [PAVEL BOGOMOLOV] [TEXT] JUDGING BY NEWS AGENCY REPORTS, THE DEVELOPMENT OF EVENTS IN EL SALVADOR HAS REACHED AN EXTREMELY DANGEROUS POINT. PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S REFUSAL TO RESPOND TO THE INSURGENTS' RECENT CEASE- FIRE PROPOSAL HAS RESULTED IN A FRESH OUTBREAK OF BLOODSHED.

HAVING REJECTED OUT OF HAND LAST WEEK THE VERY IDEA OF THE RESUMPTION OF TALKS WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI LIBERATION MOVEMENT, THE GOVERNMENT HAS MADE NO SECRET OF ITS INTENTION OF QUICKLY DRIVING THE GUERRILLAS BACK INTO THE MOUNTAINS USING U.S. MILITARY SUPPLIES. "ELITE" ARMY BATTALIONS HAD ALREADY PREPARED FOR PUNITIVE ASSAULTS. BUT WHAT HAPPENED? THE REGIME'S GAMBLE ON MILITARY FORCE PROVED FUTILE. THE INSURGENTS REGROUPED THEIR FORCES, BROUGHT UP RESERVES, AND STRUCK A POWERFUL NEW BLOW.

THE SALVADORAN DRAMA IS INCREASINGLY SHARPLY AT VARIANCE WITH THE IMPROVEMENT OF THE INTERNATIONAL CLIMATE. REPRESENTATIVES OF THE UNITED NATIONS, THE OAS, THE EEC, THE VATICAN, FRANCE, AND A NUMBER OF OTHER COUNTRIES AND ORGANIZATIONS ARE NOW STRESSING THE ACUTE NEED TO URGE THE WARRING SIDES IN EL SALVADOR TO REACH A PEACEFUL SETTLEMENT BASED ON MUTUAL COMPROMISE. AND IT IS A VERY GREAT PITY THAT SUCH AN APPEAL HAS NOT COME FROM THAT CAPITAL WHICH THE SALVADORAN AUTHORITIES HEED ABOVE ALL OTHERS -- WASHINGTON.

ATTENTION IS DRAWN TO THE URGENT EVACUATION OF U.S. CITIZENS FROM EL SALVADOR THAT WAS ANNOUNCED YESTERDAY. I RECOGNIZE THAT IN THE CONDITIONS OF AN ARMED CONFLICT THIS IS A NECESSARY STEP. BUT IT IS NO SECRET THAT IN THE RECENT PAST SUCH ACTIONS BY THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION WERE AN OMINOUS SYMPTOM OF THE PREPARATION OF OVERTLY INTERVENTIONIST PLANS.

END THE BLOODSHED -- THAT IS THE PRIORITY TASK TODAY. AND THE RESTORATION OF THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE INSURGENTS THAT WAS BROKEN OFF SHOULD BE THE FIRST STEP TOWARD THAT.

DEV-MUC3-0909 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] IMMIGRATION DIRECTOR COLONEL MAXIMILIANO LEIVA REPORTED TODAY THAT 7 FOREIGNERS HAVE BEEN DEPORTED FROM EL SALVADOR AND 14 WILL HAVE TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY WITHIN THE NEXT FEW HOURS AFTER BEING DECLARED "PERSONA NON GRATA" FOR ALLEGEDLY COLLABORATING WITH THE GUERRILLAS.

LEIVA TOLD ACAN - EFE THAT AN UNDETERMINED NUMBER OF FOREIGNERS HAVE BEEN REMANDED TO THE COURTS, CHARGED WITH ARMS POSSESSION OR FOR TAKING PART IN ARMED ACTIONS IN COMPLICITY WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN). LEIVA SAID THAT THE SEVEN DEPORTEES WILL BE "PERMANENTLY" BANNED SO THEY WILL NOT BE ABLE TO RETURN TO EL SALVADOR.

AMONG THE DEPORTED ARE U.S. CITIZENS, DUTCH, GERMANS, AND JAPANESE, ADDED LEIVA. THE SALVADORAN OFFICIAL DID NOT RELEASE THE NAMES OF THE DEPORTEES OR THE FOREIGNERS WHO WILL HAVE TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY IN THE NEXT FEW HOURS.

JENNIFER CASOLO, A U.S. CITIZEN, WAS ARRESTED BY THE SECURITY CORPS AND ACCUSED OF "ARMS POSSESSION." GRABRIELA TORNAGO, AN ITALIAN, WAS ARRESTED AND ACCUSED OF "FINANCING, RECRUITING, AND BEING INVOLVED WITH TERRORIST GROUPS."

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES, CASOLA WAS ARRESTED AT DAYBREAK ON 26 NOVEMBER AT A HOUSE LOCATED IN THE "MIRAVALLE" NEIGHBORHOOD, WHERE THE ARMY CLAIMS TO HAVE FOUND A GREAT AMOUNT OF WEAPONS. TORNAGO WAS ARRESTED MORE THAN A WEEK AGO IN THE "PRADOS DE VENECIA" NEIGHBORHOOD. POLICE SOURCES SAID THAT THE ITALIAN WAS PREPARING A FAKE WEDDING AT HER RESIDENCE TO GATHER PEOPLE LINKED WITH THE GUERRILLAS, WHO ON 11 NOVEMBER STARTED AN ALLEGED "INSURRECTION."

LEIVA ASSURED THAT THE FOREIGNERS WHO ARE LINKED TO THE GUERRILLAS WILL BE REMANDED TO THE COURTS BY THE SECURITY FORCE THAT MAKES THE ARREST.

DEV-MUC3-0911 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 NOV 89 (ACAN - EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES STATED THIS EVENING THAT THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE "HAS FAILED AND HAS NOT REPRESENTED A MILITARY THREAT" TO THE ARMY FOLLOWING 19 DAYS OF STRONG REBEL ATTACKS IN THE FRAMEWORK OF 10 YEARS OF WAR.

ARMY SPOKESMAN MAJOR MAURICIO CHAVEZ CACERES SAID THAT "FOLLOWING THE FAILURE OF THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE WHICH HAD BEEN PREPARED FOR OVER A YEAR, WHAT WE CAN EXPECT FROM THEM (THE REBELS) IS ATTACKS ON PROMINENT PEOPLE AND ON THE ECONOMIC INFRASTRUCTURE, AND ACTIONS TO SCARE THE POPULATION."

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] RENEWED ITS ATTACKS EARLY ON 29 NOVEMBER WHEN IT ATTACKED THE COUNTRY'S MOST IMPORTANT MILITARY INSTALLATION AND SET FIRE TO A RESIDENCE OF U.S. MILITARY ADVISERS AND CONFRONTED THE ARMY IN EXCLUSIVE NEIGHBORHOODS IN NORTHWEST SAN SALVADOR.

FORMER FOREIGN MINISTER AND PRESIDENT OF THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE FRANCISCO JOSE GUERRERO DIED ON 28 NOVEMBER WHEN HE WAS STRAFFED BY GUERRILLAS, ACCORDING TO MILITARY SOURCES. THIS TOOK PLACE HOURS BEFORE THE RENEWED FIGHTING WHICH PRODUCED 40 CASUALTIES AMONG GUERRILLAS AND SOLDIERS.

IN AN OFFICIAL RADIO AND TELEVISION BROADCAST, CHAVEZ CACERES TODAY ACCUSED THE FMLN OF DESTROYING SOME RESIDENCES IN THE EXCLUSIVE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD WITH DYNAMITE, IN NORTHWEST SAN SALVADOR, AND OF FIRING ON PRIVATE VEHICLES IN HIGH- AND MIDDLE-CLASS SAN SALVADOR NEIGHBORHOODS.

THE MILITARY SPOKESMAN SAID: "THEY (THE REBELS) HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO DEAL A MILITARY BLOW; THEY HAVE NOT BEEN ABLE TO PUT UP A FIGHT WITH A SINGLE ARMY BATTALION OR COMPANY."

THE FMLN GUERRILLAS TODAY VACATED THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD AFTER HOLDING, FOR OVER 24 HOURS, SEVERAL HOUSES THERE, FROM WHICH THEY CONFRONTED THE GOVERNMENT TROOPS.

THE FMLN ANNOUNCED A TRUCE FROM 0600 TO 1200 (1200 TO 1800 GMT) TODAY TO EVACUATE FOREIGNERS, DIPLOMATS, AND CIVILIAN RESIDENTS FROM ESCALON.

OVER 200 U.S. CITIZENS LEFT TODAY FOR THE UNITED STATES BECAUSE OF THE FIGHTING, PARTICULARLY IN ESCALON, A RESIDENTIAL AREA IN WHICH DIPLOMATS, HIGH-RANKING GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, AND POWERFUL BUSINESSMEN LIVE.

SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE ON 11 NOVEMBER, APPROXIMATELY 2,000 PEOPLE HAVE DIED AND HUNDREDS HAVE BEEN WOUNDED IN THE FIGHTING BETWEEN SOLDIERS AND REBELS, WHICH HAS ALSO RESULTED IN SEVERE ECONOMIC LOSSES.

DEV-MUC3-0912 (GTE)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 1 DEC 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] DOMINICAN ORDER SUPERIOR JUAN CARLOS FERNANDEZ CID REPORTED IN MANAGUA TODAY THAT A SPANISH PRIEST AND FOUR WORKERS OF THE DOMINICAN ORDER -- THREE SALVADORANS AND ONE U.S. CITIZEN -- WERE ARRESTED IN SAN SALVADOR ON 30 NOVEMBER.

THE DOMINICAN SUPERIOR TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT THE SPANISH PRIEST CARLOS DIEZ ROJO; SALVADORANS JOSE SANTANA, THE DRIVER; ESTELA CRUZ BUSTAMANTE, DIRECTOR OF THE ORDER'S CHILD CARE CENTER; AND SANTIAGO DE JESUS VASQUEZ, DIRECTOR OF THE "22 APRIL" NEIGHBORHOOD CHOIR; AS WELL AS A U.S. VOLUNTEER CALLED SCOTT, WERE STILL UNDER ARREST IN SAN SALVADOR TODAY.

HE STATED THAT HE HAD CONTACTED SPANISH EMBASSY OFFICIALS IN SAN SALVADOR THIS MORNING, AND THEY CONFIRMED THAT THE SAN SALVADOR TREASURY POLICE HAD ARRESTED THE PRIEST DIEZ ROJO AND THE FOUR WORKERS.

ACCORDING TO FERNANDEZ CID, A GROUP OF POLICEMEN RAIDED THE PARISH CENTER IN CIUDAD CREDISA, A SAN SALVADOR NEIGHBORHOOD, AND ARRESTED THE FIVE PERSONS AFTER CONDUCTING A SEARCH.

THE PRIEST WAS VISITING SAN SALVADOR AND HAD ARRIVED IN THE CITY 2 DAYS BEFORE THE GUERRILLAS LAUNCHED THEIR OFFENSIVE ON 11 NOVEMBER.

A SPANISH EMBASSY OFFICIAL IN SAN SALVADOR IS PRESENTLY MAKING EFFORTS TO VISIT CARLOS DIEZ AND THE OTHER PERSONS ARRESTED, IN THE PRESENCE OF SALVADORAN OFFICIALS.

WITHOUT ANY OFFICIAL EXPLANATIONS, TWO PRIESTS OF THE DOMINICAN ORDER -- SPANISH CITIZEN MIGUEL ANDUEZ AND THE U.S. CITIZEN JAIME BARNEE -- WERE EXPELLED FROM EL SALVADOR 5 DAYS AGO.

ON 16 NOVEMBER, SIX JESUIT PRIESTS -- FIVE SPANIARDS AND ONE SALVADORAN -- AND TWO WOMEN WERE MURDERED BY 30 MEN IN UNIFORMS WHO WERE HEAVILY ARMED.

DEV-MUC3-0914 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 1 DEC 89 (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [SALVADORAN NATIONAL COMMUNICATION SECRETARIAT] [TEXT] FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] GUERRILLAS FIRED A SAM-7 MISSILE ON 29 NOVEMBER FROM ZACATECOLUCA AND ON 30 NOVEMBER FIRED A SIMILAR MISSILE, ALSO FROM ZACATECOLUCA. BOTH MISSED THEIR TARGETS.

THE AIR FORCES OFFICERS INVOLVED REPORTED THAT IN BOTH CASES THE SAM-7 MISSILES WERE DETECTED BY OBSERVER PLANES, WHICH IN TURN WARNED THE TWO SALVADORAN AIR FORCE A-37 PLANES THAT THE MISSILES WERE HEADED TOWARD THEM. THE TWO PLANES WERE FLYING PATROL MISSIONS IN THE ZACATECOLUCA AREA. BOTH SAM-7 MISSILES FAILED TO STRIKE THEIR TARGETS THANKS TO THE PROFESSIONALISM OF THE PILOTS, WHO MANEUVERED TO PREVENT THE FMLN MISSILES FROM HITTING THEM.

THE FMLN CONTINUES TO RECEIVE SOVIET ARMS SUPPLIES THROUGH CUBA AND NICARAGUA, AN ACTION WHICH HAS ALREADY BEEN OFFICIALLY DENOUNCED TO THE ENTIRE WORLD AND WHICH THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE FULLY REPUDIATE. THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT HAS SUPPLIED THE FMLN TERRORISTS WITH THIS TYPE OF SOPHISTICATED WEAPONRY OF SOVIET MANUFACTURE, WHICH CONFIRMS THAT THE FMLN, APART FROM HAVING ITS GENERAL COMMAND INSIDE NICARAGUAN TERRITORY, HAS THE MILITARY SUPPORT AND GUIDANCE OF THE SANDINIST REGIME. OFFICIAL SOURCES BELIEVE THAT THE SAM-7 MISSILES FIRED BY THE FMLN AGAINST THE AIR FORCE PLANES COULD BE AMONG THE WEAPONS THAT WERE ONBOARD THE OTHER SMALL PLANE THAT WAS SET ON FIRE BY THE TERRORISTS AFTER THEY HAD UNLOADED IT.

AS SOON AS THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT LEARNED OF THE SAM-7 SHIPMENTS TO THE FMLN, THEY REPORTED IT TO THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY. IN RESPONSE TO THIS REPORT, THE SOVIET GOVERNMENT, SHOWING GREAT ANNOYANCE, ORDERED A FREEZE ON ALL ARMS SHIPMENTS TO THE ORTEGA GOVERNMENT, WHICH, FOLLOWING ORDERS FROM FIDEL CASTRO, SUPPLIES MILITARY EQUIPMENT TO THE FMLN TERRORISTS. IT HAS ALSO BEEN REPORTED THAT AN INVESTIGATION IS UNDER WAY ON THE PARTICIPATION OF MERCENARIES FROM DIFFERENT COUNTRIES WHO ARE FIGHTING ALONGSIDE THE FMLN, CAUSING THE GENOCIDE OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

DEV-MUC3-0917 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 NOV 89 (DIARIO LATINO) -- [TEXT] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE HAS SAID THAT IN LIGHT OF THE POSSIBILITY OF THE USE OF MISSILES BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE IS TAKING PRECAUTIONS AND HAS CHANGED ITS FLIGHT TACTICS OR ADOPTED NEW ONES.

"THE ARMED FORCES IS DETERMINED TO CONFRONT THEM, AND TO ACHIEVE THEIR GOAL THE REBELS WILL HAVE TO STEP OVER THE BODIES OF EVERY SINGLE SOLDIER," COL PONCE SAID.

COL PONCE ALSO SAID THAT THE ARREST OF U.S. CITIZEN JENNIFER JEAN CASOLO, WHO WAS COVERING UP AN FMLN SAFEHOUSE, IS A HARD BLOW TO THE TERRORISTS BECAUSE CASOLO WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR BRINGING CONGRESSIONAL STAFF AND REPRESENTATIVES OF CHURCHES AND OTHER ORGANIZATIONS INTO THE COUNTRY. THESE PEOPLE APPARENTLY CAME TO THE COUNTRY TO PROVIDE HUMANITARIAN AID TO THE DISPLACED.

PONCE ALSO SAID THAT MANY INTERNATIONALISTS JOIN THE TERRORIST GROUPS, THUS VIOLATING THE RIGHTS OF ALL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. PONCE SAID THAT THE LEADERS OF THE FRONT GROUPS DEFINED THEIR POSITIONS WHEN THEY JOINED THE FMLN TO CARRY OUT THE SO-CALLED FINAL OFFENSIVE, WHICH HAS PROVEN TO BE A TOTAL FAILURE BECAUSE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE BELIEVE IN DEMOCRACY AND NOT COMMUNISM.

THE CHIEF OF THE GENERAL STAFF ALSO MET WITH FOREIGN CORRESPONDENTS. HE SAID THAT THE FMLN CURRENTLY HAS THE SUPPORT OF ONLY NICARAGUA, CUBA, AND RUSSIA [AS PUBLISHED ], BUT THEY DO NOT HAVE THE ESSENTIAL SUPPORT OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE; THEREFORE, THYE ARE DOOMED TO POLITICAL-MILITARY FAILURE. ALL THE FMLN HAS LEFT IS ITS PROPAGANDA TACTICS AT THE NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL LEVEL.

COL PONCE TALKED ABOUT THE CASUALTIES INFLICTED ON THE FMLN TERRORISTS THROUGH 0600 [1200 GMT] ON 28 NOVEMBER. PONCE SAID THAT 1,680 REBELS HAD BEEN KILLED AND MORE THAN DOUBLE THAT NUMBER WOUNDED. COL PONCE ADDED THAT THE ARMY REGRETS THE HEROIC DEATHS OF 398 SOLDIERS AND APPROXIMATELY 800 WOUNDED IN CLASHES SINCE 11 NOVEMBER.

DEV-MUC3-0919 (GTE)

SAN SALVADOR, 1 DEC 89 (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [TEXT] THE NATIONAL GUARD HAS CAPTURED THE ACTUAL PERPETRATORS, AS WELL AS ACCOMPLICES AND HARBORERS, IN THE CASE OF THE ATTACK ON THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF ON 30 OCTOBER.

THE NATIONAL GUARD REPORTED THAT IT ARRESTED 15 PEOPLE LAST WEEK AT VARIOUS PLACES IN HERE IN SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER PERSONS AT THE OFFICES OF THE SO-CALLED AWARENESS FOR SPIRITUAL AND ECONOMIC RECOVERY OF MAN [CONCIENTIZACION PARA RECUPERACION ESPIRITUAL Y ECONOMICA DEL HOMBRE, CREDHO], AT THE EPISCOPAL CHURCH ON 63 SOUTH AVENUE AND OLIMPICA AVENUE IN SAN SALVADOR. SEVERAL PERSONS WHO WERE HELD HOSTAGE THERE ON 30 OCTOBER LATER APPEARED AT THE CENTRAL POLICE HEADQUARTERS TO REPORT THE ABUSE.

WHEN NATIONAL GUARD PERSONNEL BEGAN THE SUBSEQUENT INVESTIGATION THAT SAME DAY, IT WAS DISCOVERED THAT THE ARRESTED PERSONS HAD COMMITTED OTHER ACTIONS IN VIOLATION OF OUR LAWS AND AGAINST THE COUNTRY'S SECURITY. AFTER DETERMINING THAT THIS EPISCOPAL CHURCH WAS VISITED BY PERSONS INVOLVED IN SUBVERSIVE ACTIVITIES AND THAT IT HARBORED A GROUP THAT IS AN FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] FRONT, THE PLACE WAS SEARCH AND IT WAS DISCOVERED THAT, IN ADDITION TO THE CHURCH, OFFICES OF CREDHO ALSO OPERATED THERE -- CREDHO IS AN AFFILIATE OF AN ORGANIZATION THEY CALL DIACOMIAS; THAT 60 PERSONS ARE EMPLOYED THERE; THAT MOST OF THOSE PERSONS ARE NOT PARISHIONERS, BUT CREDHO EMPLOYEES; THAT CREDHO'S DIRECTOR IS A PRIEST OF SPANISH ORIGIN NAMED LUIS SERRANO LORENTE; AND THAT THIS PRIEST IS NOW A NATURALIZED SALVADORAN.

THERE THE NATIONAL GUARD PERSONNEL ARRESTED JOSE HORACIO GUZMAN RIVAS, JOSE EDUARDO SANCHEZ CASTILLO, LUIS GUSTAVO LOPEZ MAGANA, JOSE VIDAL ENAMORADO DIAZ, ELBA RUTH ALFARO VALENCIA, ALEX ANTONIO TOVAR FLORES, JOSE CANDELARIO AGUILAR ALVAREZ, AND RANDOLFO CAMPO BENAVIDES. IN CONNECTION WITH THE SAME CASE, THEY ALSO ARRESTED JUAN ANTONIO VERSICO NUNEZ, ANA JULIO RODRIGUEZ, AND JOSE FRANCISCO PASTORANGES AT VARIOUS PLACES IN THE CIUDAD SATELITE NEIGHBORHOOD. LATER ON, LUIS SERRANO LORENTE, PASTOR OF THIS ANGLICAN CHURCH, WAS ARRESTED IN THE LOMAS VERDES NEIGHBORHOOD. JULIO CESAR CASTRO RAMIREZ AND JULIO EUGENIA AGUILERA ESCOBAR WERE LATER ARRESTED IN SANTA ANA, AND, LASTLY, AIDA MARGARITA GOMEZ DE LEON WAS ARRESTED IN THE DON BOSCO RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOOD IN SANTA TECLA.

SERRANO SAID HE IS THE DIRECTOR OF CREDHO AND RESPONSIBLE FOR THE AFOREMENTIONED CHURCH. HE ASSERTED THAT HE LEARNED ON 29 OCTOBER THAT IN THE CHURCHYARD TWO TRUCKS WERE LOADED WITH EXPLOSIVES, WHICH WERE HURLED THE NEXT DAY AT THE MILITARY COMPLEX OF THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF. HE DECIDED TO REMAIN SILENT ABOUT THIS, THEREBY COVERING FOR THE TERRORIST CRIMINALS WHO MURDER HUMBLE WORKING PEOPLE. SERRANO ALSO SAID THAT CREDHO IS FINANCED BY A FRONT GROUP CALLED DIACOMIAS, WHICH HAS NO LEGAL STATUS, BUT IS THE CHANNEL FOR AID THAT IS SENT IN CASH BY SO-CALLED SOLIDARITY CHURCHES AND ASSOCIATIONS ORGANIZED IN SWEDEN, BRITAIN, NETHERLANDS, CANADA, THE UNITED STATES, AND AUSTRALIA. THIS MONEY IS DISTRIBUTED TO LUTHERAN, CATHOLIC, EMANUEL BAPTIST, AND EPISCOPAL CHURCHES, AS WELL AS TO THE FOUNDATION FOR PROMOTION OF COOPERATIVES [FUNDACION PROMOTORA DE COOPERATIVAS, FUNPROCOOP] AND THE FEDERATION OF COOPERATIVES FOR DEVELOPMENT [FEDERACION DE COOPERATIVAS PARA EL DESARROLLO, FEDECOOPADE]. THESE GROUPS COMPRISE DIACOMIAS AND TWICE A MONTH, ONE REPRESENTATIVE FROM EACH GROUP MEETS AT THE EPISCOPAL CHURCH TO DISCUSS DISTRIBUTION OF THESE LARGE AMOUNTS OF MONEY, MOST OF WHICH, HE SAID, IS DELIVERED TO LOW INCOME COMMUNITIES THEY HAVE ORGANIZED THAT ARE DIRECTED BY THE FMLN FRONT GROUPS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0920 (GTE)

BOGOTA, 1 DEC 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] FELLOW PATRIOTS, I AM ADDRESSING THE NATION TODAY TO EXPLAIN THE GOVERNMENT'S POSITION CONCERNING THE ISSUE OF EXTRADITION, WHICH WAS THE SUBJECT OF A VERY INTENSE DEBATE LAST NIGHT AT THE CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES' FIRST COMMISSION.

A PROPOSAL WAS PUT FORWARD TO THE EFFECT THAT IN THE EXTRAORDINARY REFERENDUM SCHEDULED FOR 21 JANUARY -- WHICH IS CONTEMPLATED IN THE CONSTITUTIONAL REFORM THAT IS CURRENTLY IN ITS FINAL STAGES -- AN ADDITIONAL QUESTION BE INCLUDED WITH REGARD TO WHETHER OR NOT YOU, THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE, WANT COLOMBIAN CRIMINALS TO BE EXTRADITED.

THIS QUESTION WOULD JOIN FOUR OTHER ISSUES THAT HAD ALREADY BEEN APPROVED FOR SUBMISSION TO POPULAR CONSULTATION ON 21 JANUARY. ON BEHALF OF THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT, THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER IMMEDIATELY EXPRESSED THE DISADVANTAGES OF APPROVING THAT PROPOSAL.

I HAVE CONSULTED WITH FORMER PRESIDENTS ALBERTO LLERAS, CARLOS LLERAS RESTREPO, ALFONSO LOPEZ, AND JULIO CESAR TURBAY ABOUT INCLUDING THE EXTRADITION ISSUE IN THE REFERENDUM, AND THEY FEEL THAT WITH THE CURRENT PUBLIC ORDER SITUATION, ESPECIALLY WHEN THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN DEALING SUCCESSFULLY WITH THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, IT WOULD BE DISADVANTAGEOUS TO USE THE REFERENDUM TO DECIDE ON EXTRADITION.

THE COUNTRY MUST NOT DECEIVE ITSELF AS TO WHERE WE WOULD BE HEADED IF WE HELD A REFERENDUM ON THE ISSUE OF EXTRADITION, AND AS TO THE FATAL CONSEQUENCES OF SUCH AN ACTION ON THE COUNTRY'S MORALE AND ON DEMOCRACY'S SURVIVAL.

INITIALLY, I AM NOT TALKING ABOUT EXTRADITING COLOMBIAN CRIMINALS FOR THEM TO STAND TRIAL IN OTHER COUNTRIES, BUT OF EXTRADITING DRUG TRAFFICKERS WHO HAVE COMMITTED CRIMES ABROAD. EXTRADITION IS NOT PUNISHMENT FOR SOCIETY BECAUSE IT REFERS ONLY TO DRUG TRAFFICKERS, NEITHER IS IT AN AFFRONT TO SOVEREIGNTY, AS SOME PEOPLE HAVE TRIED TO PORTRAY IT.

EXTRADITION HAS BEEN DEALT WITH IN COLOMBIAN INTERNATIONAL TREATIES. THE DIRECTION OF INTERNATIONAL POLICY LIES WITHIN THE EXCLUSIVE REALM OF THE PRESIDENCY OF THE REPUBLIC, ACCORDING TO THE CONSTITUTION. CONGRESS CANNOT TAKE THE INITIATIVE OF ABOLISHING PUBLIC EXTRADITION TREATIES BY RESORTING TO LEGISLATIVE OR CONSTITUENT PROVISIONS. THIS IS CLEAR IN LIGHT OF COLOMBIAN PUBLIC LAW, AND IT IS IMPERATIVE ACCORDING TO THE VIENNA CONVENTION, WHICH COLOMBIA RECENTLY APPROVED. ACCORDING TO THIS CONVENTION, THE EXTRADITION TREATY WILL PREVAIL OVER INTERNAL PROVISIONS. IN OTHER WORDS, THE TREATIES THAT COLOMBIA HAS SIGNED WITH REGARD TO EXTRADITION CANNOT BE DISREGARDED THROUGH INTERNAL LEGISLATION. THIS CAN ONLY BE DONE THROUGH DIPLOMATIC EFFORTS SUCH AS DENOUNCING THE TREATIES AND DIRECTLY INFORMING THE COUNTERPART.

FOR 100 YEARS COLOMBIAN LAW HAS AUTHORIZED THE EXTRADITION OF CRIMINALS. I REPEAT, 100 YEARS, SINCE 1888, AND ONLY NOW, WHEN EXTRADITION IS APPLIED TO DRUG TRAFFICKERS, ARE THERE OBJECTIONS TO ITS ALLEGED VIOLATIONS OF SOVEREIGNTY. PRACTICALLY ALL THE COUNTRIES OF THE WORLD, WITH VERY FEW EXCEPTION, HAVE AND APPLY TREATIES TO EXTRADITE TERRORISTS OR WHOMEVER COMMITS CRIMES AGAINST HUMANITY, SUCH AS DRUG TRAFFICKING.

OVER THE PAST 10 YEARS, NO MORE THAN 30 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN EXTRADITED TO SEVERAL COUNTRIES THAT REQUESTED THE EXTRADITIONS AND COMPLIED WITH THE NECESSARY LAWS. THEREFORE, EXTRADITION IS NOT A GENERAL THREAT AGAINST ALL COLOMBIANS. IT ONLY AFFECTS THOSE WHO HAVE COMMITTED THE CRIME OF DRUG TRAFFICKING ABROAD. SECONDLY, SOME PEOPLE HAVE SAID THAT EXTRADITION HAS CREATED VIOLENCE AND, THEREFORE, WITH ITS ELIMINATION, VIOLENCE WOULD DISAPPEAR. NEITHER IS TRUE.

THE VIOLENCE PERPETRATED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAD BEEN SUFFERED PRIOR TO THE 1979 EXTRADITION TREATY. AFTER THE TREATY WENT INTO EFFECT, HUNDREDS OF COLOMBIANS WERE MURDERED, INCLUDING JUSTICE MINISTER RODRIGO LARA BONILLA. IN DECEMBER 1986, A SUPREME COURT DECISION LEFT THE EXTRADITION TREATY INAPPLICABLE. IN OTHER WORDS, AFTER THIS, WHILE EXTRADITION WAS INAPPLICABLE, ATTORNEY GENERAL CARLOS MAURO HOYOS WAS SLAIN, BOGOTA MAYOR ANDRES PASTRANA WAS KIDNAPPED, AND NEWSMAN GUILLERMO CANO, POLITICAL LEADER JAIME PARDO LEAL, AND HUNDREDS OF COLOMBIANS WERE SACRIFICED. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0921 (GTE)

BOGOTA, 1 DEC 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] LAST YEAR, WITHOUT EXTRADITION IN EFFECT, OVER 600 ANONYMOUS COLOMBIAN PEASANTS WERE MURDERED IN MORE THAN 40 MASSACRES BY HIRED ASSASSINS PAID BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS. THERE IS EVEN MORE: LET US NOT FORGET ANTIOQUIA GOVERNOR ANTONIO ROLDAN BETANCUR, MAGISTRATE CARLOS VALENCIA, COLONEL FRANKLYN QUINTERO, AND SENATOR LUIS CARLOS GALAN WHO WERE MURDERED WHEN EXTRADITION WAS NOT IN EFFECT. LET US NOT SAY THAT EXTRADITION HAS BROUGHT US VIOLENCE. A POSTER FOUND AT THE FARM RAIDED LAST WEEK, FROM WHERE PABLO ESCOBAR ESCAPED READ: EXTRADITION IS VIOLENCE. LET US NOT BE FOOLED; VIOLENCE HAS BEEN USED BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS BY MURDERING, WHILE FLEEING FROM THE REACTION OF JUSTICE, AND INTIMIDATING COLOMBIAN SOCIETY. IT HAS ALSO BEEN SAID THAT EXTRADITION IS UNDIGNIFIED BECAUSE IT SENDS COLOMBIANS ABROAD TO BE TRIED, AND THAT IT IS MORE DIGNIFIED FOR THEM TO BE TRIED AND CONDEMNED IN THE COUNTRY BY OUR OWN JUDGES. THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS, HOWEVER, HAVE SENT MORE THAN 200 COLOMBIAN JUDGES AND JUDICIAL BRANCH OFFICIALS TO THEIR GRAVE. FOR EXAMPLE, THE INVESTIGATION INTO THE MURDER OF DR GUILLERMO CANO HAS MEANT THE DEATH OF WITNESSES, JUDICIAL OFFICIALS, AND LAWYERS AND INTIMIDATION AND THREATS TO ALL THOSE WHO WANT TO COOPERATE WITH JUSTICE TO RESOLVE A CRIME. HOW THEN CAN WE BELIEVE THESE DRUG TRAFFICKERS? CAN WE BELIEVE THAT EXTRADITION HAS CAUSED THIS VIOLENCE? CAN WE HAVE A FREE AND DIGNIFIED COUNTRY WITH THESE BANDS OF MULTIMILLIONAIRE MURDERERS?

I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO EXPLAIN TO YOU WHY THE GOVERNMENT CONSIDERS IT HARMFUL AND DANGEROUS TO SUBMIT EXTRADITION TO A REFERENDUM. WE KNOW THAT EXTRADITION IS ONLY FOR DRUG TRAFFICKERS. WE KNOW WHAT THEY HAVE DONE AND WHAT THEY ARE CAPABLE OF DOING. WE HAVE SUFFERED FROM THEIR TERRORIST ACTIONS. MANY BRAVE COLOMBIANS HAVE BEEN MURDERED FOR THE SIMPLE REASON OF NOT AGREEING WITH DRUG TRAFFICKING. DO YOU BELIEVE THAT ON THIS TOPIC OF EXTRADITION THERE COULD BE A CLEAN ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN, FREE FROM INTIMIDATION? DO YOU BELIEVE THAT THOSE WHO ARE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING CAN, WITHOUT FEAR, GIVE THEIR OPINION? IT WOULD BE A CAMPAIGN SLANTED BY TERRORISM, INTIMIDATION, AND DRUG TRAFFICKERS' MONEY.

THE GOVERNMENT CANNOT SUBJECT CITIZENS TO AN ELECTORAL PROCESS THAT WOULD NOT BE TO CONVINCE COLOMBIANS, BUT TO INTIMIDATE THEM. A REFERENDUM IS FOR PEOPLE TO EXPRESS THEIR FREE AND SOVEREIGN DECISION ON A TOPIC OF GENERAL INTEREST. TO INCLUDE EXTRADITION IN THE REFERENDUM WOULD ONLY SERVE SO THAT A HANDFUL -- LESS THAN 100 -- DRUG TRAFFICKERS CAN, BY USING THEIR MONEY AND TERROR, INTIMIDATE PUBLIC OPINION, THE MEDIA, AND ALL COLOMBIANS, SO AS TO AVOID BEING TRIED AND CONDEMNED FOR CRIMES THAT THEY HAD COMMITTED ABROAD.

CONDITIONS OF TERRORISM DO NOT ALLOW THIS TOPIC TO BE DECIDED FREELY. I CALL FOR GOOD SENSE, FOR SENSIBLENESS, SO THAT THE DARK INTERESTS OF A FEW PRIVATE PEOPLE ARE NOT CONFUSED WITH THE GENERAL INTEREST OF ALL COLOMBIANS. I CALL FOR COLOMBIANS NOT TO ALLOW THE CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS THAT ARE IN THE FINAL DISCUSSION, OR THE FIRST REFERENDUM IN OVER 30 YEARS, TO BE USED IN AN OPPORTUNISTIC WAY TO SERVE SELFISH INTERESTS. THE GOVERNMENT IS CONVINCED THAT THE CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS AND THE EXTRAORDINARY REFERENDUM WILL BE AN IMPORTANT ADVANCEMENT FOR THE INSTITUTIONS. THEY WILL ALLOW GREATER PARTICIPATION BY THE PEOPLE IN STATE DECISIONS, IN CONGRESS, AND ARE WITHOUT DOUBT A STEP TOWARD PEACE. I KNOW THERE ARE SOME WHO SAY THAT DRUG TRAFFICKERS WANT PEACE AND TRANQUILITY. I WANT TO SAY THAT ELIMINATING EXTRADITION WILL NOT BRING TRANQUILITY, BUT IMPUNITY AND MORE VIOLENCE. THIS IS WHY IT IS ADVISABLE THAT PARLIAMENTARIANS NOT ALLOW INSTITUTIONAL CHANGES TO BE ENDANGERED OR THE PEACE ACCORDS BE PUT TO SERIOUS RISK DUE TO THE INCLUSION IN THE REFERENDUM OF A TOPIC THAT NOT ONLY WOULD NOT BE GOOD FOR THE COUNTRY, BUT WOULD BE DANGEROUS TO ALL COLOMBIANS.

AS IS PUBLICLY KNOWN, I WILL TRAVEL ON 3 DECEMBER AT THE OFFICIAL INVITATION OF THE JAPANESE GOVERNMENT. THIS IS PART OF COLOMBIA'S OPENING TO THE PACIFIC. THERE, I SHALL MEET WITH EMPEROR AKIHITO; WITH PRIME MINISTER TOSHIKI KAIFU; WITH THE LEGISLATIVE CHAMBERS; WITH INDUSTRIAL, POLITICAL, AND ACADEMIC LEADERS; AND WITH JAPANESE GOVERNMENT LENDING AND TRADE ENTITIES. THERE, I SHALL PRESENT A TRUE PICTURE OF COLOMBIA -- A COUNTRY WITH DIFFICULTIES, BUT WITH THE NATIONAL RESOLVE TO OVERCOME THEM. WE ARE A COUNTRY WITH A PROMISING FUTURE, WITH HARD-WORKING PEOPLE, AND WITH VAST NATURAL RESOURCES. A FEW CRIMINALS WILL NOT BE ABLE TO SNATCH THAT FUTURE FROM US. GOOD NIGHT, AND SEE YOU SOON.

DEV-MUC3-0923 (GTE)

GUATEMALA CITY, 3 DEC 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] CENTRAL AMERICAN BISHOPS ARE "VERY WORRIED" OVER THE SITUATION OF THE CHURCH AND THE PEOPLE IN EL SALVADOR AND PANAMA, "WHO ARE ENDURING A DIFFICULT TRIAL," ACCORDING TO A DOCUMENT ISSUED BY THE EPISCOPAL SECRETARIAT OF CENTRAL AMERICA AND PANAMA (SEDAC).

IN THE DOCUMENT, SIGNED BY 42 AREA BISHOPS, THE BISHOPS "EXPRESS APPRECIATION FOR THE COURAGEOUS, EVANGELIC, AND PATRIOTIC ATTITUDE OF THE PANAMANIAN CHURCH, GUIDED BY ITS TRUE CLERGYMEN, IN FACING THE DOUBLE AGGRESSION THEY ARE ENDURING."

PANAMA IS ENDURING "EXTERNAL SANCTIONS (IMPOSED BY THE UNITED STATES) THAT IMPOVERISH THE COUNTRY, ALONG WITH THE OPEN DENIAL OF FUNDAMENTAL GUARANTEES AND RIGHTS TO THOSE WHO DISAGREE WITH THE POLICY OF THE CURRENT PROVISIONAL GOVERNMENT," THE DOCUMENT ADDS.

REGARDING EL SALVADOR, "WE ARE HURT" BY THE SUFFERING, DEATH, AND DESTRUCTION CAUSED BY THE ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE EL SALVADOR HAS BEEN ENDURING FOR A DECADE.

"THE USE OF THE CIVILIAN POPULATION FOR THE PROTECTION OF ARMED GROUPS, THE INTENSE BOMBINGS OVER DENSELY POPULATED AREAS (BY THE ARMY), AND THE USE OF THE MEDIA TO STIR UP PEOPLE'S FEELINGS AND INCREASE HATRED AMONG BROTHERS ARE ALL REPULSIVE," THE SEDAC DOCUMENT STATES.

THE SEDAC RECALLS THAT AMONG THE WAR VICTIMS ARE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS, WHO, FROM THEIR TEACHING PODIUMS, TRIED TO SHAPE MORAL AND JUST CONSCIENCES AMONG THE FUTURE BUILDERS OF SOCIETY. IT ALSO CONDEMNS THE "BRUTAL WAY IN WHICH THEY WERE MASSACRED, WHICH PROVES HOW FAR DOWN THE MORAL SENSE AND HUMAN QUALITY OF THOSE WHO PERPETRATED THE CRIME HAS FALLEN."

REGARDING PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA, THE HIGHEST RANKING LEADERS OF THE CHURCH IN THE AREA POINT OUT THAT THERE ARE MANY FACTORS PREVENTING OR HAMPERING EFFORTS TO BUILD A LONG LASTING PEACE.

AMONG THE FACTORS THE BISHOPS MENTION IS "THE PERSISTENCE OF SERIOUS SOCIAL PROBLEMS -- HUNGER, UNEMPLOYMENT, THE HIGH COST OF LIVING, AND THE REALITY OF AN UNDERPRIVILEGED CLASS -- YET MOST RULERS AND OTHER BODIES HOLDING POWER DO NOT SHOW ANY DESIRE TO ELIMINATE THESE FACTORS."

IN ADDITION, THE "CRIMINAL STUBBORNNESS" OF SEARCHING FOR A MILITARY AND ARMED SOLUTION TO THE SITUATION OF VIOLENCE HAS GENERATED "THE DEEPLY ROOTED UNJUSTICE IN OUR REALITY, WHICH IS AGGRAVATED BY THE OUTRAGEOUS MEDDLING OF FOREIGN SUPERPOWERS."

"THE INTEREST OF A GROUP OR IDEOLOGIES PREVAIL OVER THE NEEDS AND RIGHTS OF CITIZENS," THE SEDAC DOCUMENTS STATES. THE HEADS OF THE CHURCHES OF THE SIX ISTHMIAN COUNTRIES ADD THAT THIS HASTENS THE "CRIMINAL AND IMMORAL" ARMS BUILDUP, WHICH, WITH THE EXCEPTION OF COSTA RICA, HAS LED PEOPLE IN THE AREA INTO INCREASING IMPOVERISHMENT AND A RISE IN THEIR FOREIGN DEBT.

"THE SMUGGLING OF WEAPONS TO STRENGTHEN SUBVERSIVE MOVEMENTS OF VARIOUS TENDENCIES IS NO LESS OUTRAGEOUS AND CRIMINAL THAN THE EXISTENCE OF DEATH SQUADS OR PARAMILITARY GROUPS," THE SEDAC DOCUMENT ADDS.

IT IS WORRYING TO SEE HOW SOME NATIONS IN THE AREA PROMOTE CAMPAIGNS SUCH AS "AN EYE FOR AN EYE AND A TOOTH FOR A TOOTH" (PANAMA), OR PROMOTE "ANTITERRORIST" LAWS (EL SALVADOR) THAT CAN BE USED FOR THE OUTRAGEOUS ABUSE OF POWER IN ORDER TO ELIMINATE ADVERSARIES, THE BISHOPS POINTED OUT.

TO ALL THESE EVILS ONE MUST ADD THE FLIGHT OF CAPITAL, THE INCREASING DRUG TRAFFICKING, AND THE RESULTING CORRUPTION, VIOLENCE, AND DEATH.

DEV-MUC3-0924 (GTE)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] NOW THEY ARE STILL DOING THE SAME THING, EXCEPT THAT THE KILLINGS ARE THOSE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THE PLACES BURNED ARE HOMES IN THE DENSELY POPULATED NEIGHBORHOODS AND THE UN HEADQUARTERS, AND THOSE ACCUSED OF COLLABORATING WITH THE FMLN ARE THE EPISCOPAL CHURCHES. THE STRATEGY IS THE SAME. THE FMLN CONTINUES TO STRIKE AT AND MOCK THE ARMED FORCES. FAR FROM DIMINISHING IN NUMBER, IT HAS INCREASED IN NUMBER. THE PERSECUTION OF THE CHURCH, THE INDISCRIMINATE BOMBINGS, THE PRESS CENSORSHIP, AND, ABOVE ALL, THE APPARENT DIRECTION TAKEN BY THE SITUATION AS A RESULT OF THE ARMED FORCES' LEADERSHIP HAVE SHOWN THE WORLD THAT NOTHING HAS CHANGED. THE MILITARY CONTINUES TO BE IN COMMAND, AND CRISTIANI'S MODERATION WAS BUT A COSTLY MAKEOVER.

THE U.S. ANALYSTS ARE BEGINNING TO REACT. AFTER 9 YEARS OF INVESTING AT ALL LEVELS TO PUT AN END TO THE CAPITAL AND THE PRINCIPAL CITIES OF THE COUNTRY WITH A STRATEGIC SIEGE, WITH THE THEATER OF OPERATIONS IN THE TROUBLE SPOTS, AND WITHOUT ANY PROSPECT OF CONTROLLING THE SITUATION, THE ORDER OF THE DAY IN THE HALLS OF CONGRESS IS A CHANGE OF POLICY AND THE PROMOTION OF NEGOTIATION. ALL THE WORLD IS SUFFERING DEEPLY, WITHOUT THE HOPE OF A CHANGE OF POLICY. WHAT THE U.S. CONGRESS IS STUDYING IS WHETHER IT WILL CONTINUE WITH THAT POLICY WHICH DOES NOT CHANGE AT ALL, WHICH PROTECTS THE ASSASSINS OF MONSIGNOR ROMERO, THE FOUR U.S. NUNS, IGNACIO ELLACURIA, AND FIVE MORE JESUITS. IT IS STUDYING WHETHER IT IS GOING TO CONTINUE TO SUPPORT A FASCIST PARTY AND A CRIMINAL-RIDDEN ARMED FORCES AND THUS CONDEMN THIS PART OF THE WORLD SO CLOSE TO THEIR BORDERS TO TERRIBLE SUFFERING, OR WHETHER THE TIME OF CHANGE HAS ARRIVED IN THE UNITED STATES. THE POLICY TOWARD EL SALVADOR MUST BE CHANGED TO ACHIEVE THE GOAL OF DEMOCRACY SO THAT PLURALISM WILL GIVE WAY TO DEMOCRACY, JUSTICE, AND PEACE. THE UNITED STATES CAN CONTRIBUTE TO PEACE IN EL SALVADOR, BUT IN ORDER TO DO SO IT MUST CHANGE ITS POLICY.

DEV-MUC3-0926 (SRI)

LA PAZ, 4 DEC 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE POLITICAL NEGOTIATIONS THAT RESULTED IN JAIME PAZ ZAMORA'S INSTALLATION AS PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC WILL AGAIN TAKE PLACE IN THE NEXT WEEKS TO DECIDE WHO WILL BE INSTALLED AS MAYOR OF LA PAZ.

THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS HELD YESTERDAY DID NOT CLEARLY INDICATE WHO WILL BE THE MAYOR OF THE COUNTRY'S BIGGEST CITY, WHERE THE CANDIDATES OF THE POPULIST NEW POLITICAL GROUPS AND THOSE OF THE TRADITIONAL PARTIES RECEIVED APPROXIMATELY THE SAME NUMBER OF VOTES.

ACCORDING TO UNOFFICIAL RETURNS RELEASED BY THE PRIVATE TELEVISION CHANNELS, WHICH IN PREVIOUS ELECTIONS HAVE PROVEN TO BE VERY SIMILAR TO THOSE OF THE NATIONAL ELECTORAL COURT, CARLOS PALENQUE, 45, A RADIO AND TELEVISION BUSINESSMAN AND THE LEADER OF THE CONSCIENCE OF THE FATHERLAND (CONDEPA), HAS RECEIVED MOST OF THE VOTES.

PALENQUE RECEIVED 39.9 PERCENT OF THE VOTES CAST IN LA PAZ, THEREBY GIVING CONDEPA 5 OF THE 13 SEATS ON THE TOWN COUNCIL, WHICH WILL ELECT THE MAYOR OF LA PAZ ON 2 JANUARY.

THE ALLIANCE OF THE RIGHT WING NATIONALIST DEMOCRATIC ACTION (ADN) AND THE SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC MOVEMENT OF THE REVOLUTIONARY LEFT (MIR) HAS ALSO WON FIVE TOWN COUNCIL SEATS.

RONALD MACLEAN, 40 AND OF SCOTTISH ANCESTRY, THE MAYORAL CANDIDATE OF THE ADN-MIR ALLIANCE, HAS OBTAINED 36.8 PERCENT OF THE VOTES IN LA PAZ, WHERE HE HAS BEEN THE MAYOR SINCE L985.

FAR BEHIND WERE THE FORMER ADMINISTRATION'S PARTY, THE NATIONALIST REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MNR), WHICH RECEIVED TWO SEATS, AND THE POPULIST SOLIDARITY CIVIC UNION (UCS), LED BY BREWERY OWNER MAX FERNANDEZ, WITH ONE TOWN COUNCIL SEAT.

THE DECISION AS TO WHO WILL BE THE NEW LA PAZ MAYOR ON 2 JANUARY IS NOW IN THE HANDS OF THE MNR, BUT ITS LEADERS DECLINED TO COMMENT ON THEIR POSITION LAST NIGHT.

GONZALO SANCHEZ DE LOSADA, THE LEADER OF THE MNR, LAST NIGHT SAID ON TELEVISION: "WE MUST BE EXTREMELY SERIOUS IN SEARCHING FOR A SOLUTION TO THIS PROBLEM, OR THE PEOPLE WILL TURN THEIR BACKS ON POPULISM."

HE SAID HIS DECISION WILL BE "A CHRISTMAS PRESENT." HE INSISTED, HOWEVER, THAT IN HIS OPINION THE GOVERNING ADN-MIR ALLIANCE "WILL EASILY FIX THINGS BETWEEN THEM" BECAUSE "THEY ARE TWO OF A KIND."

ALTHOUGH THE MNR WAS THE PARTY TO RECEIVE MOST OF THE VOTES IN THE 7 MAY PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS, IT WAS DUE TO AN ALLIANCE BETWEEN TWO OLD POLITICAL ENEMIES -- THE ADN AND MIR -- THAT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA, WHO HAD COME THIRD IN THE ELECTIONS, WAS INSTALLED AS PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC. "IF WE APPLIED THIS SAME RULE TO THE CURRENT PROBLEM," SANCHEZ DE LOSADA SAID JOKINGLY, "GUIDO CAPRA (MNR CANDIDATE FOR MAYOR OF LA PAZ) WOULD BE ELECTED."

SANCHEZ DE LOSADA POINTED OUT THAT PALENQUE WAS ONE OF THE SUPPORTERS OF THE ADN-MIR GOVERNING ALLIANCE, WHICH PREVENTED SANCHEZ DE LOSADA FROM BECOMING PRESIDENT.

ACCORDING TO THE OPPOSITION, PALENQUE'S PARTY GAINED THE LA PAZ DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION (CORDEPAZ) AND "HALF A MINISTRY" (REFERRING TO THE COMMUNICATIONS AND TRANSPORTATION MINISTRY) AS A RESULT OF THE ALLIANCE. SANCHEZ DE LOSADA WARNED THE BOLIVIAN POLITICIANS THAT PALENQUE'S POPULIST GROUP, WHICH IS GROWING VERY FAST, HAS ITS EYES SET "ON THE L993 PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS, NOT ONLY ON THE LA PAZ MAYORSHIP."

WHILE RESPECT WAS SHOWN TOWARD RONALD MACLEAN, THE CANDIDATE MOST CRITICIZED BY THE MNR DURING THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS CAMPAIGN WAS PALENQUE.

PALENQUE STATED, HOWEVER, THAT THE COUNCILMEN WHO ON 2 JANUARY WILL ELECT THE NEXT MAYOR OF LA PAZ MUST "RESPECT THE WILL OF THE MAJORITY."

"WE HOPE THAT THERE WILL BE NO NEGOTIATION (AMONG PARTIES) AND THAT THE DESIRE OF THE MAJORITY WILL BE RESPECTED," PALENQUE STATED. HE IS WELL KNOWN, ESPECIALLY BECAUSE OF THE BEARD HE WEARS, WHICH MAKES HIM LOOK VERY MUCH LIKE FORMER U.S. PRESIDENT ABRAHAM LINCOLN.

PALENQUE, WHO IS CERTAIN OF THE SUPPORT HE WILL RECEIVE FROM THE ONLY UCS COUNCILMAN IN LA PAZ, FEARS THAT A PACT BETWEEN THE ADN-MIR COALITION AND THE MNR WILL PREVENT HIM FROM OBTAINING THE MAYORSHIP OF THE MOST IMPORTANT CITY IN THE COUNTRY.

SUCH AN ALLIANCE, HOWEVER, WITH A GREATER IDEOLOGICAL BASIS THAN ANY OTHER, WILL HAVE TO OVERCOME THE GRUDGE THAT THE MNR BEARS BECAUSE THE ADN AND THE MIR "HAD STOLEN FROM IT" THE PRESIDENCY OF THE REPUBLIC DURING THE LAST ELECTIONS, ACCORDING TO COMMENTATORS.

"WE ARE GOING TO BE VERY RESPONSIBLE, AND WE ARE NOT GOING TO BE MOTIVATED BY PERSONAL INTERESTS OR BY ANY VENGEANCE," SANCHEZ DE LOSADA STATED, COMMENTING ON THE NEGOTIATIONS THAT WILL TAKE PLACE TO DESIGNATE THE MAYOR OF LA PAZ.

LIKE IN LA PAZ, THE GOVERNMENT ALLIANCE WILL HAVE TO NEGOTIATE SUPPORT IN THE OTHER MAJOR BOLIVIAN CITIES, WHERE THE COALITION CAME IN FIRST BUT FAILED TO WIN ABSOLUTE MAJORITIES.

THE ONLY EXCEPTION IS SUCRE, WHERE THE CANDIDATE OF THE UNITED LEFT COALITION, RADIO REPORTER OMAR MONTALVO, OBTAINED 57.3 PERCENT OF THE VOTES, WHICH IS SUFFICIENT TO OBTAIN THE MAYORSHIP.

THE MOST OUTSTANDING POINTS ABOUT THE ELECTIONS WERE THE ABSTENTION OF BETWEEN 30 AND 50 PERCENT OF THE VOTERS AND THE ALMOST ABSOLUTE NORMALCY DURING THE ELECTIONS.

THE STATE OF SIEGE DECREED THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY ON 15 NOVEMBER DUE TO STREET CONFRONTATIONS CAUSED BY SOCIAL DISTURBANCES DID NOT HAMPER THE ELECTORAL PROCESS.

THE TRADITIONAL RESTRICTIONS, HOWEVER, AFFECTED TRAFFIC AND HAMPERED PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION, KEEPING VOTERS FROM CASTING THEIR VOTES. THE ABSTENTION WAS ALSO CAUSED BY THE WEARINESS OF THE VOTERS, WHO ARE VOTING FOR THE FOURTH TIME IN 4 YEARS.

DEV-MUC3-0927 (SRI)

LIMA, 28 NOV 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] DELEGATES TO A LATIN AMERICAN CONGRESS THAT IS BEING HELD IN LIMA ON MISSING DETAINEES IN LATIN AMERICA TODAY EXPRESSED THEIR "CONCERN" THAT THE LARGEST NUMBER OF DETAINEES AND MISSING PEOPLE ARE TO BE FOUND IN THE COUNTRIES THAT HAVE DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENTS.

"WE BELIEVE THAT THERE ARE GROUPS THAT ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE DISAPPEARANCES. THESE GROUPS ARE ORGANIZED BY THE STATE ITSELF TO GET RID OF ITS POLITICAL OPPONENTS AND THESE GROUPS ARE EQUIPPED WITH ALL THE RESOURCES REQUIRED TO ENGAGE IN ACTS OF IMPUNITY," SAID THE CONGRESS SPOKESPERSON.

ABOUT 200 DELEGATES FROM 12 LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES AND FROM EUROPEAN AND U.S. HUMAN RIGHTS ORGANIZATIONS ARE PARTICIPATING IN THE IX CONGRESS OF THE LATIN AMERICAN FEDERATION OF ASSOCIATIONS OF RELATIVES OF MISSING DETAINEES THAT BEGAN TODAY AND WILL END ON 30 NOVEMBER IN LIMA.

SOLA SIERRA, A MEMBER OF THE FEDERATION, HAS TOLD EFE THAT "THE ON THE ESCALATION OF THESE PRACTICES, AND ON THE IMPUNITY PREVAILING IN ALL COUNTRIES WHERE THIS METHOD OF REPRESSION PREVAILS."

SIERRA, A CHILEAN CITIZEN, SAID THAT THIS YEAR THE COUNTRIES WITH THE LARGEST NUMBER OF MISSING DETAINEES ARE COLOMBIA, EL SALVADOR, GUATEMALA, AND PERU, "WHERE POLITICAL VIOLENCE HAS INCREASED." HOWEVER, SHE FAILED TO MENTION THE NUMBER OF MISSING DETAINEES.

SIERRA, THE CHILEAN DELEGATE AND THE PRESIDENT OF THE CHILEAN ASSOCIATION OF RELATIVES OF MISSING PEOPLE, SAID THAT THERE IS NO TOTAL NUMBER OF MISSING PEOPLE, BUT THAT MORE THAN 100,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN REPORTED MISSING THROUGHOUT LATIN AMERICA SINCE 1981.

"THIS FIGURE HAS INCREASED AT A FRIGHTENING RATE, AND WE REGRET THAT THE LARGEST NUMBERS OF CASES HAVE BEEN REPORTED IN COUNTRIES WITH DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENTS," SHE ADDED.

SHE SAID THAT "NEITHER UNDER A DICTATORSHIP NOR UNDER A DEMOCRACY" HAS THE PROBLEM OF THE MISSING DETAINEES BEEN RESOLVED BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT "ALWAYS MANAGE TO TALK ITS WAY OUT OF INVESTIGATING OR PUNISHING.

"(THE GOVERNMENTS) ARGUE THAT IT IS NECESSARY TO FORGET THE PAST IN ORDER TO BUILD THE PRESENT AND THAT IT IS NECESSARY TO RECONCILE IF PEACE IS TO PREVAIL. BUT HOW CAN THERE BE PEACE AND RECONCILIATION WHILE EXTREMELY SERIOUS EVENTS LIKE THE MASSIVE KILLING OF HUMAN BEINGS CONTINUE," SHE ADDED.

SIERRA REGRETTED THAT "THERE IS VERY STRONG PRESS CENSORSHIP, AND, WHAT IS WORSE, A SELF-IMPOSED CENSORSHIP [AUTOCENSURA]" IN THE COUNTRIES WHERE MOST MISSING DETAINEES HAVE BEEN REPORTED.

THESE SITUATIONS ALWAYS LEAD US TO BELIEVE THAT IT IS THE STATE THAT PROMOTES THIS ENTIRE POLICY, THAT IS TO SAY, THE USE OF STATE TERRORISM IN COUNTRIES WHERE A STATE OF LAW, COURTS, AND ESTABLISHED LEGAL PRACTICES PREVAIL, SIERRA COMMENTED.

IN TODAY'S SESSION, A MEMBER OF THE PERUVIAN DELEGATION SAID THAT OVER THE PAST 10 YEARS AT LEAST 4,000 PEOPLE, MOSTLY PEASANTS AND ANDEAN COMMUNITY LEADERS, WHO WERE "ARRESTED BY GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS WHO LATER DENIED IT," HAVE DISAPPEARED.

THE MEMBER OF THE PERUVIAN DELEGATION SAID THAT, ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL FIGURES, ABOUT 15,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KILLED AS A RESULT OF POLITICAL VIOLENCE IN PERU, AND THAT A "NEGLIGIBLE NUMBER" HAS BEEN KILLED IN CLASHES.

DEV-MUC3-0929 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 4 DEC 89 (AFP) -- [EXCERPTS] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI TONIGHT CONFIRMED THAT HE WILL ATTEND THE SPECIAL SUMMIT OF CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS IN COSTA RICA ON 10-11 DECEMBER. CRISTIANI SAID OVER RADIO AND TELEVISION THAT HE WILL ATTEND THE SUMMIT "IN DEFENSE OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE" AND TO TELL NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA THAT "UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES IS HIS SENDING THE FMLN (FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT) PUPPETS TO KILL SALVADORANS JUSTIFIED."

CRISTIANI SAID TODAY THAT EL SALVADOR "HAS ALWAYS BEEN WILLING TO FIND A SOLUTION THROUGH PEACEFUL MEANS" BUT IN ALLUSION TO NICARAGUA, HE ADDED THAT "THOSE WHO SEEK TO SIGN COMMITMENTS WITH THE REST OF THE PRESIDENTS SHOULD ALSO FULFILL THEM."

MEANWHILE, HONDURAN PRESIDENT JOSE AZCONA SAID TODAY IN TEGUCIGALPA THAT HE WAS WILLING TO ATTEND THE SUMMIT. HOWEVER, COSTA RICAN FOREIGN MINISTER RODRIGO MADRIGAL SAID IN HIS COUNTRY THAT EL SALVADOR AND HONDURAS HAD NOT OFFICIALLY CONFIRMED THEIR ATTENDANCE.

ACCORDING TO CRISTIANI, HE WILL CONFIRM HIS ATTENDANCE ON 5 DECEMBER.

MADRIGAL PREDICTED THAT THE SUMMIT "WILL NOT BE EASY" DUE TO THE TOPICS THAT WILL BE DISCUSSED AND BECAUSE THE AGENDA WILL SURELY INCLUDE THE ALLEGED NICARAGUAN ASSISTANCE TO THE FMLN AND THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE CONTRAS AS REQUESTED BY NICARAGUA.

HOWEVER, THE AGENDA IS BEING PROCESSED AND ALTHOUGH COSTA RICA OFFERED TO HOST THE MEETING, "IT IS NOT INTERESTED IN FORCING THE ISSUE," HE EMPHASIZED.

MADRIGAL ADDED THAT WHAT INTERESTS COSTA RICA IS TO SERVE AS A "BRIDGE" FOR SOLVING THE CONFLICT BETWEEN NICARAGUA AND EL SALVADOR, AND FINDING SOME FORMULA SO THAT THE SALVADORAN AND NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENTS WILL ESTABLISH A DIALOGUE WITH THE REBELS.

HE ADDED THAT IT IS POSSIBLE THAT THE FOREIGN MINISTERS OF THE FIVE COUNTRIES WILL MEET IN SAN JOSE ON THE EVE OF THE LONG-AWAITED MEETING TO PREPARE FOR IT.

THE COSTA RICAN FOREIGN MINISTER REPORTED THAT THEY ARE ALSO CONSIDERING THE POSSIBILITY OF INVITING FOREIGN MINISTERS FROM OTHER LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES, AS WELL AS REPRESENTATIVES OF THE UN OBSERVER GROUP IN CENTRAL AMERICA (ONUCA).

DEV-MUC3-0930 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 5 DEC 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] VIOLENT CLASHES BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLA FORCES AND THE ARMY TODAY AGAIN SHOOK THE NORTHWEST SECTOR OF SAN SALVADOR, AFTER A FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) COLUMN RAIDED THE TOWN OF SAN ANTONIO ABAD.

AT LEAST FIVE MILITARY AND REBEL DEATHS, THREE STORES PARTIALLY DESTROYED, AND ONE ELECTRIC POLE BLOWN UP ARE THE PRELIMINARY RESULTS OF THE CLASHES IN SAN ANTONIO ABAD, BETWEEN 2100 ON 4 DECEMBER AND 0200 5 DECEMBER.

THE FMLN GUERRILLA FORCES TODAY ALSO ATTACKED ARMY POSITIONS IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE, A WORKERS' NEIGHBORHOOD NORTH OF THE CAPITAL, AND LA CIMA NEIGHBORHOOD, SOUTHEAST OF THE CAPITAL, WHERE THE CLASHES WERE STILL UNDERWAY AT MID-MORNING.

THE ARMY ADMITTED THAT ONE SOLDIER DIED AND FIVE WERE WOUNDED DURING THE CLASHES IN SAN ANTONIO ABAD, A MIDDLE CLASS NEIGHBORHOOD LOCATED BESIDE THE ESCALON RESIDENTIAL AREA; AND AT LEAST FOUR REBELS WERE RIPPED TO PIECES BY A LAW [LIGHT AATI-TANK WEAPON] ROUND.

LOTS OF BLOOD AND PIECES OF FLESH STUCK TO BACKPACKS AND MILITARY UNIFORM FRAGMENTS WERE SCATTERED IN A-30 METER AREA WITHIN AN EMPTY LOT IN THE DOWNTOWN AREA OF THE TOWN.

AN OFFICER OF THE NATIONAL POLICE'S ELITE PANTERA BATTALION, WHICH PARTICIPATED IN THE FIGHTING, TOLD AFP: "THE ROUND FELL EXACTLY WHERE THEY WERE. AT LEAST FOUR DIED ON THE SPOT AND MANY WERE WOUNDED."

THE REBELS BLEW UP A GROCERY STORE AND AN ELECTRIC POLE IN DOWNTOWN SAN ANTONIO ABAD; AND ONE DRUGSTORE AND OTHER STORES ALSO SUSTAINED CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE DURING THE FIGHTING.

TENSION AND NERVOUSNESS PREVAILED THIS MORNING IN SAN ANTONIO ABAD, WHERE MANY PERSONS WERE LOOKING FOR EXPLOSIVES AND TNT LEFT BEHIND BY THE REBELS.

ARMY SPOKESMEN HAVE YET TO ISSUE A REPORT ON THE FIGHTING AT LA CIMA AND AYUTUXTEPEQUE, BUT THE PEOPLE OF AYUTUXTEPEQUE SAID THERE WAS FIERCE FIGHTING IN THE SECTOR, ADDING THAT THE REBELS ENTRENCHED THEMSELVES INSIDE THE LOCAL CHURCH TO FIRE AT THE GOVERNMENT'S TROOPS.

MEANWHILE, REPORTS FROM THE INTERIOR INDICATE THAT THE FIGHTING DIMINISHED TODAY IN THE REGION OF ZACATECOLUCA, USULUTAN, AND SAN MIGUEL, WHERE THE MILITARY SITUATION WAS EXTRAORDINARILY TENSE UNTIL THE NIGHT OF 4 DECEMBER.

NEVERTHELESS, THE GOVERNMENT TODAY EXPLAINED THAT THE REDUCTION IN CURFEW HOURS, FROM 2100 TO 0500 EFFECTIVE LAST NIGHT, DOES NOT APPLY FOR THE CITY OF ZACATECOLUCA, CAPITAL OF LA PAZ DEPARTMENT -- LOCATED IN THE CENTRAL PART OF THE COUNTRY -- WHICH THE GUERRILLA FORCES HAVE BEEN CONSTANTLY HARASSING THROUGHOUT THE WEEK.

MEANWHILE, THE FMLN WARNED THE OWNERS OF COMMERCIAL AND CROP DUSTING AIRPLANES TO ABSTAIN FROM USING THEIR PLANMES FOR THE ARMY TO CONDUCTRE RECONAISSANCE FLIGHTS IN THE REGION OF ZACATECOLUCA AND USULUTAN, "BECAUSE THEY WILL BE CONSIDERED MILITARY TARGETS."

DEV-MUC3-0933 (SRI)

CLANDESTINE, 5 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] THE PEOPLE'S ANTI-AIRCRAFT POWER HAS BEGUN TO BECOME EFFECTIVE. SALVADORANS, THIS AFTERNOON WE DOWNED AN O-2 AIRPLANE IN THE AREA OF THE CITY OF USULUTAN. RADIO VENCEREMOS REPORTS THAT THE ANTI-AIRCRAFT FIRE OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] DOWNED A PUSH-PULL AIRPLANE THIS AFTERNOON. AT 1615, THE FMLN'S ANTI-AIRCRAFT FIRE DOWNED A PUSH-PULL AIRPLANE OVER THE CITY OF USULUTAN.

LATER IN THIS PROGRAM WE WILL PROVIDE DETAILS OF THE DOWNING OF THE PUSH-PULL AIRPLANE DOWNED IN THE CITY OF USULUTAN. ITS CREW DIED WHEN THE PLANE CRASHED. IT IS A PLANE THAT CRASHED JUST AS THE REGIME OF 50 YEARS OF INJUSTICE IS CRASHING. WE HAVE DOWNED ONE OF THE PLANES THAT HAD BEEN BOMBING THE ZACAMIL NEIGHBORHOOD. WE HAVE DOWNED A PLANE PILOTED BY THOSE WHO HAD BEEN BRINGING DEATH AND DESTRUCTION TO MEJICANOS, SOYAPANGO, AND SAN MIGUEL. WITH THE DOWNING OF THIS PLANE, OUR PEOPLE AVENGE THE BLOOD SPILLED BY THE GENOCIDE. THIS SHOWS THAT THE FMLN'S ANTI-AIRCRAFT FIRE HAS BEGUN TO BECOME EFFECTIVE.

DEV-MUC3-0935 (SRI)

TEGUCIGALPA, 5 DEC 89 (EL HERALDO) -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] GUATEMALA, WHERE ARMED GROUPS HAVE CONTINUED TO RUN RAMPANT, HAS BEEN THE VICTIM OF THIS INTERCONTINENTAL INTEREST. NICARAGUA HAS BEEN TAKEN OVER BY THE SANDINIST FORCES, WHICH RECEIVE ARMS OF ALL KINDS.

MORE ARMS THAN FOOD, MORE INSTRUCTORS THAN AGRICULTURAL EXPERTS, AND MORE ARMS THAN FINANCE ASSISTANCE FOR INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT KEEP REACHING NICARAGUA.

NICARAGUA HAS BECOME A DISTRIBUTION CENTER FOR OTHER COUNTRIES WHO RAISE PIRATE FLAGS, COUNTRIES WHOSE LEADERS KNOW THAT THE SOVIET UNION IS INTERESTED IN THE FIVE COUNTRIES OF THE ISTHMUS. THIS IS WHY THE SOVIET UNION CONTINUALLY AIDS THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS. THE INTERRUPTION OF FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE AND ARMS WOULD ENTAIL FAILURE OF THE STRUGGLE FOR POWER IN CENTRAL AMERICA.

OVER THE COURSE OF THE TALKS ABOARD SOVIET AND U.S. SHIPS OFF MALTA, BUSH'S POSITION REMAINED IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE INTERESTS OF BOTH THE U.S. AND OTHER WESTERN COUNTRIES. MANY OF THESE LATTER COUNTRIES ARE THREATENED BY RADICAL AND CLANDESTINE MOVEMENTS.

WE BELIEVE THAT THE U.S. PRESIDENT HAS JUST TAKEN FIRM STEPS TOWARD A DIRECT UNDERSTANDING WITH THE SOVIET UNION. THIS MEANS THAT THE GUERRILLAS MOVEMENTS IN SEVERAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES WILL HAVE TO CONSENT TO CIVILIZED DIALOGUE SO THEY CAN COEXIST WITH THE MAJORITY OF THE POPULATION, WHO DESIRE TO LIVE IN PEACE, WITH WORK AND DIGNITY.

EL SALVADOR REPRESENTS THE MOST DANGEROUS EXAMPLE OF THIS INTERCONTINENTAL PENETRATION. IN THIS COUNTRY OPERATES A GUERRILLA MOVEMENT HEAVILY SUPPLIED WITH ARMS AND AMMUNITION. THESE REBELS ARE MILITARILY AND OTHERWISE TRAINED FOR CLANDESTINE OPERATIONS THAT SOW TERROR IN THE THREATENED TOWNS AND VILLAGES. THE SOVIET UNION SUPPLIES THESE ARMS THROUGH CUBA.

SALVADORAN PRESIDENT CRISTIANI EXPECTS THE ACCORDS REACHED BY THE TWO WORLD LEADERS TO CUT THE SUPPLY OF WAR MATERIEL TO THE FMLN. THIS MATERIEL HAS MADE IT POSSIBLE TO KILL THOUSANDS OF SALVADORANS.

WE WILL HAVE WAITED FOR THE PASSAGE OF TIME TO SEE IF IT IS TRUE THAT THE SUPPLY OF ARMS HAS CEASED AND THAT NICARAGUA HAS STOPPED ASSISTING THE FMLN.

WE ONLY HOPE THE FMLN WILL NOT COME TO HONDURAS. THE CABINETS THAT DRAFT WAR PLANS ARE NOW CURRENTLY DISCUSSING THE FMLN'S MOVING INTO HONDURAS.

DEV-MUC3-0936 (SRI)

BOGOTA, 6 DEC 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] JUST A FEW MINUTES AGO TWO VERY STRONG EXPLOSIONS OCCURRED IN THE CENTER OF BOGOTA. WE FELT THESE EXPLOSIONS HERE AT THE RCN [RADIO CADENA NACIONAL] BUILDING. ONE OF THE EXPLOSIONS OCCURRED IN THE VICINITY OF THE COURTS IN THE PALO QUEMADO SECTOR, WHERE ALL THE BOGOTA JUDICIAL BRANCH OFFICES ARE LOCATED. APPARENTLY THE OTHER EXPLOSION OCCURRED IN A STREET NEAR THE PRESIDENTIAL PALACE.

THERE WERE TWO EXPLOSIONS OCCURRING CONSECUTIVELY BUT VERY CLOSE TOGETHER, WHICH IS WHY IT WAS FELT SO STRONGLY. IT INITIALLY FELT LIKE AN EARTHQUAKE: FIRST THE WAVE AND THEN THE EXPLOSION. ALL THE RESIDENTS IN THIS CENTRAL AREA OF BOGOTA FELT IT.

IT IS ALSO SAID THAT THE EXPLOSION COULD HAVE OCCURRED CLOSER TO THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY, DAS, WHICH IS LOCATED IN THE SAME AREA. THE DAS HEADQUARTERS ARE JUST AROUND THE CORNER FROM THE JUDICIAL BRANCH OFFICES IN PALO QUEMADO. THE STRONG EXPLOSION THAT WAS FELT BY ALL OF US WHO WORK AT THIS HOUR IN THE CENTRAL BOGOTA AREA TOOK PLACE AT 19TH CARRERA AND 25TH STREET IN PALO QUEMADO. I REPEAT, TWO CONSECUTIVE EXPLOSIONS OCCURRED AT 0735 IN THE CENTER OF BOGOTA.

HERE IS SOME UPDATED INFORMATION: IT WAS NOT TWO EXPLOSIONS, AS WE HAD INTIALLY BELIEVED, BUT THREE EXPLOSIONS THAT OCCURRED A FEW MINUTES AGO IN BOGOTA. ONE OF THEM WAS IN THE PALO QUEMADO SECTOR, AS WE HAVE ALREADY REPORTED, IN THE AREA WHERE BOTH THE BOGOTA COURTS AND DAS ARE LOCATED. ANOTHER EXPLOSION OCCURRED IN THE SOUTHERN PART OF BOGOTA AT 14TH CARRERA AND 28TH STREET SOUTH, APPARENTLY NEAR AN AGRARIAN TRUST BRANCH IN THE BARRIO GUSTAVO RESTREPO NEIGHBORHOOD. A THIRD EXPLOSION OCCURRED IN THE CENTRAL AREA OF BOGOTA. THESE THREE EXPLOSIONS IN BOGOTA TOOK PLACE ALMOST SIMULTANEOUSLY, JUST A FEW SECONDS APART.

WE NOW HAVE OFFICIAL FIGURES OF THE EXPLOSION NEAR THE DAS HEADQUARTERS: SEVEN PERSONS WERE KILLED, MORE THAN 50 WERE WOUNDED, AND APPROXIMATELY 25 VEHICLES AND AT LEAST 15 BUILDINGS -- INCLUDING THE DAS OFFICES THAT WERE PARTIALLY DESTROYED -- WERE DAMAGED. INITIALLY, DAS OFFICIALS HAVE ESTIMATED THAT A POWERFUL BOMB OF MORE THAN 100 KG OF DYNAMITE PLACED IN A TRUCK WAS ACTIVATED.

THE HUGE EXPLOSION CAUSED THE INITIAL DESTRUCTION OF THE FRONT PART OF THE DAS HEADQUARTERS, AS WELL AS A BUILDING WHERE THERE WAS A HARDWARE STORE, AND THE TOTAL DESTRUCTION OF SIX OR SEVEN OTHER BUILDINGS. A CRATER 15 METERS WIDE AND 6 METERS DEEP WAS CREATED IN 27TH CARRERA.

MOST OF THE VICTIMS OF THE EXPLOSION WERE IN PRIVATE VEHICLES AND TAXIS, AND ONLY FOUR WERE WALKING IN THE AREA WHEN THE EXPLOSION OCCURRED AT ALMOST 0740. OFFICIALS SAY INITIALLY THAT THERE WERE 50 PERSONS, HIT BY GLASS SHARDS AND FLYING PIECES OF VEHICLES, INJURED IN THE EXPLOSION. OFFICIALS HAVE INDICATED THAT IT IS POSSIBLE THAT THE NUMBER OF VICTIMS WILL INCREASE, AS THE ATTACK AGAINST THE DAS HEADQUARTERS WAS VERY STRONG. WE REPEAT: OFFICIALLY, SEVEN PERSONS WERE KILLED HERE IN FRONT OF THE DAS HEADQUARTERS.

DEV-MUC3-0937 (SRI)

SANTIAGO, 5 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] ADMIRAL JOSE TORIBIO MERINO CASTRO TODAY STATED THAT THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT JUNTA HAS DECIDED TO MEET TWICE A WEEK, TUESDAYS AND THURSDAYS, IN ORDER TO EXPEDITE THE HANDLING OF DRAFT LAWS CURRENTLY UNDER CONSIDERATION. ASKED ABOUT THE POLITICAL SITUATION IN CHILE, MERINO SAID THAT EVERYTHING IS CALM.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] THE POLITICAL SITUATION IS CALM, EXCEPT FOR THE LEFTISTS, THAT IS, NOT THE LEFTISTS IN GENERAL BUT THOSE WHO LIKE THROWING BOMBS AND KILLING PEOPLE. THEY ARE THE ONES THAT ARE MARRING AN EXTRAORDINARILY PERFECT DEMOCRATIC PROCESS. THIS SITUATION IS UNIQUE IN THE WORLD, BECAUSE I BELIEVE THAT ALL THOSE WHO CAN VOTE HAVE BEEN REGISTERED, AT LEAST 99 PERCENT OF THEM. [END RECORDING]

ADM MERINO ADDED THAT THE PREVAILING CALM MUST CONTINUE UNDER THE NEXT ADMINISTRATION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] THE PEACEFUL ATMOSPHERE MUST CONTINUE IF WE ARE TO LIVE IN A DEMOCRACY RESPECTFUL OF THE PEOPLE AND THEIR RIGHTS. WHAT I MEAN IS THAT AS LONG AS THERE IS RESPECT, THERE WILL BE TRANQUILLITY. [END RECORDING]

ADM MERINO STATED THAT THE NEW CENTRAL BANK EXECUTIVE BOARD WILL ENSURE GREATER STABILITY, ESPECIALLY IN THE EXCHANGE RATE FOR FOREIGN CURRENCIES. ASKED ABOUT FIDEL CASTRO'S RECENT OFFER TO MEDIATE BETWEEN CHILE AND BOLIVIA, MERINO SAID THAT THE CUBAN DICTATOR HAS NO BUSINESS MEDDLING IN CHILE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MERINO] [WORDS INDISTICT] FIDEL CASTRO. THIS SCARECROW WOULD DO BETTER TO KEEP HIS MOUTH SHUT BECAUSE HE HAS NO BUSINESS MEDDLING IN CHILE. [WORDS INDISTINCT] A CLEAR IDEA OF PERESTROYKA AND THE OTHER LESSONS THAT GORBACHEV IS TEACHING [WORDS INDISTINCT]. HE IS PROBABLY THINKING THAT BOLIVIA IS ABOUT TO FALL INTO THE HANDS OF THE COMMUNISTS BECAUSE THOSE IN THE GOVERNMENT THERE ARE LEANING TO THE LEFT, AND THAT CHILE WILL FOLLOW SUIT. SO HE FIGURES THAT HE, AS A LEFTIST, WILL HAVE THE CHANCE TO MEDDLE IN CHILEAN AFFAIRS. NOT SO. NOBODY EXCEPT WE CHILEANS WILL HANDLE OUR AFFAIRS.

THE BEST THING THIS CASTRO CAN DO IS STAY HOME. HE ALREADY VISITED CHILE; I MET HIM AND SO DID OTHERS. HE SPENT A WHOLE NIGHT TALKING TO [NAME INDISTINCT] IN PUNTA ARENAS WHEN I MET HIM. SO HE HAS NOTHING TO DO HERE. [END RECORDING]

ADM MERINO CONCLUDED BY SAYING THAT ON THE DAY OF THE ELECTION HE WILL STAY IN HIS OFFICE, JUST IN CASE.

DEV-MUC3-0938 (SRI)

BOGOTA, 6 DEC 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIA'S ACTING PRESIDENT CARLOS LEMOS HAS SAID THAT THE NARCOTERRORISTS WHO PERPETRATED AN ATTACK IN BOGOTA TODAY THAT LEFT 31 DEAD AND MORE THAN 1,000 INJURED "DESERVE NO MERCY FROM GOD."

LEMOS ADMITTED THAT THE CAR BOMB ATTACK ON THE HEADQUARTERS OF COLOMBIA'S SECRET SECURITY POLICE (DAS) IN BOGOTA "IS THE MOST SERIOUS AND THE BLOODIEST" ATTACK EVER COMMITTED IN THE COUNTRY.

LEMOS, FILLING IN FOR PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO WHO IS ON AN OFFICIAL VISIT TO JAPAN, TOLD AFP THAT CONTROLLING THE TERRORISTS "IS VERY DIFFICULT" BECAUSE "THEY ENJOY THE ADVANTAGE OF SURPRISE."

THE ACTING PRESIDENT POINTED OUT THAT "THE AUTHORITIES CANNOT GUARD EVERY METER OF THE CITY STREETS."

LEMOS SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS STEPPED UP SECURITY THROUGHOUT THE CAPITAL, AND ADDED THAT A "HEAD-ON" STRUGGLE WILL BE WAGED AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFIAS THAT ARE OPERATING IN THE COUNTRY.

"THERE IS NO POSSIBILITY FOR A TRUCE WITH DRUG TRAFFICKERS," THE ACTING MINISTER SAID. HE POINTED OUT THAT "THE SLAUGHTER," WHICH HE HAD WARNED ABOUT LAST WEEK BEFORE THE CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES, IS NOW UNDER WAY.

LEMOS HAS OPPOSED THE INCLUSION OF THE EXTRADICTION TO THE UNITED STATES OF COLOMBIANS CHARGED WITH DRUG TRAFFICKING IN A REFERENDUM SCHEDULED FOR 21 JANUARY.

LEMOS SEIZED THAT OPPORTUNITY TO URGE MEMBERS OF CONGRESS (CHAMBER AND SENATE) TO KEEP EXTRADICTION AS A TOOL TO PUNISH DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

A GROUP OF PARLIAMENTARIANS HAVE INSISTED ON INTRODUCING THE EXTRADICTION ISSUE IN THE REFERENDUM. THE GOVERNMENT BELIEVES THAT THIS IS A PERNICIOUS ACTION, BECAUSE IT COULD INCREASE THE TERRORISM THAT IS SCORCHING THE COUNTRY.

"THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT CANNOT BE DEPRIVED OF A TOOL SUCH AS EXTRADICTION," LEMOS CONCLUDED.

LAST NIGHT THE CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES SURPRISINGLY APPROVED A CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENT TO INCLUDE THE EXTRADICTION ISSUE IN THE REFERENDUM.

DEV-MUC3-0939 (SRI)

LA PAZ, 27 NOV 89 (EL DIARIO) -- [TEXT] ACCORDING TO A REPORT ISSUED BY THE CHAMBER OF DEPUTIES INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS COMMISSION, DRUG TRAFFICKING IS ONE OF THE MAIN FACTORS IN BOLIVIA PREVENTING A SOCIAL EXPLOSION BECAUSE IT CONTRIBUTES 20 PERCENT OF THE JOB OPPORTUNITIES.

"THE BOLIVIAN LABOR FORCE IS OFFICIALLY MADE UP OF 1.7 MILLION PEOPLE. THE DRUG BUSINESS PROVIDES ONE OUT OF EVERY THREE OR FOUR JOBS," THE REPORT STATES, TAKING INTO ACCOUNT DATA OBTAINED FROM GOVERNMENT CIRCLES.

IT ADDS THAT THE COCAINE "BOOM" IN BOLIVIA COINCIDED WITH THE TOUGH ECONOMIC CRISIS THAT HAS BEEN EXPERIENCED SINCE 1981 AND THAT THE "COCA-DOLLARS" HAVE CUSHIONED THE SOCIAL EXPLOSION.

"LIKE ANY OTHER BUSINESS, COCAINE TRAFFICKING ACQUIRES SYSTEMS OF CAPITAL AND DISTRIBUTION. IT ALSO HAS FIXED EXPENDITURES. THESE "INVESTMENTS" INCLUDE RAW MATERIAL (COCA LEAVES), CHEMICAL PRODUCTS AND LABORATORIES, CHEMISTS, TRANSPORTATION, SERVICES (LEGAL AND FINANCIAL), AND SECURITY, WHICH INCLUDES PAYMENTS OF TIPS TO PUBLIC OFFICIALS, POLITICIANS, JUDGES, AND POLICEMEN. IN SOME COUNTRIES THE GUERRILLAS ARE PAID TO PROVIDE PROTECTION," THE COMMISSION'S REPORT STATES.

THE COMMISSION REPORTS THAT SANTA CRUZ DE LA SIERRA HAS BECOME A PROSPEROUS TOWN PARTLY BECAUSE OF THE DRUG TRADE. "ONE OF THE CLEAREST EFFECTS RECORDED IN THE THREE COCAINE AREAS IS THAT IT PROVIDES JOB OPPORTUNITIES," THE REPORT STATES. IT ADDS THAT BETWEEN 750,000 AND 1.1 MILLION PEOPLE ARE DIRECTLY EMPLOYED IN THE DRUG BUSINESS IN BOLIVIA.

IT STATES THAT COCA LEAF PRODUCTION IS WHAT PROVIDES MOST OF THE JOB OPPORTUNTIES IN THIS BUSINESS. ACCORDING TO THE REPORT, 500,000 PEOPLE ARE EMPLOYED EXCLUSIVELY IN COCA LEAF PRODUCTION.

THE NUMBER OF PRODUCERS IN THE CHAPARE REGION IS ESTIMATED AT 36,864, AND THEY ARE LINKED IN 6 FEDERATIONS, 54 ASSOCIATIONS [CENTRALES], AND 610 UNIONS. IN THE YUNGAS ZONE OF LA PAZ, THE NUMBER OF PRODUCERS IS ESTIMATED AT 26,280, ORGANIZED INTO 4 FEDERATIONS, 14 ASSOCIATIONS, AND 650 COLONIES OR COMMUNITIES.

THE COCA CROP IS ESTIMATED TO BE 45,100 HECTARES (DATA FROM 1988) IN THE CHAPARE ZONE AND 19,695 HECTARES IN THE YUNGAS AREA OF LA PAZ.

THE ESTIMATED COCA PRODUCTION IN THE CHAPARE AND YUNGAS REGIONS AMOUNTS TO 117,486 AND 73,634 TONS PER YEAR, RESPECTIVELY.

THE OFFICIAL REPORT ADDS THAT 12,381 TONS OF COCA WERE EARMARKED FOR CHEWING AND THAT 132,038.3 TONS WERE USED TO PRODUCE COCAINE.

DEV-MUC3-0940 (SRI)

SANTIAGO, NO DATE (RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [INTERVIEW WITH AYLWIN BY SOLA] [EXCERPTS] [CONTINUED] [SOLA] RELATIONS BETWEEN CHILE AND BOLIVIA HAVE BEEN BROKEN. WHAT DO YOU THINK IS THE BEST WAY TO FACE BOLIVIA'S DEMAND FOR A SEA OUTLET?

[AYLWIN] FIRST, CHILE MAINTAINS A FIRM STAND ON THIS SUBJECT, A FACT THAT MUST BE CLEARLY UNDERSTOOD BY THE CHILEAN PEOPLE AND THE REST OF THE WORLD. CHILE DOES NOT HAVE ANY BORDER CONFLICTS WITH BOLIVIA. OUR BORDER WITH BOLIVIA HAS BEEN RATIFIED BY AN INTERNATIONAL TREATY THAT WAS FREELY APPROVED BY OUR TWO COUNTRIES. THIS TREATY CONSTITUTES AN OBLIGATORY NORM FOR CHILE AND BOLIVIA.

SECOND, ACCORDING TO THIS TREATY, CHILE HAS ALWAYS BEEN WILLING TO GRANT BOLIVIA TRANSPORTATION FACILITIES TO PORTS ON THE PACIFIC COAST.

THIRD, IN FACE OF THE BOLIVIAN ASPIRATIONS TO OBTAIN GREATER FACILITIES OR A NEW TRANSIT SYSTEM, THE FIRST THING TO BE DONE IS TO REESTABLISH DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS. THIS IS A BILATERAL ISSUE BETWEEN BOLIVIA AND CHILE. IT IS NOT AN HEMISPHERIC MATTER OR A MATTER TO BE DECIDED BY INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS.

I TRUST THAT BOLIVIA AND CHILE WILL REESTABLISH DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS IN AN ATMOSPHERE OF FRIENDSHIP AND COOPERATION. WE MUST BE AWARE THAT THE WORLD IS HEADING TOWARD INTEGRATION AND THAT IT IS MORE CONVENIENT FOR ALL OF US TO ATTAIN THE BEST AND MOST INTEGRATED RELATIONS POSSIBLE. WE MUST SEEK SOLUTIONS AND, AS THE BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT RECENTLY STATED, WE MUST SEEK IMAGINATIVE SOLUTIONS WITH A 21ST CENTURY AND NOT A 19TH CENTURY VIEW. I HOPE THAT WITHIN THIS SPIRIT WE WILL MANAGE NOT ONLY TO REESTABLISH RELATIONS WITH BOLIVIA, BUT TO ESTABLISH SATISFACTORY RELATIONS FOR THE TWO COUNTRIES.

[SOLA] CHILEAN RELATIONS WITH THE UNITED STATES HAVE NOT BEEN EXCELLENT OVER THE PAST FEW YEARS, AND THE MURDER OF ORLANDO LETELIER IS TIED INTO THIS SITUATION. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION ON THIS SUBJECT, CONSIDERING THAT A U.S. COURT HAS REQUESTED THE EXTRADITION OF GENERAL CONTRERAS AND COLONEL ESPINOZA?

[AYLWIN] WELL, I HOPE THAT CHILE WILL MAINTAIN THE BEST RELATIONS POSSIBLE WITH ALL THE COUNTRIES OF THE WORLD, INCLUDING THE UNITED STATES, A COUNTRY WITH WHICH WE ARE LINKED FOR MANY REASONS. I DISCUSSED THIS SUBJECT WITH PEOPLE FROM U.S. DIPLOMATIC, POLITICAL, AND ECONOMIC CIRCLES, AND I HAVE NOTED THEIR WILLINGNESS TO IMPROVE RELATIONS AND SOLVE THE PROBLEMS THAT ARE CURRENTLY SEPARATING US AS SOON AS A DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT IS REESTABLISHED.

I DO NOT THINK THAT AN EXTRADITION WILL SOLVE THE LETELIER CASE BECAUSE IT HAS ALREADY BEEN RULED ON BY THE SUPREME COURT. IT IS WHAT WE LAWYERS REFER TO AS AN ADJUDGED MATTER. I THINK THAT CHILE CAN DEMONSTRATE ITS WILLINGNESS TO HELP CLARIFY THE CASE AND GUARANTEE JUSTICE, AS IT IS OUR [WORD INDISTINCT] PURPOSE IN ALL HUMAN RIGHTS PROBLEMS, SO AS TO SATISFY THE MOST DEMANDING CONSCIENCES OF THE WORLD. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

DEV-MUC3-0941 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 6 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, BY UNIDENTIFIED SALVADORAN AND INTERNATIONAL REPORTERS] [TEXT] [PONCE, IN PROGRESS] ...THE OFFENSIVE OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] AS OF 11 NOVEMBER HAS BEEN MILITARILY DEFEATED HERE IN THE CITY OF SAN SALVADOR, AS WELL AS IN SAN MIGUEL, USULUTAN, AND ZACATECOLUCA, WHERE THERE WAS GREATER ACTIVITY BY THE SUBVERSIVES. LOGICALLY, AFTER BEING REJECTED SO MUCH, AFTER HAVING LOST SO MANY FIGTHERS AND WAR MATERIEL, THEY DO NOT HAVE THE CAPABILITY TO AGAIN LAUNCH AN OPERATION LIKE THEY DID ON 11 NOVEMBER. THEY WILL CONTINUE WITH INDISCRIMINATE TERRORISM AND SELECTIVE TERRORISM. WE HAVE HERE SOME OF THE FIRST EVIDENCE. FOR EXAMPLE, THE MURDER OF A PERSON USEFUL TO SALVADORAN SOCIETY LIKE DR GUERRERO, THE ACTS OF SABOTAGE AGAINST THE ELECTRICITY SYSTEM, THE DESTRUCTION OF PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION. WE CAN ALSO MENTION THE DESTRUCTION OF SOME GASOLINE STATIONS. BASICALLY, WHAT THEY SEEK IS TO SYSTEMATICALLY DESTROY THE ECONOMY OF THE COUNTRY, TO PROVOKE THE CLOSING OF SOME INDUSTRIAL CENTERS, AND TO BRING ABOUT ECONOMIC CHAOS.

THAT IS WHY, EVEN THOUGH WE BELIEVED WE WERE TAKING RISKS IN THE MILITARY FIELD OF NATIONAL DEFENSE, THE ARMED FORCES CHANGED THE CURFEW HOURS, SO THAT CURFEW HOURS ARE NOW FROM 2300 TO 0500. WE DID THIS BELIEVING THAT THE ECONOMIC ASPECT IS VERY IMPORTANT FOR THE COUNTRY, AND THAT IS WHY WE WANT TO BENEFIT THE INDUSTRIAL, BUSINESS, AND FARMING SECTORS, SO THAT THEY WILL BE ABLE TO CARRY OUT THEIR ACTIVITIES UNDER ALMOST NORMAL CONDITIONS.

WE ALSO CONSIDERED THAT THIS TIME OF THE YEAR WE ARE PICKING COFFEE AND COTTON AND HARVESTING SUGARCANE, AND THESE ARE THE THREE MAIN STAPLES OF OUR ECONOMY. THESE ACTIVITIES ARE MAINLY CARRIED OUT IN THE EVENING, AND THAT IS WHY WE HAVE CHANGED THE CURFEW HOURS TO BENEFIT BUSINESSMEN, WORKERS, AND FARMERS SO THEY CAN SUPPORT THEIR FAMILIES.

[REPORTER] COLONEL, DOES THE PRESIDENT THINK THAT DURING THE COSTA RICAN MEETING ENOUGH PRESSURE CAN BE EXERTED ON NICARAGUA SO THAT IT WILL SUSPEND ASSISTANCE TO THE FMLN AND THE WAR WILL DIMINISH IN THE COUNTRY?

[PONCE] THE CYNICISM OF THE DICTATOR ORTEGA OF THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN FULLY PROVEN. IN THE PREVIOUS MEETINGS WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF ESQUIPULAS II, HE COMMITTED HIMSELF TO DISCONTINUING SUPPORT FOR THE FMLN. THIS TOTAL WAR OFFENSIVE THAT HAS BEEN INFLICTED UPON THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE SHOULD BE SUSPENDED, BECAUSE WE ARE SURE THAT THE MOMENT NICARAGUA AND CUBA -- IT IS THROUGH THOSE COUNTRIES, RATHER THOSE GOVERNMENTS THAT THE COMMUNIST BLOC HAS BEEN HELPING THE FMLN -- THE FMLN WOULD WEAKEN TREMENDOUSLY. [SENTENCE AS HEARD]

AS A MEMBER OF THE ARMED FORCES, AS A MEMBER OF THE HIGH COMMAND, I FEEL VERY PROUD ABOUT THE PROFESSIONAL, DETERMINED, AND COURAGEOUS ATTITUDE WITH WHICH THE OFFICERS, NON-COMMISSIONED OFFICERS, AND TROOPS OF OUR ARMED FORCES HAVE NEUTRALIZED AND DEFEATED THE FMLN OFFENSIVE. IN THIS REGARD, I BELIEVE THAT THE OPINIONS VOICED BY GENERAL THURMAN ARE NOT REALLY IN LINE WITH WHAT WE HAVE LIVED HERE INSIDE THE COUNTRY. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0942 (SRI)

BOGOTA, 6 DEC 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO] [TEXT] COMPATRIOTS, AS YOU KNOW, I CAME TO JAPAN TO FULFILL A MISSION IN THIS COUNTRY, WHICH HAS ALWAYS EXPRESSED ITS SOLIDARITY WITH COLOMBIA.

I HAVE BEEN, HOWEVER, CLOSELY FOLLOWING THE COUNTRY'S SITUATION WITH DEEP SADNESS AND INDIGNATION AFTER THE CRIMINAL ATTACK ON THE DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] FACILITIES, WHICH DEEPLY SHOOK ALL COLOMBIANS.

I HAVE BEEN IN CONSTANT TOUCH WITH CARLOS LEMOS SIMMONS, THE MINISTER DESIGNATED TO ACT ON MY BEHALF AND WITH MY CLOSEST ASSISTANTS.

IN THE PAST FEW DAYS, WE HAVE EXPERIENCED AN INCREASE IN THE VILE ATTACKS CARRIED OUT BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKING CRIMINAL ORGANIZATION. THOSE ATTACKS HAVE TAKEN THE LIFE OF MANY INNOCENT COLOMBIANS. MEN, WOMEN, AND CHILDREN, WHO WERE IN THE PRIME OF THEIR LIVES, HAVE BEEN SACRIFICED BY MAD ACTIONS CARRIED OUT BY CRIMINALS, WHO INTEND TO CONTROL AN ENTIRE PEOPLE, GOVERNMENT, AND COUNTRY THROUGH TERROR AND DESTRUCTION.

THEY WILL NOT DEFEAT US. WE ARE AND WILL CONTINUE STRUGGLING. THE WAR HAS BEEN DECLARED ON THE ENTIRE COUNTRY AND ON DEMOCRACY. WE WILL NOT FALL UNDER THE CONTROL OF THE NARCOTERRORISTS' BLOODY TYRANNY.

LAST NIGHT, THE COUNTRY LEARNED ABOUT THE COLOMBIAN CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES'S DECISION TO APPROVE THE CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS WITH THE INCLUSION OF THE EXTRADITION ISSUE IN THE REFERENDUM.

THE CONFIRMATION THAT THE AVIANCA PLANE CRASH WAS CAUSED BY A BOMB; THE MURDER OF BERNARDO JARAMILLO URIBE, ROVING 13TH JUDGE OF CRIMINAL INVESTIGATION; AND THIS MORNING'S ATROCIOUS ATTACK ON THE DAS FACILITIES FURTHER PROVES THAT THE DECISION MADE BY THE CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES IS HIGHLY UNSUITABLE FOR THE ENTIRE COUNTRY.

WE ABSOLUTELY CANNOT ACCEPT DRUG TRAFFICKERS TRYING TO FORCE OUR LEGISLATORS TO ADOPT A DECISION THAT WOULD ONLY BRING MORE DESTRUCTION AND DEATH TO COLOMBIA, BECAUSE IF THE INCLUSION OF THE EXTRADITION ISSUE IS APPROVED IN THE REFERENDUM, IT WOULD NOT BE A DECISION MADE BY THE SOVEREIGN WILL OF THE PEOPLE, BUT BY THE FORCE OF BULLETS AND TERROR.

COLOMBIANS HAVE UNFORTUNATELY PAID TOO HIGH A PRICE TO FIND OUT WHAT THESE CRIMINALS REALLY THINK. THEY SPOKE ABOUT A TRUCE AND THEN THEY MURDERED A JUDGE. SUBSEQUENTLY, THE CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES APPROVED THE INCLUSION OF THE EXTRADITION ISSUE INTO THE REFERENDUM AND, IN GOOD FAITH, MANY PEOPLE THOUGHT THAT WAS THE FIRST STEP TOWARD PEACE WITH THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS. THEY WERE WRONG. THE NEXT DAY THE DAS FACILITIES WERE ATTACKED.

THOSE ACTIONS PROVE WHAT THOSE CRIMINALS ARE CAPABLE OF DOING TO OBTAIN A FAVORABLE DECISION IN THE REFERENDUM. THEY DO NOT CONDUCT AN ELECTION CAMPAIGN, BUT A CAMPAIGN OF TERROR TO ATTAIN THEIR GOALS.

I NOW REITERATE WHAT I SAID IN MY SPEECH BEFORE LEAVING FOR JAPAN. I SAID THAT THE CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS WITH THE INCLUSION OF THE REFERENDUM IS HIGHLY UNSUITABLE.

I SHARE THE SORROW AND SADNESS OF ALL MY COMPATRIOTS, ESPECIALLY VICTIMS' RELATIVES. OUR INDIGNATION MUST REPRESENT ALL COLOMBIANS' INTENTION TO JOIN EFFORTS AND DROP PERSONAL INTERESTS.

COMPATRIOTS, WE MUST NEVER, WE WILL NEVER SUCCUMB TO THE NARCOTERRORISTS. THE STABLE DEMOCRACY WE HAVE BUILT AND DEFENDED WITH GREAT EFFORT FOR OVER 1 CENTURY IS ENDANGERED. THROUGHOUT ITS HISTORY, COLOMBIA HAS OVERCOME MORE DIFFICULT TIMES. LET US ALL STAND UP WITH FAITH, COURAGE, AND FIRMNESS TO DEFEND OUR HOMELAND AND FREEDOM. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.

DEV-MUC3-0943 (SRI)

CLANDESTINE, 7 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION. PAY CLOSE ATTENTION TO THE FOLLOWING INFORMATION. FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] TROOPS STARTED TO ATTACK ENEMY POSITIONS IN SAN SALVADOR AT 2200 ON 6 DECEMBER, ENTERING THE CITY FROM THE NORTH, SOUTH, EAST, AND WEST.

ATTENTION. REPORT FROM SOYAPANGO, SAN SALVADOR. FMLN ANTIAIRCRAFT UNITS HAVE DOWNED AN ARMED FORCES HELICOPTER GUNSHIP DURING THE BATTLES THAT HAVE BEEN ONGOING IN SOYPANGO. WE AWAIT THE OFFICIAL MILITARY REPORT ON THIS ACTION IN SAN SALVADOR. WE ARE NO LONGER ONLY DOWNING AIRPLANES AND HELICOPTERS IN THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY. THOUSANDS OF SAN SALVADOR RESIDENTS WERE ABLE TO SEE THE DOWNING OF A HELICOPTER GUNSHIP IN THE METROPOLITAN AREA. WE DOWNED A HELICOPTER GUNSHIP THAT WAS SHOOTING AT THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN SOYAPANGO, SAN SALVADOR. WE HAD ALREADY WARNED [AIR FORCE GENERAL JUAN RAFAEL] BUSTILLO. WE ARE NOT GOING TO ALLOW WOMEN, CHILDREN, AND RESIDENTS OF SAN SALVADOR TO BE BOMBED AGAIN. WE ARE NOT GOING TO ALLOW MORE GENOCIDIAL ACTIONS IN SAN SALVADOR. ONCE AND FOR ALL, WE REAFFIRM TO THE FASCIST COMMAND STAFF THAT WE ARE NOT GOING TO ALLOW MORE BOMBING IN SAN SALVADOR. STARTING RIGHT NOW, GENTLEMEN, THE PEOPLE FORBID THAT YOU BOMB THE CITY. WE FORBID YOU TO DO SO, AND FOR THAT PURPOSE WE WILL DOWN YOUR AIRPLANES AND HELICOPTERS. OUR PEOPLE KNOW THAT AN A-37 AIRCRAFT WAS DOWNED IN SAN MIGUEL, A HELICOPTER WAS DOWNED IN SAN MIGUEL AT THE BEGINNING OF THE OFFENSIVE, A PUSH-PULL PLANE WAS DOWNED IN USULUTAN, AND NOW THIS HELICOPTER IN SOYAPANGO. WE AWAIT A REPORT ON THE POSSIBLE DEATH OF THE HELICOPTER'S CREW. WE AWAIT AN OFFICIAL REPORT FROM OUR COMRADES IN SOYAPANGO.

MEANWHILE, WE ALSO HAVE REPORTS THAT FIGHTING CONTINUES AT THIS TIME IN THE NORTHEASTERN AREA OF SAN SALVADOR. WE AWAIT AN OFFICIAL REPORT ON THE NUMBER OF CASUALTIES THAT HAVE BEEN INFLICTED ON THE ENEMY. OUR MEN HAVE INFLICTED MANY CASUALTIES ON SOLDIERS FROM THE ATCATL BATTALION, BELLOSO BATTALION, PARATROOPERS BATTALION, NATIONAL POLICE, TREASURY POLICE, 4TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, SONSONATE MILITARY DETACHMENT NO 6, AND 5TH INFANTRY BRIGADE DURING THE CLASHES THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE SINCE LAST NIGHT.

DEV-MUC3-0944 (SRI)

BOGOTA, 7 DEC 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO HAS BROUGHT FORWARD HIS RETURN TO THE COUNTRY BY 10 HOURS, MEANING HE HAS CANCELLED SOME EVENTS HE WAS SCHEDULED TO ATTEND IN TOKYO, AND WILL RETURN TO THE COUNTRY AROUND NOON ON 9 DECEMBER. HE WAS INITIALLY SCHEDULED TO RETURN AROUND MIDNIGHT ON SATURDAY.

PRESIDENT BARCO TOLD THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY TODAY THAT IN NO WAY WILL COLOMBIA ACCEPT THE INTERVENTION OF FOREIGN TROOPS TO FIGHT TERRORISM, VIOLENCE, AND ORGANIZED CRIME. DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE WITH JAPANESE AND FOREIGN MEDIA REPRESENTATIVES IN TOKYO, PRESIDENT BARCO ALSO SAID THAT THE LIBERAL PARTY WILL PROBABLY WIN THE 1990 PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS BECAUSE IT HAS CAPABLE PEOPLE AND IT IS THE MAJORITY PARTY. HE ALSO REFERRED TO A MID-AIR PLANE EXPLOSION -- A TERRORIST ACTION, IN HIS WORDS -- AND THE ATTACK PERPETRATED AGAINST THE DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] HEADQUARTERS IN BOGOTA WITH APPROXIMATELY 500 KG OF EXPLOSIVES.

PRESIDENT BARCO WILL RETURN TO BOGOTA AT 0900 ON 9 DECEMBER. HE WILL DEPART FROM NARITA AIRPORT, LOCATED 2 HOURS FROM TOKYO, [WORDS INDISTINCT] MEETING WITH JAPANESE INVESTORS AND POSSIBLE BUYERS OF COLOMBIAN COFFEE. THE EVENT WAS ORGANIZED BY THE COLOMBIAN COFFEE GROWERS ASSOCIATION AND THE GRAN COLOMBIAN MERCHANT FLEET'S REPRESENTATIVES IN THE FAR EAST.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [BARCO] APPROXIMATELY 2 WEEKS AGO AN AIRPLANE EXPLODED WHEN TAKING OFF FROM BOGOTA, AND EXPERTS WHO CAME FROM MANY PARTS OF THE WORLD HAVE DISCOVERED THAT IT WAS CAUSED BY A BOMB PLACED ON BOARD RATHER THAN A PROBLEM OF PRESSURIZATION.

THE OTHER CASE IS THE ATTACK WHICH WAS PERPETRATED LAST NIGHT, 2 NIGHTS AGO, AGAINST THE INTELLIGENCE HEADQUARTERS OF THE NATIONAL POLICE. YOU HAVE READ OR REPORTED THAT A LARGE AMOUNT... [CHANGES THOUGHT] ABOUT 500 KG OF DYNAMITE PLACED IN A TRUCK EXPLODED AND CAUSED THE COLLAPSE OR CONSIDERABLE DAMAGE OF THE GENERAL HEADQUARTERS OF THE COLOMBIAN INTELLIGENCE SERVICES.

THE TERRORIST ATTACK WAS PERPETRATED AGAINST THE OFFICES OF THE DAS, WHICH IS -- AS I SAID BEFORE -- WHERE THE MOST IMPORTANT INTELLIGENCE ACTIVITIES AGAINST ORGANIZED CRIME AND DRUG TRAFFICKING ARE CARRIED OUT. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0945 (SRI)

TOKYO (JAPAN), 7 DEC 89 (KYODO) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS SAID HERE ON THURSDAY HIS GOVERNMENT WILL NOT BOW TO TERRORIST THREATS EXEMPLIFIED BY WEDNESDAY'S BOMB EXPLOSION IN BOGOTA.

BARCO, WHO IS ON A FOUR-DAY VISIT TO JAPAN THROUGH FRIDAY, SAID THAT SUCH SUBVERSIVE ACTIVITIES ARE BASED ON THE MISTAKEN BELIEF OF TERRORISTS THAT VIOLENCE CAN TOPPLE THE GOVERNMENT.

HE SAID HIS GOVERNMENT WOULD FIGHT OFF SUCH CHALLENGES.

A TRUCK, PACKED WITH DYNAMITE, EXPLODED IN FRONT OF THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE DEPARTMENT OF ADMINISTRATIVE SECURITY, COLOMBIA'S FEDERAL INVESTIGATIONS POLICE, ON WEDNESDAY.

AT LEAST 35 PEOPLE DIED AND 350 PEOPLE WERE WOUNDED IN THE BLAST, WHICH IS BELIEVED TO HAVE BEEN RELATED TO THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT'S ATTEMPTS TO ELIMINATE THE DRUG TRADE.

COLOMBIA IS SAID TO BE THE LARGEST EXPORTER OF THE ILLICIT DRUG, COCAINE, TO THE UNITED STATES AND OTHER WESTERN COUNTRIES.

THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT HAS INTENSIFIED ITS CRACKDOWN ON THE COCAINE SMUGGLERS SINCE THE ASSASSINATION OF A LEADING PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE ON AUGUST 18.

BARCO, SPEAKING AT THE JAPAN NATIONAL PRESS CLUB EXPRESSED CONCERN ABOUT AN INCREASE OF COCAINE CONSUMPTION IN THE UNITED STATES AND EUROPEAN COUNTRIES, AND CALLED FOR WESTERN INDUSTRIALIZED NATIONS TO HELP STABILIZE THE POLITICAL SITUATION IN COLOMBIA, WITH PARTICULAR EMPHASIS ON MORE ECONOMIC SUPPORT.

ASKED ABOUT THE POSSIBILITY COLOMBIA WOULD CALL ON THE UNITED STATES TO HELP SOLVE THE PROBLEM WITH ARMED FORCES, THE PRESIDENT EMPHASIZED HE HAS NO INTENTION OF ALLOWING ANY INTERFERENCE BY FOREIGN COUNTRIES IN HIS NATION.

BARCO IS SCHEDULED TO LEAVE JAPAN FOR COLOMBIA FRIDAY.

DEV-MUC3-0946 (SRI)

CLANDESTINE, 7 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] ATTENTION, NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL PRESS. THIS IS A REPORT FROM SAN SALVADOR.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] REPORTS THAT AS OF 2200 ON 6 DECEMBER, FMLN COLUMNS [WORDS INDISTINCT] INSIDE THE CAPITAL CITY, STAGED ATTACKS ON MILITARY GARRISONS, AND CARRIED OUT SABOTAGE ACTIVITIES IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

AFTER BREAKING UP THE ENEMY'S DEFENSIVE POSITIONS IN SAN SALVADOR, THE FMLN OCCUPIED VARIOUS AREAS IN THE CAPITAL. THE GENERAL STAFF INSTALLATIONS WERE ATTACKED WITH 60-MM MORTARS. [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND AIR SUPPORT AGAINST OUR POSITIONS. WE ARE AWAITING DETAILED REPORTS OF THIS ATTACK ON THE GENERAL STAFF WITH 60-MM MORTARS.

SIMULTANEOUSLY, OUR GUERRILLA COLUMNS IN SAN SALVADOR ESTABLISHED POSITIONS IN SAN BENITO, ESCALON, LA MASCOTA, AND MAQUILIGUAT NEIGHBORHOODS, AND ALSO IN SAN ANTONIO ABAD AND THE NORTHERN PERIPHERY OF THE GENERAL STAFF INSTALLATIONS, BATTLING WITH MARINES, MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 7 FROM AGUACHAPAN, THE ELITE BATTALIONS STATIONED THERE, NATIONAL POLICE FORCES, AND UNITS FROM THE SAN BENITO BATTALION, WHICH IS IN CHARGE OF GUARDING THE GENERAL STAFF INSTALLATIONS. IT IS REPORTED THAT ONE M-16 RIFLE, PISTOLS, MILITARY EQUIPMENT, AND A LARGE QUANTITY OF AMMUNITION WERE SEIZED FROM THE ARMY.

AT 0100, OUR ANTIAIRCRAFT UNITS OPENED FIRE ON TWO HELICOPTERS IN ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD. ONE OF THEM WAS A TRANSPORT HELICOPTER AND THE OTHER A GUNSHIP. BOTH WERE DAMAGED. MEANWHILE, OUR GUERRILLAS ALSO USED MORTARS DURING AN ATTACK ON THE SAN BENITO BATTALION'S POSITIONS NEAR ZONA ROSA. AT THE SAME TIME, AN ATTACK WAS CARRIED OUT AGAINST THE CETIPOL [POLICE INSTRUCTION CENTER] POLICE ACADEMY IN SANTA TECLA, USING 81-MM MORTARS. ATTACKS WERE STAGED AGAINST THE CETIPOL'S PERIPHERAL DEFENSE FROM ANOTHER DIRECTION UNTIL LATE THIS MORNING.

MEANWHILE, AN ATTACK CARRIED OUT FROM THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR LED TO INCURSIONS IN SOYAPANGO, MEJICANOS, AND AYUTUXTEPEQUE. IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE THE FMLN CARRIED OUT ANNIHILATION MANEUVERS AGAINST THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE'S SORIANO BATTALION, WHICH WAS STATIONED ON EL CARMEN HILL WHERE WE KILLED 15 SOLDIERS AND WOUNDED 30. AMONG THESE CASUALTIES IS AN OFFICER FROM THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE.

THE FMLN SEIZED FIVE M-16 RIFLES, ONE [WORD INDISTINCT] GRENADE LAUNCHER, [WORDS INDISTINCT], FOUR M-60 MACHINEGUNS FROM THE ANNIHILATED TROOPS. A MILITARY VEHICLE WAS PARTIALLY DESTROYED, AND AN ENEMY PATROL WAS TOTALLY DESTROYED.

PRAL [LONG-RANGE RECONNAISSANCE PATROL] REINFORCEMENT UNITS ATTEMPTED TO SUPPORT THE ARMY TROOPS UNDER ATTACK BUT THEY WERE REPELLED BY THE FMLN.

THE ELECTRICITY SYSTEM IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE CAPITAL CITY WAS SABOTAGED, LEAVING 90 PERCENT OF THE CITY WITHOUT POWER.

ATTENTION. HERE IS THE REPORT ON THE HELICOPTER DOWNED IN SOYAPANGO. ATTENTION. ON 6 DECEMBER THERE WERE CLASHES IN SAN JOSE CORTEZ, JURISDICTION OF SOYAPANGO, WITH THE BELLOSO BATTALION WHICH RECEIVED STRONG AERIAL SUPPORT UP UNTIL THE AFTERNOON HOURS. HELICOPTERS MACHINEGUNNED AND ROCKETED THIS DENSELY POPULATED AREA. OUR ANTIAIRCRAFT UNITS, REAFFIRMING OUR DETERMINATION TO DEFEND THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AGAINST AERIAL ATTACKS, OPENED FIRE AND HIT A GUNSHIP. THE GUNSHIP FELL TO THE GROUND AT THE MORAZAN TOBACCO COMPANY.

GUERRILLA UNITS SIMULTANEOUSLY ATTACKED PARAMILITARY FORCES IN TONACATEPEQUE DURING THE EARLY HOURS OF 7 DECEMBER, WHICH PROMPTED AERIAL SUPPORT BECAUSE THIS AREA IS ON THE AIR FORCE'S SECURITY PERIMETER, BUT CALLS FROM THE BATTALION THAT WAS BEING ANNIHILATED ON THE EL CARMEN HILL IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE WENT UNHEEDED.

THESE ARE THE FIRST REPORTS ON ALL THE ACTIVITIES UNDER WAY IN SAN SALVADOR, WHERE AT 2200 ON 6 DECEMBER OUR GUERRILLA UNITS BEGAN TO FORCE AND BREAK THE DAM THAT THE HIGH COMMAND BUILT AT THE GENERAL STAFF'S BUNKER [WORDS INDISTINCT] OUR COLUMNS, UNTIL THEY PENETRATED THE AFOREMENTIONED AREAS, FIGHTING IN THE ESCALON AND SAN BENITO NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE THE OLIGARCHS LIVE.

ACTIONS HAVE ALSO TAKEN PLACE THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY. FACTORIES HAVE BEEN SABOTAGED, STRATEGIC HIGHWAYS HAVE BEEN CONTROLLED, POSITIONS HAVE BEEN ESTABLISHED, AND TOWNS HAVE BEEN OCCUPIED. WE WILL FURNISH FURTHER INFORMATION LATER.

DEV-MUC3-0947 (SRI)

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 7 DEC 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ PREDICTED A SERIOUS CRISIS ON THE CONTINENT IF A SOLUTION FOR THE CENTRAL AMERICAN CONFLICT IS NOT FOUND. HE APPEALED TO "THE FOREIGN POWERS" TO HALT THEIR INTERVENTION IN THE SUBREGION.

IN A NEWS CONFERENCE BROADCAST OVER TELEVISION FOR ALL THE COUNTRY, PEREZ TODAY PREDICTED THAT THE COMING CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS SUMMIT TO BE HELD IN SAN JOSE WILL FAIL IF WHAT HE DESCRIBED AS "FOREIGN POWERS" DO NOT HALT MILITARY AND FINANCIAL SUPPORT TO THE VARIOUS FACTIONS FIGHTING IN THE CONVULSED REGION.

THE COSTA RICAN, NICARAGUAN, GUATEMALAN, SALVADORAN, AND HONDURAN PRESIDENTS WILL MEET IN SAN JOSE SHORTLY TO FIND A SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT AND REACTIVATE THE ESQUIPULAS II AND TELA PACIFICATION ACCORDS.

"IF THE FOREIGN POWERS, BE THEY THE UNITED STATES, CUBA, THE SOVIET UNION, OR WHATEVER, PERSIST ON DISTURBING A DIRECT ANALYSIS AND PREVENTING A FRIENDLY AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS, THIS SUMMIT WILL COME TO NOTHING," PEREZ POINTED OUT.

PEREZ SAID THAT THE RECENT FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] OFFENSIVE IN EL SALVADOR INTERFERED SERIOUSLY WITH THE REGIONAL PACIFICATION PROCESS. HE REQUESTED THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT CLARIFY THE DEATH OF SIX JESUITS WHO WERE MURDERED BY THE DEATH SQUADS.

"THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT THE SALVADORAN CRISIS OCCURRED AT AN UNTIMELY MOMENT, WHEN THINGS WERE GOING SO WELL. THE RESPONSIBILITY FOR THIS, HOWEVER, RESTS HEAVILY WITH THE FMLN AND THOSE WHO GAVE ARMS TO THE REBELS SO THEY COULD CARRY OUT SO MAJOR A MILITARY OPERATION," HE SAID.

HE ADDED, HOWEVER, THAT "THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS ACCOUNTABLE FOR WHAT HAPPENED TO THE SIX JESUITS, WHO WERE MURDERED IN A LOWLY AND WICKED MANNER. THIS MUST BE CLARIFIED ALSO," HE SAID.

THE VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT, WHO OFFERED TO MEDIATE IN THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT, SAID HE REPORTED TO COSTA RICAN PRESIDENT OSCAR ARIAS, THE SUMMIT'S HOST, THE CONTENTS OF A LETTER THAT THE FMLN SENT TO PEREZ, IN WHICH THE ORGANIZATION PROPOSES A CEASE-FIRE WITH INTERNATIONAL VERIFICATION.

PEREZ ASKED THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS TO BE MORE FLEXIBLE BECAUSE "THE FATE OF ALL OF LATIN AMERICA IS AT STAKE."

REFERRING DIRECTLY TO THE SAN JOSE SUMMIT -- HE SAID HE WAS INSTRUMENTAL IN CHOOSING COSTA RICA AS SITE FOR THE MEETING -- PEREZ ASSUMED AN "OPTIMISTIC YET CONCERNED" STANCE WITH REGARD TO THE MEETING'S RESULTS.

HE FINALLY SAID: "THIS SAN JOSE SUMMIT WILL MAKE THINGS CONFORM TO ESQUIPULAS II AND TELA IF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS ARE LEFT ALONE AND PARTICULARLY IF THEY KNOW THAT NONE OF THEM WILL BE BACKED BY ANY ONE POWER WITH ARMS OR MONEY."

DEV-MUC3-0949 (SRI)

LIMA, 7 DEC 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [EXCERPTS] PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA ANNOUNCED THAT THE BORDERS WILL BE REOPENED. HE SAID THAT THE RESULTS OF THE MEASURES ADOPTED 15 DAYS AGO ARE POSITIVE. THE PRESIDENT CALLED ON ALL BUSINESSMEN AND INDUSTRIALISTS NOT TO SPECULATE ON PRICES. HE ALSO REITERATED HIS SUPPORT FOR ECONOMY AND FINANCE MINISTER CESAR VASQUEZ BAZAN, WHO HE SAID IS MAKING GREAT EFFORTS TO FACE THE PERUVIAN ECONOMIC SITUATION. GARCIA MADE THESE STATEMENTS AFTER A MEETING WITH THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] THE BORDER CLOSURE MEASURE EXPIRES TODAY. WILL IT BE EXTENDED?

[GARCIA] NO, THE BORDERS WERE NEVER CLOSED. WE ONLY ESTABLISHED SOME RESTRICTIONS ON THE USE OF TRANSIT PERMITS IN TACNA TO PREVENT AN INCREASE OF SMUGGLING BEFORE THE YEAR-END FESTIVITIES. THE 15-DAY TERM OF THAT MEASURE HAS EXPIRED, AND IT WILL NOT BE EXTENDED.

[REPORTER] APPARENTLY, THAT MEASURE HAS NOT HAD GOOD RESULTS.

[GARCIA] I THINK THAT IN GENERAL IT HAS YIELDED POSITIVE RESULTS BECAUSE SMUGGLING HAS PROBABLY DECREASED SOMEWHAT. AS YOU KNOW, A FEW YEARS AGO CHILE ESTABLISHED THE IQUIQUE FREE ZONE WHERE PRODUCTS ARE SOLD TO PERU AND BOLIVIA. THUS A STABLE MARKET OF HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE WHICH DAILY PASS THOROUGH THE TACNA BORDER WITH SMALL PACKAGES HAS BEEN ESTABLISHED.

WE SIMPLY RESTRICTED THE PERMITS THEY USE TO BRING IN A TAPE RECORDER OR LASER DISC PLAYERS. I UNDERSTAND THAT SMUGGLING DECREASED FOR A FEW DAYS. HOWEVER, THAT MERCHANDISE ENTERED THE COUNTRY BY OTHER MEANS. WE CANNOT IMPOSE TOO MANY RESTRICTIONS, BUT WE CAN ASK THE CUSTOMS OFFICE AND THE POLICE TO INCREASE THEIR EFFORTS TO CONTROL EXCESSIVE SMUGGLING INTO THE COUNTRY.

[REPORTER] DO YOU THINK THAT THE FREE-MARKET DOLLAR WILL DROP BY JANUARY?

[GARCIA] I AM SURE IT WILL. LAST YEAR, LIKE NOW, THE FREE- MARKET DOLLAR EXCHANGE RATE INCREASED SHARPLY BECAUSE COMPANIES ARE PAYING YEAR-END BONUSES AND THEY ARE CONVERTING THEIR PROFITS INTO DOLLARS. PEOPLE ARE TAKING HOLIDAY TRIPS AND BUYING MORE GOODS AND HOME APPLIANCES. THEREFORE, THE DOLLAR DEMAND AND PRICES HAVE INCREASED.

LAST YEAR, WHEN THE MUC [SINGLE EXCHANGE MARKET] DOLLAR EXCHANGE RATE WAS AT 500 INTIS TO A DOLLAR, THE FREE-MARKET DOLLAR CLIMBED TO 2,000 INTIS. LATER IT DROPPED TO 1,000 INTIS IN JANUARY. I THINK THAT THE SAME THING WILL HAPPEN THIS YEAR. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

[REPORTER] THERE HAVE BEEN SOME RUMORS IN THE PAST FEW DAYS THAT THE ECONOMY MINISTER IS ABOUT TO RESIGN OR IS BEING PRESSURED TO RESIGN. IS THIS TRUE?

[GARCIA] THE ONLY PERSON WHO COULD PRESSURE HIM IS THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC, AND I CAN TELL YOU THAT I AM NOT PRESSURING HIM. WE ACKNOWLEDGE THE CURRENT DIFFICULTIES OF THE PERUVIAN ECONOMY AS WELL AS THE EFFORTS OF THE ECONOMY MINISTER. I EXPRESS MY RECOGNITION OF AND SUPPORT FOR THE ECONOMY MINISTER BECAUSE HE IS YOUNG, WELL-INTENTIONED, AND VERY HONEST; HE HAS PROGRESSIVE IDEAS. HE IS MAKING EVERY EFFORT POSSIBLE TO STABILIZE THE ECONOMY AS WELL AS POSSIBLE, AND HE SPONSORED A DEMOCRATIC TRANSITION AFTER THE ELECTIONS.

[REPORTER] TODAY DID THE COUNCIL OF MINISTERS DISCUSS A WAGE INCREASE FOR THIS MONTH?

[GARCIA] THAT POINT MUST BE DEFINED BY THE ECONOMY AND LABOR MINISTERS. TODAY, IN ADDITION TO THE BORDER ISSUE, WE DISCUSSED A SUBJECT WE HAD TALKED ABOUT A FEW WEEKS AGO.

ON THAT OCCASION I LISTENED TO A REPORT FROM THE SO-CALLED COMMANDER HUAIHUACU. HE IS CHIEF OF SOME 85 PEASANT COMMUNITIES ALONG THE APURIMAC RIVER WHICH HAVE REBELLED AGAINST SHINING PATH CONTROL. THE APURIMAC RIVER SEPARATES THE AYACUCHO AND CUSCO DEPARTMENTS, AND THESE PEASANTS LIVE IN AN AREA CALLED OREJA DE PERRO IN LA MAR PROVINCE. THEY HAVE CARRIED OUT A DEMOCRATIC UPRISING AND ORGANIZED THEMSELVES TO KEEP SHINING PATH FROM ENTERING THEIR COMMUNITIES.

THIS SO-CALLED COMMANDER HUAIHUACU, WHO IS A MAN OF ACTION, HAS ORGANIZED APPROXIMATELY 85 COMMUNITIES ON THE BANKS OF THE APURIMAC RIVER, IN AYACUCHO PROVINCE OF LA MAR AND THE CUSCO DISTRICT OF CHARATE. HUAIHUACU HAS COME TO LIMA SEEKING SUPPORT.

WE HAVE DECIDED WITH THE DEFENSE MINISTRY TO GO TOMORROW TO RINCONADA BAJA AREA IN LA MAR PROVINCE, SHINING PATH'S PRIMARY AREA OF ACTIVITY FOR 10 YEARS. THERE I WILL DEDICATE A RADIO STATION TO BE CALLED RADIO DEMOCRACIA. ITS AIM WILL BE TO BROADCAST NEWS AND DEMOCRATIC AND PATRIOTIC MESSAGES FROM THAT AREA WHICH IS A CENTER OF PEASANT RESISTANCE AGAINST TERRORISM.

WE WILL ARRIVE THERE TOMORROW AND TALK WITH THE PEASANT LEADERS WHO FOR YEARS HAVE FOUGHT SHINING PATH TOGETHER WITH OUR NAVY INFANTRY UNITS STATIONED IN LUISIANA AND SAN FRANCISCO. [PASSAGE OMITTED] [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0951 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 8 DEC 89 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] A PUBLIC OPINION POLL CONDUCTED BY THE A.M.S. COMPANY [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] AMONG THE SALVADORAN PUBLIC ON 5 AND 6 DECEMBER REVEALS THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE'S OUTRIGHT REPUDIATION OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORIST OFFENSIVE.

ACCORDING TO SOURCES CLOSE TO THE LABOR UNION SECTOR, THE A.M.S. COMPANY, WHICH HAS BEEN WORKING IN EL SALVADOR FOR MANY YEARS, SPECIALIZES IN PUBLIC OPINION POLLS THAT ENJOY GREAT RESPECT AND CREDIBILITY BECAUSE OF THEIR EFFICIENCY, ACCURACY, AND RELIABILITY.

THE POLL'S RESULTS SHOW CLEAR AND STRONG SUPPORT FOR THE ROLE THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES HAVE PLAYED. AT THE SAME TIME, THE POLL REVEALS A CLEAR REJECTION OF THE DAMAGE INFLICTED BY TERRORISM AND THE POSSIBLE PARTICIPATION OF THE FMLN IN THE MURDERS OF THE FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] LEADERS AND THE JESUIT PRIESTS.

DESPITE ALL THE SUFFERING RESULTING FROM THE SNEAKY, SUBVERSIVE ATTACK AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR YEARNING FOR PEACE, THE MAJORITY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE BELIEVES THE DIALOGUE PROCESS MUST CONTINUE.

IN RESPONSE TO A QUESTION AS TO HOW THEY WOULD RATE THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES' ROLE, 37 PERCENT OF THE PEOPLE CHARACTERIZED IT AS EXCELLENT; 44 PERCENT AS GOOD; 9.3 PERCENT AS AVERAGE; 2.7 PERCENT AS BAD; 0.3 PERCENT AS VERY BAD; AND 6.7 PERCENT DID NOT RESPOND.

AS TO HOW WOULD THEY RATE THE JOB DONE BY THE GOVERNMENT, 21.3 PERCENT CHARACTERIZED IT AS EXCELLENT; 54.3 PERCENT AS GOOD; 15 PERCENT AS AVERAGE; 2.7 PERCENT AS BAD; 0.3 PERCENT AS VERY BAD; AND 6.4 PERCENT DID NOT RESPOND.

AS TO HOW WOULD THEY DESCRIBE PRESIDENT CRISTIANI'S PERFORMANCE, 29 PERCENT SAID EXCELLENT; 51.3 GOOD; 11 PERCENT AVERAGE; 1.3 BAD; 0 PERCENT VERY BAD; AND 7.4 PERCENT DID NOT RESPOND.

WHEN ASKED WHO THEY THOUGHT WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE BREAKING OF THE DIALOGUE, 63 PERCENT SAID THE FMLN; 5.7 PERCENT SAID THE ARMED FORCES; 4.3 PERCENT SAID THE GOVERNMENT; 22.7 PERCENT SAID THEY DO NOT KNOW; AND 3.9 PERCENT DID NOT RESPOND.

WHEN ASKED WHO THEY BELIEVED WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE FENASTRAS MASSACRE, 26.3 PERCENT SAID THE FMLN; 6.3 PERCENT SAID THE ARMED FORCES; 3.3 PERCENT SAID THE GOVERNMENT; 55.7 PERCENT SAID THEY DID NOT KNOW; AND 8.4 PERCENT DID NOT RESPOND.

REGARDING THE MASSACRE OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, 26 PERCENT ATTRIBUTED IT TO THE FMLN; 7 PERCENT TO THE ARMED FORCES; 5.3 PERCENT TO THE GOVERNMENT; 53.3 PERCENT SAID THEY DID NOT KNOW; AND 8.4 PERCENT DID NOT RESPOND.

WHEN ASKED WHETHER THE DIALOGUE SHOULD CONTINUE, 80 PERCENT RESPONDED YES; 14 PERCENT SAID NO; 5.7 PERCENT SAID THEY DID NOT KNOW; AND 0.3 PERCENT DID NOT RESPOND.

REGARDING THE CURFEW, 29 PERCENT CONSIDERED IT VERY GOOD; 55.3 PERCENT SAID IT IS GOOD; 10 PERCENT SAID IT IS NEITHER GOOD NOR BAD; 5 PERCENT SAID IT IS BAD; AND 0.1 PERCENT DID NOT RESPOND.

DEV-MUC3-0957 (SRI)

CLANDESTINE, 6 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY, URNG] [TEXT] WE CONDEMN GUATEMALAN INTERVENTION IN EL SALVADOR. THE URNG GENERAL COMMAND EXPRESSES ITS STRONG SOLIDARITY AND DEEP ADMIRATION FOR THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THEIR VANGUARD, THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT], WHO WITH GREAT HEROISM AND DETERMINATION ARE WRITING ONE OF THE MOST GLORIOUS PAGES OF ITS HISTORY.

WE VIEW WITH PROFOUND INDIGNATION HOW THE OFFICERS OF LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO THE 1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE CAPTAIN GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] AND THE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] GOVERNMENT HEADED BY CRISTIANI, IN VIEW OF THEIR INABILITY TO DEFEAT, REPEL, OR CONTAIN THE HEROIC FMLN, HAVE DECIDED TO CONTINUE MASSIVE BOMBINGS AGAINST DEFENSELESS CIVILIANS, SOW DEATH AND DESTRUCTION, AND COMMIT MASSACRES.

THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES, WHICH ARE DESPERATE DUE TO THE VICTORIOUS ADVANCES OF THE FMLN FORCES -- WHICH HAVE NOT ONLY MAINTAINED, BUT EXPANDED THEIR POSITIONS IN SAN SALVADOR AND THE REST OF THE TERRITORY OF THAT FRATERNAL COUNTRY -- HAVE LOST CONTROL.

WITH VENGEANCE IN THEIR MINDS, THEY HAVE BEGUN TO IMPLEMENT A NUMBER OF CRIMINAL ACTIONS AGAINST ALL THOSE IDENTIFIED WITH THE JUST STRUGGLES OF THE MAJORITY. AT DAWN ON 16 NOVEMBER, SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND TWO HUMBLE WOMEN WHO WORKED FOR THEM WERE BRUTALLY ASSASSINATED. WE SHARE THE GREAT SORROW OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THE COMMUNITY OF JESUIT PRIESTS AND ADD OUR PROTEST TO THOSE OF OTHERS THROUGHOUT THE WORLD WHO HAVE ALREADY PROTESTED THESE DESPICABLE ASSASSINATIONS.

THE URNG GENERAL COMMAND STRONGLY CONDEMNS THIS INCIDENT AND URGES ALL GUATEMALANS AND ALL POLITICAL, SOCIAL, DEMOCRATIC, AND RELIGIOUS ORGANIZATIONS TO SPEAK OUT IN THE FACE OF THESE GENOCIDAL AND BARBARIC ACTIONS THAT ARE ONLY COMPARABLE TO WHAT THE UNITED STATES DID IN VIETNAM AND THE NAZIS DID IN WORLD WAR II.

IN OUR 13 NOVEMBER STATEMENT, WE DENOUNCED THE GUATEMALAN ARMY'S INTERVENTIONIST PLANS AGAINST THAT FRATERNAL COUNTRY. ON 15 NOVEMBER, PRESS AGENCIES REPORTED THAT THE GUATEMALAN ARMY HAD DEPLOYED 126 UNITS OF THE SPECIAL KAIBILES [COUNTERINSURGENCY] TROOPS, WHO ARE KNOWN FOR THEIR PATHOLOGICAL SAVAGERY.

PRESIDENT CEREZO, THE COMMANDER OF THE MILITARY STAFF, AND THE OFFICIAL SPOKESMAN OF THE GUATEMALAN ARMED FORCES HAVE PUBLICLY EXPRESSED THEIR SOLIDARITY WITH CRISTIANI AND THE SALVADORAN ARMY. WE CONDEMN WITH ALL OUR STRENGTH THE GUATEMALAN ARMY'S INTERVENTION AMONG THE GLORIOUS SALVADORAN PEOPLE.

WE CALL ON ALL SEGMENTS OF THE GUATEMALAN POPULATION TO EXPRESS THEIR OPPOSITION AGAINST THIS INTERVENTION. WE WILL ENSURE THAT THE GUATEMALAN ARMY AND GOVERNMENT PAY DEARLY FOR THEIR AGGRESSION AGAINST THE FRATERNAL SALVADORAN PEOPLE. WE ADVISE THE WORLD THAT EL SALVADOR MIGHT FACE AN EVEN WORSE GENOCIDE THAN THE ONE IT IS CURRENTLY ENDURING. WE ARE SURE THAT THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE WILL DEFEAT ALL THEIR ENEMIES, WIN THIS HISTORIC STRUGGLE, AND ACHIEVE THEIR GOALS. THE BLOOD THAT HAS BEEN SHED WILL BREED NEW LIFE AND WILL UNDOUBTELY LEAD US TO FREEDOM, DEMOCRACY, AND PEACE.

GUATEMALA CITY, 17 NOVEMBER 1989

URNG GENERAL COMMAND

COMMANDERS ROLANDO MORAN, PABLO MONSANTO, GASPAR ILOM, AND CARLOS GONZALEZ, PGT [GUATEMALAN LABOR PARTY] SECRETARY GENERAL

DEV-MUC3-0958 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA SONORA) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] "JUST A FEW WORDS TO EXPLAIN THE CURRENT MILITARY SITUATION. WE BELIEVE THAT STILL, REGRETTABLY, FOLLOWING THE FMLN'S [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] IRRATIONALITY, WE CANNOT RULE OUT A CONTINUATION OF THEIR VIOLENT ACTIONS. WE KNOW THAT AROUND THE CAPITAL THERE ARE STILL GROUPS OF TERRORISTS, ESPECIALLY IN THE SOUTHERN AREA, IN THE NORTHWEST -- THE SAN SALVADOR VOLCANO-- AND IN THE NORTHEAST, TO THE NORTH OF SOYAPANGO MUNCIPALITY. THE MILITARY, HOWEVER, HAVE TAKEN THE OFFENSIVE IN THESE THREE AREAS WHERE THE FMLN GROUPS HAVE BEEN CHASED. FIGHTING HAS TAKEN PLACE OVER THE LAST FEW DAYS, WITH OVER 100 CASUALTIES INFLICTED UPON THE FMLN IN 3 DAYS.

"WE BELIEVE, HOWEVER, THEY HAVE LEFT WITHIN THE CAPITAL GREAT NUMBERS OF WEAPONS, SOME OF WHICH HAVE BEEN DISCOVERED. SOME GROUPS ARE IN HIDING, USING CIVILIANS, AND ARE CARRYING OUT TERRORIST ACTIVITIES. THEY HAVE BURNED BUSES, GASOLINE STATIONS AND MURDERED DR FRANCISCO JOSE GUERRERO; AND ON 7 DECEMBER, THEY FIRED THREE OR FOUR MORTAR ROUNDS AT RANDOM, FALLING ON PRIVATE HOMES. ONE OF THEM FELL ON THE HOUSE OF THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE PRESIDENT. WE BELIEVE THESE ACTIONS ARE JUST MERE TERRORISM, INDISCRIMINATELY FIRING MORTARS ON THE CAPITAL'S CIVILIANS.

"WE BELIEVE THEY HAVE NO FURTHER CAPACITY EXCEPT TO CARRY OUT THESE TERRORIST ACTS TO CREATE CONFUSION AND ANARCHY AMONG THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THANK GOD, OUR POPULATION IS VERY BRAVE AND HEROIC. WE HAVE BEEN NOTICING WITH PRIDE HOW THE POPULATION HAS BEEN WORKING NORMALLY IN ALL OF SAN SALVADOR, GOING TO THEIR JOBS, WITH BUSINESSES OPENING AND TRYING TO OPERATE NORMALLY. THERE ARE STILL SOME THREATS IN THE CITY OF SAN MIGUEL, WHERE A GROUP OF TERRORISTS ARE CONCENTRATED TO THE NORTHEAST OF THE CITY. HERE, TOO, THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEGUN AN OFFENSIVE AND QUICKLY END ANY IMMINENT DANGER."

PRESIDENT CRISTIANI SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT'S POSITION AT THE 10 DECEMBER PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT WILL BE OPEN TO THE POSSIBILITY OF RESTARTING A DIALOGUE WITH THE INSURGENTS ON 20 DECEMBER, IN CARACAS, VENEZUELA, AS LONG AS THE FMLN NO LONGER CARRIES OUT ARMED ACTIONS IN URBAN AREAS, BUT THEY DO NOT HAVE TO LAY DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND SHOULD CONTINUE ACTIONS ONLY AGAINST MILITARY TARGETS.

[CRISTIANI] "AS YOU ALL HAVE BEEN ABLE TO SEE FOR YOURSELVES, THE GOVERNMENT HAS NEVER BEEN AGAINST CONTINUING THE DIALOGUE PROCESS TO FIND A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT. IT HAS BEEN THE FMLN THAT UNILATERALLY BROKE THIS DIALOGUE PROCESS BY NOT TURNING UP AT CARACAS, VENEZULA, AS HAD BEEN AGREED IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA. WE, HOWEVER, ARE GOING TO MAKE A DEFINITE PROPOSAL IN COSTA RICA, WHICH IN GENERAL TERMS IS AS FOLLOWS:

"THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS WILLING TO RESTART THE DIALOGUE PROCESS. MOST CONVENIENT WOULD BE FOR THIS TO TAKE PLACE IN CARACAS, WITH THE FOLLOWING CONDITION: BEGINING 15 DECEMBER, 3 DAYS AFTER THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTIAL MEETING [3-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION], THE FMLN SHOULD PUBLICLY DECLARE AND GIVE PROOF OF COMPLIANCE THAT IT WILL END ALL TYPES OF TERRORIST ACTS, ESPECIALLY THOSE THAT DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY AFFECT CIVILIANS. WE WANT TO CLARIFY THAT WE ARE NOT ASKING THEM TO LAY DOWN THEIR ARMS, AS WAS ATTEMPTED MANY TIMES. IF THE FMLN CONTINUES ITS IRRATIONAL BEHAVIOR, THE ARMED FORCES WILL CONTINUE FIGHTING THEM. TERRORIST ACTIONS AGAINST CIVILIANS MUST END. THE PEOPLE DO NOT DESERVE TO CONTINUE BEING THE MOST AFFECTED BY THE IRRATIONALITY OF ALL THIS FIGHTING. WE THINK THE LEAST THE FMLN CAN DO IS TO STOP ALL ACTIONS THAT AFFECT, DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY, THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. MILITARY TARGETS ARE SOMETHING ELSE; BUT IF WE ANALYZE THINGS, UP TO THIS MOMENT NOT A SINGLE MILITARY OBJECTIVE WAS THE TARGET SINCE 11 NOVEMBER. THEY HAVE NOT EVEN BEEN ABLE TO TAKE OVER A CIVIL DEFENSE POST. ALL ACTIONS HAVE BEEN AGAINST CIVILIANS, TRYING TO INTIMIDATE THEM, TRYING TO CREATE TERROR AMONG THE POPULATION. THE CESSATION OF TERRORIST ACTS SHOULD BE THE FMLN'S PROOF OF SINCERITY AND WILL TO REALLY TRY AND SEEK A SOLUTION BY WAY OF DIALOGUE. IF THE FMLN TODAY ACCEPTS ENDING ALL ACTIONS AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION, THEN WE ARE WILLING ON 20 DECEMBER TO GO TO CARACAS AND TO CONTINUE THE DIALOGUE PROCESS AND TALKS ON ALL THE TOPICS THE FMLN WISHES TO TALK ABOUT. THJIS WILL BE IN ORDER TO ENSURE THAT BY 15 FEBRUARY WE HAVE A SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT." [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0959 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 10 DEC 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] MSGR ARTURO RIVERA Y DAMAS, ARCHBISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR, STATED TODAY THAT "THE UNITED STATES SAYS THAT IT WANTS TO HELP IMPROVE THE ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE IN EL SALVADOR. HOWEVER, IN THE CASE OF THE INVESTIGATION OF THE MURDER OF THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS, IT IS OBSTRUCTING JUSTICE."

ARCHBISHOP RIVERA Y DAMAS SAID, "I DO NOT KNOW WHAT THE PURPOSE OF ASSUMING THIS ATTITUDE IS. HOWEVER, WHEN EYEWITNESS LUCIA BARRERA DE CERNA FIRST TESTIFIED, SHE CLEARLY DESCRIBED THE MEN AS BEING DRESSED AS SOLDIERS AND NOT AS GUERRILLAS. I BELIEVE THAT IT IS EASY TO DISTINGUISH BETWEEN ONE WAY OF DRESSING AND ANOTHER."

IT SEEMS THAT THE PLAN IS TO LEAD THE INVESTIGATION THROUGH OTHER PATHS, AND THAT IS WHY THE U.S. OFFICIALS TOOK THE EYEWITNESS TO THE UNITED STATES, "WHERE SHE WAS GIVEN AN AUTHENTIC BRAINWASHING AND THREATENED WITH DEPORTATION IF SHE DID NOT TELL THE TRUTH."

ACCORDING TO THE JESUITS' LAWYER, SCOTT GRATHEAD, MRS. CERNA WAS SUBJECTED TO AN "AGGRESSIVE AND VIOLENT" QUESTIONING SESSION. AFTER THIS PSYCHOLOGICAL TORMENT, SHE THOUGHT IT OVER AND RETRACTED HER STATEMENT. FORTUNATELY, ONCE RID OF THE PRESSURE FROM HER "PROTECTORS," SHE HAS RETAKEN THE PATH OF TRUTH.

IN HIS HOMILY TODAY, THE ARCHBISHOP DENOUNCED THE UNITED STATES FOR TREATING THE WITNESS DIFFERENTLY ONCE SHE ARRIVED IN THE UNITED STATES, INSTEAD OF PROTECTING HER LIKE THE U.S. EMBASSY OFFICIALS IN SAN SALVADOR HAD PROMISED, KNOWING THAT THE HUMBLE WORKING WOMAN "FREELY AND SINCERELY HAD DECLARED WHAT SHE HAD SEEN AND HEARD THE NIGHT OF THE HORRIBLE MASSACRE." THE JESUIT PRIESTS WERE MURDERED ON THE MORNING OF 16 NOVEMBER.

REFERRING TO THE STATEMENT MADE BY THE NATION'S ATTORNEY GENERAL, WHO SAID THAT THE CHURCH HAS REFUSED TO COOPERATE WITH THE INVESTIGATION OF THE MURDER OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS -- A LAWYER-PRIEST HAD BEEN APPOINTED TO COOPERATE WITH THE INVESTIGATION -- THE ARCHBISHOP SAID THAT THIS STATEMENT IS NOT ONLY FALSE BUT ALSO MALICIOUS.

IN HIS HOMILY TODAY THE PRELATE SAID THAT, IN THE FIRST PLACE, IT THE LAYMEN'S GROUND, AND THAT IS WHERE THEY SHOULD PROVE THEIR EXPERTISE AND MORAL INTEGRITY. THEY SHOULD IMBUE THE EXERCISE OF THEIR PROFESSION WITH EVANGELICAL VALUES.

THE ARCHBISHOP SAID THAT, IN THE SECOND PLACE, "IT COULD BE A TRAP." HE ADDED THAT THE CHURCH IS NOT GOING TO ENDORSE WITH A CLERGYMAN'S PRESENCE SOMETHING THAT IS ALREADY BEGINNING TO BE "MURKY."

THE CHURCH AND OTHER SECTORS LINKED TO THE INVESTIGATION IN AN INDEPENDENT WAY HAVE BEEN DISTRUSTFUL EVER SINCE THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE SHOWED ITS ATTITUDE TOWARD LUCIA BARRERA DE CERNA'S TESTIMONY. SHE WAS TESTIFYING AT THE SPANISH EMBASSY BEFORE LAWYERS AND AMBASSADORS, AND AS THE CURFEW HOUR APPROACHED, THEY TOOK THE WITNESS TO ANOTHER EMBASSY. THE NEXT DAY TWO DISTRICT ATTORNEYS CAME TO HARASS THE WITNESS WITH QUESTIONS.

THE ARCHBISHOP ONCE AGAIN REJECTED THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S ACCUSATION. HE REITERATED THE BELIEF THAT THE ARMED FORCES WERE GUILTY OF THE MURDERS. HE SAID, "I AM NOT MAKING ANY ACCUSATIONS. HOWEVER, THE CHURCH IS VERY ANNOYED, AND ALTHOUGH I AM NOT SAYING THAT WE ARE THE OBJECT OF OFFICIAL PERSECUTION, WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THIS REGIME THERE IS PERSECUTION IN OTHER SECTORS."

DEV-MUC3-0961 (SRI)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 10 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [STATEMENT] [NICARAGUAN FOREIGN MINISTER MIGUEL D'ESCOTO BROCKMAN] [TEXT] I CAME BECAUSE I WAS TOLD THAT OUR REPORTER FRIENDS WERE GREATLY INTERESTED IN KNOWING WHAT IS HAPPENING. I UNDERSTAND THAT ATTITUDE BECAUSE I WORKED AS A NEWSMAN FOR MANY YEARS. I ALSO UNDERSTAND YOUR NEED TO TRANSMIT INFORMATION TO OUR CENTRAL AMERICAN PEOPLE, WHO ARE SO INTERESTED IN THE SUCCESS OF THIS CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS' SUMMIT, AND TO THE REST OF THE INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC, WHO ARE INTERESTED THAT PROGRESS IS BEING MADE TOWARD A FINAL PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA.

YESTERDAY EVENING, THE FOREIGN MINISTERS AGREED NOT TO SPEAK TO THE PRESS INDIVIDUALLY. WE APPOINTED COSTA RICAN FOREIGN MINISTER RODRIGO MADRIGAL NIETO AS OUR SPOKESMAN. HE SAID WHAT WE HAD AGREED TO SAY AT THAT TIME. IN FACT, THERE IS NOT MUCH MORE TO REPORT NOW. FOREIGN MINISTER MADRIGAL NIETO TOLD YOU YESTERDAY THAT THE FOREIGN MINISTERS HAD BASICALLY DEVOTED THEIR TIME TO EXAMINING THREE TOPICS. WE ALSO HAD TWO MORE TOPICS, BUT IN ALL THERE WERE THREE TOPICS. I THINK HE MENTIONED THE CONTRAS' DEMOBILIZATION, THE INTERNAL SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR, AND A THIRD TOPIC, BUT RIGHT NOW I DO NOT DARE TO SAY WHAT IT WAS LEST I MAKE A MISTAKE. [AT THIS POINT, AN UNIDENTIFIED PERSON INTERRUPTS, SAYING: "ONUCA"]

HE MENTIONED ONUCA [UN OBSERVER GROUP IN CENTRAL AMERICA]. THAT IS CORRECT. IN FACT, WE DISCUSSED FIVE TOPICS, BUT IF HE SAID...[CHANGES THOUGHT] ONUCA WAS ONE OF THEM. SO WE HAVE DEMOBILIZATION, THE SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR, AND ONUCA. THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS DEVOTED THEIR TIME TO THESE THREE TOPICS.

THIS WAS NOT SO EASY. SOME SAY THE THING TO DO IS TO CLEARLY AND CATEGORICALLY CONDEMN THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] FOR...[CHANGES THOUGHT] AND TO DESCRIBE IT AS A TERRORIST GROUP. OTHERS SAY: LET US CONDEMN TERRORISM IN GENERAL, AND ALSO ANYONE WHO USES IT. SOME ATTACH A GREAT DEAL OF IMPORTANCE TO WHAT INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS SPECIALIZING IN DEFENDING AND PROMOTING RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS SAY, NAMELY ORGANIZATIONS LIKE AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL, AMERICA'S WATCH, THE GENEVA-BASED INTERNATIONAL LEAGUE OF JURISTS, THE OAS' INTER-AMERICAN COMMITTEE ON HUMAN RIGHTS, THE UN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION, THE UN'S TASK FORCE ON FORCED DISAPPEARANCES, AND THE INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS CATHOLIC INSTITUTE IN LONDON, ENGLAND. ALL THESE ORGANIZATIONS, WHICH UNDOUBTEDLY FROM THE NICARAGUAN STANDPOINT DESERVE RESPECT AND CREDIBILITY, INDICATE MATTERS ARE NOT SIMPLY BLACK AND WHITE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0965 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 11 DEC 89 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) HAS ANNOUNCED THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS SUFFERED 29 CASUALTIES, INCLUDING DEAD AND WOUNDED, DURING CLASHES WITH THE ARMY OVER THE PAST 24 HOURS IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

A MILITARY SPOKESMAN GAVE ASSURANCES THAT FIVE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) REBELS WERE KILLED ON THE NIGHT OF 10 DECEMBER ALONG THE NORTHERN PERIPHERY OF THE EASTERN CITY OF SAN MIGUEL, 130 KM FROM SAN SALVADOR, IN CLASHES WITH 3D INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS.

ONE FMLN REBEL WAS KILLED AND ANOTHER WOUNDED DURING CLASHES ON THE NIGHT OF 10 DECEMBER WITH MILITARY TROOPS ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF THE SOYAPANGO NEIGHBORHOOD IN THE NORTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR.

IN OTHER NORTHERN AND NORTHEASTERN PARTS OF THE SALVADORAN CAPITAL BETWEEN 1830 AND 2200 ON 10 DECEMBER, STRONG MORTAR SHOTS WERE HEARD, AT TIMES UP TO FOUR PER MINUTE, WHILE AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS OVERFLEW THE CITY.

THE COPREFA SPOKESMAN ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT ONE GUERRILLA WAS KILLED AND FOUR WOUNDED IN A NEIGHBORHOOD IN THE NORTHERN PART OF USULUTAN, 168 KM EAST OF SAN SALVADOR, DURING A CLASH WITH 2D INFANTRY BRIGATE TROOPS.

ANOTHER INSURGENT WAS KILLED IN NUEVO CUSCATLAN, IN THE SOUTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR, WHERE FMLN FIGHTERS CLASHED WITH TROOPS FROM THE PARATROOPER BATTALION, THE SPOKEKSMAN ADDED.

THE OFFICIAL REPORT DID NOT INDICATE ARMY CASUALTIES IN THE CLASHES REPORTED OVER THE PAST 24 HOURS.

FROM 2300 ON 10 DECEMBER UNTIL 0200 TODAY, THE GUERRILLAS ALSO ATTACKED CIVIL DEFENSE MILITARY POSITIONS IN TONACATEPEQUE, 16 KM NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR, WHERE THEY KILLED TWO CIVIL DEFENSE MEMBERS.

GOVERNMENT SOURCES IN TONACATEPEQUE SAID THAT THE GUERRILLAS SACKED TWO PHARMACIES AND SEVERAL STORES, WITH REGARD TO WHICH COPREFA SAID IT HAD NOT BEEN INFORMED.

THE ARMY'S WAR BULLETIN ADDS THAT 10 REBELS WERE KILLED IN NEIGHBORHOODS LOCATED IN THE NORTHERN PART OF ZACATECOLUCA, IN THE CENTRAL LA PAZ DEPARTMENT.

A ZACATECOLUCA PEASANT WHO ARRIVED IN SAN SALVADOR TODAY SAID THAT "THE SITUATION ON 10 DECEMBER WAS DIFFICULT, THERE WERE SHOOTOUTS DURING THE DAY AND NIGHT," AND THAT THE AIR FORCE "ATTACKED."

MEANWHILE, CLANDESTINE RADIO VENCEREMOS, THE FMLN'S OFFICIAL VOICE, REPORTED THAT OVER THE WEEKEND THE REBELS KILLED 1 SOLDIER AND SERIOUSLY WOUNDED 11, AMONG THEM A TREASURY POLICE OFFICER.

THE SOLDIER DIED IN A CLASH IN TEJUTEPEQUE, IN THE NORTHERN CABANAS DEPARTMENT, THE REBEL STATION ADDED, WITHOUT REPORTING THE FMLN'S CASUALTIES.

THE GUERRILLAS CLAIM, MOREOVER, TO HAVE DESTROYED SIX PRIMARY POWER TRANSMISSION TOWERS BETWEEN THE "CERRON GRANDE" AND "15 DE SEPTIEMBRE" POWER PLANTS, IN THE NORTHERN AND EASTERN PARTS OF SAN SALVADOR.

SPOKESMEN FOR THE LEMPA RIVER HYDROELECTRIC EXECUTIVE COMMISSION (CEL) CONFIRMED THE DESTRUCTION OF THE POWER LINES TO ACAN-EFE, ADDING THAT, THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY, NINE POWER SYSTEM STRUCTURES WERE DAMAGED OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS.

THE COUNTRY'S POWER DEFICIT IS 35 PERCENT.

DEV-MUC3-0966 (SRI)

CLANDESTINE, 11 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HAS SEIZED THE TOWN OF TONACATEPEQUE, DESTROYED THE GARRISON, SABOTAGED THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND ANTEL [NATIONAL ADMINISTRATION FOR TELECOMMUNICATIONS] INSTALLATIONS, AND FREED CIVILIAN PRISONERS OF THE PARAMILITARY FORCES. THE PRISONERS WERE RESIDENTS OF TONACATEPEQUE WHO HAD BEEN TAKEN PRISONER BY THE TROOPS. THEY HAVE NOW BEEN RELEASED BY THE FMLN.

THE FMLN FORCES SEIZED 30 RIFLES AND WAR SUPPLIES. CASUALTIES INFLICTED ON THE PARAMILITARY FORCES IN TONACATEPEQUE HAVE BEEN ESTIMATED AT 10 DEAD AND 15 WOUNDED.

THE FIGHTING WITH THE PARAMILITARY FORCES IN TONACATEPEQUE BEGAN ON 10 DECEMBER AT 2300 AND THE FMLN TOOK CONTROL OF CITY AT 0200 TODAY, MONDAY. DURING THIS ACTION, OUR FORCES ATTACKED ENEMY POSITIONS WHICH FORM PART OF THE DEFENSE RING OF THE ILOPANGO AIR BASE. THE FIGHTING LASTED 3 HOURS AND OUR FORCES TOOK COMPLETE CONTROL OF THE TOWN AT 0200.

THE AIR FORCE PROVIDED SUPPORT WITH AC-47 PLANES, (HUEY 500) HELICOPTER GUNSHIPS AND OTHER AIRCRAFT, WHICH INDISCRIMINATELY BOMBED AND STRAFED THE POPULATION.

THE RESULTS ARE AS FOLLOWS: 25 CASUALTIES AND WAR MATERIAL CONSISTING OF THE FOLLOWING: 30 RIFLES, INCLUDING M-14, CZECHOSLOVAK-MADE G-3, GARAND, AND OTHER TYPES. IN ALL, 30 RIFLES WERE SEIZED IN THE CITY. WE ALSO SEIZED TWO BATTERIES FOR MILITARY RADIOS, 11,000 ROUNDS FOR RIFLES -- WE REPEAT, 11,000 ROUNDS FOR RIFLES -- 5 CLAYMORE MINES; GRENADES FOR RIFLES; 75 CLIPS FOR RIFLES; CANTEENS; AND OTHER MILITARY ITEMS LIKE HARNESSES, A LARGE NUMBER OF UNIFORMS, A SUBSTANTIAL QUANTITY OF MEDICINE, BOOTS, KNAPSACKS, AND OTHER WAR SUPPLIES IN ALTOMAR DISTRICT IN TONACATEPEQUE.

AT 0200 OUR FORCES FINISHED SEIZING CONTROL OF TONACATEPEQUE, WHICH IS BARELY 7 KM FROM THE RUNWAY OF ILOPANGO AIR FORCE BASE. THE PERSONNEL AT THE ENEMY BASE HAD BEEN PERSECUTING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION AND HAD CAPTURED THREE RESIDENTS WHO WERE RELEASED BY OUR FORCES WHEN THEY OPENED THE DOORS TO THE JAIL WHERE THE PRISONERS WER BEING HELD. AFTER SEIZING CONTROL OF THE TOWN, OUR FORCES TOTALLY DESTROYED THE GARRISON AND LOCAL COMMAND POST. THEY ALSO PARTIALLY DESTROYED THE MAYOR'S OFFICE AND THE ANTEL INSTALLATIONS.

THIS HAS BEEN A REPORT FROM TONACATEPEQUE. THE STRATEGIC SIEGE OF SAN SALVADOR HAS BEEN EXPANDED WITH THIS NEW ACTION -- THE SEIZURE OF TONACATEPEQUE, WHICH IS AN IMPORTANT POSITION IN THE DEFENSE RING OF ILOPANGO AIR FORCE BASE, LOCATED 7 KM SOUTH OF THE CITY.

DEV-MUC3-0969 (SRI)

MANAGUA, 20 MAR 89 -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] THE MURDER OF THREE JOURNALISTS IN EL SALVADOR YESTERDAY ONCE AGAIN SHOWS THE REPRESSIVE AND CRIMINAL NATURE OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY.

THOSE ACTIONS AGAINST OUR PRESS COLLEAGUES ARE ONLY COMPARABLE WITH ACTIONS CARRIED OUT BY THE ARMIES IN CHILE, PARAGUAY, AND OTHER MILITARY DICTATORSHIPS. THE SOMOZIST ARMY COMMITTED SIMILAR CRIMES IN NICARAGUA. WE JUST HAVE TO REMEMBER THE COLD WAY IN WHICH U.S. JOURNALIST BILL STEWART WAS KILLED WHILE COVERING THE LAST PHASE OF THE INSURRECTION IN MANAGUA'S WESTERN NEIGHBORHOODS.

IN EL SALVADOR, FOREIGN AND NATIONAL JOURNALISTS ARE DEMANDING A SERIOUS INVESTIGATION FROM PRESIDENT DUARTE'S GOVERNMENT TO PUNISH THE MILITARY MEN RESPONSIBLE FOR THE CRIME. WILL THE ARMY'S HIGH COMMAND BE WILLING TO CONDUCT THE INVESTIGATION? WE DOUBT IT, BASED ON ITS LACK OF WILLINGNESS TO RECTIFY THINGS IN THE PAST REGARDING OTHER CASES, SUCH AS THE ASSASSINATION OF MSGR ROMERO AND THE MURDER OF HERBERT ANAYA, PRESIDENT OF THE HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION. AFTER ALL, THAT IS THE WAY IN WHICH NAPOLEON DUARTE'S CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT RESTRAINS FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION IN HIS COUNTRY. MORE THAN 11 JOURNALISTS HAVE BEEN KILLED BY THE SALVADORAN ARMY SINCE 1981.

MEANWHILE, IN NICARAGUA, JOURNALISTS FROM INDEPENDENT MEDIA ARE CONCERNED ABOUT 39 FORMER SOMOZIST GUARDS WHO ARE STILL IN JAIL BECAUSE OF THEIR CRIMINAL RECORDS, TO THE POINT OF LAUNCHING JOURNALISTIC CAMPAIGNS DEMANDING FROM THE GOVERNMENT THE RELEASE OF THE HARMLESS PIGEONS.

WHAT WILL THEY SAY NOW ABOUT THE SALVADORAN ARMY, WHICH MURDERED THEIR COLLEAGUES WHO WERE COMPLYING WITH THEIR DUTY TO INFORM THE PUBLIC? WILL THEY DEFEND THEM AS THEY DEFENDED THE SOMOZIST GUARDS? THEY PROBABLY WILL. THEY WILL TRY TO PLAY DOWN THE ACTION, BECAUSE THEY HAVE LOST THEIR DIGNITY, GOOD SENSE, AND PROFESSIONAL PRIDE A LONG TIME AGO.

DEV-MUC3-0970 (SRI)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 11 DEC 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH LIEUTENANT COLONEL RICARDO WHEELOCK, CHIEF OF THE NICARAGUAN MILITARY INTELLIGENCE DIRECTORATE BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [WHEELOCK] I THANK YOU ALL FOR YOUR PRESENCE HERE. THIS MORNING WE RECEIVED REPORTS THAT THE SANDINIST PEOPLE'S ARMY [EPS] HAD BOMBED AND SANK SEVERAL HONDURAN BOATS. WE MEAN CIVILIAN FISHING BOATS. I WILL TELL YOU WHAT HAPPENED.

WE HAVE VERY FEW PATROL BOATS ON THE ATLANTIC COAST AND OUR BOATS THERE ARE IN CHARGE OF PROTECTING NICARAGUA'S SOVEREIGNTY AND WEALTH. FOR MANY YEARS, THE NICARAGUAN AIR FORCE AND THE SANDINIST NAVY HAVE BEEN CONDUCTING JOINT OPERATIONS. IN OTHER WORDS, THIS IS NOT THE FIRST TIME WE HAVE CONDUCTED SUCH OPERATIONS. FURTHERMORE, WE HAVE TAPED MOST OF THOSE OPERATIONS BECAUSE THEY REQUIRE THOROUGH TRAINING AND ACCURACY.

DURING THOSE OPERATIONS, HELICOPTERS HAVE DEPLOYED MEN WHO BOARD MOST OF THE SHIPS PARTICIPATING IN THE OPERATIONS. IN OTHER WORDS, HELICOPTERS FOLLOW THE SHIPS AS THEY MOVE ALONG AND THEN SPECIAL SANDINIST NAVY FORCES BOARD THE SHIP FROM THE AIR.

I WILL TELL YOU WHAT HAPPENED MORE OR LESS. ON 7 DECEMBER 1989 WE CONDUCTED AN OPERATION, BASICALLY BECAUSE SINCE NOVEMBER, WE HAVE DETECTED OVER 30 PIRATE SHIPS, IN OTHER WORDS, SHIPS THAT HAVE NEITHER LICENSE NOR PERMIT TO FISH IN NICARAGUAN TERRITORIAL WATERS.

DURING AN OPERATION OF THE TYPE I JUST DESCRIBED, OUR FORCES BOARDED THREE BOATS AT 1020 ON 7 DECEMBER. THE OPERATION WAS CARRIED OUT APPROXIMATELY 45 MILES EAST OF PUERTO CABEZAS. IN OTHER WORDS, THE THREE BOATS WERE BOARDED IN THIS AREA HERE. [WHEELOCK APPARENTLY SHOWS LOCATION ON A MAP].

THE NAMES OF THE BOATS ARE "KERRY MAC II", "DAVIS JR," "MISS PATSY," AND ANOTHER ONE CALLED "TIE WATER" [NUMBER OF BOATS AS HEARD]. THE BOATS WERE CAPTURED AND TAKEN TO ISLA DEL MAIZ. IN EACH BOAT THERE WERE FIVE NICARAGUAN SOLDIERS, ONE AIR FORCE OFFICER, AND ONE NAVY OFFICER. AS THE BOATS WERE TAKEN TO ISLA DEL MAIZ, THE MEMBERS OF THE "MISS PATSY" CREW, WHO NUMBERED APPROXIMATELY 60, MUTINIED AGAINST THE SANDINIST OFFICERS ON BOARD.

THE SHIP'S CAPTAIN AND A COOK DISARMED ONE OF THE SOLDIERS AND KILLED HIM. AS A RESULT OF THE CONFRONTATION, THE COOK WAS KILLED, BUT THE CAPTAIN WAS UNHARMED. AFTER THE MUTINY WAS OVER, AND AT APPROXIMATELY 0.7 MILES FROM CORN, I MEAN ISLA DEL MAIZ, THE SHIP'S CAPTAIN RAN THE "MISS PATSY" FISHING BOAT AGROUND ON SOME REEF NEAR ISLA DEL MAIZ GRANDE AND WE WERE FORCED TO, LET US SAY, SAVE ALL THE PEOPLE ON BOARD AND TAKE THEM TO CORN ISLAND.

ONE OF THE "MISS PATSY" SAILORS JUMPED OFF THE SHIP AND WE HAVE BEEN UNABLE TO FIND HIM. OF THE TWO BODIES, THAT OF THE ARMY OFFICER AND THE COOK, WE HAVE ONLY BEEN ABLE TO RECOVER THE COOK'S BODY BECAUSE THE SHIP SANK. MOST OF THE OTHER PEOPLE WERE TAKEN TO HOSPITALS IN BLUEFIELDS AND OTHERS ARE BEING HELD BY THE SANDINIST NAVY. THAT IS MORE OR LESS WHAT HAPPENED.

WHEN THE "MISS PATSY" RAN AGROUND, THE CREW MEMBERS OF THE OTHER SHIPS CAME TO HELP, AND DURING THIS TIME, APPARENTLY, THE SHIP CALLED "DAVIS JR" MANAGED TO ESCAPE. WE HAVE BEEN UNABLE TO FIND IT, BUT WE WANT TO TELL YOU THAT THE FOLLOWING EPS OFFICERS ARE ON THAT BOAT: AIR FORCE FIRST LIEUTENANT VICTOR RODRIGUEZ HERNANDEZ, LT JUAN CARLOS GALO TINOCO, NAVY SAILOR JOSE MARCELINO REYES, AND SAILOR JOSE RENE RODRIGUEZ.

WE DO NOT KNOW WHAT HAPPENED TO THE "DAVIS JR," BUT WE BELIEVE IT RETURNED TO HONDURAS. THAT IS MORE OR LESS WHAT HAPPENED. I AM NOW READY TO ANSWER THE QUESTIONS THAT YOU MAY WANT TO ASK. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0971 (SRI)

CLANDESTINE, 12 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN], WITH REGARD TO THE RESULTS OF THE EXTRAORDINARY MEETING OF CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS, REPORTS THE FOLLOWING:

1. THE RESULTS OF THE PRESIDENTS' MEETING HAS ALLOWED US TO MEASURE THE DEPTH OF THE CRISIS IN EL SALVADOR AND THE IMPACT OF THE FMLN'S CURRENT MILITARY OFFENSIVE, INASMUCH AS THE SUMMIT'S ENTIRE EFFORT WAS AIMED AT SAVING THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT FROM AN EXTREME POLITICAL AND MILITARY CRISIS AND FROM INTERNATIONAL ISOLATION IN EXCHANGE FOR A NEW PROMISE ON THE IMMEDIATE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE NICARAGUAN CONTRAS.

2. THE FMLN INDIGNANTLY REJECTS THE PRESIDENTS' DECLARATION BECAUSE, CONTRARY TO THE DYNAMICS OF THE ENTIRE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, THE CLAMOR OF DEMOCRATIC AND SOCIAL FORCES, AND THE CLAMOR OF CHURCHES IN THE COUNTRY, THIS DECLARATION UNCONDITIONALLY SUPPORTS THE LEADING VIOLATOR OF HUMAN RIGHTS IN THE REGION, A GOVERNMENT THAT HAS MURDERED AND PERSECUTED THE CLERGY AND BOMBED THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THIS SUPPORT ENCOURAGES THOSE WHO HAVE UNLEASHED THAT IRRATIONAL VIOLENCE AND ALLOWS MORE MURDERS IN EL SALVADOR.

3. THE SAN JOSE AGREEMENT DOES NOT CONTRIBUTE TOWARD A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION IN EL SALVADOR. THE FMLN CANNOT BE DISBANDED AS THE RESULT OF AGREEMENTS BETWEEN GOVERNMENTS BECAUSE THE FMLN CONSTITUTES A GENUINELY POPULAR POWER THROUGHOUT THE SALVADORAN TERRITORY, A FORCE THAT THE HUGE U.S.-FINANCED WAR MACHINE HAS NOT BEEN ABLE TO STOP IN 10 YEARS.

4. AS HAS ALREADY BEEN SAID IN PRIVATE, THE FMLN AGREES WITH UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ' MEDIATION TO INITIATE SERIOUS NEGOTIATIONS WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF ALL OF THE COUNTRY'S POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES.

5. WE ARE HEREBY CALLING FOR INTERNATIONAL SOLIDARITY SO OTHER COUNTRIES CAN MOBILIZE IMMEDIATELY TO DEFEND THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, WHO ARE IN DANGER OF SUFFERING FROM AN ESCALATION IN EFFORTS TO EXTERMINATE IT BECAUSE THE FASCIST POLICY HAS BEEN REINFORCED BY THE SUPPORT THAT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS' DECLARATION OFFERS TO CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT.

EL SALVADOR, 12 DECEMBER 1989.

FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

[SIGNED] COMMANDERS JOAQUIAN VILLALOBOS, FRANCISCO JOVEL, EDUARDO SANCHO, JORGE SHAFIK HANDAL, SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN

DEV-MUC3-0972 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] IN THE CASE OF EL SALVADOR, THIS IS NOT A MATTER OF THE IRREGULAR GROUP BEING AROUND SAN SALVADOR, IN GUASAPA, OR IN CHALATENANGO -- WHEREVER THEY MAY WANT TO OPERATE. WE BELIEVE THAT THE DEMOBILIZATION PROCESS IS APPLICABLE IF THE GROUP CEASES TO BE AN IRREGULAR GROUP, SOMETHING THAT NO LONGER HAS ANY JUSTIFICATION, TO BECOME A POLITICAL OR A CIVIC GROUP IN THE FRAMEWORK OF A LEGAL PROCESS.

THE MESSAGE HERE IS THAT THE PRESIDENTS NO LONGER WANT OR JUSTIFY IRREGULAR GROUPS IN THE REGION, AND IRREGULAR GROUPS HAVE NO REASON FOR CONTINUING IN THE REGION. THIS INCLUDES THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE, THE FMLN, AND OTHER GROUPS, SUCH AS THOSE THAT MAY EXIST IN GUATEMALA. IF GUATEMALA WERE TO ASK THAT A PROBLEM IN THAT SISTER COUNTRY BE CONSIDERED, WE WOULD HAVE TO CONSIDER IT BECAUSE IT IS THE SAME SITUATION.

SUPPORT AND VERIFICATION BY THE UNITED NATIONS AND THE OAS IS REQUESTED THROUGH AN ORGANIZATION KNOWN AS CIAV. THE FIRST THING TO DO IS TO CEASE TERRORIST ACTIVITIES, TO INITIATE THE DIALOGUE PROCESS, AND THEN TO BE DEMOBILIZED AND TO BECOME A LEGAL GROUP THAT WOULD FUNCTION IN THE FRAMEWORK OF SALVADORAN LAWS.

[MODERATOR] MARIA DOLORES ARGUIAQ, FROM RADIO NACIONAL, SPAIN.

[ARGUIAQ] CONTINUING WITH THE NICARAGUA PARALLELISM, IS THERE THE POSSIBILITY OF HAVING A CEASE-FIRE BEFORE OR AFTER THE VENEZUELA MEETING AS A FIRST STEP TOWARD OTHER MEASURES THAT COULD PUT AN END TO THE WAR? MY OTHER QUESTION IS: THE UNITED NATIONS HAS BEEN EXPLICITLY ASKED TO PREPARE THE REINITIATION OF THE DIALOGUE. HAS THERE BEEN ANY PREPARATION? HAS THE CHURCH MADE ANY PREPARATIONS IN THIS REGARD?

[CRISTIANI] WELL, [1-MINUTE BREAK IN TRANSMISSION] THAT HAS NOTHING TO DO WITH THAT. AN END OF HOSTILITIES IS BASICALLY LIKE SAYING: DO NOT CARRY OUT TERRORIST ACTIVITIES AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. IT IS BETTER TO DEFINE MEANINGS AND NOT TO USE TERMS THAT CREATE PROBLEMS OF SEMANTICS. WHAT IS YOUR SECOND QUESTION?

[ARGUIAQ] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI] LOGICALLY. SOMEBODY ELSE HAS ASKED ME ALSO IF WE HAVE HAD ANY CONTACT WITH THE FMLN. THIS AGREEMENT WAS SIGNED AT 0400. AT 0700 WE GOT ON A PLANE AND HERE WE ARE NOW. WE HAVE NOT HAD TIME TO SPEAK WITH MR PEREZ DE CUELLAR, MUCH LESS WITH THE FMLN. BUT THIS INFORMATION WILL BE PASSED TO THE UNITED NATIONS BECAUSE THERE IS MUCH TO BE ASKED OF THE UNITED NATIONS. WE HAVE BEEN CONFRONTED WITH THE PLEASANT SURPRISE THAT REPRESENTATIVES OF THE UN OBSERVER GROUP IN CENTRAL AMERICA [ONUCA] ARE ALREADY IN THE COUNTRY, TO BE INSTALLED.

MR ORTEGA, WHO HAD GONE THERE WITH THE POSITION THAT AS LONG AS THE RESISTANCE IS NOT DEMOBILIZED HE WOULD NOT ACCEPT ONUCA, HAD TO ABANDON THAT POSITION BECAUSE IT WAS IRRATIONAL, AND ONUCA WILL BE ASKED TO GO TO NICARAGUA IMMEDIATELY.

THE AGREEMENT WILL BE REPORTED TO MR JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR. HE WILL ALSO RECEIVE FROM EL SALVADOR A REQUEST THAT HE WORK IN FAVOR OF REINITIATING THE DIALOGUE PROCESS. THE AGREEMENT HAS SPECIAL CONTENTS. IT DOES NOT MENTION OTHER COUNTRIES BY NAME BECAUSE THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS HAVE TRIED TO PRODUCE A DOCUMENT THAT IS VERY RESPECTFUL OF COUNTRIES FROM OUTSIDE THIS AREA, BUT IT IS UNDENIABLE THAT THERE ARE STATES THAT ARE NEGATIVELY AFFECTING THE SITUATION IN CENTRAL AMERICA. THE UNITED NATIONS AND THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL, ESPECIALLY AND PERSONALLY, ARE BEING ASKED TO HELP MAKE STATES THAT MEDDLE IN THE REGION SEE THAT THEY MUST HELP THE PEACE PROCESS PROMOTED BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS.

OBVIOUSLY I DO NOT HAVE TO MENTION THE NAMES OF THE COUNTRIES TO WHICH I AM REFERRING.

IT IS NECESSARY TO UNDERSTAND THAT WE ARE TRYING TO FIND A REAL SOLUTION, TO SEE THAT ALL THE FACTORS THAT HAVE BEEN EXERTING INFLUENCE, WHETHER NEGATIVE OR POSITIVE, WORK IN A POSITIVE WAY. THE UNITED NATIONS, WHICH COMPRISES ALL THESE STATES, IS IN A BETTER POSITION TO CARRY OUT THIS WORK.

DEV-MUC3-0974 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 DEC 89 (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CRISTIANI, IN PROGRESS] ... HE [ORTEGA] WAS FACING A FACT HE COULD NO LONGER HIDE: HE IS THE ONE WHO IS SPREADING ARMED REVOLUTIONS IN CENTRAL AMERICA AND TRYING TO HAMPER DEMOCRATIC PROCESSES IN THE REGION. ONCE MORE HE HAS BEEN CAUGHT NOT HONORING THE COMMITMENTS AGREED ON IN TELA, BUT RATHER VIOLATING THESE COMMITMENTS. ON THIS OCCASION HE HAS BEEN LEFT WITH NO POSSIBLE DEFENSE.

THEREFORE, IN OUR OPINION, HE HAS NO OPTION OTHER THAN TO ACCEPT THE REALITY OF WHAT IS HAPPENING IN CENTRAL AMERICA, OR SEE HIMSELF TOTALLY ISOLATED AMID A PEACE PLAN THAT HAS INTERNATIONAL SUPPORT. THIS SITUATION WOULD CAUSE HIM MANY PROBLEMS AND HEADACHES IN POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC MATTERS. HE COULD DO NOTHING BUT ACCEPT THE REALITY. HE COULD NO LONGER DEFEND THE POSITION THAT THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE WAS SOMETHING SPECIAL AND THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WAS SOMETHING ELSE AND WAS JUSTIFIABLE. IT IS NOW CLEAR THAT HE HAS RUN OUT OF TRICKS AND HAS HAD TO ACCEPT WHAT ALL THE REMAINING FOUR CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS ARE AWARE OF AND DEFENDED AT THE COSTA RICAN SUMMIT. NOW, IF IN THEIR STRATEGY THEY SOLD OUT THE FMLN, AS HAS BEEN MENTIONED HERE, THEY WILL HAVE TO GIVE SOME EXPLANATIONS TO THEIR FMLN FRIENDS. THAT IS A PROBLEM BETWEEN HIM AND THE FMLN.

WHAT SHOULD BE OF INTEREST TO US IS THAT THE FMLN'S VIOLENT AND TERRORIST ACTIONS ARE NO LONGER JUSTIFIED FROM ANY POINT OF VIEW. THIS HAS BEEN CLEARLY AND STRONGLY EMPHASIZED IN THE COSTA RICAN AGREEMENT. IN THIS REGARD, I REPEAT THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS WILLING TO RESUME THE DIALOGUE PROCESS FROM WHICH THE FMLN UNILATERALLY WITHDREW. HOWEVER, AT THIS TIME IT IS NECESSARY FOR THE FMLN TO OPENLY PROMISE -- AND THIS IS STRONGLY DEMANDED BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS, INCLUDING THE NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT -- IT WILL CEASE TERRORIST ACTIONS, ESPECIALLY THOSE AFFECTING CIVILIANS. OBVIOUSLY A TOTAL DEMOBILIZATION AND RETURN TO THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS -- WITH THE GUARANTEES THAT MUST BE GIVEN TO THE FMLN MEMBERS -- WILL BE THE RESULT OF THE DIALOGUE PROCESS. THIS IS HOW WE UNDERSTAND AND VIEW THIS MATTER. THE DEMOBILIZATION OF THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE SHALL BE THE RESULT OF A CONVINCING EFFORT BY THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT, WHICH SHOULD PROVIDE THE NECESSARY GUARANTEES. IN THE SAME DOCUMENT, THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT HAS UNILATERALLY VOWED TO ENSURE THOSE GUARANTEES.

IT IS ALSO IMPORTANT TO POINT OUT THAT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS ASKED THE UNITED NATIONS TO ALSO JOIN THE CIAV [INTERNATIONAL COMMISSION OF SUPPORT AND VERIFICATION], SO THE CIAV BEGINS AND IMPLEMENTS THE PROCESS TO DEMOBILIZE THE FMLN. THIS IS BASICALLY THE DESIRE OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS. IF THE FMLN WANTS TO GAIN POLITICAL ADVANTAGES, IT SHOULD PURSUE THIS WITHIN THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS BECAUSE IT CAN NO LONGER BE JUSTIFIED AND HAS NEVER BEEN JUSTIFIED. HOWEVER, TODAY WE STRONGLY TELL THE FMLN THAT NO LONGER IS THERE ANY ROOM IN CENTRAL AMERICA, AND ESPECIALLY IN EL SALVADOR, FOR VIOLENT AND TERRORIST ACTIONS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0975 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI] WELL, AS I SAID BEFORE, WE BELIEVE THAT THE DEMOBILIZATION PROCESS BEING DISCUSSED FOR ANY REBEL ORGANIZATION SHOULD BE A COMPLETE PROCESS WITH THEIR PARTICIPATION IN A DEMOCRATIC PROCESS. IT IS A PROCESS THAT IS ADAPTED TO FIT THE CIRCUMSTANCES. AN INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION IS IN CHARGE OF VERIFYING THIS PROCESS. WE BELIEVE THE ORGANIZATION HAS THE NECESSARY AUTHORITY TO DO IT, AND IT SHOULD NOT BE A MATTER OF LOOKING FOR OTHER OPTIONS BECAUSE THEY DO NOT EXIST. WE HAVE NO OTHER OPTIONS BESIDES THE ONES THAT HAVE ALREADY BEEN DESIGNED FOR BOTH THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE AND FOR THE FMLN, SPECIFICALLY. IN GENERAL TERMS THESE OPTIONS COULD BE APPLIED TO ANY REBEL GROUP IN THE REGION.

[MODERATOR] LUIS FUENTES FROM PRENSA GRAFICA. [PAUSE] CARLOS ERNESTO RUGAMA FROM RADIO CADENA YSU.

[RUGAMA] [WORDS INDISTINCT] ...DIPLOMATIC AND TRADE RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA. HOW CAN THE REESTABLISHMENT OF THE RELATIONS BE ACHIEVED?

[CRISTIANI] POINT 12 OF THIS DECLARATION MAKES A FRATERNAL CALL TO EL SALVADOR AND NICARAGUA TO SEEK THE NORMALIZATION OF THE DIPLOMATIC AND CONSULAR RELATIONS THROUGH DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATIONS. WE MADE THE DECISION TO TEMPORARILY SUSPEND THE RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA BECAUSE OF THE FLAGRANT VIOLATION OF THE ESQUIPULAS AGREEMENTS. THEY WERE DIRECTLY SUPPORTING THE FMLN'S TERRORIST AGGRESSION. IN COSTA RICA WE GAVE THEM A DOCUMENT THAT CLEARLY DEFINES EL SALVADOR'S POSITION REGARDING POSSIBLE NEGOTIATIONS WHICH COULD NORMALLY REESTABLISH THE DIPLOMATIC AND CONSULAR RELATIONS. THIS DOCUMENT WAS NOT DISCUSSED BY THE FIVE PRESIDENTS BECAUSE IT ONLY CONCERNED TWO OF US. HOWEVER, THE DOCUMENT WAS GIVEN TO THE NICARAGUAN DELEGATION AND WE WILL WAIT FOR THE RESULTS. WE BELIEVE THAT IN GENERAL TERMS IT COULD STOP NICARAGUA'S INTERFERENCE AND ITS SUPPORT FOR THE FMLN.

[MODERATOR] MARIA CORTINA FROM NOTIMEX.

CORTINA WORDS INDISTINCT ...TO IMMEDIATELY INITIATE THE DIALOGUE PROCESS. IN ADDITION, THEY HAVE TO PUBLICLY STOP CONDUCTING ACTIONS AGAINST THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THAT WAS PART OF THE PROPOSAL YOU MADE HERE ON SATURDAY. HOWEVER, I AM NOT YET CLEAR ON SOMETHING. TO INITIATE THE DIALOGUE PROCESS, DOES THE FMLN HAVE TO DECLARE A CEASE-FIRE OR WOULD A PUBLIC DECLARATION BE ENOUGH?

[CRISTIANI] WELL, WE MAINTAIN THE POSITION WE STATED ON 10 DECEMBER. WE BELIEVE THAT POINT 3 OF THIS DECLARATION UPHOLDS WHAT WE HAVE BEEN DOING ALL ALONG REGARDING THE SEARCH FOR A PEACEFUL SOLUTION IN THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT. THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS WANT THE FMLN TO PUBLICLY STATE THAT THEY WILL IMMEDIATELY SUSPEND ALL THE VIOLENT ACTIONS THAT ARE DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY AFFECTING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. WE BELIEVE THAT IT IS NOT ENOUGH TO MAKE A PUBLIC STATEMENT. THEY MUST KEEP THEIR WORD. WE BELIEVE THAT THERE SHOULD AT LEAST BE A 5-DAY PERIOD BETWEEN THE PUBLIC STATEMENT AND THE BEGINNING OF A DIALOGUE. WE MAINTAIN THE POSITION, THAT IS THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS AND MYSELF, THAT NO HOSTILE ACTIONS BY THE FMLN ARE JUSTIFIABLE. WE BELIEVE THAT THE FMLN SHOULD STOP CARRYING OUT ALL HOSTILE ACTIONS IN THE COUNTRY. THIS INDICATES TWO THINGS WHICH MUST BE UNDERSTOOD. FIRST, THE FMLN ARE THE ONLY ONES CONDUCTING HOSTILE ACTIONS. THE GOVERNMENT AND THE DEMOCRATIC INSTITUTIONS THAT BELONG TO IT DO NOT GENERATE HOSTILITIES. THEY SIMPLY RESPOND TO THE ACTIONS OF ARMED GROUPS THAT ARE INTERESTED IN MAKING TROUBLE AND OVERTHROWING A LEGITIMATE GOVERNMENT. THE GOVERNMENT HAS THE CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT TO A LEGITIMATE DEFENSE AND TO THE PRESERVATION OF NATIONAL SECURITY IN FAVOR OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, AS THE CONSTITUTION STATES. SECONDLY, THE FMLN HAS LOST ALL MANEUVERING OPTIONS. THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS SAID IT CLEARLY WHEN THEY STATED THAT THE FMLN HAD NO JUSTIFICATION FOR THEIR VIOLENT ACTIONS IN EL SALVADOR. THAT IS WHY WE ARE ONCE AGAIN ASKING FOR AN IMMEDIATE AND EFFECTIVE CEASE-FIRE. THESE WERE THE SAME WORDS USED AT THE SUMMIT HELD IN TELA, HONDURAS. HOWEVER, I REPEAT, WE WILL MAINTAIN THE POSITION WE HAD BEFORE, EVEN THOUGH WE TOTALLY AGREE WITH THIS DOCUMENT. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0976 (SRI)

BOGOTA, 12 DEC 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] A COLOMBIAN OFFICIAL FROM THE INTER-AMERICAN DEVELOPMENT BANK [IDB] AND A PROSECUTOR FROM THE MEDELLIN HIGHER COURT WERE ASSASSINATED IN THE LAST FEW HOURS NEAR THIS NORTHWESTERN CITY, THE SECOND LARGEST IN COLOMBIA, POLICE SPOKESMEN HAVE REPORTED.

EDGAR HENAO, 55, CIVIL ENGINEER, ECONOMIST, AND TOP EXECUTIVE FROM THE INTERNATIONAL CREDIT ORGANIZATION, WAS SHOT SEVERAL TIMES BY SOME UNIDENTIFIED PEOPLE AT HIS FARM CALLED EL LIMON, VENECIA MUNICIPALITY, 61 KM SOUTHWEST OF MEDELLIN.

HENAO, WHO HAS BEEN WORKING FOR THE IDB FOR 13 YEARS, HAD ARRIVED IN COLOMBIA ON 7 DECEMBER AND WAS PREPARING TO LEAVE FOR JAMAICA, THE SOURCES ADDED.

MOREOVER, 4TH PROSECUTOR GABRIEL JAIME VELEZ WAS ATTACKED IN ENVIGADO, 10 KM FROM MEDELLIN, BY AN INDIVIDUAL WHO FIRED 13 SHOTS KILLING HIM INSTANTLY AS HE WAS WALKING HOME.

VELEZ, 38, WHO WAS HANDLING SEVERAL KIDNAPPING AND DRUG TRAFFICKING CASES, HAD BEING THREATENED, BUT HE HAD NO BODYGUARDS, RELATIVES OF THE VICTIM SAID.

DURING THE LAST 6 MONTHS, FIVE JUDGES AND MAGISTRATES HAVE BEEN KILLED BY HIRED ASSASSINS IN MEDELLIN.

ALSO TODAY IN BUENAVENTURA, THE MAJOR COLOMBIAN PORT ON THE PACIFIC COAST, JUDGE SOFIA DE ROLDAN WAS SHOT TO DEATH BY HIRED ASSASSINS. SHE WAS PREPARING FOR A NEW JOB IN CALI, IN WESTERN COLOMBIA.

DEV-MUC3-0978 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA CUSCATLAN) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY UNIDENTIFIED MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] AND AGAIN, BECAUSE THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS DID NOT WANT TO STATE THESE COUNTRIES BY NAME, I WILL REFRAIN MYSELF FROM DOING IT AT THIS TIME, BUT THEY ARE VERY OBVIOUS, WHO AND WHAT THEY [WORD INDISTINCT].

BUT I THINK OBVIOUSLY IT WOULD BE MUCH EASIER IF THE FMLN WOULD ACT RATIONALLY AND ACCEPT THAT THEY HAVE NO LONGER ANY RECOGNITION FOR WHAT THEY DO, AND THAT THEY HAVE BEEN CONDEMNED, AND NOT ONLY AS AN IRREGULAR FORCE OR GROUP. THEY HAVE NOW BEEN CONDEMNED AS BEING A TERRORIST GROUP, WHICH IS THE SECOND ASPECT OF THE THIRD POINT IN THE AGREEMENT. THEREFORE, MAYBE THEY SHOULD START THINKING ABOUT SOMETHING ELSE. MAYBE THE VIRGIN OF GUADALUPE, WHOSE ANNIVERSARY WE CELEBRATE TODAY, AND WHO IS THE GUARDIAN OF ALL THE AMERICAN COUNTRIES, WILL SHINE SOME LIGHT ON THESE IRRATIONAL PEOPLE. THEY MIGHT SEE THIS AS A VERY CLEAR SIGN THAT THEY CAN NO LONGER JUSTIFY OR LIE, OR TRY TO CONVINCE PEOPLE THAT WHAT THEY DO IS GOOD.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI, IN ENGLISH] THAT IS NOT WHAT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS ARE LOOKING FOR. THEY ARE LOOKING FOR A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEM AND ALL THEIR EFFORTS ARE DIRECTED IN THAT WAY.

[MODERATOR] ANA ARANDA FROM THE MIAMI HERALD.

[ARANDA, IN ENGLISH] [WORDS INDISTINCT] IF THE GOVERNMENT AT ANY POINT CONFRONTED NICARAGUA OR [WORDS INDISTINCT] WHETHER THE GOVERNMENT AS SUCH WAS TRULY INVOLVED IN SENDING WEAPONS TO THE FMLN?

[CRISTIANI, IN ENGLISH] WELL, HE WAS WATCHING SOME OF THE VIDEOTAPES THAT I TOOK. WE WERE WATCHING THEM WITH THE OTHER CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS. AFTER A FEW MINUTES, HE SAID HE HAD SOME TELEPHONE CALLS TO MAKE AND HE GOT UP AND LEFT. OBVIOUSLY HE COULD NOT JUSTIFY WHAT HE WAS SEEING AND WHAT THE OTHER PRESIDENTS WERE WITNESSING THERE ON THE TV SCREEN.

THERE WAS SOME CONFRONTATION WITH ORTEGA OBVIOUSLY, BUT I WILL, YOU KNOW, WILL SAY THAT I DID NOT MIND WHERE THE WAREHOUSE WAS OR WHERE THEY COME FROM. IT IS SIMPLY THE FACT THAT THEY WERE AT SOME POINT IN TIME IN NICARAGUA AND NICARAGUA WAS SENDING THEM OVER TO EL SALVADOR. WHETHER THEY CAME FROM THE SOVIET UNION OR WHETHER THEY BOUGHT THEM FROM SOMEWHERE ELSE, OR WHEREVER THEY CAME FROM, IT REALLY MAKES NO DIFFERENCE. WITHIN THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE PLAN, THE PROBLEM IS THAT THEY ARE COMING THROUGH NICARAGUA WITH THE KNOWLEDGE OF THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT, AND THAT IS A VIOLATION OF THE AGREEMENT.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI, IN ENGLISH] WHAT COULD HE SAY? NO, HE CAME OUT TRYING TO PRODUCE SOME SORT OF DUST OVER THE ISSUE -- LIKE WE CALL IT HERE -- THROUGH HIS MINISTER OF FOREIGN RELATIONS. HE WAS ACCUSING COSTA RICA OF SENDING AID TO THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE. AND MAYBE HE THOUGHT TO DIVERT THE ATTENTION FROM THE SALVADORAN CASE BY TRYING TO SAY THAT COSTA RICA WAS SENDING WEAPONS TO THE NICARAGUAN RESISTANCE. THEN OBVIOUSLY HE ACCUSED EVERYBODY OF SENDING WEAPONS TO NICARAGUA.

THE POINT IS, FIRST OF ALL, HE DID NOT CONVINCE ANY OF THE OTHER FOUR PRESIDENTS. THAT IS FOR SURE. AND THERE WERE NO ARGUMENTS HE MADE IN FRONT OF THE PRESS OR AT ANY POINT IN TIME WHERE THEY DENIED THAT THEY HAVE BEEN HELPING THE FMLN. I MEAN, IT IS VERY CLEAR AND OBVIOUS THAT THEY HAVE HELPED THE FMLN NOT SINCE NOVEMBER 11. ALL THE WEAPONS THAT WERE ALREADY HERE BY NOVEMBER 11 ALSO CAME THROUGH NICARAGUA.

[MODERATOR] RICARDO CLEMENS FROM VISNEWS.

[CLEMENS, IN SPANISH] [WORDS INDISTINCT] CASE OF JENNIFER CASOLO THERE WAS A SERIES OF LEGISLATIVE ISSUES THAT ARE NOT VERY CLEAR AND THERE IS SOME KIND OF IMPASSE REGARDING HER TRIAL. WILL THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH HELP TO ACCELERATE THE TRIAL, OR WILL IT ISSUE SOME KIND OF PARDON OR SOMETHING LIKE THAT?

[CRISTIANI, IN ENGLISH] NO, THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH CANNOT INTERFERE WITH THE JUDICIAL PROCESS OF ANY PERSON IN THE COUNTRY. IT WOULD HAVE TO BE THE SUPREME COURT OR THE JUDICIARY THAT DEALS WITH THE PROBLEM. THEY HAVE TO DECIDE WHAT THE LAW IS AND WHAT THE APPLICATION OF THE LAW SHOULD BE. OUR POSITION IS THAT THE LAW SHOULD BE APPLIED IMPARTIALLY, AND EVERYTHING THAT THE JUDGE OR ANYBODY ELSE DOES IN THE STATE SHOULD BE DONE WITHIN THE LEGAL FRAMEWORK.

BUT WE HAVE NO POSSIBILITY OF INTERVENING IN THE JUDICIARY PROCESS. THERE IS A SEPARATION OF POWERS BETWEEN THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH AND THE JUDICIAL BRANCH.

[MODERATOR, IN SPANISH] THANK YOU, MR PRESIDENT. THANK YOU, GENTLEMEN. THANK YOU ALL.

DEV-MUC3-0980 (SRI)

BOGOTA, 12 DEC 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] BRITISH ENGINEER JOHN MARCK JONES [NAME AS RECEIVED], KIDNAPPED BY THE MARXIST-LENINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY [ELN], RESIDES IN COLOMBIA AND BOTH HIS WIFE AND TWO CHILDREN ARE COLOMBIANS, IT WAS OFICIALLY REPORTED TODAY.

JONES, 45, WHO WAS REPORTED MISSING IN ARAUCA DEPARTMENT IN COLOMBIA'S NORTHEAST EARLY ON 11 DECEMBER, IS THE OWNER OF ALTA TENSION DE COLOMBIA, A POWER COMPANY.

JONES' RELATIVES TOLD THE LOCAL PRESS THAT, DESPITE THE INITIAL REPORTS, THE BRITISH ENGINEER DOES NOT WORK FOR A MULTINATIONAL CORPORATION.

IT IS BELIEVED THAT THE ELN MISTOOK HIM FOR THE EMPLOYEE OF SOME FOREIGN COMPANY AND THAT THEY MIGHT BE PLANNING TO DEMAND A RANSOM.

JONES WAS TAKEN IN A MOUNTAINOUS AREA OF THE CATATUMBO OIL BASIN, NEAR THE BORDER WITH VENEZUELA, WHILE DRIVING WITH TWO FELLOW WORKERS, WHO WERE NOT DETAINED.

THESE MEN TOLD THE COLOMBIAN POLICE THAT THE KIDNAPPERS IDENTIFIED THEMSELVES AS ELN MEMBERS AND THAT THEY TOOK THE ENGINEER WHEN THEY CONFIRMED HE WAS A FOREIGNER.

JONES' POWER COMPANY BUILDS POWER SUBSTATIONS IN OIL CAMPS IN THE AREA WHERE HE WAS KIDNAPPED.

A POLICE SOURCE TOLD EFE THAT A SPECIALIZED AGENCY, WHICH IS INVESTIGATING THE KIDNAPPING, IS TRYING TO DETERMINE THE ENGINEER'S WHEREABOUTS.

THE ELN HAS A LONG HISTORY OF KIDNAPPINGS AND EXTORTION AGAINST OIL GROUPS, BOARD OF DIRECTORS MEMBERS, AND ENGINEERS.

DEV-MUC3-0981 (SRI)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 13 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [SPEECH] [NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA] [TEXT] ....I WAS IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA AT A MEETING OF CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS. THIS MEETING WAS OF URGENT NATURE TO DISCUSS ISSUES SUCH AS EL SALVADOR, NICARAGUA, THE CONTRAS' DEMOBILIZATION, AND HUMAN RIGHTS.

AT THIS MEETING, WE HELD IN-DEPTH DISCUSSIONS OF PROBLEMS THAT ARE BEING EXPERIENCED IN THE CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES, ESPECIALLY THE SITUATION BEING EXPERIENCED IN NEIGHBORING EL SALVADOR, WHICH IS FACING AN INTERNAL CONFLICT -- MORE THAN A DECADE OF CONTINUED WAR AND INTERNAL CONFLICT. EL SALVADOR HAS BEEN SUBJECTED TO A VERY STRONG CONFRONTATION, WHICH LATELY HAS WORSENED. AS YOU ALL KNOW, THE CIVILIAN POPULATION, THE CLERGY, NUNS, AND UNION AND LABOR LEADERS HAVE BEEN VICTIMS OF THIS TRAGIC SITUATION. AT THIS MEETING, NICARAGUA STATED ITS POSITION THAT THE SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR MUST BE RESOLVED THROUGH NEGOTIATION AND NOT BY WAY OF VIOLENCE. THIS POSITION FULLY COINCIDES WITH THE POSITION THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HAS DEFENDED. ON VARIOUS OCCASIONS THE FMLN HAS MADE PEACE PROPOSALS AND IT HAS CALLED FOR NEGOTIATED SOLUTIONS TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT AND FOR REAL NEGOTIATIONS.

FOLLOWING A LENGTHY AND INTENSE DISCUSSION OF THE SALVADORAN ISSUE, WE CAME TO AN AGREEMENT, NOT ONLY WITH REGARD TO GENERAL PLEASE AND STATEMENTS CONCERNING THE SITUATION IN THE NEIGHBORING CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRY, BUT ON VERY SPECIFIC ISSUES THAT COULD LEAD TO SOLUTION OF THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT. THUS, IN POINT THREE, THE FIVE PRESIDENTS DECIDED TO REQUEST THAT THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL MAKE A VERY SPECIAL PERSONAL EFFORT TO BRING ABOUT A DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN, THEREBY CONTRIBUTING TOWARD THE TALKS' SUCCESSFUL DEVELOPMENT.

NICARAGUA HAS THUS SUPPORTED THE NEGOTIATED SOLUTION THE FMLN HAS VIGOROUSLY AND CONSISTENTLY CALLED FOR, AND WITH WHICH THE GOVERNMENT HEADED BY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI ALSO CLAIMS TO AGREE. SUCH NEGOTIATION WOULD LEAD TO A DIALOGUE PROCESS THAT WOULD RESULTE IN SOLVING THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT. LIKEWISE, WE UNDERSCORED HUMAN RIGHTS IN CENTRAL AMERICA, BECAUSE THESE RIGHTS ARE SYSTEMATICALLY VIOLATED IN CERTAIN COUNTRIES. THIS HAS BEEN CLEARLY STATED AT INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS. I AM ESPECIALLY WORRIED ABOUT THE HUMAN RIGHTS SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR, WHERE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS WERE RECENTLY MURDERED, AND WHERE THE ARMY HAS BEEN ACCUSED OF EXERTING INDISCRIMINATE REPRESSION AGAINST THE PEOPLE, THROUGH AERIAL AS WELL AS ARTILLERY AND INFANTRY ATTACKS.

THIS HUMAN RIGHTS ISSUE IS WORRISOME TO THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEOPLE, THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY, AND ESPECIALLY TO NICARAGUA. WE ALSO REACHED AN AGREEMENT BY WHICH THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS INSISTED ON THE NEED FOR RESPECT OF HUMAN RIGHTS. IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE ESQUIPULAS II AGREEMENTS, THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS RATIFIED THEIR PLEDGES TO FULLY RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS, INCLUDING THE CIVILIAN, POLITICAL, ECONOMIC, SOCIAL, AND CULTURAL RIGHTS ESTABLISHED IN THEIR RESPECTIVE CONSTITUTIONS, AND IN SIGNED AND RATIFIED INTERNATIONAL AGREEMENTS.

NICARAGUA'S POSITION HAS NOT WAVERED; IT HAS MAINTAINED ITS POSITIONS THAT THE CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES ARE WILLING TO HAVE RECOGNIZED INTERNATIONAL HUMAN RIGHTS ORGANIZATIONS [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN OUR RESPECTIVE COUNTRIES, AND HELP DEFEND HUMAN RIGHTS IN CENTRAL AMERICA. THERE ARE FORCES, CENTRAL AMERICAN ARMIES ESPECIALLY, AMONG THEM THE SALVADORAN ARMY -- WHICH HAS ORGANIZED DEATH SQUADS THAT SYSTEMATICALLY MURDER SALVADORAN PEOPLE -- WHOSE GOVERNMENTS AND PRESIDENTS ARE FACED WITH CERTAIN LIMITATIONS IN OVERCOMING THE PROBLEM OF HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS. THIS, I BELIEVE, IS WHERE THE GREATEST STRENGTH MUST BE EXERTED AND THE GREATEST EFFORT MADE TO DISBAND THE DEATH SQUADS SO THAT HUMAN RIGHTS CAN BE RESPECTED, A PEACEFUL SOLUTION CAN BE FOUND FOR ALL THE CONFLICTS IN THESE COUNTRIES, AND A WORSENING OF VIOLENCE CAN BE AVOIDED, ESPECIALLY SINCE THIS VIOLENCE IS ON THE INCREASE BECAUSE OF THE INJUSTICE THAT PREVAILS IN THESE COUNTRIES DUE TO A LACK OF EQUITY, FREEDOM, AND JUSTICE, WHICH IS AT THE ROOT OF THE PROBLEM. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0982 (SRI)

GUATEMALA CITY, 13 DEC 89 (RADIO NUEVO MUNDO) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO HAS REFERRED TO THE POSSIBILITY OF A DIALOGUE BETWEEN GOVERNMENT REPRESENTATIVES AND MEMBERS OF THE GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY, URNG, CLEARLY STATING THAT THE POSSIBILITY OF A DIALOGUE WITH THAT ORGANIZATION HAS BEEN DISCUSSED. HE ADDED THAT THE URNG MUST FIRST STATE THAT IT IS WILLING TO PEACEFULLY PARTICIPATE IN THE DIALOGUE.

THE GUATEMALAN PRESIDENT ADDED THAT THE REBELS MUST UNDERSTAND THA THEY CANNOT TALK ABOUT DIALOGUE WHEN PERPETRATING ACTS OF TREASON AGAINST THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEOPLE, MEANING PLACING BOMBS AND PERPETRATING ACTS OF TERRORISM. THE URNG MUST DECIDE TO SUSPEND ITS TERRORIST ACTIONS IF IT WANTS TO HOLD A DIALOGUE, HE SAID. CEREZO ADDED THAT THERE IS A POLITICAL OPPORTUNITY FOR ALL THE IDEOLOGIES IN GUATEMALA.

CEREZO AREVALO ADDED THAT IF THE URNG MEMBERS WISH TO HOLD A DIALOGUE, THEY MAY DO SO. IN FACT, HE SAID, IF THEY WANT TO RETURN TO THE COUNTRY WE CAN DISCUSS THE SECURITY CONDITIONS -- BUT THEY MUST PUBLICLY STATE THEIR DECISION TO RETURN IN PEACE. OTHERWISE, THE PRESIDENT ADDED, IT WOULD BE TANTAMOUNT TO GIVING THE OTHER, RIGHT-WING, TERRORISTS, WHO ATTACK STUDENTS, ENGAGE IN KIDNAPPING, AND PLACE BOMBS, THE RIGHT TO PARTICIPATE IN AN INTERNAL DIALOGUE. THE URNG MUST DECIDE IF IT WANTS TO JOIN US. THEY MUST DO IT PEACEFULLY BECAUSE THAT IS THE PROPER THING. THE PEOPLE ARE FED UP WITH VIOLENCE AND WAR, HE SAID.

PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO REFERRED TO THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PARLIAMENT'S FUTURE DURING THE NEWS CONFERENCE, HELD AT THE GUATEMALAN AIR FORCE'S INSTALLATIONS UPON HIS RETURN TO THE COUNTRY FROM COSTA RICA. HE SAID THAT THE SAN ISIDRO DECLARATION SIGNED BY THE FIVE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS INCLUDED TWO IMPRESSIVE DECISIONS. HE SAID THAT THEY SIGNED AN AGREEMENT ON THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PARLIAMENT -- EACH COUNTRY MAY DECIDE ON ITS CONTRIBUTION AS IT SEES FIT -- A SUBJECT WHICH HAD DELAYED THE SIGNATURE OF THE APPROPRIATE DOCUMENTS. IN ADDITION, THE ECOLOGY AND DEVELOPMENT COMMISSION WILL BEGIN TO OPERATE BECAUSE THEY BELIEVE THAT ITS EFFORTS WILL HELP CONSOLIDATE PEACE AND DEMOCRACY IN THE AREA.

DEV-MUC3-0983 (SRI)

HAVANA (CUBA), 13 DEC 89 (INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH SALVADORAN RICARDO MONTENEGRO, MEMBER OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN "RADIO VENCEREMOS INTERNATIONAL SERVICE," BY JORGE LUIS BERNARD] [TEXT] [BERNARD] MONTENEGRO, WE WOULD LIKE TO KNOW IF THE THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] WILL CONTINUE WITH THE CURRENT MILITARY OFFENSIVE THAT BEGAN ON 11 NOVEMBER SINCE THE AGREEMENT AMONG THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS WAS SIGNED?

[MONTENEGRO] THE TRUTH IS THAT THE REASONS WHY THE FMLN BEGAN ITS OFFENSIVE ON 11 NOVEMBER 1989 HAVE NOT CHANGED AT ALL. THUS, THE FMLN CANNOT STOP ITS OFFENSIVE. ON THE CONTRARY, WHAT HAPPENED IN EL SALVADOR IS THAT THE FMLN OFFENSIVE STRATEGICALLY TURNED THE WAR. THAT TURN INCLUDED A NUMBER OF MILITARY, POLITICAL, AND DIPLOMATIC IMPLICATIONS.

THUS, THE TRUTH IS THAT THE AGREEMENT SIGNED IN SAN ISIDRO DE CORONADO DID NOT PROPOSE REALISTIC NEGOTIATIONS FOR THE CONFLICT. YESTERDAY, 12 DECEMBER, THE FMLN ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE WHICH VEHEMENTLY EXPRESSED ITS ABSOLUTE REJECTION OF THE AGREEMENT SIGNED AT THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT. AT PRESENT, THE FMLN BELIEVES THAT DESPITE WHAT THE OTHER FOUR CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS SAY, IT IS CLEARER THAN EVER THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS A FASCIST, MILITARY DICTATORSHIP. THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT VIOLATES PEOPLE'S HUMAN RIGHTS AND THAT FACT HAS BEEN CLEARLY PROVED TO THE ENTIRE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY. THEREFORE, ANY ATTEMPT TO HELP THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT OR ANY KIND OF SUPPORT GIVEN TO IT NOTHING BUT A PIECE OF PAPER THAT DOES NOT HAVE TOO MUCH VALIDITY TO THE FMLN.

[BERNARD] IN OTHER WORDS COMRADE, THE FMLN WILL MAINTAIN THE SAME LEVEL OF CONFRONTATION WITH THE DICTATORSHIP?

[MONTENEGRO] I BELIEVE THE FMLN'S ARMED STRUGGLE IS NOW MORE LEGITIMATE THAN EVER. THE SUMMIT CONFIRMED THE LEGITIMACY OF THE FMLN'S STRUGGLE, BECAUSE THE AGREEMENT RESULTING FROM THAT SUMMIT IS NEITHER FEASIBLE NOR REAL. THE FMLN WILL THEREFORE CONTINUE ITS POLITICAL - MILITARY OFFENSIVE. THE FMLN WILL INCREASE ITS ACTIONS. THE FMLN IS REORGANIZING [READECUAR] ITS POLITICAL - MILITARY APPARATUS. IN THE NEXT FEW DAYS, WE WILL CLEARLY SHOW WHAT THE FMLN CAN DO. THE FMLN WILL NOT SURRENDER ITS WEAPONS, ESPECIALLY NOW. THE FMLN HAS NO OBLIGATION TO ABIDE BY AN AGREEMENT THAT DOES NOT REFLECT THE SALVADORAN REALITY AT ALL.

IF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS CHOSE TO CLOSE THEIR EYES TO WHAT IS GOING ON THAT IS REALLY THEIR PROBLEM.

[BERNARD] TWO DAYS AFTER THE END OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN SUMMIT, WHAT IS THE CURRENT MILITARY SITUATION IN EL SALVADOR?

[MONTENEGRO] AS I TOLD YOU EARLIER IN ANSWERING THE FIRST QUESTION, THE FIRST THING IS THAT THE FMLN DEFINATELY CHANGED THE WAR. THIS MEANS THAT THE FMLN MADE THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES RETREAT FROM THE MOUNTAINS TO THE HEART OF THE CITIES INCLUDING THE CAPITAL CITY OF SAN SALVADOR.

AT PRESENT, WE HAVE ALMOST ABSOLUTE CONTROL OVER THE HIGHWAYS IN 14, I MEAN 12 SALVADORAN DEPARTMENTS. THERE HAVE BEEN ACTIONS IN AHUACHAPAN AND SONSONATE, TWO DEPARTMENTS THAT HAD BEEN ALMOST UNTOUCHED BY THE WAR.

THERE IS A STRATEGIC SIEGE IN SAN SALVADOR. THE ARMY HAS 65 PERCENT OF ITS FORCES STATIONED IN SAN SALVADOR. THE ARMY HAS ABANDONED LARGE AREAS.

AS FOR SABOTAGE OPERATIONS, AT PRESENT THERE ARE 10 110,000-VOLT PRIMARY LINES THAT ARE OUT OF SERVICE. THAT REPRESENTS A 40-PERCENT ENERGY DEFICIT IN THE COUNTRY. THERE HAVE BEEN LONG PERIODS OF 100-PERCENT POWER OUTAGES IN SAN SALVADOR. IT IS VERY UNLIKELY THAT THE GOVERNMENT CAN CONTROL THAT SITUATION. WE DO NOT KNOW HOW LONG THEY WILL ENDURE IT. BUT IN ANY CASE, A STRONG BLOW BY THE FMLN FORCES IS EXPECTED TO OCCUR SOMEWHERE IN EL SALVADOR AT ANY TIME. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-0984 (SRI)

CLANDESTINE, 13 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] WE COULD SAY THAT TO A GREAT EXTENT THE DECLARATION IS FULL OF PRETTY WORDS, SIMILAR TO THOSE CRISTIANI USES, IN THE PARTS WHERE THE DECLARATION CALLS ON THE FMLN TO JOIN THE ALLEGED DEMOCRATIC PROCESS AND SAYS THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS LEGITIMATE. HOWEVER, IF WE LOOK CAREFULLY, WE CAN SEE WHAT IS BEHIND THE WORDS AND THAT IN ADDITION TO DECLARING SUPPORT FOR THE GOVERNMENT, AN ATTEMPT IS MADE TO DO THE SALVADORAN ARMY A FAVOR. THIS IS DONE BY ASKING THE FMLN TO STOP ALL VIOLENT ACTIONS THAT DIRECTLY OR INDIRECTLY AFFECT THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

WE KNOW THAT THIS IS HOW THE GOVERNMENT REFERS TO SIEGES ON CITIES, TO TRANSPORTATION STRIKES, AND TO SABOTAGE, THE ARMY'S MOST SERIOUS SOURCES OF CONCERN. UNDERNEATH THIS DECLARATION IS A REQUEST FOR THE FMLN TO LEAVE THE CITIES BECAUSE THE ARMY CAN NO LONGER STAND THE SITUATION AND FEELS IT IS NEAR COLLAPSE.

THE DECLARATION DOES NOT STATE ANY CONCERN FOR BOMBINGS BECAUSE CONSIDERING THE CONDITION IN WHICH THE GOVERNMENT IS NOW, ANY STATEMENT IN THIS REGARD WOULD BE LIKE ADDING FUEL TO THE FIRE. THE DECLARATION IS LIKE A WALKING STICK TO KEEP THE DICTATORSHIP UP, AND, AS THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND HAS STATED IN A COMMUNIQUE, IT IS EVIDENCE OF THE POLITICAL AND MILITARY CRISIS IN WHICH THIS GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN PLACED AS A RESULT OF THE OFFENSIVE CARRIED OUT BY ALL OF YOU.

TO CONCLUDE: LET US WAIT AND SEE IF THIS DECLARATION WILL SAVE CRISTIANI FROM INTERNATIONAL ISOLATION. IT IS IMPORTANT TO TAKE INTO CONSIDERATION WHAT THE GENERAL COMMAND HAS STATED IN ITS COMMUNIQUE, THAT THE AGREEMENTS BY GOVERNMENTS THAT DO NOT KNOW THE TRUE SITUATION IN OUR COUNTRY AND THAT SERVE OTHER INTERESTS CANNOT DEMOBILIZE THE FMLN BECAUSE THE FMLN ENJOYS POPULAR SUPPORT THROUGHOUT THE NATION.

THE FMLN IS NOT LIKE THE CONTRAS WHO ARE IN HONDURAS AND INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS CAN GO TO THEIR CAMPS TO DEMOBILIZE THEM. IN EL SALVADOR THE SITUATION IS VERY DIFFERENT. CRISTIANI HIMSELF WAS UNABLE TO ANSWER A JOURNALIST WHO ASKED HIM IF HE WAS GOING TO DEMOBILIZE THE FMLN IN SAN SALVADOR, IN GUAZAPA, IN CHALATENANGO, AND MORAZAN.

THE COSTA RICA DECLARATION IS NEITHER REALISTIC NOR VIABLE. THIS IS SOMETHING THAT THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY IS ALREADY POINTING OUT. AN INTERNATIONAL TELEVISION NETWORK HAS SAID THAT FOLLOWING THIS DECLARATION, THE ESQUIPULAS AGREEMENT COULD BECOME JUST WORDS. A JOURNALIST HAS ASKED HOW MUCH THIS ALLEGED INTERNATIONAL VICTORY OF CRISTIANI IS GOING TO LAST.

MEANWHILE, THE ARCHBISHOP OF GUATEMALA HAS SAID THAT HE DOES NOT EXPECT ANYTHING GOOD FROM THE MEETING BECAUSE NEITHER THE CONTRAS NOR THE FMLN WERE PRESENT.

THE REACTION TO THE RESULTS OF THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT ARE ALONG THESE LINES.

THE TRUTH IS THAT TRUE FACTS ARE WHAT COUNTS. WORDS AND PAPER ARE ALWAYS DEFEATED BY FACTS. THE TRUTH IS THAT THE ARMY KEEPS BOMBING AND THAT GENOCIDE WILL ALWAYS BE CONDEMNED.

THE TRUTH IS THAT YOUR EFFORTS, COMRADES, WILL NOT CEASE UNTIL THE DICTATORSHIP IS DEFINITELY DEFEATED.

DEV-MUC3-0986 (SRI)

WASHINGTON DC (USA), 13 DEC 89 (BEIJING XINHUA) -- [TEXT] U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH WILL GO TO VIOLENCE-TORN COLOMBIA ON FEBRUARY 15 FOR A FOUR-NATION SUMMIT ON ILLEGAL DRUGS, THE WHITE HOUSE ANNOUNCED TODAY.

WHITE HOUSE SPOKESMAN MARLIN FITZWATER SAID BUSH WILL MEET IN CARTAGENA, A PORT CITY ABOUT 640 KILOMETERS NORTH OF BOGOTA, WITH COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA AND PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA.

FITZWATER SAID BUSH IS GOING TO SHOW HIS SUPPORT FOR BARCO, WHO HAS WAGED A NATION-WIDE WAR AGAINST DRUG LORDS SINCE LAST AUGUST.

COLOMBIAN COCAINE LORDS HAVE SET OFF MORE THAN 260 BOMBS, KILLING AT LEAST 190 PEOPLE, IN RETALIATION FOR THE GOVERNMENT'S CRACKDOWN.

A U.S. ADVANCE TEAM, HEADED BY ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF STATE BERNARD ARONSON, HAS BEEN SENT TO COLOMBIA TO COMPLETE PLANS FOR THE SUMMIT.

THE FORMAL ANNOUNCEMENT FOLLOWED BUSH'S SIGNING LEGISLATION EARLIER TODAY AUTHORIZING 240 MILLION DOLLARS IN AID TO THE THREE ANDEAN NATIONS, WHICH ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR AN ESTIMATED 80 PERCENT OF THE COCAINE THAT MAKES ITS WAY INTO THE UNITED STATES.

THE LEGISLATION AUTHORIZES SPENDING 125 MILLION DOLLARS FOR MILITARY AND LAW ENFORCEMENT AID AND 115 MILLION DOLLARS FOR NARCOTICS CONTROL ASSISTANCE.

THE MEETING IS EXPECTED TO LAST ONE DAY.

DEV-MUC3-0987 (SRI)

SANTIAGO, 14 DEC 89 (RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT PINOCHET HAS BRANDED FOREIGN JOURNALISTS AS INTRUDERS. THE HEAD OF STATE WAS CLEARLY UPSET BY THE PRESENCE OF INTERNATIONAL JOURNALISTS AND OBSERVERS WHEN HE WENT TO VOTE.

JOURNALIST ELIANA HENRIQUEZ WILL NOW GIVE US MORE DETAILS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [HENRIQUEZ] GOOD AFTERNOON. PRESIDENT AUGUSTO PINOCHET THIS MORNING LEFT THE HIGHER INSTITUTE OF COMMERCE WHERE HE WENT TO VOTE, ANGRY WITH CHILEANS AND CLEARLY UPSET BY THE PRESENCE OF INTERNATIONAL OBSERVERS AND JOURNALISTS. THE HEAD OF STATE WALKED FROM THE LA MONEDA PALACE TO THE HIGHER INSTITUTE OF COMMERCE, WHICH IS AT THE INTERSECTION OF AMUNATEGUI AND MONEDA STREETS. HE WAS ACCOMPANIED BY THE INTERIOR MINISTER, THE MINISTER SECRETARY GENERAL OF GOVERNMENT, THE PRESIDENTIAL GENERAL SECRETARY, AND THE CHIEF OF THE MILITARY HOUSEHOLD. HE GREETED GENERAL CARLOS PARERA, THE MILITARY COMMANDER OF THE METROPOLITAN REGION, AND THE SANTIAGO MAYOR. PINOCHET THEN WENT TO VOTING TABLE NO 1 WHERE HE WAS SCHEDULED TO VOTE. HE SAW DOZENS OF FOREIGN TELEVISION CAMERAMEN, PHOTOGRAPHERS, AND JOURNALISTS.

BEFORE ENTERING THE VOTING BOOTH, PINOCHET SAID HE WAS IN VERY GOOD SPIRITS AND VERY HAPPY.

AFTER VOTING, PINOCHET SAID HE WAS VERY SATISFIED BECAUSE THIS MEANT THE END OF THE MISSION HE BEGAN ON 11 SEPTEMBER 1973. HE ADDED THAT HE EXPECTED THE ELECTION TO DEVELOP AS CALMLY AS USUAL. WHEN A U.S. NEWSWOMAN APPROACHED HIM FOR AN INTERVIEW, PINOCHET, IRRITATED, ASKED HER WHAT SHE WAS DOING PUTTING HER NOSE IN HERE; HE TOLD HER THAT THIS IS OUR PROBLEM, NOT YOURS, INTRUDERS. PINOCHET THEN TURNED TO THE LOCAL NEWSMEN AND TOLD THEM THAT HE IS UNHAPPY WITH CHILEANS FOR ALLOWING FOREIGN OBSERVERS TO ENTER THE COUNTRY.

[PINOCHET] I AM UNHAPPY WITH CHILEANS BECAUSE THEY HAVE LOST THEIR FEELING OF NATIONALITY BY ACCEPTING THE PRESENCE OF A BUNCH OF OUTSIDERS WHO HAVE COME TO LOOK OVER WHAT WE ARE DOING. WHAT DO THEY THINK THEY ARE DOING? LET ME TELL YOU SOMETHING ELSE: THESE OUTSIDERS ARE HERE TO CHECK ON THE WAY IN WHICH THEIR MONEY HAS BEEN INVESTED BY THE POLITICAL PARTIES AND THESE GENTLEMEN [A REFERENCE TO OPPOSITION CANDIDATES IN GENERAL].

[HENRIQUEZ] AS HE WAS LEAVING THE VOTING SITE, PINOCHET TOLD A URUGUAYAN CORRESPONDENT THAT THE OBSERVERS ARE INTRUDERS.

INTERIOR MINISTER CARLOS CACERES AFFIRMED THAT THE SITUATION AROUND THE COUNTRY REMAINS NORMAL AND ORDERLY. HE ADDED THAT THE ONLY INCIDENT WAS THE BOMB EXPLOSION AT THE EL SALVADORAN EMBASSY AND A MINOR INCIDENT THAT TOOK PLACE THIS MORNING IN THE LOCALITY OF MARIA PINTO. CACERES SAID THAT HE WILL REMAIN ALL DAY AT THE LA MONEDA PALACE IN ORDER TO BRIEF PRESIDENT PINOCHET ON THE VOTING PROCEEDINGS AND ANY SECURITY PROBLEM THAT MIGHT ARISE.

FINALLY, HE SAID THAT THE HEAD OF STATE WILL ALSO STAY IN HIS OFFICE. THIS AFTERNOON PINOCHET WILL PROBABLY VISIT THE VOTE COUNTING CENTER OF THE INTERIOR MINISTRY ON MONATEGUI STREET. GOOD AFTERNOON. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0989 (SRI)

SANTIAGO, 15 DEC 89 (TELEVISION NACIONAL DE CHILE NETWORK) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [TEXT] GOOD EVENING. THE GOVERNMENT HAS ANNOUNCED A MAJOR PORTION OF THE RESULTS OF THE ELECTIONS HELD TODAY. AFTER 93 PERCENT OF THE VOTING STATIONS HAVE BEEN COUNTED, AND WHEN ALL THAT IS NEEDED IS THE OFFICIAL REPORT OF THE ELECTORAL COURT, IT IS POSSIBLE TO SAY THAT PATRICIO AYLWIN AZOCAR HAS BEEN ELECTED PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC FOR THE L990-L994 TERM.

WITH REGARD TO THAT RESULT THE SUPREME GOVERNMENT WOULD LIKE TO CONVEY TO THE PEOPLE THE FOLLOWING:

1. ALL CHILEANS SHOULD BE PROUD FOR ONCE AGAIN PARTICIPATING IN AN EXEMPLARY ELECTION.

2. ON BEHALF OF THE SUPREME GOVERNMENT, I WOULD LIKE TO CONVEY A DESERVED RECOGNITION TO THE ARMED FORCES AND CARABINEROS, WHO HAVE LED AN ELECTORAL PROCESS IN ORDER AND TRANQUILITY, AND TO ALL THE PEOPLE WHO PARTICIPATED TODAY AT THE VOTING STATIONS. THEY ENABLED THIS ELECTION TO BE HELD IN AN ENVIRONMENT OF PEACE, AND THEREBY ALLOWED THE FREE EXPRESSION OF CIVIC WILL. WE MUST, HOWEVER, REPUDIATE THE VIOLENT MURDER OF A MEMBER OF CARABINEROS.

3. THE PEOPLE MUST REST ASSURED THAT THE GOVERNMENT OF PRESIDENT PINOCHET, FAITHFUL TO THE COMMITMENT MADE WITH THE ARMED FORCES AND POLICE, WILL HAVE THE RESULTS OF THE RECENT ELECTIONS RESPECTED. THE GOVERNMENT CALLS ON THE ENTIRE COUNTRY TO MAINTAIN PUBLIC ORDER, AND TO WAIT WITH TRANQUILITY THE FINAL RESULTS OF THIS ELECTION.

4. DURING THE LAST 16 YEARS CHILE HAS MOVED AHEAD SYSTEMATICALLY AND WITHOUT HESITATION TOWARD THE GREAT OBJECTIVES SET FORTH AT THE BEGINNING OF THE MILITARY GOVERNMENT. THE GOVERNMENT IS FULLY SATISFIED WITH THE WORK OF DEMOCRATIC, ECONOMIC, AND SOCIAL RECONSTRUCTION THAT WAS CARRIED OUT BY ALL CHILEANS UNDER THE LEADERSHIP OF PRESIDENT PINOCHET. WE HAVE SET FORTH A SOLID BASIS FOR FUTURE PROSPERITY.

5. THIS ELECTION FULFILLED ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT REQUIREMENTS FOR REACHING THE FULL DEMOCRACY THAT WAS DESTROYED IN THE PAST BY THE ENEMIES OF FREEDOM AND PLURALISM. AS HIS EXCELLENCY PRESIDENT PINOCHET SAID, 11 SEPTEMBER L973 NOT ONLY REPRESENTED THE OVERTHROW OF AN ILLEGIMATE AND FAILED GOVERNMENT, BUT IT ALSO REPRESENTED THE END OF A WORN OUT POLITICAL AND INSTITUTIONAL REGIME, AND THE NEED TO BUILD A NEW ONE. IT WAS NOT JUST A TASK OF SIMPLE RESTORATION, BUT PRIMARILY A CREATIVE TASK WHICH, IN ORDER TO SUCCEED, HAD TO BE CARRIED OUT IN THE DEEP ROOTS OF NATIONAL TRADITION.

6. THE ARMED FORCES AND CARABINEROS FULFILLED THE COMMITMENT MADE IN SEPTEMBER L973. THE MISSION HAS BEEN FULFILLED. AUTHENTIC DEMOCRACY AS A WAY OF LIFE AND A FORM OF GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN CREATED, AND THE TRANSITION PROCESS ENDS ON 11 MARCH L990. FROM NOW ON IT WILL BE THE RESPONSIBILITY OF EVERY CHILEAN TO KEEP WATCH SO THAT THE STABILITY AND PROGRESS ACHIEVED WITH POLITICAL WILL AND CONSTANT EFFORT WILL CONTINUE TO PREVAIL IN OUR FREE SOCIETY. THANK YOU VERY MUCH. GOOD NIGHT.

DEV-MUC3-0990 (SRI)

CLANDESTINE, 14 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] AFTER AN EXHAUSTIVE INVESTIGATION, THE SALVADORAN ARCHBISHOPRIC LEGAL ASSISTANCE OFFICE ISSUES THE FOLLOWING STATEMENT REGARDING THE MASSACRE OF THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS:

THE OPERATION CARRIED OUT TO MURDER THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND THE TWO MAIDS LASTED LONGER THAN 1 HOUR. DURING ALL THAT TIME, THE PERPETRARORS FIRED THEIR WEAPONS AND DETONATED EXPLOSIVES. THIS WAS PROVED BY THE FINDING OF MANY SHELL CASINGS NEAR THE JESUITS' RESIDENCE. THE WITNESS' STATEMENTS ALSO CONFIRMED THAT THE WEAPONS WERE FIRED OVER A LONG PERIOD OF TIME. THE NUMBER OF INDIVIDUALS WHO COMMITTED THE CRIME WAS LARGE. THEY WERE WEARING ARMY UNIFORMS. THE WITNESS SAW APPROXIMATELY FIVE INDIVIDUALS WEARING ARMY UNIFORMS. THE WITNESS SAW THE MEN. SHE ALSO HEARD THE SHOOTING, THE CLOSING OF DOORS, AND THE BREAKING OF GLASS IN VARIOUS PARTS OF THE FACILITIES. THE WITNESS SAID THAT FIVE INDIVIDUALS ENTERED THE SERVANTS' ENTRANCE OF THE JESUITS' RESIDENCE. OTHER INDIVIDUALS ENTERED THE RESIDENCE BY THE DOOR LOCATED IN THE NORTHWESTERN END OF THE BUILDING, WHICH IS THE AREA WHERE THE PRIESTS HAVE THEIR ROOMS. ANOTHER GROUP ENTERED THE JESUIT CENTER, SEARCHED IT, AND BURNED IT WITH SOPHISTICATED WEAPONS SUCH AS FLAMETHROWERS.

3. [NO NUMBERS 1 AND 2 AS HEARD] THE SALVADORAN MILITARY INTELLIGENCE, THE PERPETRATORS, KNEW THE JESUIT CENTER AND THE JESUIT RESIDENCE. IN OTHER WORDS, THEY KNEW THE UCA [CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY] FACILITIES. ON MONDAY, 13 NOVEMBER, INDIVIDUALS WEARING ARMY UNIFORMS SPECIFICALLY SEARCHED THE JESUIT CENTER AND RESIDENCE.

4. THE SCENE OF THE CRIME IS LOCATED INSIDE AN ARMY CONTROL AND SECURITY AREA SINCE THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF IS LOCATED IN THAT SAME GENERAL AREA. THE ARMY MAINTAINS PERMANENT MILITARY SURVEILLANCE POSTS AT THE DEMOCRACIA BUILDING, THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE MILITARY NEIGHBORHOOD, THE NORTHERN UCA ENTRANCE, AT THE VARIOUS UCA SCHOOLS, AND AT LA CEIBA DE GUADALUPE AND JARDINES DE GUADALUPE NEIGHBORHOODS. ALL THOSE AREAS ARE WELL GUARDED BY SOLDIERS.

5. DESPITE THE EVIDENT AND VERIFIABLE MILITARIZATION OF THE AREA WHERE THE CRIME TOOK PLACE, THE CURFEW, THE EXTENDED AND HEAVY FIRING INSIDE THE UCA PREMISES, THE DETONATION OF EXPLOSIVES FOR AN EXTENDED PERIOD OF TIME DURING WHICH THE PERPETRATORS REMAINED INSIDE THE JESUIT FACILITIES -- WHICH GAVE THE PERPETRATORS TIME TO SEARCH THE JESUIT PRIESTS' ROOMS, KILL THEM ALONG WITH THE OTHER TWO VICTIMS, AND SEARCH AND BURN THE JESUIT CENTER CHURCH, THUS PROVING THE SIZE OF THE OPERATION -- THE ARMED FORCES DID NOT REACT AS THEY WOULD HAVE IF THIS OPERATION HAD BEEN CARRIED OUT BY THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT]. THIS INDICATES THAT THE SOLDIERS IN CHARGE OF SECURITY IN THE MANUEL JOSE ARCE MILITARY NEIGHBORHOOD AND THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF INSTALLATIONS WERE AWARE OF THE OPERATION THAT WAS BEING CARRIED OUT.

THEREFORE, THE ARCHBISHOPRIC'S LEGAL ASSISTANCE OFFICE CONCLUDES THAT ALL THE EVIDENCE INDICATES THAT MILITARY PERSONNEL OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MURDER OF THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND THE TWO MAIDS.

DEV-MUC3-0991 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 DEC 89 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS NOT PROPOSED TO THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT RESUMING DIPLOMATIC AND CONSULAR RELATIONS, PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI EXPLAINED ON 13 DECEMBER AT THE PRESIDENTIAL PALACE.

"I HAVE NOT TALKED ABOUT UNILATERALLY NORMALIZING RELATIONS, NOR ARE WE THINKING OF DOING THIS UNLESS THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT COMPLIES WITH CERTAIN REQUIREMENTS THAT WE PRESENTED IN A DOCUMENT IN SAN JOSE," THE PRESIDENT SAID.

IN A NEWS CONFERENCE HOSTED ON 12 DECEMBER, HE SAID THAT THE PRESIDENTS OF GUATEMALA, HONDURAS, AND COSTA RICA HAD URGED SOME TYPE OF DIALOGUE OR NEGOTIATIONS WITH ORTEGA TO SEEK NORMALIZING RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA, AND AS A RESULT HE PRESENTED THE DOCUMENTS WITH THE REQUIREMENTS.

UNTIL THE AFTERNOON OF 13 DECEMBER, THE NICARAGUAN REGIME HAD NOT ANSWERED THE MINIMUM CONDITIONS FOR EL SALVADOR TO REESTABLISH OR NORMALIZE RELATIONS WITH MANAGUA.

EL SALVADOR SUSPENDED ALL TYPES OF RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA ON 26 NOVEMBER, AFTER THE SALVADORAN ARMY DISCOVERED A PLANE COMING FROM MANAGUA WITH WEAPONS FOR THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN].

CRISTIANI HAS INSISTED THAT "WITHOUT THE MATERIAL SUPPORT THAT THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT GIVES THE TERRORISTS OPERATING HERE, THEY WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN ABLE TO LAUNCH THE UNSUCCESSFUL OFFENSIVE OF 11 NOVEMBER IN SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER IMPORTANT CITIES AROUND THE COUNTRY.

THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT IN SAN JOSE, COSTA RICA, HE SHOWED ORTEGA A GREAT DEAL OF EVIDENCE OF THE NICARAGUAN INTERVENTION IN SALVADORAN AFFAIRS.

HE ALSO SHOWED ALL THE PRESIDENTS A VIDEO IN WHICH MEMBERS OF THE FMLN ARE SHOWN RECEIVING TRAINING IN NICARAGUA, AND IN WHICH FMLN LEADERS SUCH AS JORGE SHAFIK HANDAL AND OTHERS ARE SHOWN RECEIVING INSTRUCTIONS IN MANAGUA, AND OTHER EVIDENCE. AFTER VIEWING SEVERAL MINUTES OF SUCH EVIDENCE, ORTEGA GOT UP AND TOLD THE PRESIDENTS HE WAS GOING TO MAKE A TELEPHONE CALL, BUT HE NEVER RETURNED TO THE ROOM, CRISTIANI SAID. "IN OTHER WORDS, ORTEGA WAS NEVER ABLE TO DENY HE IS SENDING WEAPONS AND HELP TO THE FMLN," THE PRESIDENT POINTED OUT.

DEV-MUC3-0992 (SRI)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 15 DEC 89 (RADIO SANDINO) -- [TEXT] NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA HAS CALLED ON THE U.S. GOVERNMENT TO RESPECT THE PEACE AGREEMENTS SIGNED BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS. AT A MEETING WITH RESIDENTS OF NIQUINOMO, ORTEGA TALKED ABOUT THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED BY THE PRESIDENTS OF THE REGION DURING THE MEETING IN SAN ISIDRO DE CORONADO, COSTA RICA.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ORTEGA] THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED IN COSTA RICA ARE ANOTHER STEP FOWARD IN THE INTEREST OF PEACE IN CENTRAL AMERICA. HOWEVER, WE ARE NOT COMPLETELY SATISFIED, BECAUSE, AS I WAS TELLING THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS YESTERDAY, IT IS ONE THING TO AGREE ON SOMETHING AND SIGN AN AGREEMENT, BUT WHAT WE DO WHEN WE RETURN TO OUR COUNTRIES IS QUITE ANOTHER. THERE MUST BE CONSISTENCY BETWEEN WHAT IS SIGNED AND WHAT IS DONE. IF WE SIGN AN AGREEMENT AND PROMISE TO RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS, THEN WE MUST RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS - - NOT KILL PRIESTS AND BRUTALLY REPRESS THE PEOPLE AS IN EL SALVADOR. IF WE AGREE THAT THE CONTRAS MUST BE DEMOBILIZED, THEN THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT MUST DO ITS PART TO ENSURE THAT THE CONTRAS ARE DEMOBILIZED. WE MUST DEMAND THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT RESPECT THE AGREEMENTS. THE PROBLEM WE FACE IS THAT AFTER EVERY PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT IS HELD AND AGREEMENTS ARE SIGNED, THE YANKEE GOVERNMENT DOES NOT RESPECT THEM AND CONTINUES TO DO AS IT PLEASES. I HOPE THE U.S. GOVERNMENT WILL, ONCE AND FOR ALL, RESPECT THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS. THE UNITED STATES CAN SHOW ITS WILLINGNESS TO RESPECT THESE AGREEMENTS BY REFRAINING FROM HINDERING THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] AND THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE SEARCH FOR A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION TO THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT. IF THE U.S. GOVERNMENT IS TRULY WILLING TO RESPECT THESE AGREEMENTS, THEN IT MUST NO LONGER GIVE THE CONTRAS MONEY TO MURDER THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE. LIKE THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS SAID, THAT MONEY SHOULD BE GIVEN TO THE INTERNATIONAL COMMISSION OF SUPPORT AND VERIFICATION. ONLY IN THIS WAY WILL THE CONTRAS STOP BEING A THREAT TO THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-0997 (SRI)

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 15 DEC 89 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN 19 APRIL MOVEMENT [M-19] HAS ASKED VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ FOR POLITICAL SUPPORT TO SECURE COMPLIANCE WITH THE AGREEMENTS SIGNED BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND THE GOVERNMENT OF COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO.

EVERTH BUSTAMANTE, THE M-19'S INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS SECRETARY, SAID TODAY IN CARACAS THAT ON 14 DECEMBER HE INFORMED PEREZ ABOUT THE GRAVE POLITICAL CRISIS WHICH HAD EXPLODED IN HIS COUNTRY IN RECENT DAYS.

THE RESIGNATION OF THE PRESIDENTS OF COLOMBIA'S TWO LARGEST POLITICAL PARTIES, AS WELL AS THE COLOMBIAN CONGRESS' POSITION IN FAVOR OF SUBMITTING TO A REFERENDUM THE RULING ON EXTRADITING DRUG TRAFFICKING SUSPECTS, IN DEFIANCE OF THE GOVERNMENT'S POSITION, HAS CREATED A POLITICAL VACUUM IN THE COUNTRY AND, BUSTAMANTE SAID, THE GOVERNMENT NO LONGER HAS A MONOPOLY OF POWER. THIS SITUATION, HE ADDED, CREATES DOUBTS ABOUT COMPLIANCE WITH THE AGREEMENT SIGNED IN NOVEMBER 1988 [AS RECEIVED] BY THE M-19 AND THE GOVERNMENT. IN LINE WITH THIS AGREEMENT, THE REBELS WOULD SURRENDER THEIR WEAPONS.

IN RECENT MONTHS THE VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT HAS MET ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS WITH REPRESENTATIVES OF THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT AND THE M-19 AND HAS PROPOSED THAT THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL RECEIVE THE ARMS OF THIS GUERRILLA ORGANIZATION WHICH WANTS TO JOIN COLOMBIA'S POLITICAL LIFE.

BUSTAMANTE SAID THAT THE SITUATION THAT HAS EMERGED HAS IMPOSED A DELAY IN THE SURRENDERING THE WEAPONS WHICH HAD BEEN SCHEDULED FOR 19 DECEMBER. HE DID NOT GIVE A NEW DATE FOR THIS ACTION, BUT HE DID NOT DISCARD EITHER THE POSSIBILITY THAT IT COULD BE IN JANUARY OF NEXT YEAR.

AN ACUTE POLITICAL CONFRONTATION EXPLODED IN COLOMBIA WHEN THE COLOMBIA CONGRESS DECIDED, AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT'S WILL, TO SUBMIT TO A REFERENDUM THE PRACTICE OF EXTRADITING DRUG TRAFFICKING SUSPECTS TO THE UNITED STATES SO THAT THEY MAY BE TRIED THERE.

BUSTAMANTE NOTED: THIS MAKES IT EVIDENT THAT MANY LEGISLATORS SUPPORT THE DEMANDS OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS. BUSTAMANTE ADMITTED, HOWEVER, THAT THESE EXTRADITIONS VIOLATE COLOMBIA'S CONSTITUTION.

ACCORDING TO THE M-19 LEADER, "THE ONLY WAY" OF OVERCOMING THE CURRENT POLITICAL CRISIS IS TO POSTPONE THE ELECTIONS SCHEDULED TO TAKE PLACE NEXT YEAR AND TO CONVOKE A CONSTITUENT NATIONAL ASSEMBLY AND A REFERENDUM TO DECIDE ON CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS.

THESE TWO POINTS FORM PART OF THE AGREEMENT SIGNED IN NOVEMBER 1988 [AS RECEIVED] BY THE M-19 AND THE GOVERNMENT.

BUSTAMANTE, WHO LEAVES TOMORROW FOR MEXICO CITY AND LONDON, CALLED ON THE COLOMBIAN GUERRILLA GROUPS TO SURRENDER THEIR WEAPONS IF THE GOVERNMENT CONVOKES A CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY.

DEV-MUC3-0998 (SRI)

SAN SALVADOR, 15 DEC 89 (TCS TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] YESTERDAY, MARIA JULIA HERNANADEZ, DIRECTOR OF THE ARCHBISHOPRIC LEGAL ASSITANCE OFFICE, MADE OFFICIAL STATEMENTS BEFORE THE COURT REGARDING THE MURDER OF THE UCA [CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY] PRIESTS.

IN RESPONSE TO A REQUEST ISSUED BY THE SALVADORAN 4TH CRIMINAL COURT, MARIA JULIA HERNANDEZ MADE STATEMENTS BEFORE THE COURT REGARDING THE MURDER OF SIX UCA JESUIT PRIESTS. THE PRIESTS WERE KILLED ON 16 NOVEMBER.

ACCORDING TO HERNANDEZ, HER STATEMENT WAS PERSONAL AND SHE LIMITED HERSELF TO REPORTING ON THE INVESTIGATIONS SHE CONDUCTED AT UCA AFTER THE MURDER. IN HER STATEMENT, HERNANDEZ SAID THAT SHE FOUND FOUR BULLET CASINGS INSIDE UCA. THE PROSECUTORS THEN ALLEGED THAT SHE HAD COMMITTED A CRIME BY PICKING UP EVIDENCE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [HERNANDEZ] I MADE PERSONAL STATEMENTS AS A WITNESS. I TOLD THEM WHAT I SAW AND HEARD AT THE SITE OF THE CRIME. THAT IS WHAT I DID. THE PROSECUTORS ASKED ME ABOUT THE EVIDENCE I HAD GATHERED AT THE SITE OF THE CRIME. I PICKED UP FOUR BULLET CASINGS. THE PROSECUTORS SAID I HAD COMMITTED A CRIME. THAT IS, THEREFORE, THE CRIME I COMMITTED. [END RECORDING]

ALTHOUGH SHE DID NOT PROVIDE SUFFICIENT FACTS TO FORMULATE AN OPINION, HERNANDEZ SAID THAT AS AN INSTITUTION, THE ARCHBISHOPRIC LEGAL ASSISTANCE OFFICE BELIEVES THAT THE EVIDENCE, WHICH SHE DID NOT MENTION, INDICATES THAT ARMED FORCES MEMBERS, WHO REMAIN UNIDENTIFIED, ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MURDER OF THE JESUITS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [HERNANDEZ] THE CHURCH ALREADY ISSUED ITS OFFICIAL DOCUMENT CLEARLY STATING THAT THERE ARE ARMED FORCES MEMBERS INVOLVED IN THE MURDER OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS.

[REPORTER] ON WHAT DOES THE CHURCH BASE THAT ASSERTION?

[HERNANDEZ] ON THE INVESTIGATIONS CONDUCTED BY THE ARCHBISHOPRIC LEGAL ASSISTANCE OFFICE.

[REPORTER] YES, BUT WHAT PROOF DOES THE CHURCH HAVE TO MAKE THAT ASSERTION?

[HERNANDEZ] ALL THAT IS CONTAINED IN THE CHURCH DOCUMENT THAT WAS ALREADY RELEASED. YOU CAN GET THAT DOCUMENT IF YOU WANT. [END RECORDING]

IN ADDITION, MARIA JULIA HERNANDEZ DENIED STATEMENTS MADE BY SOME MILITARY CHIEFS WHO SAID THAT WITNESS LUCIA CERNA, WHO IS OUT OF THE COUNTRY, WAS NEVER MANIPULATED OR PRESSURED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [HERNANDEZ] I WAS INTRODUCED TO MRS CERNA BY THE HEAD OF THE PROVINCIAL JESUIT ORDER ON MONDAY, 20 NOVEMBER. IN FRONT OF HIM, MRS CERNA MADE HER STATEMENT. AND SHE MADE THAT SAME STATEMENT BEFORE THE JUDGE AND THE PROSECUTORS AT THE SPANISH EMBASSY. THEY ARE WITNESSES TO THOSE STATEMENTS.

IN OTHER WORDS, SHE MADE THE STATEMENT AT THE SPANISH EMBASSY BEFORE I MET HER. I COULD NOT HAVE MANIPULATED HER AT ALL. [END RECORDING]

THE 4TH CRIMINAL COURT PROCEDURES REGARDING THIS CASE WILL CONTINUE IN ORDER TO TRY TO CLARIFY THE DEATH OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS INCLUDING IGNACIO ELLACURIA. CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY LEADER FIDEL CHAVEZ MENA AND SAN SALVADOR AUXILIARY BISHOP MSGR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ STILL HAVE TO MAKE THEIR STATEMENTS BEFORE THE COURT.

DEV-MUC3-0999 (SRI)

BOGOTA, 15 DEC 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE COLOMBIAN SENATE TODAY APPROVED A PARDON LAW THAT AUTHORIZES COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO TO "PARDON" OVER THE NEXT 6 MONTHS THE ARMED GROUPS THAT HAVE DEMONSTRATED THEIR DESIRE FOR PEACE.

THE MEASURE INITIALLY FAVORS THE 19-APRIL MOVEMENT [M-19], WHICH PROMISED THE GOVERNMENT TO SURRENDER ITS WEAPONS AND GIVE UP VIOLENCE IN ORDER TO BECOME A POLITICAL PARTY.

THE PARDON LAW IS ONE OF THE COMMITMENTS MADE BY THE GOVERNMENT IN THE AGREEMENT SIGNED WITH THE M-19 AS A RESULT OF THE NEGOTIATIONS THAT BEGAN LAST MARCH AND THAT SHOULD CONCLUDE WITH THE TOTAL DEMOBILIZATION OF THE M-19 AND THE DELIVERY OF ITS WEAPONS TO THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL.

ONCE ITS MAIN LEADERS, AGAINST WHOM THERE ARE SERIOUS CHARGES FOR AGGRESSION AGAINST THE STATE, ARE PARDONED, THE M-19 WILL BECOME A LEGAL, POLITICAL GROUP.

THE M-19 WAS SCHEDULED TO DELIVER ITS WEAPONS ON 19 DECEMBER, BUT THE ACTION WAS SUSPENDED UNTIL A DECISION IS MADE REGARDING THE AGREED UPON CREATION OF A "SPECIAL ELECTORAL DISTRICT, WHICH WOULD "GUARANTEE THE M-19" AN ACTIVE PRESENCE IN THE NATIONAL CONGRESS.

THAT MEASURE, WHICH IS PART OF THE "PACKAGE" OF CONSTITUTIONAL REFORMS PROPOSED BY THE GOVERNMENT, WAS SUSPENDED AT THE CONGRESS, WHICH COULD NOT REACH AN AGREEMENT ON IT BEFORE THE END OF ITS REGULAR SESSION.

THE REFORMS ALSO INCLUDED THE HOLDING OF A REFERENDUM TO CONSULT THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE ON THE EXTRADITION ISSUE. LEGAL EXTRADITION WAS ADOPTED THROUGH AN ADMINISTRATIVE MEASURE IN ORDER TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING. THE COLOMBIAN CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES' APPROVAL OF THE INCLUSION OF THE EXTRADITION ISSUE IN THE REFERENDUM CAUSED A POLITICAL CRISIS WITH THE RESIGNATION OF THE PRESIDENTS OF THE LIBERAL AND CONSERVATIVE PARTIES.

TODAY THE PLENUM OF THE COLOMBIAN CONGRESS DID NOT APPROVE THE HOLDING OF A PLEBISCITE IN SEPTEMBER 1990, IN WHICH THE VOTERS WOULD DECIDE TO EITHER APPROVE OR DISAPPROVE THE EXTRADITION OF DRUG TRAFFICKERS, BECAUSE OF THE RESIGNATIONS OF FORMER PRESIDENTS JULIO CESAR TURBAY AYALA AND MISAEL PASTRANA BORRERO, LEADERS OF THE LIBERAL AND CONSERVATIVE PARTIES, RESPECTIVELY.

TODAY, IN ADDITION TO THE DECISION MADE IN CONGRESS, WHICH ALONG WITH THE CHAMBER OF REPRESENTATIVES WILL CLOSE ITS REGULAR SESSION PERIOD ON 17 DECEMBER, GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, A.K.A THE MEXICAN, ONE OF THE MOST WANTED COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND THE NUMBER-TWO MAN IN THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, WAS KILLED DURING A CLASH WITH THE POLICE.

DEV-MUC3-1000 (SRI)

NO CITY (COLOMBIA), NO DATE -- [INTERVIEW WITH GENERAL CARLOS ARTURO CASADIEGO TORRADO, SECOND IN COMMAND OF THE COLOMBIAN POLICE BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] GENERAL, WHO CONDUCTED THE OPERATIONS -- THE ELITE FORCES, THE SPECIAL OPERATIONS GROUP [GOES] ...HOW MANY UNITS PARTICIPATED IN THIS ACTION?

[CASADIEGO] IT WAS A STRIKE THAT WAS CONDUCTED BY A SPECIALIZED GROUP, BUT THE WORK WAS ACCOMPLISHED BY ALL DEPARTMENTS OF THE NATIONAL POLICE IN GENERAL. THIS WORK WAS UNDERTAKEN BY ALL THOSE WHO ARE IN CHARGE OF FIGHTING DRUG TRAFFICKING.

[REPORTER] HOW WAS THE GOVERNMENT AND PRESIDENT INFORMED ABOUT THIS?

[CASADIEGO] JUST AS I AM REPORTING IT TO YOU. I TOLD THE PRESIDENT THAT WE HAD IDENTIFIED RODRIGUEZ GACHA, HIS SON, AND 15 OTHERS AFTER THE OPERATION WAS CARRIED OUT.

[REPORTER] WHAT DID THE PRESIDENT TELL YOU AFTER YOU GAVE HIM THE NEWS?

[CASADIEGO] IT WAS SIMPLY A NATIONAL POLICE REPORT TO THE PRESIDENT. LATER ON, WE WILL PROVIDE HIM WITH THE DETAILS AFTER THE INSPECTORS RETURN.

[REPORTER] WHAT ELSE DID YOU FIND IN THE AREA WHERE THE OPERATION WAS CARRIED OUT? DID YOU FIND WEAPONS? WERE SOME PEOPLE ABLE TO ESCAPE?

[CASADIEGO] NO, I HAVE NO MORE DETAILS. WE ARE JUST RECEIVING THE INFORMATION OVER THE RADIO, AND WE CANNOT GIVE DETAILS OVER THE RADIO.

[REPORTER] WHAT CAN WE EXPECT IN THE NEXT FEW MINUTES REGARDING THIS INFORMATION?

[CASADIEGO] WITHOUT DOUBT, THIS INFORMATION WILL BE ANNOUNCED WITH FULLER DETAILS BY THE DIRECTOR OF THE NATIONAL POLICE. THE GENERALS AND THE NATIONAL POLICE STAFF ARE MEETING HERE. WE ARE GOING TO CONDUCT A SERIES OF OPERATIONS TO CONSOLIDATE THE AREA AND TO DO WHAT THE LAW REQUIRES.

[REPORTER] WHAT ABOUT THE OTHER MAJOR DRUG CARTEL LEADERS?

[CASADIEGO] WE ARE DOING OUR JOB AND THIS IS PROOF THAT WE ARE DOING OUR JOB. I BELIEVE THAT COLOMBIA MUST CONGRATULATE THE NATIONAL POLICE FOR THE JOB THEY HAVE DONE.

[REPORTER] GENERAL, YOU HAVE SAID THE AREA IS BEING REINFORCED. DOES THIS MEAN MORE NATIONAL POLICE TROOPS ARE BEING DEPLOYED TO THE AREA? WILL THE OPERATIONS CONTINUE IN SEARCH OF OTHER DRUG CARTEL LEADERS?

[CASADIEGO] WE ARE SEARCHING AND BLOCKING OFF THE AREA. THAT IS WHAT WE ARE DOING.

[REPORTER] IS THAT THE REPORT THE NATIONAL POLICE HAVE RELEASED TO THE GOVERNMENT AND TO COLOMBIANS?

[CASADIEGO] THAT IS THE REPORT WE HAVE RELEASED TO THEM, AND WE ASK ALL CITIZENS TO CONTINUE COOPERATING WITH US. THEY CAN BE SURE THAT WE WILL TRY TO SIGNIFICANTLY CUT THE NUMBER OF CRIMES BEING COMMITTED.

DEV-MUC3-1001 (TRW)

BOGOTA, 15 DEC 89 -- [REPORT] [TEXT] GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ALIAS THE MEXICAN, ONE OF THE MOST DANGEROUS COLOMBIAN DRUG TRAFFICKERS WAS KILLED TODAY ALONG WITH HIS SON FREDDY AND A GROUP OF BODYGUARDS AT A FARM PRESUMABLY OWNED BY DRUG TRAFFICKER PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, LOCATED BETWEEN TOLU VAND COBENAS, IN SUCRE DEPARTMENT.

THE GOVERNOR OF SUCRE TOLD THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER THAT IT IS POSSIBLE THAT PABLO ESCOBAR IS IN THE SAME AREA WHICH HAS BEEN SURROUNDED AND ALL FLIGHTS HAVE BEEN RESTRICTED.

REGARDING THIS HISTORICAL NEWS, WHICH COULD BE THE MOST IMPORTANT OF THE DECADE ON THE SUBJECT OF PUBLIC ORDER AND THE GOVERNMENT'S STRUGGLE AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS, HERE IS A REPORT ON A NEWS CONFERENCE ATTENDED BY VIOLA CONGOTE:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GOMEZ PADILLA, IN PROGRESS] ...GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ALIAS THE MEXICAN, BETWEEN COBENAS AND TOLU, SPECIFICALLY AT THE TOLUGAS FARM. THERE WAS A CLASH IN WHICH THE POLICE KILLED THIS MAN, HIS SON, AND FIVE INDIVIDUALS WHO WERE ACCOMPANYING HIM.

[REPORTER] ARE YOU ABSOLUTELY SURE THAT IT WAS GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA?

[GOMEZ PADILLA] HE HAS BEEN FULLY IDENTIFIED AS GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA, ALIAS THE MEXICAN.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[GOMEZ PADILLA] FOR A LONG TIME, THE NATIONAL POLICE IN COLLABORATION WITH THE DAS AND OTHER STATE INTELLIGENCE AGENCIES HAVE BEEN GATHERING INTELLIGENCE DATA WHICH TODAY HAS YIELDED POSITIVE RESULTS.

[REPORTER] HOW MANY POLICEMEN PARTICIPATED IN THE OPERATION?

[GOMEZ PADILLA] SEVERAL SPECIALIZED UNITS OF THE NATIONAL POLICE PARTICIPATED IN THE OPERATION ALONG WITH THE POLICE IN CORDOBA AND SUCRE DEPARTMENTS.

[REPORTER] ARE THERE ANY POLICEMEN WOUNDED?

[GOMEZ PADILLA] WE DO NOT KNOW OF ANY POLICEMEN BEING WOUNDED.

[REPORTER] HOW LONG DID THE CLASH BETWEEN THE ARMY AND THE BODYGUARDS OR BETWEEN THE POLICE AND THE DEAD KILLED LAST?

[GOMEZ PADILLA] RIGHT NOW WE DO NOT KNOW EXACTLY HOW LONG THE CLASH WAS.

[REPORTER] ARE THE CORPSES STILL AT THE SITE OF THE INCIDENT OR WILL THEY BE IMMEDIATELY TRANSFERRED TO BOGOTA?

[GOMEZ PADILLA] WE HAVE SENT CRIMINAL ARRAIGNMENT JUDGES THERE, AS WELL AS NATIONAL POLICE INSPECTORS. THE JUDGES WILL DECIDE WHAT TO DO.

[REPORTER] HOW WAS IT CONFIRMED THAT IT WAS ACTUALLY GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA?

[GOMEZ PADILLA] BASED ON MEANS WE HAVE OF CONFIRMING HIS IDENTITY. [END RECORDING] [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1002 (TRW)

BOGOTA, 16 DEC 89 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] ALL PRIVATE AIRCRAFT AND FLIGHTS IN THE COUNTRY HAVE BEEN PLACED UNDER MILITARY CONTROL AND SUBJECT TO STRICT RESTRICTIONS BY THE COLOMBIAN AIR FORCE [FAC]. NO PRIVATE AIRCRAFT WILL BE ALLOWED TO LEAVE ANY AIRPORT TERMINAL OR FLY IN COLOMBIA'S AIR SPACE WITHOUT THE PERMISSION OF THE MILITARY AUTHORITIES. THE AIRCRAFT WILL BE SUBJECT TO THE REGULATIONS CONCERNING THE VIOLATION OF COLOMBIA'S AIR SPACE.

PERMITS FOR PRIVATE AIRCRAFT ARE NOW UNDER THE CONTROL OF MILITARY AUTHORITIES, WHICH ARE EXERTING TOTAL CONTROL OF THE AIR SPACE. THE NORTHERN AIR FORCE COMMAND BASE, LOCATED IN BARRANQUILLA, HAS BEEN REINFORCED WITH PLANES SENT FROM PALANQUERO AIR FORCE BASE TO CONTROL COLOMBIA'S CARIBBEAN COAST. KFIR, MIRAGES, M-5S, COMBAT PLANES, AND T-33 AND T-41 RECONAISSANCE AIRCRAFT ARE CONSTANTLY PATROLLING COLOMBIAN AIR SPACE.

MEANWHILE, ALL COMMERCIAL AND PRIVATE AIR OPERATIONS IN SUCRE DEPARTMENT AND THE COLOMBIAN CARIBBEAN COAST HAVE BEEN PLACED UNDER MILITARY CONTROL WITH HEAVY RESTRICTIONS. THE FAC ASSUMED CONTROL WITH COMBAT AND RECONAISSANCE AIRCRAFT. THE COMMERCIAL AIRPORTS' CONTROL TOWERS HAVE WARNED THAT THE FAC HAS THE AIR SPACE UNDER CONTROL AND ANY AIRPLANE FLYING OVER THE ZONE MAY BE SHOT DOWN IF IT IS DECLARED A MILITARY ZONE. PRIVATE AIRPLANES MUST HAVE THEIR FLIGHT PLANS CHECKED WITH THE MILITARY AUTHORITIES.

DEV-MUC3-1003 (TRW)

SANTIAGO, 16 DEC 89 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] CHILEAN TERRORISTS MIGHT BE INVOLVED IN THE KIDNAPPING OF IMPORTANT BRAZILIAN BUSINESSMAN. THIS MORNING AN ANTIKIDNAPPING SQUAD OF THE POLICE OF SAO PAULO, BRAZIL, LOCATED BUSINESSMAN ABILIO DINIZ, DIRECTOR AND MAIN SHAREHOLDER OF ONE OF THE LARGEST ECONOMIC GROUPS IN BRAZIL. ABILIO DINIZ IS IN THE HANDS OF A GROUP PRESUMED TO BE CHILEAN TERRORISTS.

FIVE CHILEANS WERE ARRESTED LAST NIGHT. ANOTHER FOUR ARE HOLDING THE BRAZILIAN MULTIMILLIONAIRE IN A HOUSE IN THE SAO PAULO NEIGHBORHOOD OF JABAQUARA. THE KIPNAPPERS, WHO ARE SAID TO BE MEMBERS OF A GROUP CALLED CHILE'S INDEPENDENCE MOVEMENT, DEMANDED AN UNSPECIFIED SUM IN DOLLARS FOR THEIR GUERRILLA ACTIVITIES, AN ARMORED VEHICLE. WEAPONS, AND A PLANE TO GET AWAY.

THE WEALTHY BUSINESSMAN WAS KIDNAPPED LAST MONDAY IN SAO PAULO BY A GROUP THAT DROVE UP IN AMBULANCE AS DINIZ WAS JOGGING IN A CITY PARK. THE LOCAL POLICE HONORED A REQUEST FROM THE BUSINESSMAN'S FAMILY TO KEEP SILENT TO PROTECT THE VICTIM. POLICE SOURCES EXPRESSED THE SUSPICION THAT THE KIDNAPPERS OF ABILIO DINIZ ARE FROM THE SAME GROUP THAT KIDNAPPED THE PUBLISHER LUIZ SALLES AND RELEASED HIM AFTER A RANSOM OF $2.5 MILLION WAS PAID.

DEV-MUC3-1005 (TRW)

BOGOTA, 16 DEC 89 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [PATRICIA JARAMILLO] [TEXT] AN ELITE NATIONAL POLICE FORCE, SPECIALLY TRAINED FOR THIS TYPE OF COMMANDO ACTION, CARRIED OUT THE OPERATION IN WHICH GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA WAS KILLED. THE SPECIAL ARMED CORPS [CUERPO ESPECIAL ARMADO], CEA, WAS ESTABLISHED BY DECREE NO 814 OF 19 APRIL 1989. THIS CORPS IS MORE COMMONLY KNOWN AS THE ELITE FORCE.

THE GROUP WAS INITIALLY FORMED BY 250 QUALIFIED POLICEMEN AND WAS GIVEN RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DEATH SQUADS, BANDS OF PAID ASSASSINS, AND SELF-DEFENSE OR PRIVATE VIGILANTE GROUPS THAT ARE SOMETIMES CALLED PARAMILITARY GROUPS. THE ANTI-TERRORIST FORCE MEMBERS WERE TRAINED AT THE POLICE NON-COMMISSIONED OFFICERS ACADEMY LOCATED IN A MOUNTAINOUS REGION IN THE OUTSKIRTS OF BOGOTA FOR 3 MONTHS. LATER ON, THESE MEN WERE SENT TO DIFFERENT AREAS WITHIN THE COUNTRY, ESPECIALLY IN ANTIOQUIA.

THE ELITE FORCES STARTED TO WORK ON 2 MAY, AND RESULTS APPEARED VERY SOON AFTER THAT. THE CEA UNDERTOOK AN OPERATION NAMED RAINBOW [ARCOIRIS] AND DISMANTLED 10 COCAINE PROCESSING LABORATORIES IN THE MID-MAGADALENA REGION IN LESS THAN 8 DAYS. GENERAL BENJAMIN FRANKLIN LOST HIS LIFE DURING THIS OPERATION. LATER ON THEY ALSO DISMANTLED AN ASSASSIN TRAINING SCHOOL AT META, DESTROYED CLANDESTINE AIRPORTS, AND ABORTED A TERRORIST PLAN IN CARTAGENA THAT INCLUDED DYNAMITING ITS NAVAL BASE, MAIN INDUSTRIES, AND CAIS [IMMEDIATE ATTENTION CENTERS]. AFTER LUIS CARLOS GALAN WAS KILLED, THE ELITE FORCES HELD TWO BIG OPERATIONS IN YACOPI, THE RIO NEGRO REGION WHERE RODRIGUEZ GACHA ESTABLISHED SELF-DEFENSE GROUPS. THE OPERATIVES HAD THE OBJECTIVE OF CAPTURING RODRIGUEZ GACHA BUT HE MANAGED TO ESCAPE. THE SPECIAL FORCES ALSO CONDUCTED AN OPERATION AT COCORNAC IN AN ATTEMPT TO CAPTURE PABLO ESCOBAR BUT HE ALSO MANAGED TO ESCAPE. THE BLOW DELIVERED BY THE ELITE FORCES YESTERDAY, IN WHICH THE MEXICANO [GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA] FELL, WAS ACCOMPLISHED WITH HARD INTELLIGENCE, INVESTIGATION, AND ESPIONAGE WORK. HERE IS WHAT POLICE DIRECTOR MAJOR GENERAL MIGUEL GOMEZ HAS TO SAY:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GOMEZ] WE ARE VERY SATISFIED TO HAVE ACCOMPLISHED OUR MISSION. OUR INSTITUTION HAS RESPONDED TO THE DEMANDS OF THE COUNTRY. WE ARE HELPING COLOMBIA RID ITSELF OF ALL FORMS OF VIOLENCE GENERATED BY THESE CRIMINALS. [END RECORDING]

THE ELITE FORCES WILL CONTINUE ITS WORK WITH 1,000 MEN, 17 HELICOPTERS, THE ADVISE OF BRITISH AND ITALIAN EXPERTS, AND THE UNITED STATES' ECONOMIC AND LOGISTICAL AID.

DEV-MUC3-1009 (TRW)

CLANDESTINE, 18 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN)] [TEXT] THIS IS A COMMUNIQUE FROM THE GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FMLN TO ALL SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND TO OUR HEROIC LEADERS AND FIGHTERS:

ON 11 NOVEMBER, ALL OF OUR FORCES BEGAN THE MAJOR NATIONAL OFFENSIVE THAT GAVE A STRATEGIC TURN TO THE WAR. OUR FIGHTERS HAVE CARRIED OUT COUNTLESS HEROIC AND DARING ACTS SINCE THEM. NEITHER THE CONCENTRATION OF THE ELITE BATTALIONS IN SAN SALVADOR NOR THE MILLIONS OF DOLLARS OF U.S. MILITARY ASSISTANCE OR FULL RANGE OF U.S. TECHNOLOGY AND EXPERIENCE COULD PREVENT OUR FORCES FROM ENTERING AND OCCUPYING EXTENSIVE URBAN AREAS AND ORGANIZING STRATEGIC HARASSMENT OF THE CITY.

OUR HEROIC FIGHTERS ASSAULTED THE COUNTRY'S FIVE MAJOR VITAL CENTERS -- SAN SALVADOR, SAN MIGUEL, SANTA ANA, USULUTAN, AND ZACATECOLUCA. BEGINNING ON THE 11TH, THE WAR THEATRE IRREVERSIBLY MOVED FROM THE COUNTRYSIDE TO THE MAIN CITIES. TO POSTPONE IMMINENT COLLAPSE AND TO STOP A PEOPLE'S UPRISING, THE FATALLY WOUNDED MILITARY LEADERSHIP AND THE FASCIST GOVERNMENT ORDERED THAT THE LOW-INCOME NEIGHBORHOODS BE BOMBARDED. THEY DID NOT CARE HOW MANY CIVILIAN LIVES IT WOULD COST. WITH ALL OF ITS ELITE AND REGULAR BATTALIONS, THE ENEMY ARMY WAS REDUCED TO THE DEFENSIVE AND TO GUARDING THE CITIES. EXTENSIVE AREAS AROUND THE REST OF THE COUNTRY ARE LIBERATED TERRITORY.

THE WAR IS NOW WHERE IT CAN BE DEFINED -- IN THE VITAL CENTERS. THERE IS NO WAY THE OLIGARCHS' EXCLUSIVE ECONOMIC PROGRAM CAN TAKE OFF AND THE FASCIST GOVERNMENT OF ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE], WITH ITS GENOCIDAL BRUTALITY UNMASKED, IS INTERNATIONALLY ISOLATED AND HATED BY THE PEOPLE FOR ITS CRIMES.

THIS GREAT EFFORT OF AUDACITY AND HEROISM THAT BEGAN ON 11 NOVEMBER HAS PLACED THE MILITARY LEADERSHIP AND THE CRISTIANI ADMINISTRATION IN THEIR MOST CRITICAL POSITION OF THE 9 YEARS OF WAR. THUS FAR, DURING THIS EXTRAORDINARY EFFORT -- WHICH HAS GIVEN TO EL SALVADOR AND THE WORLD REAL HOPE FOR DEMOCRACY AND PEACE FOR OUR COUNTRY -- 401 OF THE MOST GENEROUS AND BRAVE SONS OF OUR HOMELAND HAVE FALLEN IN COMBAT. THIS LIST IS HEADED BY OUR DEAR AND UNFORGETTABLE COMRADE COMMANDER DIMAS RODRIGUEZ, TO WHOM WE OWE DECISIVE CONTRIBUTIONS IN THE CONDUCT OF OUR STRUGGLE TOWARD VICTORY.

THE FOLLOWING MILITARY COMMANDERS WHO FELL IN COMBAT ALSO MADE A CONTRIBUTION: JORGE ORLANDO SANDOVAL CERVELLON, COMMANDER OSCAR; JEHOVA VASQUEZ, COMMANDER CIRILO; OVIDIO LOPEZ, COMMANDER ORLANDO MORALES; COMMANDER MISAEL GALLARDO; COMMANDER NICOLAS ALBERTO SARAVIA, WILBERT; COMMANDER RICARDO MIRANDA, ESTEBAN RUIZ; AND THE COMMANDER ODIR POLITICAL DIRECTORS [RESPONSABLES] -- JOSE SANTOS YANEZ, PEPE; AND MILAGRO ALVARADO, JUDY.

WE RELEASE THE NAMES OF THESE HEROES IN ORDER FOR THE PEOPLE TO REGISTER THEM ETERNALLY IN THE HIGHEST PLACE IN OUR HISTORY. THEIR DEVOTION MULTIPLIES AND STRENGTHENS THE PEOPLE'S POWER. HUNDREDS OF NEW FIGHTERS ALREADY HAVE THE WEAPONS AND ENTHUSIASM OF THOSE WHO HAVE FALLEN. THEY ARE AT THE FRONTLINE OF THIS POWER OF THE FUTURE WHICH IS BUILDING, BEFORE THE WORLD'S ADMIRING EYES, DEMOCRATIC AND JUST EL SALVADOR.

ALONGSIDE OUR HEROES, THOUSANDS OF OTHER SALVADORANS HAVE FERTILIZED THE PATH TO PEACE WITH THEIR BLOOD, VICTIMS OF THE FATALLY WOUNDED BEAST -- THE FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION) UNION MEMBERS, THE JESUIT PRIESTS, THE ANONYMOUS PEOPLE MASSACRED IN THE GENOCIDAL BOMBINGS.

THE REALIZATION OF A GENUINE AND DEFINITIVE CHANGE IS ENSURED BY THE GREAT POWER OF OUR REVOLUTIONARY ARMY, OF ALL OF OUR PEOPLE, AND OF WORLD SOLIDARITY. THOSE WHO FELL TAUGHT TO US THE COURAGE AND DETERMINATION TO FINISH THIS EXTRAORDINARY EFFORT, TO CONQUER WHAT WE THINK THE PEOPLE JUSTLY DESERVE -- DEMOCRACY, PROGRESS, AND PEACE.

ETERNAL GLORY TO THE HEROES AND MARTYRS, BUILDERS OF DEMOCRACY AND PEACE. THE OFFENSIVE CONTINUES, VICTORY IS NEAR.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND; COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS, EDUARDO SANCHO, FRANCISCO JOVEL, AND SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL.

[DATED] 18 DECEMBER 1989, EL SALVADOR

DEV-MUC3-1010 (TRW)

CLANDESTINE, 12 DEC 89 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH LEO CABRAL, FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) COMMANDER, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] THE FIRST QUESTION WE ASK COMRADE LEO CABRAL IS: WHAT ARE THE RESULTS OF THE OFFENSIVE AFTER 1 MONTH?

[CABRAL] TODAY, 11 DECEMBER, AFTER 1 MONTH OF A GLORIOUS AND VICTORIOUS OFFENSIVE, WE HAVE SOME THOUGHTS REGARDING THIS LATEST FIGHT. WE WANT TO STRESS THAT ALL OUR OFFENSIVES HAVE CENTERED AROUND THE MAIN CITIES IN OUR COUNTRY. ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT AND SIGNIFICANT ACHIEVEMENTS OF THIS STRUGGLE BY THE PEOPLE AND THE FMLN IS HAVING MAINTAINED THE BESIEGEMENT ON THE MOST IMPORTANT POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC POINTS, MOST ESPECIALLY ON THE COUNTRY'S CAPITAL. THERE HAS BEEN GREAT PRESSURE IN THE CASE OF SAN SALVADOR, AND THE FMLN HAS FORCED THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, COLONEL PONCE, AND THE FASCIST HIGH COMMAND TO CHANGE THEIR STRATEGIC TACTICS THREE TIMES.

YOU WILL RECALL THAT THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF FIRST TRIED TO DISLODGE THE FMLN FORCES THAT HAD ENTERED SINCE THE EVENING OF 11 NOVEMBER. WHEN THE FIRST PUPPET ARMY STRATEGIC DEFENSE TACTIC FAILED, THEY THEN TRIED TO ISOLATE THE FMLN FORCES FROM ONE ANOTHER AND ANNIHILATE THEM ONE BY ONE. FOR THIS, THEY CONCENTRATED SPECIAL FORCES, ESPECIALLY USING ELITE BATTALIONS, IN A SIEGE MODALITY FOR ANNIHILATION. THIS ALSO FAILED. FACED WITH THE SECOND FAILURE OF THEIR SPECIAL TACTICS TO END THE OFFENSIVE IN A FEW DAYS, AS CRISTIANI AND THE HIGH MILITARY COMMAND HAD SAID, THEY MOVED A GREAT NUMBER OF OPERATIONAL FORCES FROM THE COUNTRY'S INTERIOR, SUCH AS THE ELITE BATTALIONS, TO SET UP AN EXTENSIVE SIEGE TO DEFEND THE CAPITAL CITY AND PREVENT OUR FORCES FROM ENTERING IT. AS ALL OUR PEOPLE HAVE BEEN ABLE TO SEE -- AND INTERNATIONAL PUBLIC OPINION HAS ALSO BEEN ABLE TO VERIFY THIS THROUGH A GREAT AMOUNT OF INFORMATION FLOWING THROUGH INTERNATIONAL REPORTERS -- THAT SIEGE TO KEEP OUT THE FMLN HAS ALSO FAILED. THIS MEANS MORE VICTORIES AND SUCCESSES, SUCH AS INCURSIONS INTO THE ESCALON NEIGHBORHOOD AND THE SOUTHERN AREA OF ANTIGUO CUSCATLAN, AND TWO IMPORTANT ATTACKS ON THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF.

RIGHT NOW WE SEE THAT THE PUPPET ARMY'S SPECIAL CITY OPERATION IS THEIR THIRD AND LAST PLAN. THEY HAVE FORMED FOUR COMMANDS TO CONTROL THE CITY, WHICH WILL ALSO BE DEFEATED BY OUR FMLN MILITARY FORCES. WE ALSO MUST ADD TO THIS LIST OF ACHIEVEMENTS THAT THE GREAT CONCENTRATION OF ENEMY ARMY OPERATIONAL FORCES IN THE CAPITAL HAS CAUSED A GREAT NATIONAL IMBALANCE IN FORCES. THIS MEANS THAT EXTENSIVE AREAS OF THE COUNTRY ARE WITHOUT THE PROTECTION OF THE PUPPET TROOPS. WE HAVE TAKEN ADVANTAGE OF THIS AND HAVE WORKED ON ORGANIZING THE PEOPLE AND RAISING A PEOPLE'S POWER, AN ALTERNATIVE TO LOCAL REACTIONARY POWER.

WE ALSO RECORD AS A SUCCESSFUL OFFENSIVE DURING THIS FIRST MONTH THE FACT THAT OUR ENEMY'S INTELLIGENCE WORK HAS BEEN COMPLETELY SMASHED. THE SEARCHES, WHICH HAVE BEEN ENTRUSTED IN AN IMPROVISED MANNER TO MILITARY TROOPS CONCENTRATED IN THE CITIES, ESPECIALLY THE REPRESSIVE CORPS, HAVE ATTEMPTED TO RESTORE ALL THE INTELLIGENCE DATA BANKS TO BE ABLE TO TRY AND DESTROY THE PEOPLE'S STRUGGLE. WE MUST ALSO RECORD AS ONE OF THE SUCCESSES OF OUR GENERAL OFFENSIVE DURING THIS FIRST MONTH THE FACT THAT THE PUPPET ARMY WAS FORCED TO ABORT ANOTHER PLAN. EVEN THOUGH THERE WERE SOME BLOODY EVENTS, SUCH AS THE MURDER OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS, ALONG WITH A GREAT AMOUNT OF KIDNAPPINGS AND MISSING PEOPLE AND ARRESTS OF MEMBERS OR LEADERS OF GRASSROOT PEOPLE'S MOVEMENTS, WE FEEL THAT THE ARMY AND REPRESSIVE CORPS ARE INCAPABLE OF ATTENDING TO THE FMLN OFFENSIVE AND THE BESIEGEMENT AT THE SAME TIME THAT THEY ARE TRYING TO CARRY OUT THEIR ANNIHILATION OF THE PEOPLE'S MOVEMENT. SO THIS IS ANOTHER SUCCESS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1013 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 DEC 89 (TCS TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] A FEW MONTHS AGO, IT WAS SPECULATED THAT CHANGES OF COMMAND IN CERTAIN ARMED FORCES KEY POSTS WOULD TAKE PLACE LATE IN 1989.

COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, JOINT CHIEF OF STAFF, DISREGARDED THIS POSSIBILITY AND SAID THAT THE SITUATION OF VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY, PARTICULARLY SINCE THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] OFFENSIVE, REQUIRES, MORE THAN EVER, THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE MILITARILY STABLE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] I THINK THE SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY DEMANDS MILITARY STABILITY. CHANGES COULD PROVOKE SOME UNREST. WE THINK NO SIGNIFICANT CHANGES IN THE MILITARY COMMAND SHOULD BE MADE AT PRESENT BECAUSE OF THE CURRENT SITUATION. SHOULD ANY CHANGES BE MADE, IT WOULD BE FOR MAJOR REASONS IN THE SERVICE. NO HIGH-LEVEL CHANGES HAVE BEEN ANTICIPATED, HOWEVER. [END RECORDING]

REFERRING TO THE REBELS' ACTIVITIES, COL PONCE SAID THE ARMED ACTIONS INITIATED, PARTICULARLY IN SAN SALVADOR ON 11 NOVEMBER, HAVE ENDED WITH UNFAVORABLE RESULTS FOR THE GUERRILLAS. HE ADVISED, HOWEVER, THAT THE GUERRILLAS WILL CONTINUE TO SABOTAGE THE COUNTRY'S ECONOMY AND PERPETRATE TERRORIST ACTIONS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] I CAN TELL YOU THAT THE FMLN HAS FAILED, MILITARILY SPEAKING. THE FMLN'S FAMOUS ALL - THE - WAY OFFENSIVE HAS ENDED IN TREMENDOUS FAILURE, DETERMINED BY THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. WE CAN ANTICIPATE THAT THE FMLN WILL CONTINUE ITS SABOTAGING ACTIONS AND TERRORISM WHICH COULD DESTROY STORES IN SAN SALVADOR, AS WELL AS POSTS AND PYLONS ON HIGHWAYS. THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE CAN REST ASSURED, HOWEVER, THAT AN OFFENSIVE ACTION BY THE FMLN AT PRESENT CAN BE DISREGARDED. [END RECORDING]

REGARDING THE CHRISTMAS AND NEW YEAR FESTIVITIES, WHICH HAVE BEEN MARRED BY THE WAVE OF VIOLENCE, MANY PEOPLE HAVE WONDERED WHETHER THE 2300 - TO - 0500 CURFEW IS STILL IN FORCE. PONCE SAID THE POSSIBILITY OF LIFTING THE CURFEW AT LEAST ON 24 AND 31 DECEMBER IS BEING CONSIDERED SO THAT THE SALVADORAN FAMILIES CAN ENJOY THESE FESTIVITIES. HE ADDED THAT SUCH A MEASURE, HOWEVER, WILL DEPEND ON THE FMLN'S STANCE. FINALLY, PONCE REPORTED THAT THE FMLN MACHINEGUNNED A BUILDING WITH COFFEE HARVESTERS IN SANTA ANA AND MAIMED TWO PEOPLE SIMPLY BECAUSE THEY REFUSED TO STOP HARVESTING COFFEE.

DEV-MUC3-1016 (TRW)

LIMA, 20 DEC 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [TEXT] THE PANAMANIAN CHARGE D'AFFAIRS IN OUR COUNTRY, JAIME CERDA, DID NOT [AS HEARD] MAKE AN URGENT CALL TO ALL LATIN AMERICAN PEOPLE TO REPUDIATE THE U.S. INTERVENTION IN HIS COUNTRY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CERDA] WE DEFINITELY CALL ON THE WORLD, ON THE CONSCIENCE OF THE WORLD, TO END THIS SITUATION.

[REPORTER] IT HAS BEEN SAID THAT THE TORRIJOS-CARTER TREATY COULD BE ONE OF THE MAIN REASONS FOR THIS CONFLICT THAT HAS BEEN BREWING FOR SOME TIME BETWEEN THE U.S. GOVERNMENT AND THE PANAMANIAN STATE. DO YOU BELIEVE, AS A CITIZEN, THAT THERE IS A SHORT-TERM SOLUTION TO THIS CONFLICT?

[CERDA] THAT WOULD DEPEND ON THE GOOD FAITH OF THE U.S. GOVERNMENT TOWARD PANAMANIANS. I BELIEVE THAT NO PEOPLE, NO MAN, INDEPENDENTLY OF WHAT HE MAY THINK OF THE GOVERNMENTS, CAN AGREE WITH THIS TYPE OF INTERVENTION BY THE WORLD'S MOST POWERFUL POWER DIRECTED AGAINST A SMALL PEOPLE WHO DO NOT HAVE THE RESOURCES TO CONFRONT THE MILITARY MIGHT OF THE UNITED STATES. ACCORDING TO INTERNATIONAL PRESS AGENCIES REPORTS, CIVILIANS ARE BEING KILLED THERE ARE MANY MILITIAMEN WHO ARE FIGHTING THE U.S. SOLDIERS. I REITERATE MY CALL TO THE PEOPLE OF THE WORLD, ON THE LATIN AMERICAN PEOPLE, ON OUR PERUVIAN BROTHERS TO DECLARE THEMSELVES AGAINST THIS ACT OF AGGRESSION THAT CANNOT BE TOLERATED BY FREE NATIONS.

[REPORTER] IN PANAMA, WHERE ARE THE CLASHES TAKING PLACE?

[CERDA] IN PANAMA CITY. INTERNATIONAL PRESS DISPATCHES HAVE MENTIONED THIS.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS THE SOCIAL COST SO FAR? IS THERE SOME ESTIMATE?

[CERDA] WELL, INTERNATIONAL DISPATCHES SPEAK OF 50 DEAD, MOSTLY CIVILIANS. FROM THE SANTO TOMAS HOSPITAL, WHICH IS A PUBLIC HEALTH HOSPITAL, THERE HAS BEEN NO INFORMATION ON THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE THAT BEEN GIVEN MEDICAL ATTENTION, NOR FROM OTHER HOSPITALS.

DEV-MUC3-1017 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 DEC 89 (AFP) -- [TEXT] MILITARY AND CIVILIAN SOURCES HAVE CONFIRMED THAT HEAVY FIGHTING BETWEEN REBELS AND SOLDIERS BROKE OUT THIS EVENING IN CIUDAD MERLIOT, AN AREA WEST OF SAN SALVADOR.

THE FIGHTING BEGAN AT 1830 (0030 GMT) WHEN FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] COLUMNS ENTERED CIUDAD MERLIOT, A MIDDLE CLASS NEIGHBORHOOD LOCATED APPROXIMATELY 12 KM SOUTHWEST OF SAN SALVADOR.

ACCORDING TO POLICE SOURCES, THE FIGHTING WAS REPORTED IN THE AREAS OF JARDINES DE LA HACIENDA AND JARDINES DEL VOLCAN, WHERE THE GOVERNMENT TROOPS ARE USING AIR SUPPORT. THE HELICOPTERS FIRED ROCKETS AGAINST SUPPOSED REBEL POSITIONS.

THE SHOOTING COULD BE HEARD IN DOWNTOWN SAN SALVADOR. MEANWHILE, RESIDENTS OF THE AFFECTED AREAS TOLD LOCAL RADIO STATIONS THAT THERE WAS HEAVY SHOOTING.

THE ARMED ACTIONS ARE TAKING PLACE WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF AN OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE FMLN IN MID- NOVEMBER. ACCORDING TO ARMY SOURCES, THE OFFENSIVE HAS RESULTED IN 5,000 CASUALTIES, CIVILIAN CASUALTIES NOT INCLUDED.

DEV-MUC3-1018 (TRW)

LIMA, 20 DEC 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [EXCERPTS] IN BARRANCA DISTRICT THIS AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA REITERATED HIS REJECTION AND THE PERUVIAN PEOPLE'S CONDEMNATION OF THE INVASION OF PANAMA BY U.S. TROOPS.

THE HEAD OF STATE DESCRIBED THIS ACTION AS AN ACT OF ROBBERY AND PIRACY. HE NOTED THAT THIS REPRESENTS AGGRESSION NOT ONLY AGAINST THE PANAMANIAN PEOPLE BUT AGAINST THE SOVEREIGNTY OF ALL LATIN AMERICA.

GARCIA SAID THAT THIS INSULT AND OUTRAGE AGAINST SOVEREIGN PEOPLES CANNOT OCCUR ON THE THRESHOLD OF THE 21ST CENTURY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GARCIA] A DRAMATIC EVENT IS SHAKING ALL LATIN AMERICA AT THIS MOMENT. BEGINNING EARLY THIS MORNING, THE INVADING FORCES OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA HAVE PENETRATED AND INTERVENED IN LATIN AMERICAN TERRITORY IN PANAMA.

THIS IS WHY I AM LATE, BECAUSE SINCE EARLY THIS MORNING WE HAVE BEEN WITNESSING AN ASTONISHING ACT OF IMPERIALIST ROBBERY AND PIRACY TARNISHING THE SACRED SOIL OF PANAMA AND LATIN AMERICA.

WE ARE JUST LATIN AMERICANS. IF A LATIN AMERICAN IS OFFENDED AND ATTACKED, THEN WE ARE ALL OFFENDED AND ATTACKED. AND YOU, THE HUANCA PEASANTS, MUST KNOW THAT IN PANAMA IN THE [WORDS INDISTINCT] THERE ARE ALSO PEASANTS WHO ARE NOW THE VICTIMS OF THE U.S. INVASION. AND WE MUST STAND UP TO RESCUE [WORDS DROWNED OUT CHEERS AND APPLAUSE].

SEVENTY YEARS ELAPSED BEFORE GENERAL OMAR TORRIJOS MANAGED TO SIGN AN AGREEMENT WITH PRESIDENT JIMMY CARTER FOR THE PANAMA CANAL TO BE TURNED OVER TO PANAMANIAN SOVEREIGNTY. SINCE THAT 1977 TREATY, HOWEVER, MANY THINGS HAVE HAPPENED AND EFFORTS HAVE ALWAYS BEEN MADE TO PREVENT THE CANAL FROM BEING RETURNED TO LATIN AMERICA.

THEY DO NOT WANT TO LEAVE THE CANAL ZONE WHERE THEY HAVE THEIR TROOPS, THEIR AIRPLANES, AND THEIR BOMBS TO THREATEN THE CONTINENT AND TELL ALL OF US THAT IF WE DO NOT BEHAVE WELL THEY CAN INVADE US AT ANY MOMENT.

I CANNOT ACCEPT WHAT WAS DONE THIS MORNING WHEN THE NEW PRESIDENT OF PANAMA WAS SWORN IN ON A U.S. BASE IN THE CANAL ZONE. THE AMERICANS DO NOT HAVE THE RIGHT TO SAY WHO IS GOING TO GOVERN IN LATIN AMERICA; ONLY THE LATIN AMERICAN PEOPLE HAVE THE RIGHT TO DECIDE THEIR DESTINY. APPLAUSE AND CHEERS

IN THE LAST 14 HOURS, 24,000 MEN AND MORE THAN 100 COMBAT VEHICLES HAVE ENTERED PANAMA CITY, AND THE HELICOPTERS HAVE ATTACKED MILITARY INSTALLATIONS ADJACENT TO THE CIVILIAN ZONES. WE HAVE BEEN TOLD THAT HUNDREDS HAVE BEEN KILLED. AS PRESIDENT OF PERU, AS A CHIEF OF STATE, AND AS A REPRESENTATIVE OF THE POOR PEASANTS I CANNOT SILENCE OUR PROTEST. I CANNOT SILENCE OUR CONDEMNATION.

I CALL ON THE LATIN AMERICAN PEOPLE; I CALL ON THE YOUTH OF LATIN AMERICA IN THE FACE OF THIS IMPERIALISTIC ATTACK. WE CANNOT REMAIN SILENT. WE MAY BE POOR, WE MAY HAVE PROBLEMS, BUT WE ARE DIGNIFIED PEOPLE, WE ARE FREE, WE ARE SOVEREIGN [DROWNED OUT BY APPLAUSE]. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1022 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 20 DEC 89 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHIEF OF THE SALVADORAN JOINT STAFF, HAS STATED THAT THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] DOES NOT HAVE THE SLIGHTEST CHANCE TO LAUNCH A NEW OFFENSIVE BECAUSE THE RANK-AND-FILE OF THIS ORGANIZATION ARE TOTALLY DEMORALIZED DUE TO THE HEAVY CASUALTIES THAT THEY HAVE TAKEN. HE ADDED THAT THESE CASUALTIES INCLUDE NINE "COMMANDERS."

COL PONCE ADDED: "THE ARMED FORCES HAVE DEFEATED THE FMLN IN THE NORTHERN ZONE AND IN SOYAPANGO, SAN SALVADOR, SAN MIGUEL AND MORAZAN, CAUSING IN THE PROCESS OVER 2,000 CASUALTIES INCLUDING SEVERAL COMMANDERS AND MERCENARIES."

THE FMLN HAS PUBLICLY ADMITTED THAT "COMMANDERS" HERNAN SOLORZANO ("DIMAS RODRIGUEZ"), JORGE ORLANDO SANDOVAL ("OSCAR"), GEOMAR ARI ("CIRILO"), OVIDIO LOPEZ ("ORLANDO MORALES"), AND "POLITICAL OFFICERS" JOSE SANTOS LLANES ("PEPE") AND MILAGROS ALVARADO ("JUDY"), HAVE BEEN KILLED.

TERRORIST LEADERS MISAEL GALLARDO, NICOLAS ALBERTO SARAVIA, AND RICARDO MIRANDA HAVE ALSO BEEN KILLED SINCE THE BEGINNING OF THE FAILED FMLN OFFENSIVE ON 11 NOVEMBER.

COL PONCE REPORTED THAT MANY MERCENARIES, INCLUDING SOME WHO LOOKED EUROPEAN, DIED DURING THE CLASH WITH THE ARMY IN COLONIA ESCALON. PONCE ADDED THAT THE FAMILIES OF THESE MERCENARIES ARE NOW INQUIRING ABOUT THEM IN NICARAGUA.

COL PONCE BELIEVES THAT THE SABOTAGE WHICH THE FMLN IS CARRYING OUT BY BURNING BUSSES, DESTROYING POWER PYLONS, AND STAGING SMALL- SCALE ATTACKS, ARE MERELY THE "LAST KICKS" OF A DROWNING PERSON.

ASSISTED BY THE AIR FORCE, THE SALVADORAN ARMY CONTINUES TO STRIKE AT THE FEW TERRORISTS STRONGHOLDS IN THE NORTH, PARTS OF THE CAPITAL, AND OTHER AREAS IN THE INTERIOR.

PONCE INDICATED THAT THE FMLN IS SPREADING LIES IN AN ATTEMPT TO MAINTAIN ITS CREDIBILITY AND TO COVER UP THE HEAVY CASUALTIES IT HAS TAKEN. THE CASUALTIES REALLY NUMBER OVER 2,000 ALTHOUGH THE FMLN CLAIMS ONLY TO HAVE LOST 400 PEOPLE.

THE OFFICIAL ARMED FORCES REPORT ISSUED ON 30 NOVEMBER STATES THAT THE FMLN SUSTAINED 2,132 KILLED IN ACTION DURING THE OFFENSIVE WHILE THE GOVERNMENT LOST 476 TROOPS.

COL PONCE ADDED THAT THE INVESTIGATION CONTINUES INTO THE DEATH OF FOUR PEOPLE WHO DIED IN THE CRASH OF A PLANE THAT WAS BRINGING ARMS FOR THE FMLN FROM NICARAGUA. THE CRASH OCCURED IN AN ISOLATED AREA OF USULUTAN DEPARTMENT.

UNTIL YESTERDAY THE FMLN HAD NOT ADMITTED THAT THE CREW OF THE PLANE CARRYING ARMS THAT CRASHED ON 25 SEPTEMBER BELONGED TO TERRORIST GROUPS. ACCORDING TO THE FMLN THE CREW MEMBERS WERE SALVADORANS.

THE TERRORISTS REPORTED THAT THE DEAD CREWMEN WERE PILOT OSVALDO ALFARO AGUINADA, ALSO KNOWN AS "LUIS" AND "ANTIAIRCRAFT GUNNERS" ROMEL HERNANDEZ ARGUETA ("HELO"), ISIDRO PARADA MARTINEZ ("DENIS"), AND SANTIAGO RAUDA POSADA ("WILLIAM").

COL PONCE STATED THAT THIS "RUMOR IS A COMMUNIST MANEUVER TO MAKE SURE THAT DANIEL ORTEGA DOES NOT GET BLAMED IN THE LIGHT OF THE INTERNATIONAL PRESSURE AGAINST HIM BECAUSE OF HIS SUBVERSIVE CAMPAIGN IN AREA COUNTRIES."

PONCE ADDED THAT THE CURRENT STRATEGY OF THE DEFEATED FMLN IS LIMITED TO TALKING ABOUT FALSE VICTORIES TO NEWS MEDIA THAT THEY CONTROL, SO AS NOT TO DEMORALIZE THEIR RANK-AND-FILE; TO REFUTING ARMY REPORTS; AND TO DISSEMINATING FALSE FIGURES ON CASUALTIES ALLEGEDLY INFLICTED TO THE ARMY.

DEV-MUC3-1023 (TRW)

GUATEMALA CITY, 22 DEC 89 (PRENSA LIBRE) -- [TEXT] THREE MEMBERS OF THE INTERNATIONAL PEACE BRIGADES [BRIGADAS DE PAZ INTERNACIONALES] ASSIGNED TO GUATEMALA WERE ATTACKED YESTERDAY BY ALLEGED CRIMINALS WHO STABBED THEM NEAR THE THEIR BRIGADE HEADQUARTERS ON MARISCAL STREET IN THIS CAPITAL.

ACCORDING TO AUTHORITIES FROM THE INTERNATIONAL PEACE BRIGADES, THE VICTIMS WERE TWO CANADIAN WOMEN AND AN AMERICAN MALE CITIZEN.

THE REPORT STATES THAT THE THREE MEMBERS WERE RETURNING TO THEIR HEADQUARTERS WHEN THEY WERE INTERCEPTED AND ATTACKED BY TWO YOUNG MEN WHO STABBED THEM. THE AGGRESSORS FIRST STABBED THE TWO WOMEN IN THE CHEST, CAUSING DEEP WOUNDS. THE AMERICAN MAN TRIED TO DEFEND THE TWO WOMEN BUT HE SUFFERED CUTS ON HIS HANDS AND WRISTS, AND AROUND HIS WAIST.

THE INTERNATIONAL PEACE BRIGADES IN GUATEMALA REPORT STATES:

WE CONSIDER THAT THE ATTACK ON THEIR MEMBERS REPRESENTS AN ACTION OF INTIMIDATION AGAINST THIS ORGANIZATION AND THE HUMANITARIAN TASK IT CARRIES OUT IN GUATEMALA. THE AGGRESSORS DID NOT ASK FOR MONEY OR TRY TO STEAL ANYTHING FROM THE THREE VICTIMS. DURING THE ATTACK THE WOMEN DROPPED THEIR PURSES AND THE ATTACKERS DID NOT TRY TO STEAL THEM.

WE CONSIDER THAT THIS IS ANOTHER ATTACK IN THE ESCALATION OF VIOLENCE TO INTIMIDATE THE INTERNATIONAL PEACE BRIGADES, WHOSE PERSONNEL HAVE BEEN RECEIVING DEATH THREATS SINCE MAY. TWO GRENADES WERE HURLED AT THE ORGANIZATION'S HEADQUARTERS IN AUGUST.

THE INTERNATIONAL PEACE BRIGADES ARE AN INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS THAT PROMOTES THE THEORY AND PRACTICE OF NON-VIOLENCE, SEEKING PEACE THROUGH NON-VIOLENT MEANS. THIS PEACE INVOLVES NEGOTIATION, DIALOGUE, AND OTHER NON-VIOLENT METHODS.

THE INTERNATIONAL PEACE BRIGADES DO NOT INTERFERE IN GUATEMALAN DOMESTIC AFFAIRS OR IN THE ACTIVITIES OF ANY GUATEMALAN ORGANIZATION. THEY ONLY GIVE HUMANITARIAN HELP AND MAINTAIN AN INDEPENDENT ATTITUDE.

DEV-MUC3-1024 (TRW)

LIMA, 23 DEC 89 (EFE) -- [TEXT] PERUVIAN AMBASSADOR IN PANAMA MARIO CASTRO ARENAS TODAY ASKED THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENT TO SEND MILITARY PLANES TO PANAMA TO EVACUATE PERUVIAN CITIZENS WHO ARE IN DANGER.

THE AMBASSADOR TOLD A LOCAL RADIO STATION THAT HE HAD URGED PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA TO SEND PLANES THAT COULD ALSO BRING FOOD AND MEDICINE TO THE PANAMANIANS.

CASTRO ARENAS, WHO HAS BEEN IN LIMA SINCE AUGUST THIS YEAR, RECALLED BY HIS GOVERNMENT, SAID THAT EARLY THIS MORNING HE RECEIVED A DESPERATE CALL FROM A GROUP OF PERUVIAN CITIZENS WHO WERE AFRAID THAT THEY WERE ABOUT TO BE ATTACKED BY A MOB OF PANAMANIANS.

THE AMBASSADOR EXPLAINED THAT THERE IS "WIDESPREAD LOOTING" IN PANAMA BECAUSE THE POOREST PEOPLE ARE HUNGRY, AND HE ADDED THAT THE SITUATION IS ONE OF "CHAOS AND ANARCHY AND NOT OF TRANQUILLITY AS THE PEOPLE IN LIMA BELIEVE."

CASTRO ARENAS EXPLAINED THAT THE ATTACKS ON BUILDINGS FROM WHICH U.S. SOLDIERS ARE BEING RESISTED IS CONSTANTLY THREATENING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. HE SAID THAT HE COULD HEAR "THE BOMBS GOING OFF" OVER THE TELEPHONE.

CASTRO ARENAS SAID THAT THERE ARE APPROXIMATELY 3,000 PERUVIANS IN PANAMA. HE ADDED THAT SEVERAL PEOPLE HAVE SOUGHT REFUGE AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY IN PANAMA BUT DID NOT SPECIFY THE EXACT NUMBER. HE ALSO SAID THAT "THERE IS NO ONE THERE TO TAKE CARE OF THEM."

ACCORDING TO THE AMBASSADOR, THE PERUVIAN DIPLOMATS ARE ALL BLOCKED AT THEIR HOMES; THEIR CARS HAVE BEEN TAKEN AWAY, AND ONE OF THEM HAS BEEN WOUNDED BY A GUNSHOT.

CASTRO ARENAS SAID THAT HE IS CONSTANTLY RECEIVING CALLS THAT KEEP HIM INFORMED OF WHAT IS GOING ON IN PANAMA. HE SAID THAT THE NATIONS THAT HAVE BEEN SHOWING SO MUCH CONCERN OVER WHAT IS HAPPENING IN PANAMA SHOULD START URGENTLY SENDING FOOD AND MEDICINE AND "NOT STOP AT MERE DECLARATIONS."

DEV-MUC3-1026 (TRW)

BEIJING (PRC), 15 DEC 89 (JIEFANGJUN BAO) -- [TEXT] FROM 10 TO 12 DECEMBER, PRESIDENTS OF FIVE CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES HELD A SPECIAL MEETING TO MEDIATE BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND GUERRILLAS. BUT SO FAR NO AGREEMENT HAS BEEN REACHED BY BOTH SIDES ON BRINGING ABOUT A CEASE-FIRE DURING CHRISTMAS. THEIR 1-MONTH-LONG FIERCE BATTLE HAS LEFT 3,000 PEOPLE DEAD AND ALSO CAST A SHADOW OVER THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE PROCESS.

THE CURRENT CIVIL WAR IN EL SALVADOR WAS TRIGGERED OFF BY THE DESTRUCTION OF THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE LABOR FEDERATION, THE COUNTRY'S BIGGEST TRADE UNION ORGANIZATION. ON 31 OCTOBER, AN ULTRARIGHTIST "DARE-TO-DIE SQUAD" SUPPORTED BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE MILITARY USED A HEAVY BOMB TO BOMBARD THE HEADQUARTERS BUILDING OF THE LABOR FEDERATION, KILLING AND WOUNDING OVER 40 PEOPLE INCLUDING PRINCIPAL LEADERS OF THE FEDERATION. ON 2 NOVEMBER, THE GUERRILLAS ISSUED A STATEMENT STRONGLY CONDEMNING THE TERRORIST ACTIVITY OF THE SQUAD AND DECLARING THE CANCELLATION OF THE THIRD ROUND OF TALKS WITH THE GOVERNMENT SCHEDULED IN VENEZUELA. ON THE SAME NIGHT THE GUERRILLAS LAUNCHED A LARGE-SCALE OFFENSIVE "TO ELIMINATE FASCISM." ABOUT 8,000 GUERRILLAS SWIFTLY CAPTURED MANY TOWNS AND STRATEGIC POSITIONS NORTHWEST OF THE CAPITAL AND CUT KEY COMMUNICATIONS LINES BETWEEN THE CAPITAL AND THE HINTERLAND. IN THE MEANTIME, THEY ALSO ATTACKED SOME 50 GOVERNMENT ARMY BASES AND POLICE STATIONS IN THE HINTERLAND, THUS CONTROLLING 30 PERCENT OF THE COUNTRY'S TERRITORY. THEY HAVE ESTABLISHED "LOCAL PEOPLE'S GOVERNMENTS" IN 8 OF THE 14 PROVINCES THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY. DURING THIS PERIOD, THE GOVERNMENT DISPATCHED ARMORED CARS AND AIR FORCE UNITS TO CARRY OUT COUNTERATTACKS. THEY WANTONLY BOMBARDED THE RESIDENTIAL AREAS NEAR THE CAPITAL CITY OCCUPIED BY THE GUERRILLAS. AFTER 8 DAYS OF FIERCE BATTLE, THE GUERRILLAS SHOT DOWN 12 GOVERNMENT FIGHTER PLANES AND HELICOPTERS; DESTROYED 34 TANKS, ARMORED CARS, AND PATROL CARS; AND CAPTURED A LARGE AMOUNT OF ARMS AND AMMUNITION. SUBSEQUENTLY BATTLES CONTINUED IN REGIONS OUTSIDE THE CAPITAL CITY. SINCE EARLY DECEMBER BOTH SIDES HAVE ENGAGED IN FIERCE BATTLES IN THE CAPITAL CITY AND THE HINTERLAND. THE GUERRILLAS USED MORTARS TO ATTACK THE BUILDING OF THE GOVERNMENT ARMY GENERAL STAFF HEADQUARTERS, THE U.S. EMBASSY, AND THE PRESIDENTIAL RESTAURANT, WHEREAS THE GOVERNMENT ARMY DISPATCHED PLANES TO BOMBARD THE GUERRILLA POSITIONS. FIERCE BATTLES HAVE ALSO BROKEN OUT IN CHALATENANGO, SAN MIGUEL, AND OTHER TOWNS, THEREBY CAUSING HEAVY CASUALTIES AND PROPERTY LOSSES.

THIS WAR HAS DEEP-ROOTED CAUSES. EL SALVADOR IS A SMALL COUNTRY WITH AN AREA OF 21,000 SQUARE KM AND A POPULATION OF 5 MILLION. DURING THIS 10-YEAR-LONG WAR, 70,000 PEOPLE HAVE DIED AND THE NATIONAL ECONOMY HAS BEEN SERIOUSLY DESTROYED. THE ULTRARIGHTIST NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE [ARENA] WON THE GENERAL ELECTION EARLY THIS YEAR, THUS AGGRAVATING THE CONFLICT BETWEEN THE GUERRILLAS AND THE GOVERNMENT. PRIOR TO THE ELECTION, THE GUERRILLAS PUT FORWARD A PEACE PROPOSAL DEMANDING SIX MONTHS' POSPONEMENT OF THE ELECTION SO AS TO MAKE THEIR PARTICIPATION POSSIBLE. BUT THIS PROPOSAL WAS REJECTED BY THE GOVERNMENT. BECAUSE ALMOST HALF OF THE VOTERS DID NOT VOTE, THE GUERRILLAS DECLARED IT DID NOT RECOGNIZE THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT. PRESSED BY DOMESTIC PUBLIC OPINION AND URGED BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE AGREEMENT, THE GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS HELD TWO ROUNDS OF TALKS IN SEPTEMBER AND OCTOBER. DURING THEIR TALKS THE GUERRILLAS DEMANDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT STOP ITS SUPPRESSION, INTRODUCE POLITICAL, ECONOMIC, AND JUDICIAL REFORMS, REORGANIZE THE ARMED FORCES, AND PUNISH THE "DARE-TO-DIE SQUAD." THE GOVERNMENT INSISTED THAT THE GUERRILLAS SHOULD LAY DOWN THEIR ARMS BEFORE REFORMS WERE CARRIED OUT. THE HARD-LINE POSITION OF THE GOVERNMENT REFLECTED THE ESTABLISHED POLICY OF THE RULING PARTY, WHICH HAS ALL ALONG STOOD FOR RULING THE COUNTRY BY MILITARY MEANS, ADVOCATED THE SUPPRESSION OF DEMOCRATIC FORCES, AND SUPPORTED THE "DARE-TO-DIE SQUAD" IN CARRYING OUT ASSASSINATION. A UNIVERSITY PRESIDENT IN CENTRAL AMERICA WAS ASSASSINATED BY THE SQUAD FOR CRITICIZING THE ULTRARIGHTIST POLICY OF THE RULING PARTY. RECENTLY THE RULING PARTY SUPPORTED THE "DARE-TO-DIE SQUAD" IN ATTACKING THE LABOR FEDERATION'S BUILDING. THIS IGNITED THE CURRENT CIVIL WAR AND UNDERMINED THE PEACE PROCESS IN THE COUNTRY. THE GUERRILLAS ISSUED A STATEMENT ON 12 DECEMBER CONDEMNING THE MEETING OF THE FIVE HEADS OF STATE FOR BEING PARTIAL TO THE ULTRARIGHTIST SALVADORIAN GOVERNMENT. THEY MADE IT CLEAR THAT THEY WOULD NOT ACCEPT ANY EFFORT TO DISSOLVE THE GUERRILLA FORCES AND WOULD CARRY ON THEIR STRUGGLE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1030 (TRW)

LIMA, 25 DEC 89 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT GARCIA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [GARCIA] WHEN I APPLY ALL MY ARGUMENTATIVE AND RETHORICAL ENERGY TO THE SUBJECT OF PANAMA, AND I DO SO WITH ABSOLUTE SINCERITY, NOT SIMPLY TO TAKE A STANCE, BUT BECAUSE AS A LATIN AMERICAN I FEEL GREATLY OFFENDED IN A WAY THAT YOU COULD NOT UNDERSTAND. I FEEL TERRIBLY OFFENDED. IF I MAKE DEMANDS AND IF I CONDEMN, I KNOW THAT NOBODY WILL QUICKLY FOLLOW ME DOWN THIS ROAD OF FIRMNESS AND CONDEMNATION. BUT THIS IS A SECONDARY ASPECT. I WISH I WERE FOLLOWED, BUT IF AM NOT, THIS DOES NOT DETRACT FROM THE JUSTICE OF WHAT I AM DOING. ONE TRIES TO DO WHAT IS INTRINSICALLY GOOD, NOT SIMPLY WHAT ONE CAN NECESSARILY WIN.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[GARCIA] PARDON ME. IT WOULD BE WORSE IF YOU DIDN'T DO IT. IT WOULD BE LESS EFFECTIVE, THOUGH IT WOULD BE SOMEWHAT EFFECTIVE. DON'T BE UNJUST. IT WOULD BE EVEN LESS EFFECTIVE IF WE ALL REMAINED SILENT AND SAID: YES, UNCLE SAM, YOU ARE THE MASTER AND WE MUST OBEY. WE ARE THE UNCLE TOM IN LATIN AMERICA.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[GARCIA] LOOK, I DON'T EXPECT....[CHANGES THOUGHT] WE DON'T HAVE TO MIX THEM [PASSAGE INDISTINCT]. WE CONTINUE OUR NEGOTIATION WITH THE IMF, AND THAT TO ME STILL SEEMS VERY POSITIVE. MAY IT NOT TURN OUT AS THE ILLUSION I HAD THAT RELATIONS WERE CHANGING AT THE POLTICAL LEVEL. FIRST, I WOULD NOT ALLOW A HARDENING OF PERU ATTITUDE TOWARD THE UNITED STATES. THERE IS A HARDENING WHEN ONE SLAPS SOMEONE ELSE IN THE FACE. IN THIS CASE WE HAVE A CONCRETE SUBJECT OF DISCUSSION. THERE IS A GREAT ISSUE TO DISCUSS BETWEEN LATIN AMERICA AND THE UNITED STATES. YOU DON'T HAVE THE RIGHT TO INVADE. WHO CALLED YOU? ENDARA HIMSELF HAD TO SAY -- BECAUSE HE KNOWS WHAT THE PANAMANIAN PEOPLE THINKING, THOUGH A PERCENTAGE OF THEM ARE INDIFFERENT -- THAT HE DID NOT CALL THEM. DO YOU KNOW WHAT THAT MEANS? PRESIDENT ENDARA SAYS THAT HE DIDN'T CALL FOR THE INVASION. THIS SHOULD BE AUTOMATICALLY UNDERSTOOD. FOR SOME REASON HE SAID IT. SO I WOULD NOT CALL IT A HARDENING. I BEG YOU TO UNDERSTAND THE EXACT SHADE OF THE TERM. WE ARE ENERGIC IN OPPOSING A CONCRETE FACT, BUT WHAT DO THE PEOPLE OF NEW HAMPSHIRE, THE PEOPLE OF CALIFORNIA, THE PEOPLE OF GEORGIA, THE PEOPLE OF JEFFERSON, OF WHITMAN, OF LINCLON -- THAT GREAT DEFENDER OF HUMAN RIGHTS AND RACIAL EQUALITY -- WHAT HAVE THEY HAVE TO DO WITH THAT ACT? WE HAVE TO RESPECT THE GREATNESS OF THE UNITED STATES. FROM LATIN AMERICA, THE UNITED STATES IS SEEN IN VARIOUS WAYS. FOR THE TIME BEING, I SEE IT AS THE ROME OF THE MODERN WORLD. I HAVE ALWAYS THOUGHT THAT THE LATIN AMERICANS MUST BE UNDERSTOOD INSIDE THE UNITED STATES. THE LATIN AMERICAN EXPERIENCE HAS TO SEEN INSIDE THE UNITED STATES. THEN A SOUND RELATIONSHINP WILL EMERGE BETWEEN THE TWO CONTINENTS. BECAUSE THE UNITED STATES IS THE ROME OF THE MODERN WORLD -- FOR THE CAPACITY OF ITS ATOMIC LEGIONS; FOR THEIR HAVING CONCENTRATED SCIENCE AND PHILOSOPHY, ALTHOUGH BOTH WERE BROUGHT OVER FROM EUROPE AS THE ROMANS BROUGHT THEM FROM GREECE; FOR THEIR HAVING GENERATED AN EXTRAORDINARY TECHNOLOGY, AND FOR THEIR BEING A DEMOCRACY -- THE UNITED STATES MUST BE RESPECTED. WE WILL HAVE TO DISTINGUISH ALL THAT FROM A PARTICULAR ACT BY THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION. THIS IS WHY WE SAY AMERICANS REFERRING TO THE PEOPLE OF THE UNITED STATES, AND SAY YANKEE TO DEFINE SOME ACTS BY THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION. SO I DON'T BELIEVE, SIR, THAT THERE IS A HARDENING, AND I ALSO BELIEVE THAT THEY UNDERSTAND IT VERY WELL. I BELIEVE THEY UNDERSTAND ME WHEN I TELL THEM THAT I CANNOT SIT AT THE TABLE WITH THEM WHEN THEY ARE KILLING PANAMANIAN PEOPLE. LET THE MINISTERS, THE POLICE CHIEFS, THE PROSECUTORS, THE ATTORNEY GENERALS SIT AT A TABLE. THAT IS GOOD. BUT THE REPRESENTATIVE OF THE NATION? DO YOU UNDERSTAND WHAT I MEAN? I THINK THIS IS A GOOD OPPORTUNITY TO EXPLAIN IT. I DO NOT BELIEVE IT WOULD BE A BAD THING FOR MR MANTILLA TO SIT WITH MR BENNETT OR WITH THE JUSTICE MINISTER OF COLOMBIA. I DO NOT BELIEVE THIS WOULD BE BAD. THIS IS THE PROOF THAT WE WANT TO CONTINUE THE ANTIDRUG PLAN. BUT THOSE WHO PERSONIFY THE NATION CANNOT MEET. WE CANNOT DO SO UNDER THE PRESENT CIRCUMSTANCES. SO THIS IS NOT HARDENING. AS FOR THE IMF, I BELIEVE THAT IT IS AN ABSOLUTELY DIFFERENT MATTER. THESE MATTERS ARE WELL DIFFERENTIATED. I AM NOT HERE AS A DEMAGOGUE, AS SOME RIGHT WING MEDIA ASSERT. THOSE PEOPLE ARE FIGHTENED WHEN I DRAW A LOT OF PEOPLE DESPITE MY POLTICAL DECLINE. I AM NOT BEING A DEMAGOGUE, AND I AM NOT HERE BECAUSE THE BEST WAY TO WIN VOTES IS TO INDULGE IN ANTI-AMERICAN POLITICS FROM HERE UNTIL 28 JULY 1990. I WILL NOT LAPSE INTO THAT IRRESPONSIBILITY. HERE WE HAVE A CONCRETE FACT THAT HAS NOTHING TO DO WITH OUR CULTURAL, COMMERCIAL, POLITICAL, AND ECONOMIC RELATIONS WITH ORGANIZATIONS WHERE THE UNITED STATES MAY OR MAY NOT HAVE INFLUENCE. I SEPARATE THINGS VERY WELL. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1031 (TRW)

BUENOS AIRES, 28 DEC 89 (TELAM) -- [TEXT] THE ARGENTINE CHAMBER OF DEPUTIES TODAY "STRONGLY REPUDIATED" THE U.S. MILITARY INTERVENTION IN PANAMA BY APPROVING A DECLARATION SPONSORED BY THE JUSTICIALIST PARTY (PJ) AND THE RADICAL CIVIC UNION (UCR) BLOCS. THE PROPOSAL MET WITH STRONG OPPOSITION FROM THE DEMOCRATIC CENTRIST UNION (UCEDE) DEPUTIES.

THE DECLARATION PROPOSED BY PJ DEPUTY JUAN PABLO CAFIERO CALLS FOR THE IMMEDIATE WITHDRAWAL OF THE U.S. TROOPS THAT INVADED PANAMA TO OUST GENERAL MANUEL NORIEGA'S GOVERNMENT.

IT ALSO URGES THE UNITED STATES TO "STRICTLY COMPLY WITH THE TORRIJOS-CARTER TREATIES" ON THE FUTURE OF THE PANAMA CANAL. THE DECLARATION REJECTS ALL TYPES OF DICTATORIAL REGIMES, IMPLICITLY REFERRING TO NORIEGA.

THIS STATEMENT WAS INCLUDED IN THE DECLARATION AT THE SUGGESTION OF FEDERAL PARTY DEPUTY RUTH MONJARDIN AFTER OBTAINING THE SUPPORT OF JOSE MANZANO, THE SPEAKER FOR THE PJ BLOC; SATURNINO ARANA (PJ), CHAIRMAN OF THE FOREIGN RELATIONS COMMITTEE; AND UCR DEPUTY DANTE CAPUTO.

THE DECLARATION ALSO RECEIVED THE SUPPORT OF INTRANSIGENT PARTY DEPUTY OSCAR ALENDE, CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY DEPUTY HECTOR GATTI, AND POPULAR DEMOCRATIC PARTY DEPUTY ALBERTO ARAMOUNI. DEPUTY LUIS ZAMORA OF THE MOVEMENT TOWARD SOCIALISM REJECTED THE DECLARATION ON THE GROUNDS THAT IT WAS MEANINGLESS "TO ASK ANYTHING OF A COUNTRY THAT IS KILLING PANAMANIANS."

THE UCEDE OPPOSED THE DECLARATION, AND BLOC SPEAKER FEDERICO CLERICI WAS MOCKED BY PJ AND UCR DEPUTIES WHEN HE READ AN ALTERNATE DECLARATION PREPARED BY UCEDE DEPUTY ADELINA DALESSIO DE VIOLA, WHICH URGED THE GOVERNMENTS OF BOTH THE UNITED STATES AND PANAMA TO "STOP USING VIOLENCE."

UCEDE DEPUTY FRANCISCO DURANONA Y VEDIA CRITICIZED THE DECLARATION BY STATING THAT IT IMPLIED SUPPORT FOR GENERAL NORIEGA'S REGIME. DEPUTY FEDERICO ZAMORA, ALSO FROM THE UCEDE, LAMENTED THAT "THERE ARE SO MANY FORGETFUL PEOPLE HERE. A LOT IS BEING SAID ABOUT WHAT HAPPENED IN PANAMA, BUT NOTHING IS BEING SAID ABOUT ROMANIA."

FORMER FOREIGN MINISTER AND UCR DEPUTY DANTE CAPUTO SUPPORTED THE DECLARATION AND SAID THAT "TO ACCEPT THE U.S. INVASION WOULD BE TANTAMOUNT TO ADMITTING THAT THE END JUSTIFIES THE MEANS," ADDING THAT SUCH IDEAS MUST BE REJECTED, EVEN THOUGH PANAMA MAY HAVE HAD AN "ILLEGAL, DICTATORIAL AND CORRUPT" GOVERNMENT.

TOWARD THE END OF THE DEBATE, PJ BLOC SPEAKER JOSE MANZANO SAID THAT "BY CRITICIZING THIS SAVAGERY WE SEEK TO HELP RELATIONS BETWEEN THE UNITED STATES AND LATIN AMERICA [LE HACEMOS UN FAVOR A LA RELACION DE ESTADOS UNIDOS CON AMERICA LATINA]. HE ADDED THAT THE UNITED STATES HAS DIFFERENT STANDARDS FOR THE DESIRE FOR FREEDOM OF TALL BLOND EAST GERMANS AND OF SHORT DARK PANAMANIANS."

DEV-MUC3-1033 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 28 DEC 89 (LA PRENSA GRAFICA) -- [TEXT] FATHER JOSE MARIA TOJEIRA S.J. [SOCIETY OF JESUS], THE JESUIT PROVINCIAL SPOKESMAN FOR CENTRAL AMERICA, HAS RELEASED A NOTE DENYING INEXACT REPORTS ON THE CASE OF THE MURDERED JESUIT PRIESTS. HE SAID THAT THEY NOT WERE MARXIST GUERRILLA SYMPATHIZERS.

THE NOTE READS AS FOLLOWS:

23 DECEMBER 1989

PROV. 264/89

DIRECTOR DUTRIZ

DIRECTOR OF LA PRENSA GRAFICA

SAN SALVADOR

DEAR MR.DIRECTOR:

THE NEWSPAPER WHICH YOU DIRECT, ON 21 DECEMBER 1989, PUBLISHED ON PAGES 6 AND 7 TWO ARTICLES ON THE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS THAT WERE MURDERED ON 16 NOVEMBER. THESE ARTICLES ARE WRITTEN IN SUCH A WAY THAT THEY DISTORT THE REALITY OF THE CASE OR THEY INCORRECTLY DESCRIBE THE ACTIVITY OF THE SOCIETY OF JESUS.

ON PAGE 6 AN ARTICLE ENTITLED "FRATRICIDAL STRUGGLE," WHICH IS SIGNED BY MR. LUIS PAZOS, SAYS THAT "THE PRIESTS WERE MARXIST GUERRILLA SYMPATHIZERS" AND THAT THE UNIVERSITY IN WHICH THEY WORK "IS KNOWN IN EL SALVADOR AS AN INTELLECTUAL CENTER FOR GUERRILLAS."

THE ARTICLE SPEAKS OF "THESE PRIESTS' NEOMARXIST-PHILOSOPHICAL POSITION WHICH IS CONTRARY TO CHRISTIAN DOCTRINE."

I WISH TO STATE THAT:

1. THE MURDERED PRIESTS WERE NOT SYMPATHIZERS OF THE MARXIST GUERRILLAS. THEY ONLY TRIED TO TALK WITH THE DIFFERENT SECTORS IN CONFLICT IN EL SALVADOR, SEEKING TO MEDIATE IN AN EFFORT TO FIND PEACE WITH JUSTICE.

2. PERHAPS SOME PEOPLE IN EL SALVADOR CONSIDER THE UCA [CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY] AS AN INTELLECTUAL CENTER FOR GUERRILLAS, BUT THERE ARE ALSO MANY PEOPLE WHO THINK THAT THE UCA COURAGEOUSLY FOLLOWS THE CHURCH'S SOCIAL DOCTRINE. THIS STATEMENT, IF MADE WITHOUT THE RESERVATION THAT IT ONLY REPRESENTS THE VIEWS OF A GROUP OF PEOPLE AND THE FACT THAT THE ARTICLE FORGETS TO MENTION THE MANY OTHERS DO NOT BELIEVE, IS IN OUR OPINION A MANIPULATION OF THE TRUTH.

3. THE POSITION OF THE PRIESTS WAS NOT "NEOMARXIST" IN THE PHILOSOPHICAL FIELD. FATHER ELLACURIA CAME FROM THE SCHOOL OF THE SPANISH PHILOSOPHER ZUBIRI, WHOSE THOUGHTS WERE DEEPLY ROOTED IN CHRISTIAN PHILOSOPHY. FATHER AMANDO LOPEZ WROTE HIS DOCTORAL THESIS ON THE SPANISH PHILOSOPHER AND PRIEST AMOR RUIBAL. THE "ZUBIRIAN" INCLINATION OF FATHER ELLACURIA WAS INTERNATIONALLY KNOWN IN MOST PHILOSOPHICAL SCHOOLS. THOSE WHO ACCUSE THE MURDERED PRIESTS OF HAVING NEOMARXIST PHILOSOPHICAL POSITIONS ARE PUBLICLY ACKNOWLEDGING THEIR IGNORANCE.

4. STATEMENTS SUCH AS THESE, WHICH WERE REPEATED IN OTHER MEDIA BEFORE THE MURDER OF THE PRIESTS, PARTLY PROMOTED THEIR MURDER. WE THEREFORE CONSIDER THEIR REPETITION TO BE A VERY SERIOUS MATTER.

ON PAGE 7, AND IN AN EDITORIAL ARTICLE, THE NEWSPAPER MENTIONS THE NEED TO AVOID "THE DAMAGE CAUSED BY PRIVATE PSEUDO-INVESTIGATIONS, WHEREVER THEY MIGHT COME FROM." ON THIS STATEMENT I WANT TO SIMPLY ADD THAT IN A CASE LIKE THIS THE INJURED PARTY HAS EVERY RIGHT, BOTH IN EL SALVADOR AND IN ANY OTHER PART OF THE WORLD, TO CONDUCT ITS OWN PRIVATE INVESTIGATION. FURTHERMORE, UNLESS PUBLICLY AND IRREFUTABLY PROVEN HARMFUL, NO ONE HAS THE RIGHT TO CONDEMN IT "IN ADVANCE" SAYING THAT IT IS PLAYING DETECTIVES.

I BEG OF YOU MR. DIRECTOR, BASED ON THE RIGHT TO REPLY AND THE JUSTICE THAT THE MURDERED JESUITS AND THOSE WHO BELIEVE IN THEM DESERVE, THAT YOU PUBLISH THIS CLARIFICATIONS IN YOUR NEWSPAPER WITH THE SAME DESIRE TO REACH YOUR READERS AS THOSE WHO WROTE THE ARTICLES.

YOURS TRULY.

FATHER JOSE MARIA TOJEIRA

SOCIETY OF JESUS PROVINCIAL."

DEV-MUC3-1034 (TRW)

TEGUCIGALPA, 31 DEC 89 (TELEVISORA HONDURENA) -- [SPEECH] [HONDURAN PRESIDENT JOSE SIMEON AZCONA HOYO] [EXCERPTS] COUNTRYMEN: NOW THAT THE NEW YEAR IS JUST MOMENTS AWAY, WE APPEAR BEFORE THE NATION, AS WE HAVE DONE IN THE PREVIOUS YEARS OF OUR ADMINISTRATION, TO EXPRESS OUR MOST SINCERE WISHES FOR THE PERSONAL WELL-BEING OF ALL HONDURAN PEOPLE. OUR GREATEST WISH IS FOR EACH INDIVIDUAL IN THE NATION, WITHOUT EXCEPTION, TO ENJOY WELL- BEING AND PEACE AT HOME. WE CAN AFFIRM THAT DURING OUR TENURE WE HAVE CONSTANTLY STRIVEN TOWARD THE HIGHER GOALS OF COLLECTIVE PROGRESS AND WELL-BEING IN THE SPECIFIC SITUATIONS WE HAVE FACED DURING THESE 4 YEARS OF GOVERNMENT -- SITUATIONS THAT ARE NATURAL TO A DEVELOPING COUNTRY LIKE OURS.

ON 25 JANUARY 1990 WE WILL PRESENT TO CONGRESS A REPORT SUMMING UP THE ACHIEVEMENTS MADE DURING OUR ADMINISTRATION. THUS, ALL THE PEOPLE WILL BE TRUTHFULLY INFORMED OF OUR ACCOMPLISHMENTS AND OF THE PROJECTS THAT HAVE BEEN UNDERTAKEN SO THAT THE HONDURAN PEOPLE CAN DEVELOP MATERIAL AND SOCIAL CONDITIONS IN ACCORDANCE WITH THE HISTORICAL EVOLUTION TO WHICH WE ASPIRE, BOTH AS INDIVIDUALS AND AS A STATE. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

WE HAVE EXPRESSED OUR DESIRE FOR PEACE AT SIX CENTRAL AMERICAN SUMMITS, WHERE WE DEFENDED THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESSES AND CONDEMNED ANY FORM OF TOTALITARIANISM AS WELL AS THE TERRORIST ACTIONS THAT HAVE CAUSED MANY DEATHS AND BROUGHT SORROW TO THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEOPLE.

I AM PROUD TO SAY THAT THE TELA SUMMIT HAS CONTRIBUTED TO THE SEARCH FOR PEACE AND DEMOCRACY IN CENTRAL AMERICA, ESPECIALLY IN THOSE COUNTRIES PLAGUED BY VIOLENCE.

WE HAVE ALWAYS MAINTAINED THAT GREAT SACRIFICES ARE NECESSARY IF WE ARE TO MAKE SOCIAL PROGRESS, AND WE HAVE CONSTANTLY WORKED TO ESTABLISH THE NECESSARY CONDITIONS FOR THE COUNTRY'S DEVELOPMENT.

OUR ACHIEVEMENTS ARE LASTING AND HAVE GIVEN THE COUNTRY BETTER PROSPECTS FOR THE FUTURE. THAT HAS BEEN OUR MAIN OBJECTIVE. WE DID NOT RESORT TO DEMAGOGUERY, AND WE SPOKE THE TRUTH -- DURING THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN AND LATER AS THE LEADER OF THE NATION'S DESTINY -- SO AS NOT TO CREATE FALSE EXPECTATIONS AMONG THE PEOPLE. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

I WANT TO REASSERT THAT ONCE I STEP DOWN FROM THE PRESIDENCY, I WILL CONTINUE FROM THE PRIVATE SECTOR TO STRIVE FOR THE UNITY OF THE HONDURAN PEOPLE SO THAT WITH EFFORT AND WORK WE MAY IMPROVE OUR LIVING STANDARDS. [PASSAGE OMITTED]

FINALLY I WANT TO EXPRESS MY SINCERE DESIRE FOR SUCCESS -- FOR THE WELL-BEING OF THE FATHERLAND -- TO RAFAEL LEONARDO CALLEJAS ROMERO, WHO WILL TAKE OFFICE AS PRESIDENT ON 27 JANUARY L990. THANK YOU VERY MUCH.

DEV-MUC3-1036 (TRW)

HAVANA (CUBA), 4 JAN 90 (RADIO REBELDE NETWORK) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] THE BLOW DEALT TO THE LATIN AMERICAN CONSCIENCE BY THE U.S. INTERVENTION IN PANAMA IS ABOUT TO DEFLATE THE OPTIMISTIC HOPES FOR A JOINT STRUGGLE AGAINST THE DRUG TRADE. EVEN GEORGE BUSH'S 15 FEBRUARY MEETING IN CARTAGENA DE INDIAS, COLOMBIA, WITH THE PRESIDENTS OF BOLIVIA, PERU, AND COLOMBIA -- THE LEADING PRODUCERS OF COCA LEAVES -- IS IN JEOPARDY. PERUVIAN CHIEF EXECUTIVE ALAN GARCIA MADE IT KNOWN THAT HE WILL NOT ATTEND THE MEETING IN PROTEST OF THE PANAMA INVASION. BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA IS BEING QUESTIONED BY THE BOLIVIAN SUPREME COURT OVER THE EXTRADITION TO THE UNITED STATES OF FORMER COLONEL LUIS ARCE GOMEZ. THE COURT REGARDS PAZ ZAMORA'S DECISION ON THIS MATTER AS UNDUE EXERCISE OF JURISDICTIONAL POWERS AND AN ATTACK ON THE JUDICIAL BRANCH. BOLIVIAN CHIEF JUSTICE EDGAR OBLITAS CHARGED THAT THE EXTRADITION OF ARCE GOMEZ, WHO WAS A NOTORIOUS DRUG TRAFFICKER, AN EXECUTIONER AND A PLOTTER, HAS PREVENTED THE AUTHORITIES FROM CLEARING UP SEVERAL RECENT EVENTS IN BOLIVIAN HISTORY, WHICH THUS REMAIN JUST PARTIALLY KNOWN.

FOR ITS PART, COLOMBIA REACTED WITH SURPRISE AND INDIGNATION TO REPORTS THAT THE UNITED STATES PLANS TO ESTABLISH AIRSPACE AND NAVAL PATROLS WITHIN COLOMBIAN JURISDICTION WITHOUT CONSULTING WITH BOGOTA. THE WHITE HOUSE IN WASHINGTON STATED LATER THAT THE PATROLS WILL TAKE PLACE OVER INTERNATIONAL WATERS AND THAT THEY WILL ENTAIL CONCERTED ACTIONS. IT IS KNOWN, HOWEVER, THAT AN EVENTUAL BLOCKADE OF THE COLOMBIAN COAST IS PART OF A PACKAGE OF SPECIAL MEASURES COORDINATED BY U.S. DEFENSE SECRETARY DICK CHENEY.

THE COLOMBIAN POLICE, WHO HAVE BEEN CREDITED WITH SEIZING 80 PERCENT OF THE TOTAL ANNUAL AMOUNT OF COCAINE SEIZED WORLDWIDE, HAVE IN RECENT WEEKS DEALT SEVERE BLOWS TO THE MEDELLIN CARTEL DRUG LORDS. THE PUNITIVE U.S. ACTION WOULD IN PRACTICE ENTAIL THAT THE UNITED STATES DOES NOT RECOGNIZE THESE ACHIEVEMENTS AND WOULD CREATE AN EMBARRASSING SITUATION FOR PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO IN A YEAR WHEN COLOMBIANS WILL ELECT A NEW PRESIDENT, MEMBERS OF CONGRESS, MAYORS, DEPARTMENTAL DEPUTIES, AND COUNCILMEN.

THE CLAIM THAT THE ACTION IS INTENDED TO MORE EFFECTIVELY PREVENT THE DRUG TRADE IS HIGHLY SUSPICIOUS, TAKING INTO ACCOUNT THAT IT WILL NOT BE MATCHED BY EQUIVALENT STIFF MEASURES IN THE COUNTRY HOLDING THE WORLD RECORD IN DRUG CONSUMPTION AND THAT U.S. TROOPS ARE CURRENTLY OCCUPYING COLOMBIA'S NEIGHBORING COUNTRY, PANAMA.

WHERE DOES THE U.S. DESIRE TO CHASE CRIMINALS END AND WHERE DOES ITS IMPERIALIST DESIRE TO LIMIT LATIN AMERICAN SOVEREIGNTY AND TO DECIDE THE FATE OF OUR PEOPLES START? THE PANAMANIAN CASE IS AN EXAMPLE. IT IS NOT NOT ONLY LEGITIMATE BUT NECESSARY FOR US TO BE DISTRUSTFUL.

DEV-MUC3-1038 (TRW)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE VIOLENT AND SURPRISING EVENTS IN VENEZUELA AND ARGENTINA EARLIER IN THE YEAR, WHICH RESULTED IN THOUSANDS KILLED, ARE AN INDICATION OF WHAT WILL HAPPEN IN COMING YEARS. WITH ITS INTERVENTIONIST POLICY, THE UNITED STATES HAS NEGATED OUR PEOPLES' SELF - DETERMINATION AND EMBITTERED THE RELATIONS BETWEEN THE COUNTRIES IN THE AREA. BY PREVENTING THE SOCIAL FORCES FROM ACTING FREELY, THE UNITED STATES PROLONGS THE WAR AND ELIMINATES THE POSSIBILITY OF ACHIEVING TRUE DEMOCRATIZATION. THE U.S. IMPERIALIST POLICY HAS WEAKENED IN THE DECADE ENDING TODAY. LATIN AMERICANISM HAS ADVANCED AND THE TIME OF A DOCILE AND PUPPET CONTINENT HAS BEEN LEFT BEHIND.

LATIN AMERICAN INTERESTS AND SOCIAL FORCES HAVE MATURED. DESPITE 30 YEARS OF INVASION AND COMMERCIAL FREEZING, CUBA IS STILL UNBEATEN. NICARAGUA HAS RESISTED, HAS DEFEATED 10 YEARS OF WAR WAGED BY MERCENARIES, AND IS PREPARING TO LEGITIMIZE ITS REVOLUTION. IN EL SALVADOR, THE 10 YEARS OF COUNTERINSURGENCY WITH WHICH THE UNITED STATES HAS TRIED TO DEFEAT US AND WHICH THE UNITED STATES HAS TRIED TO IMPOSE ON US HAVE FAILED. THE INSURGENCY PROBLEMS THAT WERE PREVIOUSLY RESOLVED WITH A FEW ADVISERS AND IN A COUPLE OF YEARS REMAIN UNSETTLED IN EL SALVADOR DESPITE A $3 BILLION AID PACKAGE, NEARLY 1,000 ADVISERS, AND 10 YEARS OF BLOODY WAR. IN THE PAST THE PROBLEM OF PANAMA WOULD HAVE BEEN SETTLED WITH A COUP IN A FEW HOURS' TIME, BUT NOW 2 YEARS OF ECONOMIC FREEZING, SUBVERSION, BUSINESSMEN'S STRIKES, ATTACKS, AND THWARTED COUPS WERE NECESSARY. FINALLY, THE UNITED STATES HAD TO USE 30,000 MEN, DESTROY A COUNTRY, AND FIGHT FOR 1 WEEK TO BRING TO SUBMISSION AN ARMY AND A MILITARY HEAD THEY THEMSELVES HAD TRAINED.

LATIN AMERICANISM IS ON ITS WAY FORWARD. THE DECADE NOW BEGINNING BELONGS TO LATIN AMERICA. THE STRUGGLE IN OUR CONTINENT IS OF AN ANTI-IMPERIALIST NATURE. OUR STRUGGLE, AS EVERYONE KNOWS, STARTED IN CENTRAL AMERICA 10 YEARS AGO WITH THE TRIUMPH OF THE SANDINIST REVOLUTION AND THE BEGINNING OF WAR IN OUR COUNTRY. THIS HAS TURNED THE REGION INTO A TRUE VIETNAM DURING THIS DECADE. BECAUSE OF ALL THIS, THE SACRIFICE THAT OUR STRUGGLE ENTAILS IS GREAT AND THE PROCESS IS COMPLEX, BECAUSE BOTH THE STRUGGLE AND THE PROCESS OCCUR IN A CHANGING WORLD SITUATION. WHILE IN EASTERN EUROPE THE AREAS OF INFLUENCE ARE DISAPPEARING AND THE PEOPLES' SELF - DETERMINATION IS OPENING TO AN UNHINDERED PATH, THE U.S. EMPIRE WALKS IN THE OPPOSITE DIRECTION AND CLINGS TO ITS NEOCOLONIAL DOMINATION OF LATIN AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN. WHAT IS AT STAKE IN EL SALVADOR IS NOT PRECISELY COMMUNISM OR CAPITALISM, BUT DEMOCRACY AND THE CONTINENT'S INDEPENDENCE. LATIN AMERICA ASPIRES, NOT TO A RESTRICTED SOCIETY, BUT TO A SELF-SUFFICIENT DEVELOPMENT AND INTERNAL SOCIAL BALANCE WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF MANY SOCIAL SECTORS. THE CENTRAL AMERICAN SOCIETIES APPEAR TO BE POLARIZED IN THE EYES OF BOTH EMPLOYERS AND WORKERS, BUT THE NEED FOR INDEPENDENCE WILL COALESCE ALL OF THESE FORCES. IN THIS CONTEXT, OUR STRUGGLE, WHICH IS ESSENTIALLY FOR SELF - DETERMINATION AND DEMOCRACY, IS IN THE CAPITALIST WORLD THE SPEARHEAD OF THE STRUGGLE OF ALL LATIN AMERICAN AND THIRD WORLD COUNTRIES, WHICH DEMAND THESE TRANSFORMATIONS. ALL THAT OUR PEOPLE HAVE DONE THESE YEARS AND ALL THAT HAS BEEN CONSTRUCTED BY OUR COMBATANTS, MILITARY COMMANDERS, POLITICAL LEADERS, AND THOSE WHO HAVE WORKED EITHER AS DIPLOMATS OR GUERRILLAS HAS NOW BECOME VERY SIGNIFICANT. THE CHANGES IN STRATEGY, THE RESHUFFLING OF PLANS, THE HEROIC RESISTANCE OF THE MASSES, THE UNITY OF THE REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT, THE POLITICAL - IDEOLOGICAL FLEXIBILITY, THE DEFINITION OF A POLITICAL PLATFORM ADAPTED TO THE DEMAND OF THE STRUGGLE, THE LARGE NUMBER OF BOTH LOCAL AND INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS THAT HAVE BEEN ESTABLISHED, AND ALL THAT HAS BEEN CONSTRUCTED WITH THE BLOOD OF THE BEST CHILDREN OF THE PEOPLE CONSTITUTE OUR FULL CONTRIBUTION TO THE CONSTRUCTION OF DEMOCRACY AND SOVEREIGNTY IN EL SALVADOR AND LATIN AMERICA AND HELP MAKE THE PEOPLE'S VICTORY MORE LIKELY THAN EVER. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1040 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 8 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHIEF OF THE SALVADOAN ARMED FORCES' GENERAL STAFF, HAS ADMITTED THAT 2 OFFICERS AND 45 SOLDIERS OF AN ELITE BATTALION ARE "BEING HELD IN VARIOUS GUARRISONS OF SAN SALVADOR" WHILE INVESTIGATIONS INTO THE KILLING OF THE SIX JESUITS CONTINUE.

ACCORDING TO PONCE, THESE OFFICERS AND SOLDIERS OF THE ATLACATL BATTALION WERE PLACED AT THE DISPOSITION OF THE CRIMES INVESTIGATIVE COMMISSION, WHICH IS STUDYING THE CASE OF THE JESUITS WHO WERE SHOT TO DEATH ON 16 NOVEMBER.

SPANISH, BRITISH, FRENCH, AND CANADIAN POLICE AGENTS HAVE PARTICIPATED IN THESE INVESTIGATIONS.

THESE SALVADORAN SOLDIERS HAD SEARCHED THE JESUITS' RESIDENCE 2 DAYS BEFORE THE KILLING, PONCE TOLD THE MEDIA TODAY WITHOUT GIVING MUCH DETAIL.

HOWEVER, DIPLOMATIC SOURCES STATED THAT THE SOLDIERS WILL BE "CONFINED" TO THEIR RESPECTIVE GARRISONS AND ADDED THAT THEY INCLUDE "FIVE OFFICERS."

FRANCISCO ESTRADA, A SALVADORAN PRIEST WHO WAS APPOINTED NEW RECTOR OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY (UCA), SAID THAT "THE PRESIDENT'S ANNOUNCEMENT THAT MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES COMMITTED THIS CRIME, IS AN IMPORTANT STEP VERY SELDOM TAKEN IN THIS COUNTRY." HOWEVER, THIS "MATTER IS NOT OVER WITH YET."

"WHAT WOULD REALLY BE NEW IS FOR HIM TO SAY WHO DID IT, INSTEAD OF JUST SAYING THAT IT WAS THE ARMED FORCES," THE PRIEST TOLD ACAN-EFE AND ADDED THAT HE TRUSTS IN THE "GOODWILL AND ETHICS" OF PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI.

EVERY SOURCE CONSULTED WITH BY ACAN-EFE, WHETHER DIPLOMATIC OR RELIGIOUS, AGREED TO SAY THAT NOW IT IS IMPORTANT FOR CRISTIANI TO TAKE ONE STEP FURTHER AND MENTION THE NAMES OF THE PEOPLE INVOLVED IN THIS MURDER CARRIED OUT AT UCA.

TWO DOMESTIC SERVANTS (A MOTHER AND A DAUGHTER) WERE KILLED TOGETHER WITH THE CLERGYMEN, FIVE SPANIARDS, INCLUDING UCA RECTOR IGNACIO ELLACURIA, AND A SALVADORAN.

THE U.S. EMBASSY IN EL SALVADOR ALSO CONGRATULATED CRISTIANI TODAY FOR HIS EFFORTS TO CLARIFY THE ASSASSINATION, AS U.S. CONGRESSMEN AND OFFICIALS OF THE [GEORGE] BUSH ADMINISTRATION HAD ASKED OF HIM.

IN FACT, DIPLOMATIC SOURCES COMMENTED TO ACAN-EFE THAT BEGINNING ON 22 JANUARY, THE U.S. CONGRESS IS TO DISCUSS A NEW $90 MILLION PACKAGE OF ECONOMIC AND MILITARY AID TO EL SALVADOR THAT MIGHT HINGE ON THE STATUS OF THE INVESTIGATIONS.

THE UNITED STATES HAS GIVEN OVER $3 BILLION IN MILITARY AND ECONOMIC AID TO EL SALVADOR OVER THE PAST DECADE, AND AT PRESENT IT IS GIVING ABOUT $1.4 MILLION DAILY, ACCORDING TO SALVADORAN POLITICAL SOURCES.

UCA RECTOR FRANCISCO ESTRADA SAID THAT CRISTIANI COULD TAKE THIS STEP BECAUSE "HE IS CONFIDENT THAT HE CAN CONTROL ANY INTERNAL RESENTMENT WITHIN HIS GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES."

A SIMILAR OPINION WAS EXPRESSED BY A EUROPEAN DIPLOMAT, WHO TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT CRISTIANI IS TAKING A GREAT RISK BY ACCUSING MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES OF THIS CRIME. HE ADDED: " IF HE HAS DONE THIS, IT IS BECAUSE HE FEELS VERY SELF-CONFIDENT."

OBSERVERS COMPARE THE INVESTIGATION BEING CARRIED OUT BY THE PRESENT RIGHTIST GOVERNMENT WITH ONE CARRIED OUT BY THE GOVERNMENT OF JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE, A CHRISTIAN DEMOCRAT, INTO THE 1980 MURDER OF SALVADORAN ARCHBISHOP OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO.

DUARTE, WHO TURNED OVER POWER TO CRISTIANI ON 1 JUNE 1989, ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS ATTRIBUTED THE MURDER OF ARCHBISHOP ROMERO TO ROBERTO D' AUBUISSON, A PRESENT DEPUTY AND LEADER OF THE RULING NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE, BUT THE INVESTIGATIONS NEVER LED TO ANY CONCRETE RESULTS.

DEV-MUC3-1041 (TRW)

MADRID (SPAIN), 8 JAN 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] HERE IN MADRID, THE LEFT-WING LEADER OF THE SALVADORAN OPPOSITION, RUBEN ZAMORA, HAD A MEETING JUST A FEW MINUTES' AGO WITH FOREIGN MINISTER FRANCISCO FERNANDEZ ORDONEZ, BEFORE STARTING A EUROPEAN TOUR SEEKING AID TO OVERCOME THE CRISIS FACING THE CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRY. GLORIA DEL CAMPO REPORTS FROM THE FOREIGN MINISTRY, SANTA CRUZ PALACE:

[DEL CAMPO] RUBEN ZAMORA BELIEVES THAT IF, AS IT HAS BEEN ANNOUNCED, OFFICIALS OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY ARE TO BE BROUGHT TO TRIAL FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF SIX JESUITS AND TWO EMPLOYEES OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY, IT WILL BE THE FIRST TIME THAT THIS HAS BEEN DONE AND THAT, TO A LARGE EXTENT, THIS IS DUE TO THE PRESSURE OF COUNTRIES LIKE SPAIN, THE EEC, AND THE REST OF THE WORLD. BUT, SPEAKING TO RNE, RUBEN ZAMORA EXPRESSED HIS RESERVATIONS ABOUT THE REAL IDENTITY AND RESPONSIBILITY OF THE PERPETRATORS OF THE MASSACRE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ZAMORA] PRESIDENT CRISTIANI HAS STILL NOT GIVEN ANY NAMES AND SO WE CAN'T SAY ANYTHING BECAUSE IT'S ALL BASED ON RUMORS. THEREFORE, THE FIRST THING TO BE SEEN IS WHO IS INVOLVED AND, SECONDLY, WHETHER THEY ARE REALLY BROUGHT TO TRIAL AND, THIRDLY, WHETHER THEY REALLY ARE SENTENCED FOR THE CRIME WHICH THEY HAVE COMMITTED. SO, THERE ARE STILL MANY OBSTACLES IN THE WAY BEFORE GIVING A FINAL OPINION ON THE MATTER. [END RECORDING]

[DEL CAMPO] RUBEN ZAMORA HAD A 45-MINUTE MEETING WITH SPANISH FOREIGN MINISTER FRANCISCO FERNANDEZ ORDONEZ AT THE FOREIGN MINISTRY. HE EXPRESSED THE NEED FOR AND URGENCY OF A POLITICAL SOLUTION IN EL SALVADOR, OF AIDING -- THROUGH THE MEDIATION OF THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL -- NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT GUERRILLAS. HE EXPLAINED THE SITUATION OF THE DEMOCRATIC FORCES IN EL SALVADOR AND THE NEED FOR THE POLITICAL ARENA TO BE OPENED UP TO PROMOTE THE PEACE PROCESS.

DEV-MUC3-1042 (TRW)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 12 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] SOME 150 PEOPLE THREW STONES AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY IN PANAMA CITY TODAY TO PROTEST THE PRESENCE AT THE EMBASSY OF 12 REFUGEES CLOSELY LINKED TO FORMER GENERAL MANUEL ANTONIO NORIEGA.

RESIDENTS OF A NEARBY NEIGHBORHOOD GATHERED IN FRONT OF THE EMBASSY SHOUTING SLOGANS AGAINST THE MILITARY AND CIVILIAN REFUGEES, WHOM THEY SHOUTED SHOULD BE "SHOT," AND AGAINST THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT FOR GRANTING THEM ASYLUM.

THE DEMONSTRATORS, WHO BROKE THE WINDSHIELDS OF SOME VEHICLES PASSING IN FRONT OF THE EMBASSY, WERE FORCED AWAY FROM THE FRONT OF THE EMBASSY BY MEMBERS OF THE PANAMANIAN PUBLIC FORCE AND U.S. SOLDIERS.

THE PANAMANIANS WHO SOUGHT SHELTER AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY ARE MAJOR EDGARDO LOPEZ GRIMALDO, SPOKESMEN OF THE FORMER DEFENSE FORCES; MAJOR GONZALO GONZALEZ, CHIEF OF THE ELITE "MACHO DE MONTE" COMPANY; NORIEGA'S FORMER SECRETARY, MARCELA TASON; CAPTAIN NARCISA CASTILLERO; MAJOR HERACLIDES SUCRE; AND SEVEN RELATIVES OF THE ABOVE-MENTIONED PEOPLE.

SUCRE WAS CHARGED TODAY BY PANAMANIAN ATTORNEY GENERAL ROGELIO CRUZ WITH BEING INVOLVED IN THE ASSASSINATION OF MAJOR MOISES GIROLDI, WHO PROMOTED A FOILED COUP AGAINST NORIEGA ON 3 OCTOBER 1989.

PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA TODAY EXPRESSED HIS WILLINGNESS TO PROTECT "AS LONG AS NECESSARY" THE FORMER NORIEGA AIDES WHO SOUGHT SHELTER AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY IN PANAMA.

PERU ANNOUNCED ON 9 JANUARY THAT IT HAS GRANTED ASYLUM TO FIVE PANAMANIAN MILITARY AND SEVEN OF THEIR RELATIVES. THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT SAID ON 12 JANUARY THAT IT WILL NOT GRANT SAFE-CONDUCT FOR THESE PEOPLE, WHOM IT CONSIDERS "COMMON CRIMINALS," TO LEAVE THE COUNTRY.

THE U.S. GOVERNMENT ON 11 JANUARY SAID THE PANAMANIAN PUBLIC FORCE IS IN CHARGE OF GUARDING THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY AND POINTED OUT THAT THE SOLUTION TO THE CRISIS POSED BY THE PRESENCE OF THE REFUGEES SHOULD BE HANDLED BY THE GOVERNMENTS OF PANAMA AND PERU.

THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENT SAID TODAY THAT THE GOVERNMENT OF PANAMANIAN PRESIDENT GUILLERMO ENDARA IS "UNLAWFUL." HE ADDED THAT PANAMA IS BEING RULED BY "THE STATE DEPARTMENT, THE PENTAGON, THE SOUTHERN COMMAND, AND THE U.S. TROOPS."

DEV-MUC3-1043 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 10 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] A MILITARY SOURCE, QUOTING INTELLIGENCE SOURCES, SAID TODAY THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS HAVE ABANDONED THEIR STRICTLY MILITARY GOALS TO INSTEAD DIRECT THEIR ACTIONS AGAINST ECONOMIC TARGETS, WITHIN THEIR USUAL PATTERN OF WEARING DOWN THE ECONOMY.

THE SOURCE ATTRIBUTED THE CHANGE IN TACTICS TO THE "FAILURE" OF THE OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) ON 11 NOVEMBER, IN WHICH SIX GUERRILLA COMMANDERS AND ALL GUERRILLA TROOPS TOOK PART.

ACCORDING TO THE FMLN, THE OFFENSIVE'S GOAL WAS TO NEGOTIATE WITH THE GOVERNMENT ON A "ONE-TO-ONE" BASIS. IN THE OPINION OF THE ARMY, HOWEVER, THE FMLN WAS TRYING TO CAUSE AN INSURRECTION AMONG THE PEOPLE TO GRAB POWER.

THE SOURCE, WHO REQUESTED ANONYMITY, TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT FOLLOWING THE OFFENSIVE, THE FMLN DECIDED TO "READAPT" THEIR MILITARY CADRES TO THE TRADITIONAL "PROLONGED PEOPLE'S WAR."

MILITARY INTELLIGENCE BELIEVES THAT WITH THIS CHANGE IN TACTICS, THE GUERRILLAS ARE TRYING TO "MAINTAIN THEIR MILITARY PRESENCE AND THUS RAISE THE FIGHTERS MORALE FOLLOWING THE DISBANDING OF IMPORTANT MILITARY CADRES."

FOLLOWING THE SUSPENSION OF THE UNILATERAL TRUCE DECREED BY THE FMLN BETWEEN 23 DECEMBER AND 2 JANUARY, THE GUERRILLAS RESTARTED THEIR ACTIONS AGAINST THE COUNTRY'S ECONOMY BY BLOWING-UP THE COUNTRY'S POWER GRID AND SHOPS IN SAN SALVADOR.

ECONOMIC LOSSES LAST YEAR DUE TO GUERRILLA SABOTAGE TO THE TRANSPORT, POWER AND TELEPHONE SYSTEMS, AND OTHER INFRASTRUCTURES SURPASSED $100 MILLION, ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES.

THE SOURCE SAID THAT THE MILITARY RESTRUCTURE ENCOMPASSED THE SIX ORGANIZATIONS THAT COMPRISE THE FMLN: THE REVOLUTIONARY PARTY OF CENTRAL AMERICAN WORKERS (PRTC), THE NATIONAL RESISTANCE (RN), THE SALVADORAN COMMUNIST PARTY (PCS), THE POPULAR LIBERATION FORCES (FPL), THE ARMED FORCES OF LIBERATION (FAL), AND THE PEOPLE'S REVOLUTIONARY ARMY (ERP).

ACCORDING TO MILITARY INTELLIGENCE, THE PRTC, RN, AND THE PCS NOW OPERATE IN SAN SALVADOR AND OTHER IMPORTANT CITIES OF THE COUNTRY, WHILE THE FPL OPERATES IN THE CENTRAL REGION, THE ERP IN THE NORTHEAST, AND THE FAL IN THE SOUTHEAST.

DEV-MUC3-1044 (TRW)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 13 JAN 90 (LA PRENSA) -- [ARTICLE] [MANOLO ALVAREZ CEDENO] [TEXT] SOME 150 PERSONS PICKETED AND THREW STONES AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY ON 12 JANUARY. THE DEMONSTRATORS DEMANDED THAT FORMER PANAMA DEFENSE FORCES [FDP] MAJOR EDGARDO LOPEZ GRIMALDO, AND OTHERS CLOSELY LINKED TO THE FORMER MILITARY REGIME WHO SOUGHT REFUGE AT THE EMBASSY, BE ASKED TO LEAVE THE MISSION.

THE DEMONSTRATORS SHOUTED SLOGANS AGAINST NORIEGA AND THREW SOME STONES. THEY BROKE THE REAR WINDSHIELDS OF TWO DIPLOMATIC VEHICLES PARKED IN FRONT OF THE EMBASSY: A WHITE MITSUBISHI, LICENSE PLATES CD-325, AND A RED MITSUBISHI, LICENSE PLATES CD-142.

"GRIMALDO...COWARD KILLER, COME OUT AND SHOW YOUR FACE," THE CROWD SHOUTED WHILE THE U.S. SOLDIERS GUARDING THE MISSION GENTLY MOVED THEM IN THE DIRECTION OF THE SIDEWALK ACROSS THE STREET. SOME EIGHT MEMBERS OF THE NEW PANAMANIAN PUBLIC FORCE, ALSO GUARDING THE EMBASSY, DID NOT INTERVENE.

DESPITE THE SHOUTS DEMANDING "JUSTICE AND PRISON" FOR NORIEGA'S FOLLOWERS, NO ONE CAME OUT OF THE EMBASSY LOCATED ON "F" STREET, EL CANGREJO, A MIDDLE-CLASS NEIGHBORHOOD IN PANAMA CITY.

MAJOR GONZALO GONZALEZ, COMMANDER OF THE ELITE "MACHO DE MONTE" COMPANY THAT FOILED THE 3 OCTOBER COUP AGAINST NORIEGA; HERACLIDES SUCRE, WHO HAS BEEN IDENTIFIED AS ONE OF THE TWO OFFICERS WHO "SHOT" MOISES GIROLDI; AND MARCELA TASON, NORIEGA'S PERSONAL SECRETARY ARE ALSO AT THE EMBASSY WITH LOPEZ GRIMALDO, WHO WAS THE SPOKESMAN FOR THE DISMANTLED FDP.

APPROXIMATELY 40 U.S. SOLDIERS, SUPPORTED BY AN ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIER AND THREE "HUMMER" ARMORED VEHICLES, ARE GUARDING THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY.

AT THE TIME OF THE DEMOSTRATIONS, RESIDENTS IN NEARBY BUILDINGS WAVED WHITE HANDERCHIEFS AND BANGED POTS AND PANS, AND EMPTY CANS. A SIMILAR SITUATION WAS OCCURRING ON THE STREET.

ONE OF THE DEMONSTRATORS TOLD LA PRENSA: "WE WILL STAY HERE UNTIL THEY COME OUT BECAUSE THEY MUST PAY FOR THEIR CRIMES; WE WILL COME BACK HERE EVERY AFTERNOON."

THE U.S. SOLDIERS CORDONED OFF THE AREA WITH CONCERTINA WIRE WHILE A GROUP OF PEOPLE "BOOED" THEM FOR DOING THIS.

DEV-MUC3-1045 (TRW)

BOGOTA, 13 JAN 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT MINISTER CARLOS LEMOS SIMMONDS SAID ON 12 JANUARY THAT AS LONG AS THE GUERRILLA GROUPS CONTINUE TO RESPOND TO THE GOVERNMENT'S PEACE EFFORTS WITH MILITARY ACTIONS, THE GOVERNMENT'S RESPONSE WILL ALSO HAVE TO RESPOND MILITARILY. MINISTER LEMOS WAS REFERRING TO THE CURRENT ATTACKS WHICH HAVE BEEN LAUNCHED BY SEVERAL REBEL GROUPS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY. MINISTER LEMOS SAID THAT THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH IS WORRIED ABOUT THE COUNTRY'S PUBLIC ORDER, AND ADDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS DETERMINED TO USE THE ARMY AND THE POLICE TO FIGHT VIOLENCE.

LIKEWISE, LEMOS SIMMONDS DESCRIBED THE GUERRILLA GROUPS STILL LAUNCHING ATTACKS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY AS ANACHRONIC AND OUT-DATED. HE SAID THAT WE HOPE THIS SITUATION WILL CHANGE SOON, AND STRESSED THAT SEEING WHAT IS HAPPENING IN EASTERN EUROPE, WE CANNOT UNDERSTAND WHY MANY OF THE REBEL GROUPS ARE BENT ON IMPOSING A SYSTEM THAT THEY CONSIDER IDEAL WHEN IT IS BEING REJECTED AND REPUDIATED BY SO MANY STATES THAT IMPOSED IT. MINISTER LEMOS SAID THAT THE THE GUERRILLA ACTION SHOULD BE UP-DATED; THE REBELS SHOULD STOP AND CONSIDER WHETHER THE STRUGGLE THEY ARE WAGING IS WORTH IT SINCE THE SYSTEM THEY ARE DEFENDING IS SOMETHING OF THE PAST.

MINISTER LEMOS ALSO TALKED ABOUT THE WAVE OF KIDNAPPINGS THAT IS ROCKING THE COUNTRY. HE SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND DEFENSE MINISTRIES ARE TAKING SPECIAL MEASURES TO DEAL WITH THE SITUATION. HE SAID THAT WE CANNOT CONTINUE TO JUSTIFY THE USE OF KIDNAPPING AS A POLITICAL WEAPON AND ADDED THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL DEAL WITH ALL THOSE INVOLVED IN KIDNAPPINGS AS COMMON CRIMINALS. THE MINISTER ALSO ASKED THE PEOPLE TO COOPERATE WITH THE AUTHORITIES IN LOCATING THOSE AREAS WHERE THE BANDS OF CRIMINALS ARE OPERATING.

THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER ALSO TALKED ABOUT A DIALOGUE WITH THE REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA, FARC, AND SAID THAT TALKING ABOUT A DIALOGUE IS USELESS IF THEY CONTINUE THEIR SUBVERSIVE ACTIVITIES.

DEV-MUC3-1047 (TRW)

NO CITY (EL SALVADOR), NO DATE -- [SPEECH] [PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] NOW THAT THE INVESTIGATION HAS ADVANCED TO A SIGNIFICANT POINT, I BELIEVE THE TIME IS RIGHT TO SAY THAT THE RESULTS OBTAINED THUS FAR RESPOND TO THE WIDESPREAD OUTCRY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE - - IN THE SENSE THAT THOSE CHARGED WITH CRIMINAL ACTIONS STAND TRIAL SO CRIMINALS ARE NOT LEFT UNPUNISHED. THIS IS THE COMMITMENT OF THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND THE ARMED FORCES. HOWEVER, IT IS WISE TO CLARIFY THAT, IN THE SAME MANNER THAT PEOPLE HAVE MADE DEMANDS AND CONDEMNED THE CASE AT ISSUE TODAY, ACTIONS RESULTING FROM THE WAVE OF FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TERRORIST VIOLENCE SHOULD ALSO BE CONDEMNED AND PUNISHED WITH THE SAME VEHEMENCE.

IN THE SAME MANNER, AGAIN WE WANT TO URGE ALL SALVADORANS TO ABSTAIN FROM SPECULATING OVER THESE REGRETTABLE INCIDENTS, BECAUSE THAT WILL ONLY HINDER THE JUDICIAL PROCESS. IT IS NECESSARY THAT LAW AND JUSTICE PREVAIL IN OUR COUNTRY, SO THAT NO ONE TRAMPLES ON THEM.

IN REGARD TO THIS INVESTIGATION, WE WISH TO REAFFIRM THAT AN OBJECTIVITY HAS PREVAILED AT ALL TIMES, AND THAT THE ACCUSED WILL BE SENT TO THE PERTINENT COURT SO THAT THEY STAND TRIAL ACCORDING TO THE MECHANISMS ESTABLISHED IN THE CONSTITUTION AND IN OTHER LAWS.

IN CONCLUSION, WE WANT TO TELL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THAT, ALTHOUGH IT IS TRUE THIS IS A REGRETTABLE INCIDENT, WE MUST ACCEPT IT AS AN UNAVOIDABLE REALITY AND AS EVIDENCE TO THE WORLD THAT WE SALVADORANS AND OUR INSTITUTIONS HAVE A HIGH SENSE OF JUSTICE, MORALITY, AND ETHICS.

AS COMMANDER OF THE ARMED FORCES, I WANT TO CONGRATULATE ALL ITS MEMBERS FOR THEIR PROFESSIONALISM, DEDICATION, AND EXEMPLARY CONDUCT, EVIDENCED NOT ONLY IN VIEW OF THIS INCIDENT, BUT ALSO BY HALTING -- IN DEFENSE OF DEMOCRACY AND PEACE -- THE FMLN TERRORIST AGGRESSION. THAT BRILLIANT HISTORIC EVENT WILL ALWAYS BE PRESENT IN THE HEARTS OF OUR PEOPLE, WHO WILL RENDER HOMAGE TO THE ARMED FORCES FOR HAVING PROTECTED THE FREEDOM OF OUR FUTURE GENERATIONS.

THANK YOU VERY MUCH. MAY GOD BLESS YOU.

DEV-MUC3-1052 (TRW)

BOGOTA, 17 JAN 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] ON LEARNING OF THE EXTRADITABLES' STATEMENT CONCERNING THE RELEASE OF KIDNAPPED PERSONS AND THE SUSPENSION OF DRUG- TRAFFICKING ACTIVITIES, GOVERNMENT MINISTER CARLOS LEMOS SIMMONDS, EXPRESSING HIS SATISFACTION, SAID TODAY THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS WON THE WAR AGAINST DRUG-TRAFFICKING WITHOUT ENGAGING IN ANY NEGOTIATIONS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [LEMOS SIMMONDS] I AM VERY PLEASED, KNOWING THAT WE HAVE FULFILLED OUR DUTIES AND THAT THE AUTHORITIES WHO IMPLEMENTED THE NO-DEAL POLICY HAVE WON A WAR THAT MANY BELIEVED HAD BEEN LOST. [END RECORDING]

MINISTER LEMOS SIMMONDS ALSO SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT REVERSE ITS EXTRADITION POLICY BECAUSE EXTRADITIONS ARE A LEGAL TOOL THAT HAS BEEN IN EFFECT IN COLOMBIA SINCE 1888.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [LEMOS SIMMONDS] I SIGNED THE DECREE THAT REESTABLISHED ADMINISTRATIVE EXTRADITION PROCEDURES, AND I SIGNED IT WITH COMPLETE AWARENESS. I CANNOT SAY ANYTHING DIFFERENT NOW FROM WHAT I SAID 4 OR 5 MONTHS AGO. [END RECORDING]

THE MINISTER SAID THE GOVERNMENT WILL NOT NEGOTIATE WITH THE DRUG-TRAFFICKERS, BUT ALSO WILL NOT ACT ARROGANTLY IN DEFEATING THEM. HE ADDED THAT NEW MEASURES AIMED AT STOPPING KIDNAPPINGS IN THE COUNTRY ARE BEING STUDIED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [LEMOS SIMMONDS] OF COURSE NOT ALL THE KIDNAPPED PEOPLE HAVE BEEN RELEASED. LET US HOPE THAT THE DRUG-TRAFFICKERS AND EXTRADITABLES' PROMISE -- THAT NO ONE WILL BE KIDNAPPED AGAIN -- IS KEPT. THE TRUTH IS I CANNOT SAY THAT THERE WILL BE NO MORE KIDNAPPINGS. [END RECORDING]

THE GOVERNMENT HAS CONSIDERED THE POSSIBILITY OF SUSPENDING THE EXTRADITION OF DRUG-TRAFFICKERS TO THE UNITED STATES IF THEY PUT DOWN THEIR WEAPONS AND SUSPEND THEIR DRUG SHIPMENTS ABROAD.

DEV-MUC3-1054 (TRW)

BRIDGETOWN (BARBADOS), 18 JAN 90 (CANA) -- [TEXT] CARIBBEAN RIGHTS, WHICH GROUPS SEVEN HUMAN RIGHTS ORGANISATIONS IN THE REGION, ON THURSDAY JOINED AMNESTY INTERNATIONAL IN A CAMPAIGN DENOUNCING WHAT WAS DESCRIBED AS THE "INHUMANE AND VIOLENT CONDITIONS" PERPETRATED BY THE PERUVIAN ARMED FORCES.

IN A CABLE TO PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA, CARIBBEAN RIGHTS CALLED UPON THE AUTHORITIES TO INVESTIGATE ALL CASES OF EXTRAJUDICIAL EXECUTIONS AND TO PUNISH THOSE RESPONSIBLE. THE GROUP SAID THAT PREVIOUSLY THE MAJORITY OF THE VICTIMS WERE PEASANT FAMILIES IN REMOTE AREAS AND THAT THE VICTIMISATION HAS NOW BEEN EXTENDED TO THE DENSELY POPULARED DISTRICTS.

THE VICTIMS INCLUDE HUMAN RIGHTS ACTIVISTS, TRADE UNIONISTS, LAWYERS, JOURNALISTS, AND OTHERS WHO TRY TO EXPOSE ABUSES AT THE LOCAL AND INTERNATIONAL LEVELS, THE CABLE SAID. CHILDREN WERE REPORTED TO BE PRIME TARGETS.

A RECENT REPORT PUBLISHED BY AMNESTY STATED THAT TORTURE, MURDER, RAPE, AND DISAPPEARANCES WERE METHODS ADOPTED BY THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT IN COMBATING VIOLENT OPPOSITION GROUPS LIKE THE "SHINING PATH" GUERRILLAS. IT SAID MOST OF THE VICTIMS WERE SECONDARY SCHOOL CHILDREN WHO ARE A MAJOR RECRUITMENT TARGET FOR THE SHINING PATH.

THE BARBADOS-BASED CARIBBEAN RIGHTS STRESSED IN ITS CABLE THAT IT WAS AWARE OF THE PROBLEMS THE GOVERNMENT WAS FACING WITH THE GUERRILLAS BUT EMPHASISED THAT IT WAS THE ULTIMATE RESPONSIBILITY OF THE GOVERNMENT TO UPHOLD LAW EVEN IN THE FACE OF VIOLENT OPPOSITION.

DEV-MUC3-1055 (TRW)

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 19 JAN 90 (TELEVEN CANAL 10) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA AND BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA BY MODERATOR NAPOLEON BRAVO AND TEODORO PETKOFF, LEADER OF THE VENEZUELAN MOVEMENT FOR SOCIALISM (MAS)] [TEXT] [BRAVO] WE ALREADY HAVE AUDIO AND VIDEO SIGNALS WITH LIMA AND LA PAZ. WE TALKED WITH PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA A FEW MINUTES AGO. GOOD MORNING AGAIN PRESIDENT GARCIA. GOOD MORNING PRESIDENT PAZ ZAMORA. CAN YOU HEAR ME?

[PAZ ZAMORA] YES, I CAN HEAR YOU. GOOD MORNING, NAPOLEON BRAVO. IT IS MY PLEASURE TO BE TALKING TO YOU TODAY.

[BRAVO] IT IS ALSO A PLEASURE FOR US. WE HAVE TEODORO PETKOFF, LEADER OF MAS HERE IN THE STUDIO. AS YOU, PRESIDENT GARCIA, AND TEODORO PETKOFF AGREED, THE TOPIC TO BE DISCUSSED HERE TODAY IS LATIN AMERICA'S FUTURE OVER THE NEXT 10 YEARS. YOU WILL DISCUSS THE INCREASING IMPOVERISHMENT OF THE CONTINENT, THE POPULATION EXPLOSION, AND ECONOMIC GROWTH.

THE FIRST QUESTION IS FOR PRESIDENT GARCIA. MR PRESIDENT, IN YOUR OPINION AND TAKING INTO ACCOUNT ALL THE PROBLEMS THAT LATIN AMERICA IS CURRENTLY EXPERIENCING, INCLUDING THE FOREIGN DEBT AND ECONOMIC STAGNATION, WHAT CAN LATIN AMERICA EXPECT OVER THE NEXT 10 YEARS?

[GARCIA] [WORDS INDISTINCT] SOCIALISM, I HAVE, HOWEVER, [WORD INDISTINCT] DIFFICULT REGARDING LATIN AMERICA'S FUTURE. WE CANNOT [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE FOREIGN DEBT [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] EXPLOITATION OF OUR COUNTRIES OVER THE PAST 10 YEARS. WE CANNOT FORGET THAT OVER THE PAST 10 YEARS, LATIN AMERICA HAS BEEN EXPORTING CAPITAL AND THAT [WORDS INDISTINCT] PAID $250 BILLION OVER THE PAST 10 YEARS [WORDS INDISTINCT], $430,000 AFTER THE BEGINNING OF THE DECADE [WORDS INDISTINCT] $190,000.

[WORDS INDISTINCT] POLITICAL AND MILITARY INTERVENTIONISM [WORDS INDISTINCT] WHICH THE CASE OF PANAMA CONFIRMS. [WORDS INDISTINCT] DEMOCRATIC OR TOTALITARIAN SOCIETIES [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] AND ALL ENDANGERS THE VERY EXISTENCE OF LATIN AMERICA INSOFAR AS THERE IS NOT A PROMPT AND VIGOROUS REACTION FROM ALL THE LATIN AMERICAN POLITICAL LEADERS TO STRENGTHEN OUR PEOPLES' UNITY. THAT UNITY WILL SERVE AS AN ANTI-IMPERIALIST INSTRUMENT OF DEFENSE AND AS AN INSTRUMENT FOR SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT.

[WORDS INDISTINCT] FAVORABLE CONDITIONS FOR OUR CONTINENT OVER THE NEXT 10 YEARS. THAT IS THE ESSENTIAL PROTEST OF ALL THE LATIN AMERICAN MOVEMENTS THAT EMPHASIZE THE NEED FOR DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM, RESPECT FOR LATIN AMERICAN FREEDOM, AND ESPECIALLY RESPECT FOR LATIN AMERICAN UNITY.

[BRAVO] THANK YOU MR PRESIDENT. PRESIDENT PAZ ZAMORA, I AM GOING TO ASK YOU THE SAME QUESTION. IN YOUR OPINION, AND TAKING INTO ACCOUNT THE INCREASING IMPOVERISHMENT IN LATIN AMERICA, POPULATION EXPLOSION, THE DRUG TRAFFICKING PROBLEM, THE CURRENT LATIN AMERICAN ECONOMIC GROWTH, AND THE FOREIGN DEBT PROBLEM, ABOUT WHICH IN FACT I THINK I HEARD -- AND I SAY I THINK, BECAUSE IT WAS TOO EARLY IN THE MORNING -- OVER THE ECO LATIN AMERICAN TELEVISION NETWORK THIS MORNING THAT YOU ARE SOLVING THE FOREIGN DEBT PROBLEM, WHAT IS LATIN AMERICA'S FUTURE FOR THE LAST DECADE OF THIS CENTURY?

[PAZ] MY FRIEND NAPOLEON BRAVO, I HAVE A FAIRLY OPTIMISTIC VIEWPOINT WITH REGARD TO LATIN AMERICA'S FUTURE FOR THIS LAST DECADE OF THE CENTURY. I BELIEVE WE MUST ADMIT THAT DESPITE ALL THE DIFFICULTIES, THE FOREIGN DEBT PROBLEM, THE MISERY THAT EXISTS ON OUR CONTINENT, THE POPULATION EXPLOSION, AND OTHER PROBLEMS, SINCE THE LATIN AMERICAN REPUBLICS WERE FORMED, OUR CONTINENT HAS NEVER BEEN BETTER THAN TODAY. IN OTHER WORDS, SINCE THE LATIN AMERICAN REPUBLICS WERE FORMED, WE HAVE NEVER HAD ALMOST 90 PERCENT OF THE CONTINENT LIVING WITHIN DEMOCRATIC SYSTEMS AS WE DO NOW. WE HAVE NEVER HAD THE PERSPECTIVES WE HAD TODAY. I AM OPTIMISTIC ABOUT THE FUTURE OF MY COUNTRY, OF LATIN AMERICA, AND ESPECIALLY OF OUR THREE COUNTRIES.

I AM SO OPTIMISTIC THAT I EVEN WANT TO POINT OUT SOMETHING THAT TOUCHES OUR SOULS. WE WILL BEGIN THE DECADE BY WINNING THE WORLD SOCCER CHAMPIONSHIP IN ITALY. WE MUST NOT UNDERESTIMATE SOCCER, BECAUSE SOCCER IS CULTURE, TOO, AND REPRESENTS OUR PEOPLES' STRENGTH.

TAKING INTO ACCOUNT THAT MINE IS AN OPTIMISTIC POINT OF VIEW, I WOULD LIKE TO TELL YOU THAT OVER THE NEXT 10 YEARS, LATIN AMERICA WILL FACE A NUMBER OF PROBLEMS. ONE OF THOSE PROBLEMS WILL BE TO FIND A WAY TO REJOIN AN ECONOMIC, FINANCIAL, AND COMMERCIAL WORLD FROM WHICH LATIN AMERICA WAS GRADUALLY EXPELLED DURING THE LAST DECADE AND EVEN DURING THE 1970'S. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1057 (TRW)

BOGOTA, 19 JAN 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [STATEMENT] [TEXT] IN RESPONSE TO REPORTS DISSEMINATED BY THE MEDIA WITH REGARD TO THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING AND TERRORISM, THE COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT ADVISES THE COLOMBIA PEOPLE OF THE FOLLOWING:

1. THE GOVERNMENT'S FIRM, COHERENT, AND EFFICIENT POLICY TO ENFORCE THE LAW HAS HAD SIGNIFICANT RESULTS WITH REGARD TO THE CONTROL OF DRUG TRAFFICKING AND TERRORIST ACTIVITIES. THAT POLICY HAS CREATED A NEW SITUATION, WHICH HAS RAISED A NUMBER OF EXPECTATIONS AMONG THE PEOPLE.

2. THE ACTIONS CONDUCTED BY THE ARMED FORCES, THE NATIONAL POLICE, AND THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY HAVE BEEN SUCCESSFUL. THEY WILL CONTINUE TO BE CARRIED OUT TO COMPLETE THE DISMANTLING OF GROUPS OF MURDERERS AND NARCO-TERRORIST ORGANIZATIONS.

3. THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT AND THE ALL THE COLOMBIAN AUTHORITIES WILL CONTINUE TO FULFILL THEIR DUTY OF ENFORCING THE LAW AND BRINGING CRIMINALS BEFORE JUSTICE ACCORDING TO CONSTITUTIONAL AND LEGAL PROCEDURES AND THE OPTIONS OFFERED BY THE LAW.

4. THE STATEMENTS BY FOUR FORMER COLOMBIAN PRESIDENTS, BY THE CARDINAL AND ARCHBISHOP OF COLOMBIA, AND BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE PATRIOTIC UNION ARE PATRIOTIC ACTIONS INTENDED TO SPARE COLOMBIANS MORE SUFFERING AND PAIN. THE GOVERNMENT HIGHLY APPRECIATES THE MEANING OF THOSE STATEMENTS. THOSE STATEMENTS REPRESENT THE THREE COLOMBIAN PARTIES AND THE CHURCH. [SENTENCE AS HEARD]

5. THE COUNTRY HAS ACTED WITH CALM, CAUTION, REALISM, AND RESPONSIBILITY. THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE DID NOT LET THEMSELVES BE CARRIED AWAY BY RECKLESS EXPECTATIONS. THE COUNTRY MUST MAINTAIN THAT ATTITUDE.

6. AUTHORIZED MEDIA SPOKESMEN HAVE MENTIONED THE MANY QUESTIONS THAT THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE ASK THEMSELVES CONCERNING THAT SITUATION, WHICH ONLY THE FUTURE CAN CONVINCINGLY CLARIFY.

7. THE COUNTRY LONGS FOR THE COMPLETE END TO CRIMES, MURDERS, AND ATTACKS AGAINST PUBLIC OFFICIALS, NEWSMEN, POLITICAL LEADERS, AND MEN, WOMEN, AND CHILDREN. THE COUNTRY LONGS FOR THE RELEASE OF ALL THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN ABDUCTED AND THE DEFINITIVE SUSPENSION OF DRUG TRAFFICKING ACTIVITIES.

THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICY AND THE ENORMOUS SACRIFICES COURAGEOUSLY MADE BY THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE SEEK THOSE OBJECTIVES, AMONG OTHER THINGS.

8. NOW THAT THE STATE'S VICTORY AND THE NEED TO ABIDE BY THE COUNTRY'S LAW ARE ADMITTED, WE MUST WALK ALONG THE BEST PATH TO ENSURE THE FINAL SUCCESS OF THE GOVERNMENT'S POLICY, WHICH HAS BEEN SUPPORTED BY THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY.

DEV-MUC3-1059 (TRW)

QUITO, 18 JAN 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] A CALL FOR FREE ELECTIONS IN PANAMA, SUPPORT FOR PUERTO RICAN INDEPENDENCE, AND THE CONDEMNATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS IN GUATEMALA AND EL SALVADOR WERE SOME OF THE CONCLUSIONS REACHED AT THE END OF THE MEETING OF THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL [IS] COMMISSION FOR LATIN AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN THIS AFTERNOON IN QUITO. THE IS FOCUSED ON THE SITUATION IN PANAMA, REITERATING ITS STRONG CONDEMNATION OF THE U.S. INVASION AND DEMANDING "THE IMMEDIATE AND UNCONDITIONAL WITHDRAWAL" OF THOSE TROOPS. IT ALSO DEMANDED THAT "FREE AND DEMOCRATIC ELECTIONS BE HELD WITHOUT FOREIGN MEDDLING."

THE IS CONDEMNED THE SERIOUS HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS AND DEATHS DURING THE U.S. INVASION AND SAID IT WAS NECESSARY TO ESTABLISH AN INVESTIGATIVE COMMISSION WITH THE COOPERATION OF THE INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS. IN ADDITION, IT ASKED THAT THE TORRIJOS - CARTER TREATIES BE RESPECTED. THE GROUP ALSO DEMANDED ABSOLUTE RESPECT FOR DIPLOMATIC IMMUNITY AND SANCTITY, AND REJECTED THE ROLE OF "POLICEMAN TO PROTECT DEMOCRACY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT WANTS TO ASSIGN ITSELF." IT NOTED THE URGENCY IN JOINING EFFORTS TO FIND PATHS THAT WILL LEAD TO THE REESTABLISHMENT OF SOVEREIGNTY AND DEMOCRACY IN PANAMA.

MOREOVER, THE IS VOICED SUPPORT FOR THE EFFORTS THE PUERTO RICAN INDEPENDENTIST PARTY IS MAKING TO GET THE U.S. CONGRESS TO ALLOW A REFERENDUM IN PUERTO RICO. THE REFERENDUM WILL LET PUERTO RICANS DECIDE THEIR POLITICAL FUTURE, WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF INDEPENDENCE SOME AREA COUNTRIES ARE DEMANDING.

THE IS COMMITTEE ALSO NOTED ITS CONCERN OVER THE CLIMATE OF INSECURITY AND REPEATED HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS THE PROPERO AVRIL GOVERNMENT IS FOSTERING IN HAITI. AFTER INDICATING THAT THIS SITUATION "IMPERILS" THE ELECTIONS SET FOR THIS YEAR, THE IS CALLED ON THE GOVERNMENT TO ADOPT THE MEASURES THAT ENSURE HUMAN RIGHTS ARE RESPECTED.

IN ADDITION, THE COMMITTEE CONDEMNED THE RECENT MURDER IN GUATEMALA OF POLITICAL LEADERS HECTOR OQUELI COLINDRES AND GILDA AMPARO FLORES AREVALO. IT ALSO ANNOUNCED A COMMISSION WILL BE SENT TO THE GOVERNMENTS OF EL SALVADOR AND GUATEMALA TO FIND THE PERSONS RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MURDERS.

ON THE TOPIC OF DRUG TRAFFICKING, THE IS COMMISSION DEMANDS THAT THE GOVERNMENTS OF THE DEVELOPING COUNTRIES ADOPT THE MEASURES NEEDED TO LOWER INTERNAL DISTRIBUTION AND CONSUMPTION OF DRUGS AND TO FIGHT MONEY LAUNDERING.

IN CONCLUSION, THE COMMISSION DISCUSSED A PRELIMINARY REPORT BY AN IS MISSION THAT VISITED NICARAGUA TO OBSERVE THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN. THE REPORT NOTES THAT, "CONSIDERING THE COUNTRY'S SITUATION, THE MISSION FEELS THE ELECTORAL PROCESS HAS BEEN SATISFACTORY SO FAR."

ENRIQUE SILVA CIMMA, IS VICE PRESIDENT AND FUTURE CHILEAN FOREIGN MINISTER, CHAIRED THE 2-DAY MEETING THAT GATHERED 64 POLITICAL LEADERS FROM 10 COUNTRIES OF THE REGION AND GUESTS FROM THE UNITED STATES, FRG, ISRAEL, THE INTERNATIONAL SOCIALIST OF WOMEN, AND THE INTER-AMERICAN REGIONAL ORGANIZATION OF WORKERS.

SILVA CIMMA SAID THAT THIS AND OTHER MEETINGS DO NOT AIM AT SETTING GUIDELINES THE PARTIES ARE OBLIGATED TO FOLLOW. INSTEAD, THE MEETINGS ALLOW PARTIES TO EXCHANGE VIEWS REGARDING THE NEED TO DEAL WITH THE FUNDAMENTAL VIEWS OF THIS IDEOLOGICAL CONCEPT WITHIN THE BASIC IDEAL OF DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM.

DEV-MUC3-1060 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 19 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [ARTICLE] [MARISOL MARIN] [TEXT] SALVADORAN COLONEL GUILLERMO BENAVIDES GAVE THE ORDER TO ASSASSINATE SIX JESUIT PRIESTS WITH A PEREMPTORY SENTENCE: "EVERYTHING IS AT STAKE; IT IS EITHER US OR THEM. THESE HAVE BEEN THE INTELLECTUALS WHO HAVE BEEN GUIDING THE GUERRILLA GROUPS FOR A LONG TIME."

THIS IS STATED IN A RESOLUTION ISSUED THIS MORNING BY JUDGE RICARDO ZAMORA WHO ORDERED A PROVISIONAL ARREST WHILE WAITING FOR THE TRIAL OF THE EIGHT MILITARY OFFICERS IMPLICATED IN THE CRIME AND THE ARREST OF A THIRD ONE WHO HAS BEEN AT LARGE SINCE DECEMBER.

TWO LIEUTENANTS AND A SECOND LIEUTENANT HAVE ACCUSED BENAVIDES IN THEIR DEPOSITIONS AS THE PERSON WHO "GAVE THE ORDER" ON THE EVENING 15 NOVEMBER AT THE MILITARY SCHOOL HE DIRECTED AND WHICH WAS IN CHARGE OF CONTROLLING THE SECTOR WHERE THE CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY (UCA) IS LOCATED.

"WE WILL START WITH THE LEADERS. THE UNIVERSITY IS IN OUR SECTOR AND ELLACURIA IS THERE. HE MUST BE ELIMINATED AND I WANT NO WITNESSES," BENAVIDES SAID TO LIEUTENANT YUSSAY RENE MENDOZA VALLECILLOS, ACCORDING TO THE LATTER'S TESTIMONY.

A FEW HOURS LATER, EARLY IN THE MORNING OF 16 NOVEMBER, JESUIT PRIESTS IGNACIO ELLACURIA, RECTOR OF THE UCA; IGNACIO MARTIN BARO, JUAN RAMON MORENO, JOAQUIN LOPEZ Y LOPEZ, SEGUNDO MONTES (SPANIARDS), AND AMANDO LOPEZ (SALVADORAN), AS WELL AS THEIR COOK, ELBA JULIA RAMOS, AND HER DAUGHTER, CELINA MARICET RAMOS, WERE ASSASSINATED.

IT ALL HAPPENED DURING THE CURFEW AND 5 DAYS AFTER THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GUERRILLA GROUPS HAD LAUNCHED THEIR LARGEST OFFENSIVE.

BENAVIDES GAVE THE ORDER TO LIEUTENANT MENDOZA, LIEUTENANT ESPINOZA, AND SECOND LIEUTENANT GUEVARA CERRITOS, OFFICERS OF THE ATLACATL BATTALION, AN ELITE UNIT TRAINED BY THE UNITED STATES, WHICH HAD BEEN SENT TO THE MILITARY SCHOOL.

THE SOLDIERS WERE TOLD THAT IT WAS NECESSARY "TO ELIMINATE THE GUERRILLA GROUPS' INTELLECTUAL LEADERS AND THAT THEY WERE AT THE UCA," ACCORDING TO CORPORAL ANGEL PEREZ VASQUEZ' DEPOSITION.

THEY WERE ALSO TOLD THAT "THERE WAS INFORMATION THAT SOME INJURED TERRORIST CRIMINALS WOULD BE TAKEN TO THE UCA" AND THEY WERE INSISTENTLY TOLD THAT "ALL THE PEOPLE THERE WERE TERRORISTS."

ACCORDING TO SECOND SERGEANT ANTONIO RAMIRO AVALOS VARGAS' VERSION, THE MISSION MUST BE SECRETLY CARRIED OUT BECAUSE THEY WOULD FIND SUBVERSIVE MATERIAL AND OTHER KINDS OF MATERIAL THAT COULD BE USED, SUCH AS MEDICINE, BOOTS, AND CLOTHES.

ACCORDING TO THE MILITARY OFFICERS' DEPOSITIONS GATHERED IN THE JUDGE'S RESOLUTION, A FLARE WOULD BE FIRED WHEN THEY WERE ABOUT TO WITHDRAW, TO INDICATE THERE HAD BEEN A CLASH.

SECOND SERGEANT ANTONIO RAMIRO AVALOS VARGAS SAYS THAT FIVE OF THE SIX JESUITS WERE TAKEN OUT TO THE GARDEN AND ORDERED TO LIE FACE DOWN, THEN LIEUTENANT ESPINOZA ORDERED HIM AND PRIVATE MARIANO AMAYA GRIMALDI TO PROCEED.

THE THREE OFFICERS ADMITTED THAT THEY KNEW ABOUT THIS, BUT NOT ABOUT THEIR PARTICIPATION IN THE CRIME. THE FOUR SOLDIERS ADMITTED THEIR ROLE AS EXECUTIONERS, OUT OF LOYALTY TO THEIR SUPERIORS AND BECAUSE THEY WERE AFRAID THEY WOULD BE CONSIDERED TRAITORS.

THE JUDGE SAID THERE ARE "ENOUGH ELEMENTS" TO ESTABLISH THE PARTICIPATION OF COLONEL GUILLERMO BENAVIDES IN THESE ACTIONS, INCLUDING, FIRST OF ALL, THE DEPOSITION SIGNED BY COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF.

PONCE SAID HE ORDERED THE CREATION OF A SECURITY COMMANDO, WITH HEADQUARTERS IN THE MILITARY SCHOOL AND UNDER COLONEL GUILLERMO ALFREDO BENAVIDES' COMMAND, TO DEFEND THE MILITARY INSTALLATIONS LOCATED IN THE ZONE WHICH MIGHT BECOME THE TARGETS OF "A TERRORIST AGGRESSION." THE UCA IS ALSO LOCATED IN THE ZONE.

THE JUDICIAL RESOLUTION INCLUDES THE DEPOSITIONS GIVEN BY ALL THE PRISONERS TO THE POLICE, EXCEPT COL BENAVIDES, WHO MET WITH JUDGE RICARDO ZAMORA FOR OVER 2 HOURS.

THE INVESTIGATION WAS CARRIED OUT BY A CRIME INVESTIGATION COMMISSION WHICH LATER SENT THE EVIDENCE AND FINDINGS TO AN ARMY HONOR COMMISSION THAT WILL COOPERATE IN DETERMING WHO IS RESPONSIBLE.

DEV-MUC3-1061 (TRW)

LIMA, 21 JAN 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] IT WAS OFFICIALLY REPORTED TODAY IN LIMA THAT PERUVIAN SECURITY FORCES KILLED 14 TERRORISTS IN CONFRONTATIONS THAT OCCURRED ON 20 JANUARY IN SEVERAL POINTS OF THE COUNTRY.

AN INTERIOR MINISTRY COMMUNIQUE INDICATES THAT THE ARMED CONFRONTATIONS OCCURRED IN THE CENTRAL MOUNTAIN JUNIN DEPARTMENT AND IN PUNO DEPARTMENT, IN THE SOUTHEASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY.

THE DOCUMENT STATES THAT THE POLICE INTERCEPTED THE GROUP FOLLOWING A TIPOFF BY AGENTS WHO SPECIALIZE IN OBTAINING INFORMATION. THE CLASH OCCURRED IN CONRAY, TARMA PROVINCE, JUNIN DEPARTMENT, WHERE A COMBINED ARMY-NATIONAL POLICE PATROL KILLED SEVEN "SUBVERSIVE CRIMINALS" INCLUDING ONE WOMAN.

THE PATROL SEIZED TWO RIFLES, ONE CARBINE, ONE REVOLVER, AND EXPLOSIVES.

IN THE VILLAGE OF SOLLOCOTA, THE NATIONAL POLICE REPELLED A 3-HOUR ATTACK CARRIED OUT BY APPROXIMATELY 20 TERRORISTS, 4 OF WHOM DIED.

THE INTERIOR MINISTRY COMMUNIQUE INDICATES THAT A PATROL PURSUED THE ATTACKERS, WHO WITHDREW TO THE AREA OF VILCASUSUYA WHERE THE SECURITY FORCES KILLED THREE SUBVERSIVES. FIVE GUNS, HAND GRENADES, CARBINE LAUNCHED GRENADES, AND ABUNDANT QUANTITIES OF AMMUNITION WERE SEIZED.

THE DOCUMENT STATES THAT THE ARMY AND NATIONAL POLICE DID NOT SUFFER ANY CASUALTIES.

THE COMMUNIQUE ONLY DEFINES THE TERRORISTS AS "SUBVERSIVE CRIMINALS" WITHOUT INDICATING WHETHER THEY BELONG TO THE MAOIST SHINING PATH GROUP OR TO THE GUEVARIST TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA).

ACCORDING TO PRESS SOURCES, DURING THE MONTH OF JANUARY THERE HAVE BEEN APPROXIMATELY 170 DEATHS, INCLUDING THOSE OF THE 20-JANUARY CONFRONTATIONS, DUE TO PERU'S POLITICAL VIOLENCE.

A CONGRESSIONAL COMMITTEE IS STUDYING THE CAUSES OF VIOLENCE. IT HAS REPORTED THAT SINCE MAY 1980, WHEN SHINING PATH BEGAN ITS ARMED STRUGGLE, AND DECEMBER 1989 THERE HAVE BEEN 17,500 DEATHS DUE TO POLITICAL VIOLENCE.

DEV-MUC3-1063 (TRW)

MOSCOW (USSR), 23 JAN 90 (TASS INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [TEXT] FROM THE SOVIET POINT OF VIEW, THE QUESTION OF DELIVERIES OF WEAPONS TO THE GOVERNMENT OF EL SALVADOR TAKES ON, IN PRESENT CONDITIONS, A PARTICULAR SIGNIFICANCE. THIS WAS ANNOUNCED TODAY AT A BRIEFING BY GENNADIY GERASIMOV, HEAD OF THE USSR MINISTRY OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS INFORMATION DIRECTORATE, WHO REPORTED THE DEBATES OPENING IN THE U.S. CONGRESS ON GIVING U.S. MILITARY AID TO THAT COUNTRY.

IN RECENT TIMES, THE USSR FOREIGN MINISTRY SPOKESMAN NOTED, CERTAIN ADVANCES HAVE BEEN OUTLINED IN THE MATTER OF RENEWING DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE OPPOSING SIDES IN EL SALVADOR. HOWEVER, THE OPPONENTS OF NATIONAL RECONCILIATION IN THAT COUNTRY ARE TRYING TO PREVENT A CONSTRUCTIVE DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE REBELS AND ARE COUNTING ON THE CONTINUATION OF BLOODSHED. THE EL SALVADOR PRESIDENT ALFONSO CRISTIAN CONFIRMED THE INVOLVEMENT OF TROOPS IN THE MURDER OF PRIESTS. A NEW VICTIM OF THE TERROR IS HECTOR OQUELI, EXECUTIVE SECRETARY OF THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL COMMITTEE ON THE PROBLEMS OF THE COUNTRIES OF LATIN AMERICA AND THE CARIBBEAN BASIN AND ONE OF THE LEADERS OF THE NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT PARTY, SAID GENNADIY GERASIMOV.

THE LEADERSHIP OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, THE SOVIET DIPLOMAT NOTED, HAS STATED ITS DECISION TO STOP CONDUCTING FURTHER COMBAT OPERATIONS IF THE UNITED STATES HALTS ITS MILITARY AID TO THE RULING REGIME.

IN THESE CONDITIONS, GERASIMOV STRESSED, THE CONTINUATION OF ARMS SUPPLIES TO THE SALVADORAN ARMY IN FACT PLAYS INTO THE HANDS OF THOSE WHO BLATANTLY VIOLATE HUMAN RIGHTS AND DOES NOT PROMOTE THE STRENGTHENING OF THE POSITIONS OF THOSE WHO CHAMPION DIALOGUE AND NATIONAL RECONCILIATION IN EL SALVADOR. "ALL OF THAT MAY BECOME A SERIOUS OBSTACLE IN THE WAY TOWARD A PEACEFUL SETTLEMENT IN THAT COUNTRY AND CENTRAL AMERICA IN GENERAL", HE SAID.

DEV-MUC3-1065 (TRW)

BOGOTA, 23 JAN 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [TEXT] AN UNUSUAL COMMUNIQUE SIGNED BY PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA WAS DELIVERED TO EL TIEMPO NEWSPAPER DIRECTOR HERNANDO SANTOS CASTILLO. IN THIS COMMUNIQUE, ESCOBAR DENIED THAT THE MEDELLIN CARTEL IS DIVIDED AND STRESSED THAT THOSE WHO TOLD ON GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA WERE CALI CARTEL MEMBERS. FOR SEVERAL MONTHS, ESCOBAR'S GROUP HAS BEEN ENGAGED IN A FIGHT TO THE DEATH WITH THE MEMBERS OF THE CALI CARTEL.

ESCOBAR'S COMMUNIQUE EVEN GIVES THE NAME OF THE PERSON WHO COLLECTED THE REWARD FROM THE AUTHORITIES, A REWARD THAT HAD BEEN ANNOUNCED ON TELEVISION AS A PRIZE FOR DENOUNCING EL MEJICANO [RODRIGUEZ GACHA'S ALIAS].

HERE IS MORE ON THIS COMMUNIQUE:

IN A NEW EXCHANGE OF COMMUNIQUES, A PRACTICE THAT HAS BECOME COMMON NOWADAYS, ESCOBAR DECIDED TO WRITE A LETTER TO SANTOS TO CLARIFY CERTAIN DOUBTS: FIRST, TO SAY THAT HIS FRIENDS AND COLLABORATORS HAVE NOT WITHDRAWN THEIR SUPPORT AS A RESULT OF A CAMPAIGN CARRIED OUT BY THE 4TH BRIDAGE IN ANTIOQUIA, AS REPORTED IN EL TIEMPO. ESCOBAR STRESSED THAT THE BEST PROOF THAT HIS FRIENDS HAVE NOT BETRAYED OR ABANDONED HIM IS THAT HE IS STILL FREE. SECOND, HE SAID THAT IF THE GOVERNMENT EVER DECIDES TO FIGHT FOR PEACE, IT WILL FIND A LONG, ENDLESS LIST OF EXTRADITABLES, DRUG TRAFFICKERS, HENCHMEN, AND PARAMILITARY GROUP MEMBERS WHO WANT TO ACCOMPANY THE GOVERNMENT IN THAT PROCESS. THIRD, HE ACCUSED JORGE VELAZQUEZ, A MEMBER OF THE CALI CARTEL WHOSE ALIAS IS "THE NAVIGATOR," OF DENOUNCING RODRIGUEZ GACHA AND COLLECTING THE REWARD. HE ALSO ACCUSED CALI CARTEL MEMBERS OF DENOUNCING JORGE LUIS OCHOA IN PALMIRA AND OF BEING RESPONSIBLE FOR THE DISAPPEARANCE AND MURDER OF ANTIOQUIA PEOPLE WHO VISITED VALLE DEL CAUCA DEPARTMENT. ESCOBAR ALSO CHARGED THAT CALI CARTEL MEMBERS PLACED 700 KG OF DYNAMITE IN HIS FAMILY'S BUILDING. FOURTH, HE NOTED THAT HIS STRUGGLE IS AGAINST THE CALI CARTEL NOT THE VALLE DEL CAUCA PEOPLE AND ADDED: I FEEL GREAT ADMIRATION AND PROFOUND RESPECT FOR VALLE PEOPLE BECAUSE MY WIFE, VICTORIA, WAS BORN IN THAT BEAUTIFUL LAND, HER ANCESTORS ALL LIVED THERE. CONCLUDING HE SAID THAT ALTHOUGH HE HAS NEVER ACCEPTED THE CALI CARTEL'S PEACE PROPOSAL, HE HAS NEVER REJECTED DIALOGUE AS AN ALTERNATIVE FOR SOLUTIONS.

DEV-MUC3-1066 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 24 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHIEF OF THE ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF, TODAY DISCLOSED AN ALLEGED PLAN ACCORDING TO WHICH THE GUERRILLAS WILL ATTEMPT TO ATTACK MILITARY POSITIONS IN SAN SALVADOR "TO PRESSURE THE GOVERNMENT INTO NEGOTIATING A POLITICAL SOLUTION" TO THE ARMED CONFLICT.

CITING MILITARY INTELLIGENCE REPORTS, PONCE ANTICIPATED THAT "AS OF NEXT WEEKEND, UNTIL 10 FEBRUARY, THE GUERRILLAS WILL CARRY OUT TERRORIST ACTIONS AND ATTACKS ON MILITARY UNITS, PRIMARILY IN THE METROPOLITAN AREA, IN ORDER TO INFLUENCE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY IN A PROPAGANDISTIC MANNER."

"THEY ARE TRYING TO INFLUENCE THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY SO THAT IT, IN TURN, WILL MOVE TOWARD NEGOTIATING A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE ARMED CONFLICT," PONCE SAID DURING A NEWS CONFERENCE AT THE GENERAL STAFF'S HEADQUARTERS.

THE EXECUTION OF THE ALLEGED FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) PLAN WILL COINCIDE WITH SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S SCHEDULED TRIP TO THE UNITED NATIONS AT THE END OF THE MONTH.

CRISTIANI WILL MEET ON 31 JANUARY WITH UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR, TO REQUEST HIS GOOD OFFICES IN FAVOR OF RESUMING THE DIALOGUE WITH THE GUERRILLAS, WHICH WAS SUSPENDED IN OCTOBER.

FOLLOWING NOVEMBER'S GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE, THE GOVERNMENT AND FMLN HAVE EXPRESSED A WILLINGNESS TO RESUME THE DIALOGUE, WITH UNITED NATIONS PARTICIPATION.

PONCE POINTED OUT THAT THE "SPECIFIC AREAS" THE GUERRILLAS WILL ATTEMPT TO ATTACK ARE SOME OF THE MILITARY POSITIONS AT THE EL ESPINO FARM IN THE NORTHWESTERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR, AYUTUXTEPEQUE IN THE NORTHERN PART OF THE COUNTRY, ZARAGOZA AND HUIZUCAR IN THE SOUTHERN PART OF SAN SALVADOR, AND SOYAPANGO IN THE EAST.

THESE AREAS ARE AMONG THE LEADING SITES OF THE BLOODIEST CLASHES BETWEEN SOLDIERS AND GUERRILLAS DURING THE REBELS' HARSHEST OFFENSIVE 11 NOVEMBER.

THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND REBELS WAS SUSPENDED IN OCTOBER FOLLOWING A DYNAMITE ATTACK AGAINST A LABOR UNION HEADQUARTERS IN WHICH 10 WORKERS WERE KILLED AND 30 OTHERS WOUNDED.

PRIOR TO THE SUSPENSION OF THE DIALOGUE, THE GOVERNMENT AND FMLN HELD TWO ROUNDS OF TALKS IN MEXICO AND COSTA RICA, BUT FAILED TO REACH AGREEMENTS THAT WOULD HAVE ENDED THE COUNTRY'S ARMED CONFLICT.

DEV-MUC3-1069 (TRW)

TEGUCIGALPA, NO DATE (VOZ DE HONDURAS NETWORK) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH BORGE] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [MATERO] MILTON MATEO OF HRN, COMMANDER BORGE. IN RESPONSE TO A QUESTION FROM MY COLLEAGUE FROM EL SALVADOR, YOU SAID THAT YOU HOPED FOR AN AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN REBELS AND THE SALVADORAN ARMY AND GOVERNMENT. YOU, LIKE ALL CENTRAL AMERICANS, WANT PEACE, BUT DO YOU NOT THINK THAT THIS RUNS CONTRARY TO THE FACT THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS PRESENTED RELIABLE PROOF OF MILITARY AID [FROM NICARAGUA] TO THE LEFTIST SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS, AND RECENTLY, AN ARMED FORCES PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICER SAID THAT NICARAGUA IS A SANCTUARY FOR A SUBVERSIVE GROUP KNOWN AS THE CINCHONEROS OF HONDURAS?

[BORGE] AS FOR THE STATEMENT THAT NICARAGUA IS A SANCTUARY FOR A HONDURAN GUERRILLA GROUP, I WISH TO SAY THAT THE STATEMENT IS NOT ONLY FALSE, BUT A SERIOUS CHARGE. I INVITE ANYONE WHO WANTS TO COME TO NICARAGUA, INCLUDING THE HONDURAN AUTHORITIES, TO DO SO. WE WILL GIVE THEM ABSOLUTE FREEDOM TO SHOW WHERE THE CINCHONEROS CAMPS ARE LOCATED, WHERE THEIR HEADQUARTERS ARE LOCATED OR THEIR ACTIVITIES ARE BEING CARRIED OUT. IF THIS EXISTS, IT CANNOT BE HIDDEN. IT IS VERY DIFFICULT TO HIDE A MILITARY TRAINING CAMP. I ASSURE THE HONDURAN GOVERNMENT AND PEOPLE VERY SERIOUSLY AND WITH A HIGH SENSE OF RESPONSIBILITY, THAT NICARAGUA WILL NOT PROVIDE ANY OPPORTUNITY FOR GUERRILLA GROUPS FROM OTHER COUNTRIES TO ESTABLISH CAMPS IN NICARAGUA, ESPECIALLY WHEN IT CONCERNS HONDURAS.

[REPORTER] WHAT ABOUT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS?

[BORGE] MANY THINGS HAVE BEEN SAID ABOUT EL SALVADOR. IT IS SAID THAT WE SUPPLY WEAPONS TO THE SALVADORAN REVOLUTIONARIES. THIS CHARGE HAS BEEN MADE FOR MANY YEARS. I COULD SAY THAT THE AIRPLANE THAT WE DOWNED IN NICARAGUA, FLOWN BY THE FAMOUS HASENFUS, CAME FROM EL SALVADOR, BUT WHY BRING THAT UP? THE FACT IS THAT THERE EXISTS IN THE WORLD A POWERFUL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY, KNOWN AS THE CIA, WHICH HAS ENORMOUS TECHNICAL AND HUMAN RESOURCES THAT CAN ENABLE IT TO ACCURATELY DETERMINE WHAT IS HAPPENING ANYWHERE, AND YET IT HAS NEVER BEEN ABLE TO DEMONSTRATE THAT NICARAGUA IS PROVIDING WEAPONS TO ANY ARMED MOVEMENT ANYWHERE. THEREFORE, LET US PUT THAT INTO THE SAME CONTEXT AS THE STATEMENT THAT OUR RELATIONS WITH CUBA ARE COOLING. WE COULD ALSO POINT OUT OTHER LIES TOLD ABOUT US. WE HAVE BEEN ACCUSED OF ALL KINDS OF THINGS. WE HAVE BEEN CALLED DRUG TRAFFICKERS. WE ARE ACCUSED OF BURNING DOWN A JEWISH SYNAGOGUE IN NICARAGUA. INCIDENTALLY, LET ME TELL YOU THAT THERE HAS NEVER BEEN A JEWISH SYNAGOGUE IN NICARAGUA, YET THIS WAS SAID BY NO LESS THAN U.S. PRESIDENT REAGAN.

THUS, THEY TELL ALL THOSE LIES ABOUT NICARAGUA AND THAT IS ONE OF THE THINGS THAT THEY SAY, JUST AS THEY SAY THAT WE ARE THE ENEMIES OF HUMAN RIGHTS, THAT WE PERSECUTE CLERGYMEN. NOTE THAT IN NICARAGUA NO PRIEST HAS EVER BEEN IMPRISONED, MURDERED, OR EXILED, EXCEPT ON ONE OCCASION BECAUSE OF VERY SPECIAL CIRCUMSTANCES. IN NICARAGUA, WE HAVE MADE CONSCIENTIOUS EFFORTS TO RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS, BUT THE MAIN ACCUSATION LEVELED AGAINST OUR COUNTRY IS FAILURE TO RESPECT HUMAN RIGHTS.

WE ARE ACCUSED OF PLANNING ELECTORAL FRAUD. THERE WAS A POLL DONE BY A U.S. FIRM THAT GIVES THE SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FSLN]... [CHANGES THOUGHT] I WISH TO POINT OUT THAT IT IS NOT A SANDINIST COMPANY; IT MIGHT HAVE VERY LITTLE SYMPATHY FOR SANDINISM, BUT IT IS APPARENTLY A RELIABLE COMPANY. IT GIVES THE FSLN A MAJORITY OF 51 PERCENT, AND THE NATIONAL OPPOSITION UNION [UNO] -- ONE OF THE POLITICAL FORCES PARTICIPATING IN THE ELECTORAL CONTEST -- 24 PERCENT.

OTHER POLLS THAT HAVE BEEN TAKEN HAVE GIVEN THE FSLN CLOSE TO 69 PERCENT, AS OPPOSED TO UNO, TO WHICH THEY ATTRIBUTED 27 PERCENT. YET, WHAT IS BEING SAID? THAT THERE WILL BE ELECTORAL FRAUD. THEREFORE, THAT CHARGE AND OTHERS THAT HAVE BEEN MADE, LIKE THIS ONE WHICH GREATLY BOTHERS ME, TO THE EFFECT THAT WE ARE HARBORING SUBVERSIVE GROUPS FOR THEM TO COME TO HONDURAS... [CHANGES THOUGHT] I CAN GUARANTEE TO THE HONDURAN ARMED FORCES AND TO THE NEW HONDURAN GOVERNMENT THAT IN NICARAGUA WE WILL NOT TAKE A SINGLE STEP IN THAT DIRECTION.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[BORGE] ON PANAMA, I DO NOT NEED TO SAY ANYTHING. THE FACTS SPEAK FOR THEMSELVES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1070 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 15 JAN 90 (EL MUNDO) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN VICE PRESIDENT FRANCISCO MERINO LOPEZ HAS SAID THAT "THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] DOES NOT HAVE THE CAPACITY TO REPEAT A TERRORIST ATTACK LIKE THE ONE LAUNCHED ON 11 NOVEMBER BECAUSE IT DOES NOT HAVE THE LOGISTICAL OR OTHER NECESSARY SUPPORT AT THIS TIME, NOR WILL IT HAVE SUCH SUPPORT IN THE MONTHS TO COME."

MERINO SAID THAT THE FMLN REPEATS ITS TERRORIST ACTIVITIES IN CYCLES THAT MUST BE BROKEN TO PREVENT FURTHER SUFFERING AND BLOODSHED.

THE VICE PRESIDENT SAID THAT THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS HAVE LOST GROUND IN EVERY WAY AND THE DIALOGUE MUST BE RESUMED AS THE ONLY WAY TO ACHIEVE A FIRM AND LASTING PEACE IN THE COUNTRY.

"THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC HAS NEVER BEEN NAIVE REGARDING THE FMLN'S LACK OF SINCERITY DURING THE DIALOGUE, BUT IT IS OUR DUTY TO SEEK PEACE THROUGH REASON, EVEN THOUGH WE ARE AWARE OF THE FMLN'S WARLIKE ATTITUDE," MERINO SAID.

REGARDING THE FMLN'S DESIRE TO PARTICIPATE IN THE MEETING TO BE HELD BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC WITH THE SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE UNITED NATIONS IN NEW YORK, MERINO SAID THE GUERRILLAS CANNOT HOPE TO BE ON AN EQUAL FOOTING WITH THE PRESIDENT OF EL SALVADOR.

"THE PRESIDENT IS GOING TO NEW YORK TO EXPRESS, ONCE AGAIN, THE SINCERITY WITH WHICH THE GOVERNMENT SEEKS TO ACHIEVE PEACE THROUGH DIALOGUE. THE FMLN'S HOPE OF HAVING A TETE-A-TETE WITH THE PRESIDENT AT THE UNITED NATIONS IS TOTALLY ABSURD," THE VICE PRESIDENT SAID.

MERINO SAID THAT THE GUERRILLA'S ONLY WAY OUT IS TO GIVE UP THE ARMED STRUGGLE AND JOIN IN THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIC LIFE, ALTHOUGH HE CONCEDED THAT THE PROCESS WILL BE DIFFICULT AND THAT IT WILL NATURALLY HAVE TO BE GRADUAL IN ORDER FOR THE GUERRILLA FIGHTERS TO FEEL SAFE "WITHOUT HAVING A WEAPON AT THE READY."

ON THE OTHER HAND, IN REFERENCE TO THE CASE OF THE JESUITS, IN WHICH MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN IMPLICATED, MERINO ADVISED CAUTION REGARDING STATEMENTS THAT VARIOUS GROUPS IN THE COUNTRY MIGHT MAKE.

"PRUDENCE IS NECESSARY IN ORDER TO GET TO THE TRUTH," MERINO SAID. HE POINTED OUT THAT THE ADVANCES MADE IN INVESTIGATIONS OF THE CASE PROVE THE DEGREE OF DEMOCRACY THAT PREVAILS IN THE COUNTRY.

DEV-MUC3-1071 (TRW)

CLANDESTINE, 28 JAN 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON, LIFETIME PRESIDENT OF ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE], HAS SAID THAT THERE WILL BE NO FURTHER ARRESTS OR DETENTIONS OF SOLDIERS IN CONNECTION WITH THE JESUIT MURDER CASE.

THE GOVERNMENT'S STRONGMAN HAS SAID IT IS OVER, PERIOD. D'AUBUISSON INSISTS THAT THERE ARE NO OTHER MILITARY MEN INVOLVED IN THE JESUIT CASE, ACCORDING TO A HEADLINE IN TODAY'S LA PRENSA GRAFICA, IN WHICH IT PUBLISHES D'AUBUISSON'S STATEMENTS.

WE DO NOT BELIEVE THE PROSECUTOR'S OFFICE WILL SUMMON D'AUBUISSON TO PRESENT THE EVIDENCE THAT HAS LED HIM TO ASSERT CATEGORICALLY THAT NO OTHER SENIOR OFFICERS WERE INVOLVED IN THE ASSASSINATION OF THE PRIESTS. WE DO NOT BELIEVE SO, BECAUSE THAT PROSECUTOR'S OFFICE HAS NOT BEEN ESTABLISHED TO SUMMON OR TO INQUIRE, NOT EVEN TO SUMMON THE MAIN SUSPECT IN THE MURDERS, WHICH HAVE BEEN BLAMED ON THE DEATH SQUADS. ONE OF THEM IS FORMER PRESIDENT JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE, WHO ACCUSED HIM OF BEING THE MASTERMIND OF MSGR ROMERO'S ASSASSINATION. YET, D'AUBUISSON GOES ON COMPLETELY UNSCATHED.

THEREFORE, ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON TODAY PLACED A FINAL PERIOD ON THE INVESTIGATION OF COLONEL [GUILLERMO] BENAVIDES. OBVIOUSLY, MAJOR D'AUBUISSON, THE ARENA STRONGMAN, IS PLACING A FINAL PERIOD ON THE CASE, AND HE IS TELLING THIS DIRECTLY AND PUBLICLY TO CRISTIANI, THE YANKEES, AND THE REST OF LA TANDONA [REFERENCE TO THE 1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF CAPTAIN GENERAL GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY].

IT IS IMPERATIVE FOR ARENA MEMBERS TO TELL CRISTIANI HOW FAR TO GO WITH THE INVESTIGATION. THEY NEVER APPROVED OF HAVING EVEN THE LIEUTENANTS OF THE ATLACATL BATTALION INVESTIGATED. THE HEATED ARGUMENTS WITHIN THE ARENA LEADERSHIP HAVE DESTABILIZED THE GOVERNMENT TO SUCH AN EXTENT THAT MERINO'S SUDDEN FALL IS BUT THE TIP OF THE ICEBERG AND D'AUBUISSON'S SIGNAL TO STOP A SHOW OF FORCE. D'AUBUISSON BELIEVES THAT SERVING UP BENAVIDES' HEAD IS MORE THAN ENOUGH, AND THIS IS THE FRANK MESSAGE THAT ARENA AND THE GOVERNMENT ARE SENDING TO THE U.S. CONGRESS, PRECISELY AT THE TIME THE YANKEE POLICY ON EL SALVADOR IS UNDER SERIOUS SCRUTINY.

THE STRONGMAN IS TELLING LA TANDONA: DO NOT WORRY ANY MORE. WE HAD TO GIVE SOMETHING TO THE CONGRESS, BUT CRISTIANI'S MODERATION WILL GO JUST SO FAR. D'AUBUISSON CONTINUES TO BE THE STRONGMAN.

DEV-MUC3-1072 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 29 JAN 90 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] TODAY, 2 DAYS BEFORE HIS MEETING WITH UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR, PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI REAFFIRMED HIS WILLINGNESS TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. HOWEVER, CRISTIANI SAID, THE FLMN IS SENDING CONTRADICTORY SIGNALS ON ITS COMMITMENT TO PEACE.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [MARCO ANTONIO GUEVARA, CORRESPONDENT] A FEW HOURS BEFORE DEPARTING ON HIS TRIP TO WASHINGTON TODAY, THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC REITERATED HIS WILLINGNESS TO RESUME A DIALOGUE WITH THE FMLN, WHICH, HE SAID, IS ONE OF THE REASONS FOR HIS VISIT TO THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL.

[CRISTIANI] THE MAIN GOAL IS TO HOLD A WORK SESSION WITH THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL. THIS WILL BE ON 31 JANUARY. THE GOAL IS TO SEARCH FOR AND COME UP WITH ANY MECHANISMS THAT COULD EASE THE RESUMPTION OF THE DIALOGUE PROCESS, SO ALL VIOLENT ACTIONS CEASE AND SO WE CAN SEARCH FOR AN AGREEMENT FOR THE REINCORPORATION OF THE FMLN THROUGH POLITICAL MEANS. THEN WE WILL HOLD A MEETING WITH PRESIDENT BUSH ON 1 FEBRUARY IN WASHINGTON. WE WILL ALSO VISIT OTHER GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS.

[GUEVARA] THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT, WHO JUST RETURNED FROM HONDURAS WHERE HE MET U.S. VICE PRESIDENT DAN QUAYLE AND OTHER LATIN AMERICAN PRESIDENTS, TOLD NEWSMEN TODAY THAT HE HAS RECEIVED OFFERS FROM THE VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT TO CONTINUE THE DIALOGUE IN VENEZUELA.

[CRISTIANI] WE ARE DETERMINED TO SEARCH FOR A SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT THROUGH DIALOGUE. THIS IS BASICALLY WHAT WE WILL DISCUSS WITH UN SECRETARY GENERAL PEREZ DE CUELLAR -- SEARCHING FOR ELEMENTS THAT WOULD MAKE THIS POSSIBLE. REGARDING THE FMLN, WE SEE SOME CONTRADICTORY INDICATIONS AT THIS TIME. IN SOME COMMUNIQUES, THE FMLN IS SOMEHOW EXPRESSING THE DESIRE TO RETURN TO THE DIALOGUE PROCESS, BUT, ON THE OTHER HAND, THERE ARE REPORTS THAT THE FMLN CONTINUES TRYING TO PLAN SOME ATTACKS ON SAN SALVADOR, IN ADDITION TO OTHER TERRORIST ACTIONS AIMED AT THE ECONOMIC INFRASTRUCTURE. WE BELIEVE THIS IS CONTRADICTORY. HOWEVER, I MYSELF BELIEVE THERE ARE SOME POSITIVE ELEMENTS THAT WILL PERMIT RESUMING A DIALOGUE PROCESS THAT COULD BRING SOME BENEFITS.

[GUEVARA] ASKED ABOUT REPORTS BY THE SAN SALVADOR AUXILIARY BISHOP REGARDING SEARCHES AT SOME CATHOLIC CHURCH OFFICES, CRISTIANI SAID THIS SHOULD NOT BE SOMETHING TO WORRY ABOUT, BECAUSE THIS HAS BEEN FOR SECURITY REASONS.

[CRISTIANI] AS PART OF THE THINGS TAKING PLACE IN THE COUNTRY AT THIS TIME, IT IS POSSIBLE THAT SOME REPORTS HAVE BEEN TOTALLY WRONG. HOWEVER, I DO NOT BELIEVE THIS SHOULD BE TAKEN AT ALL AS A SIGN OF SOMETHING TO WORRY ABOUT. THESE ACTIONS HAVE BEEN FOR SECURITY REASONS, BASED ON REPORTS WE HAVE RECEIVED. THEREFORE, WE MUST TAKE ACTION, AND IF THERE IS NOTHING...[CHANGES THOUGHT]. THOSE WHO HAVE NO PROBLEM AND HAVE NOT BEEN INVOLVED IN ILLEGAL MATTERS SHOULD HAVE NOTHING TO FEAR.

[GUEVARA] THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT SAID HE IS PLEASED WITH THE STATEMENTS BY NEW HONDURAN PRESIDENT RAFAEL CALLEJAS, WHO EXPRESSED HIS TOTAL SUPPORT FOR THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PEACE PLAN. CONCERNING AN UPCOMING CENTRAL AMERICAN SUMMIT, THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT NO DATE HAS BEEN SET YET AND HE BELIEVES THIS CANNOT BE DONE BEFORE THE NICARAGUAN ELECTIONS. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1073 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 29 JAN 90 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] COLONEL MAURICIO ERNESTO VARGAS TODAY HAS SAID THERE IS NO NEED OR REASON FOR THE UNITED STATES TO SUSPEND AID TO THE COUNTRY. HOWEVER, SHOULD WE GET TO THAT POINT, THE ARMED FORCES ARE READY TO CONTINUE DEFENDING THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ALFREDO VILLARREAL, CORRESPONDENT] COL VARGAS BELIEVES THE U.S. AID IS NOT ONLY A MATTER OF MILITARY ASSISTANCE PROVIDED TO THE SALVADORAN ARMY, BUT ALSO A MATTER OF DEFENDING THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IN THE COUNTRY. THE MILITARY OFFICER SAID IT IS NOT POSSIBLE THAT A MINORITY, AS HE TERMED THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WILL AFFECT, WITH ITS DISINFORMATION METHODS AIMED AT COUNTRIES ABROAD, U.S. MILITARY AID BEING CUT OFF OR DECREASED. HOWEVER, IN ANY CASE, COL VARGAS SAID THAT IF THE AID IS SUSPENDED, THIS WOULD COMPLICATE THE ARMED FORCES PLANS CONCERNING THE COUNTERINSURGENCY STRUGGLE.

[COL VARGAS] I CERTAINLY DO NOT BELIEVE THAT WE, HAVING A DEMOCRATIC SOCIETY, HAVE SO LITTLE CAPACITY TO DEFEND THE TRUTH. IT CAN TAKE 100 DAYS TO SPREAD A LIE, BUT YOU CAN TELL THE TRUTH IN 1 DAY. I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT IN THIS CONTEXT....[CHANGES THOUGHT] I BELIEVE WE ARE OVERESTIMATING THE LEFT-WING ACTIONS. WE VIEW THEM AS BEING SMART, AND WE SEE OURSELVES AS FOOLS. ANY CUT OR SUSPENSION IN THE AID WILL CAUSE PROBLEMS BECAUSE IT WILL CREATE FURTHER NEEDS WHENEVER WE NEED TO FULFILL A MISSION. THEREFORE, MISSIONS WILL BE A BIT MORE COMPLICATED, BUT WE WILL FULFILL THEM. IF MARXISTS -- THROUGH THEIR CONCEPT OF DISINFORMATION -- BELIEVE THEY CAN ATTEMPT TO HARM THE UNITED STATES-EL SALVADOR ALLIANCE THROUGH THIS PROCESS, AND THAT THIS WILL LEAD THEM TO POWER, THEY ARE COMPLETELY WRONG. THEY WILL FIND AN ARMED FORCES WHICH WILL ALWAYS BE FIRMLY DETERMINED TO DEFEND THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.

[CORRESPONDENT VILLARREAL] COL VARGAS, IN CHARGE OF THE 3D MILITARY ZONE IN SAN MIGUEL, SAID HE AGREES WITH THE DECISION TO PROSECUTE THE EIGHT MILITARY MEN, INCLUDING ONE COLONEL AND TWO LIEUTENANTS, CHARGED WITH KILLING SIX JESUIT PRIESTS. COL VARGAS SAID THOSE WHO HAVE BROKEN THE LAW MUST PAY FOR IT, NO MATTER WHO THEY ARE.

[COL VARGAS] THE ARMY WILL FEEL PAIN IN THE EVENT ANY OF ITS MEMBERS ARE INVOLVED IN ACTIONS WHICH VIOLATE THE PRINCIPLES THAT RULE THE ARMED FORCES. THIS IS VERY PAINFUL. HOWEVER, IF WE ARE BUILDING A DEMOCRACY, THERE ARE FACTS THAT MUST BE JUDGED ACCORDING TO THE NORMS PREVAILING IN A DEMOCRACY. DEMOCRACY MUST PREVAIL OVER PEOPLE. DEMOCRACY IS MORE IMPORTANT THAN INDIVIDUALS AND THAN INSTITUTIONS IN INDIVIDUAL TERMS, AND MORE IMPORTANT THAN THE INDIVIDUAL INTEREST OF PEOPLE OR GROUPS, WHICH CANNOT PREVAIL OVER THE NATIONAL INTEREST.

[CORRESPONDENT VILLARREAL] IN THE MILITARY ASPECT, COL VARGAS SAID THAT AS OF 1990, IN HIS AREA OF RESPONSIBILITY, THEY ARE IMPLEMENTING THE PLANS DRAFTED BY THE JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF KNOWN AS "VICTORY AND HAMMER" WHICH HAS OFFERED, AS PRELIMINARY RESULTS, 53 CLASHES, 37 GUERRILLAS AND 12 SOLDIERS KILLED, AND WEAPONS SEIZURES. THE TWO OPERATIONS, HE ADDED, HAVE BEEN SUCCESSFUL. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1074 (TRW)

SAN SALVADOR, 25 JAN 90 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] ON TUESDAY AFTERNOON THE POLICE IN WASHINGTON ARRESTED THE LEADERS OF A GROUP OF DEMONSTRATORS WHO HAD GATHERED IN FRONT OF THE CAPITOL TO DEMAND THE SUSPENSION OF MILITARY AID TO EL SALVADOR. A FEW HOURS LATER, REPRESENTATIVES OF SEVERAL CHURCHES ASSERTED THAT A PERSECUTION HAD BEEN LAUNCHED IN OUR COUNTRY AGAINST "RELIGIOUS PEOPLE" AND THAT THE AID SHOULD BE SUSPENDED FOR THAT REASON. THE FOREGONE CONCLUSION WAS THAT, BECAUSE OF THE SUSPENSION OF THE AID, OUR GOVERNMENT WOULD HAVE NO OTHER OPTION BUT TO NEGOTIATE WITH THE TERRORISTS.

THIS CAMPAIGN DATES BACK A LONG TIME. IT BEGAN WITH THE ARRIVAL IN EL SALVADOR OF SEVERAL JESUIT PRIESTS FROM LOVAINA UNIVERSITY IN THE EARLY 1960'S AND CONTINUED WITH THE FOUNDING OF UCA [JOSE SIMEON CANAS CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY], THE ACTIVE PARTICIPATION OF CERTAIN PRIESTS IN THE SUBVERSIVE MOVEMENTS, THE AGITATION LAUNCHED BY THE ALAS [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] PRIESTS, THE TRAGIC EPISODE INVOLVING MSGR OSCAR ARNULFO ROMERO, AND THE USE OF THAT EPISODE BY THE LEFT. EL SALVADOR WAS, AND TO SOME EXTENT CONTINUES TO BE, THE SCENARIO IN WHICH THE "THEOLOGY OF LIBERATION" REACHED ITS ULTIMATE CONSEQUENCES BY PLACING THE INQUISITORIAL FANATICISM OF CERTAIN PRIESTS AND PASTORS SIDE BY SIDE WITH THE MOST RADICAL CURRENTS OF SOCIALISM.

THE VIRULENCE OF THE ONSLAUGHT WENT THAT FAR PARTLY BECAUSE OF THE PASSIVE ATTITUDE -- OR, RATHER, THE CONNIVING PERMISSIVENESS -- OF THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC REGIME, WHICH TRIED TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THE STRIDENT CAMPAIGN TO FURTHER ITS OWN POLITICAL ENDS. DUARTE NEVER TRULY DISTANCED HIMSELF FAR FROM THE GUERRILLAS BECAUSE OF HIS ILL-DISGUISED IDEOLOGICAL LEANINGS, WHICH LED HIM TO COINCIDE IN GREAT PART WITH THE SUBVERSIVES' TENETS AND ABOVE ALL WITH THE FANCIFUL IDEA THAT THE PEOPLE APPROVED OF THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A COMMUNIST STATE IN EL SALVADOR.

IT IS CERTAINLY DIFFICULT TO COUNTER ORGANIZED SLANDER, TAKING INTO CONSIDERATION HOW FAR CERTAIN NOTIONS HAVE GONE AND HOW MUCH SUPPORT THEY RECEIVE FROM THE NEWS MEDIA IN A LARGE PART OF THE WORLD. THE POSSIBILITIES OF SUCCESSFULLY COUNTERING THIS PROPAGANDA OFFENSIVE MAY NOT BE THE BEST, BUT IT WOULD BE WORSE TO REMAIN SILENT AND DO NOTHING. WE HAVE YET TO SEE THE ORGANIZATION OF A TRUE EFFORT TO REJECT THE PERMANENT DEFAMATION BEING WITHSTOOD BY THE COUNTRY.

THERE IS NO ANSWER TO THE ACCUSATIONS AND INSULTS ISSUED BY CERTAIN SECTORS, EITHER. TO ALLOW A PERSON WHO ACTS AS LEADER OF THE TERRORISTS' POLITICAL FRONT TO COME TO THE COUNTRY AND SCOLD PRESIDENT CRISTIANI WITHOUT HAVING THE AUTHORITIES ARREST HIM FOR HIS PARTICIPATION IN CRIMES PERPETRATED AGAINST THE REPUBLIC IS TO FALL INTO DANGEROUS EXTREMES OF TOLERANCE. WAS NOT JENNIFER CASOLO ALLOWED TO OPENLY REPRESENT THE SUBVERSIVES FOR MANY YEARS WITHOUT INVESTIGATING HER MORE CLOSELY? IS IT PERHAPS THAT THE LAWS ALLOW A FOREIGNER TO MEDDLE IN THE COUNTRY'S INTERNAL AFFAIRS?

HOW CAN JUDGES BE BANNED FROM CERTAIN INSTALLATIONS, SUCH AS THE THE BOMBED FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] HEADQUARTERS, UNIVERSITIES, AND SIMILAR PLACES, WHEN THERE ARE SUFFICIENT GROUNDS TO SUSPECT THAT TERRORISTS ARE HIDDEN IN SUCH PLACES?

DEV-MUC3-1075 (TRW)

BOGOTA, 26 JAN 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 2) -- [INTERVIEW WITH 19 APRIL MOVEMENT, M-19, LEADER CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ, BY GLORIA ORTEGA] [TEXT] [ORTEGA] IN A REPORT FOR TELEVISION YESTERDAY YOU POINTED OUT THE INEFFECTIVENESS OF THE GUERRILLAS IN COLOMBIA. WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT KIDNAPPINGS?

[PIZARRO] WE ARE LIVING IN A TIME WHERE ALL HAVE TO BECOME UP TO DATE, BUT BEING UP TO DATE DOES NOT MEAN WE HAVE TO BECOME DARKER. QUITE THE CONTRARY, IT MEANS SHEDDING MORE LIGHT ON LIFE. WE ARE BENT ON THIS. OF COURSE, THIS ALSO MEANS THAT WE HAVE TO ABANDON PRACTICES LIKE KIDNAPPING.

[ORTEGA] SURELY YOU KNOW VERY WELL WHO YOUR NEMESIS WAS 24 HOURS AGO. WHAT WOULD YOU SUGGEST REGARDING MILITARY TRAINING AND ORIENTATION IN COLOMBIA?

[PIZARRO] ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN ORGANIZED FOR CENTURIES TO WIN WARS. IN COLOMBIA WE HAVE TO ORGANIZE THE MILITARY TO ACHIEVE PEACE, PARTICULARLY PEACE AT HOME. THE MILITARY HAS A GREAT CONTRIBUTION TO MAKE AND THERE ARE VALUABLE INDIVIDUALS WITHIN IT. THE DEMOCRATIC LINEAGE DOES NOT EXHAUST ITSELF IN GUERRILLAS, AND THERE IS ALSO A GREAT DEMOCRATIC QUALITY IN THE ARMED FORCES.

[ORTEGA] WHAT DO YOU FEEL AFTER KILLING SO MANY POLICEMEN?

[PIZARRO] WE WILL HAVE TO ASK THE POLICE WHAT THEY THINK AFTER KILLING SO MANY GUERRILLAS. WE HAVE LIVED IN VIOLENCE IN THIS COUNTRY. QUESTIONS DEALING WITH VIOLENCE AND WAR SHOULD BE AVOIDED.

[ORTEGA] WHAT DID YOU FEEL WHEN YOU PASSED IN FRONT OF THE PALACE OF JUSTICE YESTERDAY?

[PIZARRO] I DID NOT DO THAT. I AM STILL LOOKING FORWARD TO WALKING PAST THE PALACE OF JUSTICE.

[ORTEGA] WHAT DO YOU THINK YOU WILL FEEL AFTER WHAT HAPPENED IN THE PALACE?

[PIZARRO] WELL, THAT THIS IS SOMETHING TO PONDER.

[ORTEGA] ACCORDING TO WHAT THE PEOPLE HAVE EXPRESSED TO ME, SOME COLOMBIAN SECTORS FIND IT DIFFICULT TO BELIEVE THAT YOU PEOPLE, WHO STORMED THE PALACE OF JUSTICE, ARE THE SAME ONES WHO ARE AMONG THE MOST PROTECTED IN THIS COUNTRY.

[PIZARRO] I HAVE ALWAYS WONDERED HOW COLOMBIA DEALT WITH THE FACT THAT SANTANDER WAS THE FIRST MAN PARDONED IN COLOMBIA.

[ORTEGA] WHAT DOES THAT MEAN?

[PIZARRO] THAT MEANS THAT IF SANTANDER, A LAWMAKER, WAS PARDONED AFTER HIS ATTEMPT ON BOLIVAR'S LIFE, AND WE ARE LIVING IN A NATION BUILT LARGELY ON WHAT SANTANDER DID, THE LIFE OF MEN IS MADE OF LIGHT AND SHADES. AND THEY HAVE TO LIVE AS THEY ARE.

DEV-MUC3-1076 (UNISYS)

MEDELLIN, 30 JAN 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN DRUG MAFIAS HAVE DENIED THAT THEY ARE PREPARING AN ATTACK ON THE LIFE OF U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH, WHO WILL VISIT THIS CARIBBEAN COLONIAL BEACH RESORT ON 15 FEBRUARY FOR AN ANTI-DRUG SUMMIT MEETING.

BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA, COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA, AND U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH WILL SIGN A MANIFESTO IN CARTAGENA THAT WAS DESIGNED IN SANTA CRUZ DE LA SIERRA, BOLIVIA. THE DOCUMENT WILL OUTLINE STRATEGIES THAT THEY WILL ADOPT TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING.

THE MYSTERIOUS CLANDESTINE GROUP THE "EXTRADITABLES," -- THE ARMED BRANCH OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL DRUG TRAFFICKERS -- SAID IN A BULLETIN RELEASED EARLY THIS MORNING THAT THE REPORTS OF A POSSIBLE ATTACK ON BUSH IN CARTAGENA ARE FALSE.

"THESE REPORTS ARE PART OF A PLAN TO UNDERMINE THE CREDIBILITY OF ALL OUR PEACE PROPOSALS," THE DOCUMENT SAID. IN THE DOCUMENT, THE "EXTRADITABLES" ALSO [WORDS INDISTINCT].

LAST WEEKEND, THE U.S. CBS TELEVISION NETWORK REPORTED THE POSSIBILITY OF AN ATTACK WITH ROCKETS AND MISSILES BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS ON BUSH'S PLANE IN CARTAGENA.

IN A STATEMENT BY FOREIGN MINISTER JULIO LONDONO, THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT SAID THAT IT HAD NO KNOWLEDGE OF TERRORIST PLANS AGAINST THE U.S. PRESIDENT, AND ADDED THAT U.S. AND COLOMBIAN SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS WERE CAPABLE OF GUARANTEEING THE SAFETY OF THE FOUR PRESIDENTS.

THE EXTRADITABLES, A MAFIA GROUP BASED IN MEDELLIN, IN NORTHWEST COLOMBIAN, HAS BEEN INSISTING SINCE 17 JANUARY THAT THEY WANT A PEACE DIALOGUE WITH THE ADMINISTRATION OF LIBERAL PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, WHO DECLARED WAR ON THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN AUGUST, 1989. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1078 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 21 JAN 90 (EL DIARIO DE HOY) -- [TEXT] THE NATIONAL POLICE ANNOUNCED ON 20 JANUARY THAT IT HAS ABUNDANT EVIDENCE OF THE GUILT OF U.S. CITIZEN JENNIFER JEAN CASOLO, WHO WAS ARRESTED ON 24 NOVEMBER IN HER HOME IN THE MIRALVALLE NEIGHBORHOOD OF THIS CAPITAL, WHERE A LARGE NUMBER OF WEAPONS AND A GREAT QUANTITY OF DOCUMENTS BELONGING TO THE FMLN-FDR [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT - REVOLUTIONARY DEMOCRATIC FRONT] WERE FOUND BURIED IN THE YARD.

CASOLO WAS ARRAIGNED 8 DAYS [AS PUBLISHED] AFTER HER ARREST, BUT WAS RELEASED BY THE JUDGE "FOR LACK OF EVIDENCE," ACCORDING TO THE JUDICIAL RECORDS.

ALTHOUGH IN SALVADORAN JUDICIAL CIRCLES IT IS NOT CLEAR WHY CASOLO WAS RELEASED, IT IS BELIEVED THAT THERE WERE POLITICAL FACTORS INVOLVED.

AT PRESENT, CASOLO HEADS GROUPS THAT HAVE LAUNCHED A VIRULENT CAMPAIGN AGAINST EL SALVADOR IN THE UNITED STATES, CLAIMING ALLEGED "RELIGIOUS PERSECUTION."

CASOLO WAS CAPTURED AFTER THE TERRORIST FAUSTO GALLARDO VALDEZ GAVE HER NAME TO THE POLICE, TELLING THEM WHERE TO FIND THE WEAPONS THAT HE AND HIS ACCOMPLICES USED FOR TERRORIST ACTS. THE PRISONER SAID THAT THE WEAPONS WERE PROVIDED BY CASOLO AT HER HOME IN THE MIRALVALLE NEIGHBORHOOD, WHICH SERVED AS A CLANDESTINE ARSENAL.

IN VIEW OF THIS CONFESSION, THE POLICE REQUESTED THE PARTICIPATION OF REPRESENTATIVES OF THE U.S. EMBASSY, WHO WERE PRESENT IN THE COURSE OF THE PROCEEDINGS AND WHEN THE WEAPONS WERE DUG UP IN FRONT OF CASOLO HERSELF.

WHEN CASOLO RETURNED TO THE UNITED STATES, SHE ADMITTED THAT SHE HAD BURIED DOCUMENTS IN THE YARD OF THE HOUSE WHERE SHE LIVED, BUT SHE LIED BY SAYING THAT SHE DID THIS BECAUSE "IN EL SALVADOR PEOPLE COMMONLY BURY DOCUMENTS OR JEWELS TO KEEP THEM FROM BEING STOLEN BY CRIMINALS."

SOURCES SAY THAT AT PRESENT, AT THE HEAD OF GROUPS OF COMMUNISTS FROM THE UNITED STATES AND OTHER COUNTRIES WHO SUPPORT THEIR SALVADORAN COUNTERPARTS, CASOLO HAS BEGUN A NATIONWIDE CAMPAIGN TO DISCREDIT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNRMENT AND TO PRESSURE CONGRESS TO REDUCE OR ELIMINATE AID TO OUR COUNTRY IN ORDER TO WEAKEN THE COUNTRY INSTITUTIONALLY AND STRENGTHEN THE FMLN-FDR TERRORIST GROUPS.

THE POLICE REPORT THAT THE TERRORIST GALLARDO VALDEZ, FROM WHOM WEAPONS AND AMMOUNITION WERE SEIZED ON 24 NOVEMBER, SAID THAT HE HAD OBTAINED THE WEAPONS AT THE HOME OF A WOMAN WHO APPEARED TO BE A FOREIGNER ON BARCELONA AVENUE, MIRALVALLE NEIGHBORHOOD, IN SAN SALVADOR.

THAT SAME DAY, POLICE INVESTIGATORS LOCATED THE HOUSE, IDENTIFIED THE PERSON LIVING THERE, AND INVITED U.S. EMBASSY OFFICIALS TO PARTICIPATE IN THE SEARCH.

BURIED AT THE HOUSE THEY FOUND 103 SHELLS FOR 60-MM MORTARS, 213 STICKS OF TNT, 405 ELECTRIC DETONATING CAPS, 150 FEET OF SLOW FUSES, 15 KNIVES, 3 CARTRIDGE CLIPS FOR AK-47 RIFLES, 12,510 AK-47 SHELLS, 9,110 M-16 RIFLE SHELLS, 325 G-3 RIFLE SHELLS, AND DOCUMENTS.

IN HER UNOFFICIAL STATEMENT, CASOLO SAID THAT SHE DID NOT BELONG TO ANY SUBVERSIVE GROUP OR ASSOCIATION, AND THAT SHE DID NOT KNOW HOW THE ARTICLES CAME TO BE IN HER HOUSE.

ON 5 DECEMBER, CASOLO AND A GROUP OF SALVADORANS WERE ARRAIGNED BEFORE A MILITARY JUDGE, WHO 5 DAYS LATER RELEASED THEM "FOR LACK OF EVIDENCE."

ON 9 DECEMBER, POLICEMEN ARRESTED A WOMAN NAMED RUTH ESPERANZA AGUILAR MARROQUIN, ALIAS MARINA, WHO WAS FLEEING AFTER HAVING PLACED A BOMB IN THE ENGINE OF A BUS. ON BEING QUESTIONED, SHE SAID SHE WAS AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF THE PEOPLE'S REVOLUTIONARY ARMY, THAT THE PERSON IN CHARGE OF LOGISTICS WAS THE AMERICAN, CASOLO, AND THAT SHE HAD OBTAINED THE EXPLOSIVE MATERIAL AT CASOLO'S HOME IN MIRALVALLE.

THE POLICE HAVE DENIED CASOLO'S CHARGES THAT DURING HER DETENTION SHE WAS SUBJECTED TO PHYSICAL AND PSYCHOLOGICAL TORTURE, BECAUSE IT CAN PROVE THAT WHILE CASOLO WAS UNDER ARREST, SHE WAS ACCOMPANIED BY AN EMBASSY OFFICIAL, EVEN AT MEALTIME.

DEV-MUC3-1079 (UNISYS)

AYACUCHO, 28 JAN 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE POLICE HAVE REPORTED THAT TOMAS EVANGELISTA, A LEADER OF THE RULING AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE (APRA) AND DIRECTOR OF THE AYACUCHO DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION, WAS SHOT DEAD BY TERRORISTS HERE TODAY.

THE POLICE SAID THAT A GROUP OF HOODED INDIVIDUALS EARLY THIS MORNING ENTERED EVANGELISTA'S HOUSE AND, AFTER TYING THE HANDS OF HIS WIFE AND FIVE CHILDREN, TOOK EVANGELISTA OUT OF THE HOUSE AND SHOT HIM AT LEAST 20 TIMES.

EVANGELISTA, WHO WAS 50 YEARS OLD, HAD HELD THE MOST IMPORTANT REGIONAL APRA POSTS FOR 30 YEARS.

EVANGELISTA'S WIFE TOLD THE POLICE THAT BEFORE HER HUSBAND WAS KILLED, THE HOODED MAN SHOUTED THEIR SUPPORT FOR THE PRO-MAOIST SHINING PATH TERRORIST GROUP. ANTHROPOLOGIST ABIMAEL GUZMAN, THE FOUNDER OF THE SHINING PATH TERRORIST ORGANIZATION, WAS EVANGELISTA'S PROFESSOR AT THE HUAMANGA UNIVERSITY IN AYACUCHO.

THE NATIONAL POLICE HAVE ALSO REPORTED THAT ON 26 JANUARY SHINING PATH TERRORISTS MURDERED BROTHERS MARTIZA AND JOHN PAOLO PUZO OCHOA AND THEIR MOTHER MARTA OCHOA IN THE TOWNSHIP OF CAMPINA, 60 KM SOUTH OF AYACUCHO.

WITNESSES TOLD THE POLICE THAT THE OCHOAS WERE KILLED BECAUSE THEY REFUSED TO SUPPLY FOOD AND LODGING TO THE TERRORISTS.

MORE THAN 200 PEOPLE HAVE DIED SO FAR THIS MONTH OWING TO THE ARMED STRUGGLE THAT THE SHINING PATH TERRORISTS BEGAN IN 1980 AND THAT HAS ALREADY CLAIMED THE LIVES OF AT LEAST 17,700 PEOPLE AND CAUSED DAMAGE OF OVER $16 BILLION, WHICH IS THE EQUIVALENT TO THE 70 PERCENT OF THE PERUVIAN FOREIGN DEBT.

DEV-MUC3-1082 (UNISYS)

LIMA, 30 JAN 90 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [REPORT] [EXCERPTS] PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA HAS CALLED FOR CALM AND SERIOUSNESS IN THE POLITICAL DEBATES AMONG THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES. HE DESCRIBED ONE OF THEM AS BEING INTELLECTUALLY IMMATURE IN VIEW OF THE CONSTANT ATTACKS THE LATTER ALWAYS MAKES. THE RIGHT, GARCIA SAID, MUST BE TAUGHT A LESSON OF MATURITY AND SERIOUSNESS.

THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT THE FIRST SPECIAL CONGRESSIONAL SESSION WILL BE HELD FROM 5-6 FEBRUARY TO SPECIFICALLY DISCUSS INTERNAL BORDER DELIMITATIONS. HE ALSO SAID THAT NO NEW CENTRAL BANK DIRECTOR WILL BE APPOINTED, WHICH WILL ALLOW THE NEXT ADMINISTRATION TO DO SO.

FOR THE TIME BEING, THE PRESIDENT ADDED, HE CANNOT EITHER CONFIRM OR DENY THAT HE WILL ATTEND THE ANTIDRUG SUMMIT IN COLOMBIA BECAUSE THE SITUATION IN PANAMA COULD CHANGE IN THE REMAINING 15 DAYS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [REPORTER] MR PRESIDENT, THERE ARE STILL 16 DAYS UNTIL THE CARTAGENA SUMMIT. HAVE YOU MADE A FINAL DECISION ON WHETHER YOU WILL ATTEND OR NOT?

[GARCIA] NO, I HAVE NOT MADE A DECISION YET BECAUSE PERUVIAN FOREIGN POLICY FOLLOWS ITS PRINCIPLES, WHILE THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC -- DESPITE WHAT SOME PEOPLE MAY SAY -- FOLLOWS HIS, AND THESE PRINCIPLES ARE LOYAL TO CERTAIN ESSENTIAL CONCEPTS.

WE ARE YET NOT COMPLETELY SURE THAT THE INVADING COUNTRY, THE UNITED STATES, IS TOTALLY WILLING TO OR INTENDS TO WITHDRAW ITS SOLDIERS FROM A SMALL LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRY. AS LONG AS THIS DOES NOT OCCUR, AS YOU MUST UNDERSTAND, IT IS DESPICABLE AND NEARLY IMPOSSIBLE FOR ME TO SIT DOWN AT A TABLE WITH SOMEONE WHO IS ABUSING A SMALL COUNTRY WITH HIS ALMIGHTY POSITION. MANY THINGS CAN HAPPEN IN 15 OR 16 DAYS.

I AM NOT SAYING EITHER YES OR NO, BUT I THINK THAT THINGS MUST SOMEHOW CHANGE FOR THE BETTER IN ORDER TO HOLD A CORDIAL MEETING. UNDER THE CURRENT CIRCUMSTANCES, IT IS DOUBTFUL THAT THE PRESIDENTS CAN HOLD A CORDIAL MEETING AS LONG AS ONE OF THEM IS PLACING AN ATOMIC BOMB AND THE THREAT OF INVASION ON THE TABLE.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[GARCIA] YES, I THINK THAT THAT MAGAZINE IS WELL INFORMED, BECAUSE THERE HAVE BEEN SOME MISUNDERSTANDINGS. AS YOU KNOW, EXPERTS FROM THE FOUR COUNTRIES MET IN SANTA CRUZ DE LA SIERRA, BOLIVIA, TO PREPARE A DOCUMENT. WHEN EVERYTHING SEEMED TO BE READY TO SIGN THE FINAL DOCUMENT, ONE OF THE COUNTRIES PROPOSED SOME MODIFICATIONS CHANGING THE STRUCTURE OF THE CONCEPT.

THE FIRST TIME I WENT TO THE UNITED NATIONS, 4 AND 1/2 YEARS AGO, I TOLD THE UNITED STATES THAT THIS IS NOT A PROBLEM OF HELICOPTERS OR BULLETS. THIS IS A PROBLEM OF BETTER PRICES FOR COCOA, COFFEE, AND ANNATTO SEEDS. THIS IS A PROBLEM WITH THE PROCESSING FACTORIES IN THE HIGHER HUALLAGA VALLEY AREA AND AIRLINES THAT TRANSPORT THESE PRODUCTS TO THE UNITED STATES.

THIS CONCEPT HAS BEEN ACCEPTED AFTER 4 AND 1/2 YEARS; WHEN IT WAS FINALLY ABOUT TO BE PUT DOWN IN THE DOCUMENT IN SANTA CRUZ, ONE OF THE COUNTRIES MODIFIED IT, THUS HINDERING FURTHER PROGRESS IN THE NEGOTIATIONS. THIS SUBJECT IS NOW BEING REVIEWED, AND THE SUMMIT COULD BE POSTPONED FOR A FEW DAYS UNTIL WE REACH FULL AGREEMENT ON SUCH AN IMPORTANT SUMMIT, WHICH WAS PROPOSED BY THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENCY.

WE MUST GATHER AT THE CARTAGENA SUMMIT WITH A CONCRETE PROPOSAL. IT CANNOT BE SIMPLY A SOCIAL GATHERING. WE ARE NOT TEENAGERS WHO ARE ATTENDING THE MEETING SIMPLY BECAUSE THE PRESIDENT OF THE MOST IMPORTANT COUNTRY IN THE WORLD WILL BE THERE. WE CANNOT GO THERE AS DESPERATE AND DAZZLED YOUNGSTERS TO HOLD HIS HAND. WE MUST MAKE CONCRETE PROPOSALS TO OBTAIN FUNDS FOR PERU, WORK AND HONOR FOR THE HUALLAGA VALLEY PEASANTS, AND RESPECT FOR THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES, PARTICULARLY SINCE IT IS CLEAR THAT THE ORIGIN OF THE PROBLEM IS IN THE CONSUMERS OF THE RICH COUNTRIES, ESPECIALLY THE UNITED STATES. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1083 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 31 JAN 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS TODAY REAFFIRMED THEIR WILLINGNESS TO MEET WITH THE GOVERNMENT AND THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL TO AGREE ON A DATE TO RESUME THE DIALOGUE AND THEY PROPOSED A CEASE-FIRE IN EXCHANGE FOR A SUSPENSION OF U.S. AID.

IN A COMMUNIQUE FROM THE GENERAL COMMAND, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) EXPRESSED THE NEED TO "REORIENT" THE TERMS OF THE DIALOGUE AND NEGOTIATION SO AS TO TURN THEM INTO A NATIONAL PROCESS IN WHICH ALL THE COUNTRY'S SOCIAL AND POLITICAL FORCES CAN PARTICIPATE.

"WE BELIEVE THE U.S. AID TO THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT IS DIRECTED AGAINST DEMOCRATIZATION AND THE POLITICAL SOLUTION OF THE CONFLICT. THE SUSPENSION OF THAT AID COULD FORM PART OF A NEGOTIATED AGREEMENT THAT WOULD SIMULTANEOUSLY ENTAIL A CEASE-FIRE," THE COMMUNIQUE STATED.

THE FMLN'S MESSAGE COINCIDED WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S VISIT TO THE UNITED NATIONS, WHERE TODAY HE WILL MEET WITH JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR TO REQUEST HIS GOOD OFFICES TO ACHIEVE THE RESUMPTION OF THE TALKS WITH THE REBELS, WHICH HAD BEEN SUSPENDED IN OCTOBER.

THE GUERRILLAS STATED THAT THEY HOPE THAT CRISTIANI'S MEETING WITH PEREZ DE CUELLAR WILL LEAD TO SETTING A DATE FOR A FUTURE MEETING.

NEVERTHELESS, THE FMLN RECALLED THE 11 NOVEMBER OFFENSIVE AND WARNED THAT THE GOVERNMENT'S INSISTENCE OF THE GUERRILLAS' ALLEGED MILITARY WEAKNESS "WILL ONLY LEAD TO GREATER LEVELS OF CONFRONTATION."

THE GUERRILLAS EXPRESSED THEIR "CONCERN" ABOUT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMY'S REJECTION OF PEREZ DE CUELLAR'S MEDIATION ROLE, DESCRIBING THE REJECTION AS "AN OBSTACLE TO A PROCEDURE DESIGNED TO BRING SERIOUSNESS TO THE NEGOTIATING EFFORT."

"ON OUR PART," THE COMMUNIQUE STATED, "WE ACCEPT THAT MEDIATION AND WE HAVE MADE EFFORTS TOWARD ACHIEVING IT."

THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT WANTS PEREZ DE CUELLAR TO PLAY ONLY THE ROLE OF OBSERVER IN THE DIALOGUE PROCESS.

SINCE ALFREDO CRISTIANI TOOK OFFICE ON 1 JUNE, THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN HAVE HELD TWO ROUNDS OF TALKS, THE FIRST IN MEXICO IN SEPTEMBER AND THE SECOND IN COSTA RICA IN OCTOBER.

THE GOVERNMENT MAINTAINS THAT THE FMLN SHOULD GIVE UP ITS WEAPONS AND JOIN THE POLITICAL PROCESS AS A PARTY. HOWEVER, THE GUERRILLAS DEMAND A PURGE OF THE ARMED FORCES AND AMENDMENTS TO THE CONSTITUTION IN EXCHANGE FOR A CEASE-FIRE.

DEV-MUC3-1084 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 31 JAN 90 (CANAL DOCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] [ALFREDO VILLAREAL] COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE ARMED FORCES' JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, TODAY POINTED OUT THAT THE COUNTRY'S SITUATION DOES NOT WARRANT LIFTING THE CURRENT STATE OF SIEGE. THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY IS EXPECTED TO DISCUSS WHETHER TO CONTINUE THIS MEASURE NEXT WEEK.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] OUR STANCE IS COMPLETELY OFFENSIVE THROUGHOUT OUR NATIONAL TERRITORY. WE WILL MAINTAIN THIS POLICY WHETHER THERE IS A STATE OF SIEGE OR NOT. [END RECORDING]

THE TOP MILITARY LEADER COMMENTED ON THE DECISION THAT THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY MUST MAKE ON 8 FEBRUARY. COL PONCE SAID THAT THIS IS A POLITICAL DECISION AND WHATEVER THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY DECIDES WILL BE RESPECTED BY THE ARMED FORCES. HOWEVER, HE NOTED THAT FULL GUARANTEES FOR NATIONAL SECURITY WOULD BE NONEXISTENT IF THIS MEASURE IS REPEALED.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] WE WILL RESPECT THE DECISION OF THE INSTITUTIONS TASKED WITH MAKING THE DECISION. WE BELIEVE THAT THE SITUATION IS NOT YET NORMAL ENOUGH TO WARRANT THE LIFTING OF THE STATE OF SIEGE. HOWEVER, THE DECISION IS IN THE HANDS OF THE ASSEMBLY OR THE GOVERNMENT.

[REPORTER] WHY DO YOU BELIEVE THAT THERE ARE NO CONDITIONS FOR LIFTING THE STATE OF SIEGE?

[PONCE] THE PLANS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. THE FMLN PLANS TO CONTINUE ITS TERRORIST, SELECTIVE, AND INDISCRIMINATE ACTIONS, AND ITS ATTACKS IN THE CAPITAL AND THE COUNTRYSIDE. I BELIEVE THAT THERE ARE NO CONDITIONS. THE SITUATION IS NOT YET NORMAL. [END RECORDING]

AS FOR AN OFFENSIVE THAT THE FMLN HAD PLANNED FOR LAST WEEK, THE MILITARY LEADER SAID THAT IT WAS FOILED BECAUSE ARMY INTELLIGENCE DETECTED IT IN TIME. COL PONCE ADDED THAT THE MOST RECENT GUERRILLA ATTACKS IN THE CAPITAL AIM TO FRIGHTEN CIVILIANS.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PONCE] WE BELIEVE THAT THE FMLN IS SEEKING TO MAINTAIN A PSYCHOLOGY OF FEAR AND COMPLETE INSECURITY AND DISTRUST AMONG THE POPULATION, BECAUSE THIS WORKS IN THEIR FAVOR. THEY ARE INVOLVED IN A PURELY TERRORIST, SELECTIVE, AND INDISCRIMINATE SCHEME. I HAVE MENTIONED THE INDISCRIMINATE NATURE BEFORE. THEIR RECENT ATTACKS ARE SELECTIVE. THEY SEEK TO DESTABILIZE THE GOVERNMENT, CREATE DISTRUST IN THE GOVERNMENT, AND CREATE INSECURITY. [END RECORDING]

AS FOR THE VICTORIA AND MARTILLO OPERATIONS, COL PONCE SAID THAT THE FMLN HAD SUSTAINED 2,352 DEAD FROM 11 NOVEMBER 1989 TO 30 JANUARY 1990, AND HE REGRETTED THE DEATH OF 537 ARMY TROOPS.

DEV-MUC3-1085 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 1 FEB 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] COL GUILLERMO ALFREDO BENAVIDES, PRIMARY PERSON IMPLICATED IN THE MURDER OF SIX JESUIT PRIESTS AND THEIR TWO EMPLOYEES, WAS OFFICIALLY REMOVED TODAY FROM HIS POST AS DIRECTOR OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY MILITARY SCHOOL.

BENAVIDES' REPLACEMENT WAS PART OF A HIGH-LEVEL REORGANIZATION IN THE ARMED FORCES WHICH, ACCORDING TO WESTERN DIPLOMATIC SOURCES, REFLECTS AN INTENTION TO MAKE GRADUAL CHANGES THROUGHOUT THE YEAR,

BENAVIDES, WHO IS ACCUSED OF HAVING GIVEN THE ORDER TO KILL THE JESUITS (FIVE SPANIARDS AND ONE SALVADORAN), WILL BE REPLACED AS DIRECTOR OF THE MILITARY SCHOOL BY COL RICARDO ALFONSO CASANOVA, WHO WAS FORMERLY COMMANDER OF THE 6TH INFANTRY BRIGADE, BASED IN THE EASTERN USULUTAN DEPARTMENT.

COL HERIBERTO HERNANDEZ, WHO TO DATE HAS BEEN DIRECTOR OF THE TREASURY POLICE, WILL BE TRANSFERRED TO USULUTAN, A DEPARTMENT WHERE GUERRILLAS ARE CONSTANTLY ACTIVE. HERNANDEZ WILL BE REPLACED BY COL CIRO LOPEZ ROQUE.

IN ADDITION TO THE MILITARY SCHOOL AND THE TREASURY POLICE, THE CHANGES PRIMARILY AFFECT COMMANDERS IN THE AREAS OF PERSISTENT GUERRILLA ACTIVITY, SUCH AS USULUTAN AND CHALATENANGO, AND THE ARCE BATTALION, AN ELITE UNIT TO COMBAT THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN), WHICH IS BASED IN THE EASTERN DEPARTMENT OF SAN MIGUEL.

THESE TRANSFERS AND APPOINTMENTS AFFECT A TOTAL OF 12 COLONELS AND, ALTHOUGH THE ARMED FORCES DESCRIBED THEM TODAY AS "ROUTINE CHANGES," DIPLOMATIC SOURCES FEEL THAT THEY ARE DESIGNED TO SEEK GREATER EFFICIENCY IN MILITARY ACTION. THE SOURCES FEEL THAT MORE CHANGES WILL BE MADE THROUGHOUT THIS YEAR.

THE FIRST RESHUFFLING IN THE ARMED FORCES FOR 1990 WAS ANNOUNCED ON 1 JANUARY, THAT IS, SHORTLY AFTER THE FMLN OFFENSIVE, THE SCALE OF WHICH SURPRISED EVEN THE ARMY ITSELF, AS MILITARY SOURCES ADMITTED.

ON THAT DATE, GENERAL RAFAEL BUSTILLO, CHIEF OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES AND ONE OF THE OFFICERS MOST OPENLY OPPOSED TO DIALOGUE WITH THE FMLN, WAS RELIEVED OF HIS DUTIES AND SENT TO EUROPE AS A MILITARY ATTACHE.

REPLACED WITH BUSTILLO WERE THE CHIEFS OF THE MILITARY DETACHMENTS OF CUSCATLAN AND LA UNION, IN THE CENTRAL AND EASTERN PARTS OF THE COUNTRY, RESPECTIVELY, AND THE CHIEF OF ARMY INTELLIGENCE.

DEV-MUC3-1086 (UNISYS)

CLANDESTINE, 2 FEB 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN)] [TEXT] THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] HEREBY NOTIFIES THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE AND THE INTERNATIONAL COMMUNITY OF THE FOLLOWING:

1. WE SEE AS POSITIVE THAT MR CRISTIANI HAS ACCEPTED UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR'S PARTICIPATION IN THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS IN EL SALVADOR. WE FEEL THAT THE MEDIATION OF THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL AND THE FRAMEWORK OF THAT INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION SERIOUSLY COMMIT BOTH PARTIES TO NEGOTIATION AND OFFER TRUE POSSIBILITIES SO THAT THE PROCESS WILL LEAD TOWARD A SOLUTION THAT WILL PUT AN END TO THE WAR IN OUR COUNTRY.

2. IN VIEW OF THESE POSSIBILITIES, IT IS HIGHLY NEGATIVE THAT THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION HAS ANNOUNCED THAT THE ECONOMIC AND MILITARY ASSISTANCE TO THE GOVERNMENT WILL BE INCREASED IN THE FORTHCOMING FISCAL PERIODS. IF THIS DECISION IS RATIFIED BY THE U.S. CONGRESS, IT WOULD MEAN A DEFINITE DETERMINATION TO PROLONG THE WAR AND THE FAILURE OF THE POSSIBILITY THAT COULD LEAD TO THE NEGOTIATED SOLUTION OF THE SALVADORAN CONFLICT. THE ASSISTANCE STRENGTHENS THE EXTREMISTS. THE POLITICAL PRESSURE MAKES IT NECESSARY TO TAKE POLITICAL ACTIONS AND STRENGTHENS THE NEGOTIATED SOLUTION.

3. THE ARMY CONTINUES TO CARRY OUT PERMANENT MILITARY OFFENSIVES AND REPRESSION. THERE CONTINUE TO BE A STATE OF SIEGE, MURDERS, ARRESTS, AND PERSECUTION AGAINST PEOPLE'S AND RELIGIOUS ORGANIZATIONS; THE PRESS CONTINUES TO BE CONTROLLED; AND INTERNATIONAL AGREEMENTS CONTINUE TO BE VIOLATED AS THE EVACUATION OF FMLN WAR CRIPPLES IS NOT ALLOWED.

COL PONCE OPENLY PROCLAIMS HIS "VICTORY AND HAMMER" OFFENSIVE AGAINST FMLN POSITIONS. THIS IS NOT COMPATIBLE, AS THE GOVERNMENT WANTS THE FMLN TO UNILATERALLY SUSPEND OPERATIONS. AS LONG AS THERE ARE REPRESSION AND LARGE MILITARY OFFENSIVES, AND A CEASE-FIRE IS NOT AGREED UPON BY THE PARTIES, WE ARE OBLIGED TO REMAIN AT WAR AND MAKE OFFENSIVE USE OF OUR MILITARY FORCE IN ANY PART OF THE NATION TO ACHIEVE SERIOUS NEGOTIATION THAT WILL FIND A JUST SOLUTION TO THE WAR.

[SIGNED] THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

[DATED] 2 FEBURARY 1990, EL SALVADOR

DEV-MUC3-1087 (UNISYS)

TEGUCIGALPA, 2 FEB 90 (VOZ DE HONDURAS NETWORK) -- [COMMENTARY] [TEXT] SOME PEOPLE NAIVELY THINK THAT A COUNTRY CURRY FAVOR WITH THE U.S. JUST BY BEING DEMOCRATIC. SOME PEOPLE HAVE PLACED THEMSELVES AT THE SERVICE OF THIS SUPERPOWER, AS LONG AS THE SUPERPOWER HAS HAD NEED OF THEM. HOWEVER, ONCE THEY HAVE OUTLIVED THEIR USEFULNESS, NOT ONLY ARE THEY ABANDONED, BUT NOW THEY ARE EVEN KIDNAPPED, JAILED, AND SENTENCED.

THIS HAPPENED TO PEREZ JIMENEZ OF VENEZUELA; LEONIDAS TRUJILLO OF THE DOMINICAN REPUBLIC, WHO WAS MURDERED BY THE CIA; SOMOZA OF NICARAGUA; AND LATELY NORIEGA OF PANAMA.

THESE MEN ARE VALUED ONLY AS LONG AS THEY ARE USEFUL TO THE UNITED STATES. ONCE THEY ARE NO LONGER USEFUL, THEY ARE NO LONGER REGARDED AS MEN. APPARENTLY SOMETHING SIMILAR HAPPENS WITH COUNTRIES. IF A COUNTRY HAS ANY POLITICAL, MILITARY, OR STRATEGIC VALUE, THAT COUNTRY WILL ENJOY WASHINGTON'S PREFERENCE. HOWEVER, ONCE THE INTEREST NO LONGER EXISTS, THE AID IS OVER. IF THE INTEREST DECREASES, THE AID DECRESES.

HONDURAS IS A TYPICAL EXAMPLE OF THIS POLICY FOR THE WORLD TO SEE. THE POINDEXTER TRIAL SHOWED THAT OVER THE SENATE'S OBJECTION, SPECIAL AID WAS GRANTED TO HONDURAS IN EXCHANGE FOR CONVERTING IT INTO A LEASED TERRITORY FOR CONTRA OPERATIONS.

THE YEARS IN WHICH OUR TERRITORY SHAMEFULLY SERVED TO SHED BLOOD IN ONE OUR NEIGHBORING COUNTRIES, ARE YEARS IN WHICH HONDURAS WAS REGARDED AS A COUNTRY DESERVING MILITARY AND ECONOMIC AID.

WITH THE CHANGE OF U.S. POLICY, AFTER IT ACCEPTED ITS MILITARY FAILURE AGAINST NICARAGUA, HONDURAS IS NO LONGER THE APPLE OF ITS EYE, ACCORDING TO THE UNITED STATES. THAT IS WHY THE UNITED STATES IS NOT ONLY GRUDGING ITS AID, BUT IS NOT EVEN GRANTING THE SCANT AID ALREADY APPROVED, UNLESS HONDURAS AGREES TO ADDITIONAL CONDITIONS.

THERE IS SOMETHING ELSE. SINCE THE UNITED STATES IS THE IMF'S MOST IMPORTANT MEMBER AND SUPPORTER, IT HAS ASKED THE IMF TO TIGHTEN THE SCREWS ON HONDURAS, AND TO EVEN LET HONDURAS USE UP ITS MEAGER GOLD RESERVES UNTIL HONDURAS IS FORCED TO SAY, "FORGIVE ME, MASTER."

AS WE CAN RECALL, WHEN THE GOLD STANDARD WAS ABANDONED FOR THE DOLLAR STANDARD AND SPECIAL DRAWING RIGHTS, THE IMF, AND OTHER MEASURES WERE CREATED, EACH COUNTRY DEPOSITED GOLD RESEVES TO BACK UP ITS CURRENCY EXCHANGE. THEREAFTER, ITS MONETARY BACKING WOULD DEPEND ON ITS RESERVE OF DOLLARS AND OTHER STRONG CURRENCIES.

THAT IS HOW GETTING FOREIGN RESERVES BECAME THE MAIN CONCERN OF NATIONS, IF THEY WANTED TO MAINTAIN THE PARITY OF THEIR CURRENCY.

AS A RESULT OF THE OIL CRISIS, WHICH ON THE ONE HAND SAVED THE OIL-PRODUCING COUNTRIES, AND ON THE OTHER HAND DEALT A BLOW TO THE OIL IMPORTERS, PLUS THE UNCONTROLLED FOREIGN DEBT THAT THE PETRODOLLARS BOOM BROUGHT WITH IT, THE COUNTRIES WENT TO THE HILT IN DEBT. AT THE SAME TIME THEY LOST HUGE SUMS IN THE INTERNATIONAL MARKETS BECAUSE OF THE DROP IN THE PRICES OF COFFEE, SILVER, TIN, COPPER, AND OTHER EXPORT PRODUCTS.

IN SHORT, THE SOURCE OF EXCHANGE DECREASED FOR EVERYONE, EVEN THOUGH PRODUCTION OF EACH ITEM INCREASED. DEBTS GREW UNTIL THEY BECAME NIGHTMARES THAT ABSORBED ALMOST ALL THE COUNTRY'S FOREIGN INCOME. THE MONETARY RESERVES THAT WERE BACKING THE CURRENCIES FELL. THAT IS WHY IN LATIN AMERICA THERE HAS BEEN ONE DEVALUATION AFTER ANOTHER, COUNTRY AFTER COUNTRY.

IN THE BEGINNING THE IMF USED WHAT WAS CALLED A STAND-BY LOAN, WHICH HELPED COUNTRIES WHEN THEY RAN SHORT OF RESERVES. WITH THOSE EMERGENCY LOANS THEY COULD MAINTAIN THE PARITY OF THEIR CURRENCY, UNTIL THEY COULD BALANCE THEIR RESERVES.

HOWEVER, COUNTRIES LIKE HONDURAS, WHICH WERE DEEPLY INDEBTED, BEGAN TO FILL THEIR LACK OF INTERNATIONAL RESERVES WITH LOANS AND DONATIONS. EVEN SO THE COUNTRY CONTINUED TO PAY ITS IMPORTS AND EXPENSES IN FOREIGN EXCHANGE, UNTIL IT REACHED THE CURRENT SITUATION IN WHICH WE CANNOT PAY THE DEBT. WE ARE OVERDUE $140 MILLION IN PAYMENTS ON OUR DEBT. OUR CREDIT IS NO LONGER GOOD. THE IMF HAS NO MORE MONEY TO GIVE TO HONDURAS TO CONTINUE ITS VICIOUS CYCLE OF GETTING INTO DEBT TO PAY OFF ITS DEBTS. YET THE UNITED STATES HAS ASKED THE IMF TO TIGHTEN OUR SCREWS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1088 (UNISYS)

BOGOTA, 4 FEB 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [INTERVIEW WITH NORTH SANTANDER GOVERNOR EDUARDO ASSAF ELCURE BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [REPORTER] WE ARE SAYING HELLO AT THIS HOUR TO NORTH SANTANDER GOVERNOR EDUARDO ASSAF ELCURE. DR ASSAF, GOOD DAY.

[ASSAF] GOOD MORNING, RCN [STATION CALL SIGN].

[REPORTER] MR. GOVERNOR, WHAT INFORMATION DOES THE DEPARTMENTAL ADMINISTRATION HAVE ABOUT EVENTS DEALING WITH PUBLIC ORDER, SUCH AS REGRETTABLE INCIDENT IN ARBOLEDAS [MURDER OF ARBOLEDAS MAYOR PEDRO JESUS HERNANDEZ].

[ASSAF] THE OFFICIAL REPORTS ON THE REGRETTABLE CASE IN ARBOLEDAS AT NOON TODAY, AND THOSE CARRIED BY RCN AND OTHER STATIONS, DESCRIBING THE WAY IN WHICH MAYOR PEDRO JESUS HERNANDEZ WAS MURDERED WHILE INAUGURATING A DINING HALL FOR CHILDREN AT JUAN BUENO, ARBOLEDAS MUNICIPALITY, LEAD US TO BELIEVE THAT SOMETHING EXTREMELY SERIOUS IS HAPPENING. HERNANDEZ WAS GOING TO INAUGURATE ON 20-25 FEBRUARY FOUR OR FIVE WORKS THAT ARE IMPORTANT FOR THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE COMMUNITIES AND HAD BEEN DEMANDED BY THEM FOR A LONG TIME. THIS LEADS US TO BELIEVE THAT THE SITUATION IS REALLY DIFFICULT AND THAT OTHER MEASURES WILL HAVE TO BE ADOPTED TO PREVENT A CONTINUATION OF THESE REGRETTABLE ACTIONS, WHICH DESTABILIZE PUBLIC ORDER IN THE DEPARTMENT.

I THINK THAT AFTER THE PEACE TALKS WITH M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] ARE CONCLUDED NEXT WEEK, DR. OCTAVIO PARDO SHOULD IN SOME WAY PROMOTE A TRUCE WITH THE NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY [ELN] AND THE EPL [POPULAR LIBERATION ARMY] TO SEE IF IT IS POSSIBLE TO BEGIN A DIALOGUE AND KEEP THE BLOODSHED FROM CONTINUING IN OUR COUNTRY, MOST PARTICULARLY IN OUR DEPARTMENT. OVER THE COURSE OF A MONTH, TWO MAYORS, WHO WERE CHARACTERIZED AS THE FIGHTINGEST MAYORS -- IN THE SENSE THAT THEY LAUNCHED, EXECUTED, AND COMPLETED WORKS -- HAVE BEEN KILLED IN OUR DEPARTMENT.

[REPORTER] MR. GOVERNOR, HOW MANY MAYORS DID YOU SAY HAVE BEEN KILLED DURING THAT TIME?

[ASSAF] WHAT DID YOU SAY?

[REPOERTER] MR. GOVERNOR, DO YOU BELIEVE THAT, FOR INSTANCE, CIVIC OR POLITICAL LEADERS IN THE AREA OF NORTH SANTANDER CAN PARTICIPATE IN TALKS WITH THE EPL AND THE ELN TO MAKE SERIOUS PROPOSALS TO THE GOVERNMENT ABOUT A POSSIBLE TRUCE, AS YOU SUGGEST?

[ASSAF] IN VIEW OF OUR CURRENT SITUATION, THAT IS, IN VIEW OF THE FACT THAT A MONTH AGO THE MAYOR OF ABREGO WAS KILLED AND THE ARBOLEDAS MAYOR WAS KILLED YESTERDAY, I BELIEVE THAT THE COUNTRY IS PLEASED THAT THE PACIFICATION PROCESS WITH M-19 WILL END THIS WEEK. SO, WHY NOT LOOK FOR AVENUES OF COMMUNICATION WITH THE [1-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] AND THE EPL TO ESTABLISH A TRUCE, AT LEAST DURING THIS ELECTORAL PERIOD, SO THAT ALL COLOMBIANS, ESPECIALLY THOSE OF NORTH SANTANDER, CAN FREELY EXERCISE THEIR SOVEREIGN RIGHT TO PARTICIPATE IN AN ELECTION AND EXPRESS THEIR SATISFACTION WITH OR CONDEMNATION OF THE PEOPLE WHO ARE CURRENTLY GOVERNING THE MUNICIPALITIES? [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1089 (UNISYS)

NO CITY, NO DATE -- [INTERVIEW WITH GARCIA BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] YOU HAVE ALREADY HEARD THE OPINION, FOR EXAMPLE, OF THE AGRARIAN BANK, PROBABLY ALSO THAT OF ENCI [NATIONAL ENTERPRISE FOR INDUSTRIAL MARKETING], CASA, THE CORA PROJECT [WORDS INDISTINCT]. THE COCA GROWERS ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE A FEW DAYS AGO STATING THAT THEY ARE NOT AGAINST THE ERADICATION OF COCA PLANTATIONS BUT COMPLAINING ABOUT THE AGRARIAN BANK'S UNSATISFACTORY SERVICE IN GRANTING LOANS. THIS COMMUNIQUE WAS PUBLISHED BY THE MEDIA A FEW DAYS AGO.

[GARCIA] YES, WE HEARD ABOUT THIS AND ARE ANALYZING IT. BUT THE PROBLEM OF THE 200,000 HECTARES USED FOR ILLEGAL COCA GROWING BY FAR EXCEEDS THE CAPACITY OF THE AGRARIAN BANK, OF THE NATIONAL COCA LEAF ENTERPRISE [EMPRESA NACIONAL DE LA COCA], OR THE ENCI TO FINANCE FERTILIZER. THIS IS A SUBJECT THAT MUST BE DISCUSSED AT THE CONTINENTAL LEVEL. THE HUALLAGA VALLEY IS AN ENCLAVE OF THE U.S. CONSUMERS. IT IS A PERVERSE PROBLEM WITH ECONOMIC REPERCUSSIONS AND IT IS DISTORTING AND DESTROYING THE POSSIBILITY OF OUR PLANTING OTHER CROPS IN THAT AREA. THIS IS WHY WE MUST CONSIDER IT FROM A CONTINENTAL VIEWPOINT, DISCUSSING IT WITH THE COUNTRY WHERE THE PROBLEM ORIGINATES, WHERE IT IS CONSUMED. THE ENCI AND THE AGRARIAN BANK PROBLEM IS IMPORTANT, BUT IT IS VERY SMALL IN COMPARISON TO THE SERIOUSNESS OF THE OVERALL PROBLEM.

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, IS IT TRUE -- AS IT WAS SAID IN THE UNITED STATES -- THAT THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT IS REFUSING TO REPLACE THE PLANTATIONS BECAUSE IT IS NOT ECONOMICALLY CONVENIENT?

[GARCIA] NO, ACCORDING TO SOLID INFORMATION I HAVE AT HAND FROM THE STATE DEPARTMENT AND THE DEPARTMENT IN CHARGE OF DRUG TRAFFICKING, OUR GOVERNMENT HAS MADE THE GREATEST EFFORTS DURING THE PAST FEW YEARS TO ERADICATE COCA PLANTATIONS. A FEW MONTHS AGO THEY RELEASED A REPORT TO THE U.S. MEDIA FROM MAY 1989 THAT SHOWED THAT PERU HAD BROKEN ALL RECORDS FOR ERADICATING COCA IN 1988, IN KEEPING WITH ITS INTERNATIONAL AGREEMENTS. PERU ERADICATED MORE THAN 5,000 HECTARES OF COCA PLANTATIONS THAT YEAR, THUS STABILIZING THE OVERALL AMOUNT OF HECTARES USED FOR COCA GROWING. NOBODY, MUCH LESS THE UNITED STATES, CAN SAY THAT PERU HAS DONE NOTHING.

WE HAVE CARRIED OUT VAST OPERATIONS AND HAVE CONTINUED OUR SILENT TASK TO ERADICATE THESE PLANTATIONS, SOMETIMES WITH REGRETTABLE CONSEQUENCES. THE PEASANT WHO IS FACED WITH BARE LAND AFTER THE COCA IS UPROOTED EITHER ENGAGES IN TERRORIST ACTIVITIES OR IS CONDEMNED TO LIVE IN MISERY. THIS IS WHY WE NEED AN OVERALL ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT ALTERNATIVE THAT MUST BE PART OF A REEVALUATED LATIN AMERICAN-U.S. RELATIONSHIP.

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, THE SITUATION IS NOW THE OPPOSITE TO WHAT THE UNITED STATES IS DOING FOR [WORDS INDISTINCT] A MEETING PUT FORWARD BY THE PRESIDENTS, BECAUSE THEY GIVE $1 TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING WHILE THERE ARE $100 FOR CONSUMPTION.

[GARCIA] YOU ARE RIGHT. IT IS BELIEVED THAT THE TOTAL COST OF COCAINE SOLD ON THE U.S. STREETS IS $100 BILLION. ONLY $8 OR $9 MILLION IS BEING OFFERED TO FIGHT THE ILLEGAL PRODUCTION OF COCA AND TO REPLACE THE CROPS HERE IN PERU. WHAT THE UNITED STATES -- THE MAIN CONSUMER -- HAS BEEN OFFERING IS NOT PROPORTIONAL TO THE MAGNITUDE OF THE PROBLEM.

IF THERE WERE NO CONSUMPTION IN THE UNITED STATES, PERU WOULD NOT PRODUCE COCA LEAVES, EXCEPT FOR THE TRADITIONAL, ANCIENT USES OF PERUVIAN PEOPLE. THE PROBLEM BEGINS THERE. THE RESPONSIBILITY FOR PROVIDING MASSIVE RESOURCES SHOULD BE ASSUMED THROUGH CONCERTED DIALOGUE, NOT UNILATERAL MEASURES, BECAUSE THERE ARE HAWKS IN THE UNITED STATES. THE HAWKS ARE THE BOLDEST MILITARISTS WHO BELIEVE THAT TROOPS CAN BE SENT TO THE HUALLAGA VALLEY, THUS SOLVING THIS SERIOUS PROBLEM.

SUCH AN ACTION WOULD REPRESENT THE VIOLATION OF A NATION'S SOVEREIGNTY, AN UNWANTED UNILATERAL INTERVENTION. WE WANT A SERIOUS, RESPONSIBLE, CONCERTED, FAR-REACHING SOCIOECONOMIC POLICY. THIS IS OUR OBJECTIVE FOR CARTAGENA.

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, CHANGING THE SUBJECT, THE ELECTORAL CAMPAIGN HAS ENTERED THE FINAL STRETCH. OPPOSITION PARTIES HAVE CONSTANTLY MENTIONED YOUR NAME AND WHAT YOU HAVE SAID OR HAVE NOT SAID. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION OF THE CAMPAIGN?

[GARCIA] THOSE ARE MINOR SINS BY THE OPPOSITION. THEY ARE USING ELEMENTS THAT ARE NOT TOTALLY LEGITIMATE, BUT I WILL NOT WASTE MY TIME PASSING JUDGMENT ON MY DEAR FRIEND ENRIQUE CHIRINO SOTO OR ON ANY OF THE LAWMAKERS. I UNDERSTAND THEIR DESIRE AND THEIR NEED TO BE ELECTED. OTHERWISE WHAT WOULD THEY DO IN THE FUTURE? IF THEY WANT TO USE MY NAME, LET THEM USE IT, EVEN IF IT'S IN A NEGATIVE WAY. I HAVE LISTENED TO SO MANY THINGS OVER FOUR AND A HALF YEARS IN OFFICE THAT I AM ACTUALLY A LITTLE PLEASED BY THE FACT THAT THEY ARE DESPERATELY USING MY NAME. AT LEAST I AM HELPING THEM.

[REPORTER] SINCE THE ELECTIONS WILL BE HELD ON 8 APRIL, WHEN WILL SCHOOL CLASSES BEGIN?

[GARCIA] I SAW THAT THE EDUCATION MINISTRY ISSUED A NOTE ANNOUNCING THAT CLASSES WILL BEGIN ON 1 OR 2 APRIL. I WOULD LIKE TO PROPOSE TO THE EDUCATION MINISTER THAT CLASSES BEGIN AFTER 8 APRIL. IT WOULD BE MEANINGLESS TO BEGIN CLASSES AND TO THEN DISCONTINUE THEM IN ORDER TO OPEN THE SCHOOLS FOR THE ELECTIONS. CLASSES COULD THEREFORE BEGIN ON 10 APRIL OR WHEN THE MINISTRY DECIDES. THIS SHOULD BE AFTER 8 APRIL. WE SHOULD CONCENTRATE ALL OF OUR EFFORTS ON OPENING THE VOTING SITES. I AM ANNOUNCING THAT CLASSES WILL BEGIN AFTER 8 APRIL.

DEV-MUC3-1090 (UNISYS)

TEGUCIGALPA, 6 FEB 90 (CNA) -- [TEXT] PRESIDENT RAFAEL LEONARDO CALLEJAS ROMERO SAID TUESDAY HONDURAS IS FACING AN EXTREMELY CHALLENGING SITUATION AND THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA CAN HELP A GREAT DEAL IN SOLVING THE PROBLEMS CONFRONTING HIS COUNTRY.

CALLEJAS, INAUGURATED ON JAN. 27, TOLD THE CNA HONDURAS IS FACING A CRISIS WHICH HIS NEW ADMINISTRATION, WITH HELP AND SUPPORT FROM THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA, WILL BE ABLE TO TIDE OVER.

HONDURAS LACKS FOREIGN EXCHANGE TO BUY OIL, MEDICINE AND FOOD FROM ABROAD. TEGUCIGALPA'S FOREIGN DEBTS TOTAL WELL OVER U.S. DLRS [DOLLARS] 200 MILLION. "WE ARE FACING A STEEP SHORTAGE OF BASIC FOODS, CORN IN PARTICULAR," CALLEJAS SAID.

A POTENTIALLY RICH COUNTRY, HONDURAS CAN OVERCOME ALL ITS DIFFICULT PROBLEMS AND ACHIEVE PROSPERITY IN THE LONG RUN, BUT IT NEEDS A SHOT IN THE ARM, CALLEJAS SAID.

THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA, CALLEJAS APPEALED, CAN EXTEND "SHORT-TERM BRIDGE LOANS" TO HONDURAS TO HELP SOLVE THE PROBLEMS OF ACUTE SHORTAGE IN FOOD AND OTHER NECESSITIES. "A SHORT-TERM CREDIT OF DLRS 5 MILLION, FOR INSTANCE, CAN HELP US MAKE UP FOR THE SHORTAGE AND THEN WE CAN MOVE AHEAD," CALLEJAS SAID.

"THE SITUATION IS A CRITICAL ONE," CALLEJAS SAID, "BUT WE WILL BE ABLE TO COPE WITH IT AND SURGE AHEAD FOR GREATER PROSPERITY, AND WHAT WE NOW NEED IS A SHORT-TERM HELP FROM OUR FRIENDS IN THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA."

HE SAID THE PEOPLE OF HONDURAS HAVE YET TO SENSE THE CRISIS THEY ARE FACING NOW. THE FINANCIAL CRISIS, IN PARTICULAR, IS COMPARABLE TO THE ONE THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA FACED IN AND SHORTLY AFTER 1950.

"MY ADMINISTRATION KNOWS WHAT SHALL BE DONE," CALLEJAS SAID. HE WILL LET THE PEOPLE FULLY UNDERSTAND THE CRISIS AND CULTIVATE A SENSE OF CRISIS THAT IS NEEDED TO RALLY THEMSELVES BEHIND THE GOVERNMENT TO MOVE FORWARD.

THE PEOPLE OF THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA HAVE SET A "GOOD EXAMPLE" FOR OTHER NATIONS IN CRISIS TO FOLLOW, CALLEJAS SAID. "OVER THE PAST 40 YEARS," HE POINTED OUT, "YOU HAVE DEMONSTRATED WHAT CAN BE DONE TO OVERCOME THE DIFFICULTIES AND ACHIEVE PROSPERITY."

ASIDE FROM THE SHORT-TERM CREDIT, THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA CAN SEND A HIGH-LEVEL MISSION TO ADVISE HONDURAS ON HOW TO SOLVE ITS LONG-TERM FINANCIAL PROBLEM, CALLEJAS SAID. "YOUR COUNTRY HAS EXPERIENCE IN THIS FIELD," HE ADDED, "AND WE HOPE WE WILL BENEFIT FROM YOUR EXPERIENCE."

ANOTHER FIELD OF COOPERATION BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES IS TRADE AND INVESTMENT, CALLEJAS SAID. HONDURAS IS SETTING UP AN INDUSTRIAL PARK, AND INVESTMENT FROM THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA IS MORE THAN WELCOME, HE ADDED.

THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA IS OPENING ITS MARKET TO FOREIGN IMPORTS, AND A SMALL PERCENTAGE OF TAIWAN'S TOBACCO MARKET, IF HONDURAS CAN EARN IT, "WILL HELP A GREAT DEAL AND START A CHAIN ACTION OF DEVELOPMENT," CALLEJAS SAID. THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE GENERATED FROM THE SALES OF TOBACCO CAN BE USED TO PAY BACK SOME OF TEGUCIGALPA'S FOREIGN DEBT. THE REPAYMENT WILL EARN MORE INTERNATIONAL CREDIT, WHICH IN TURN SUPPORTS OTHER PROJECTS OF DEVELOPMENT.

THE PRESENCE OF A U.N. MILITARY OBSERVER GROUP IN HONDURAS, CALLEJAS SAID, WILL HELP STABILIZE THE SITUATION IN CENTRAL AMERICA. THE MISSION IS TO HELP EASE THE TENSION ALONG THE BORDERS OF EL SALVADOR AND NICARAGUA, WHICH WAS HEIGHTENED BY GUERRILLA ACTIVITIES.

CALLEJAS HAS VISITED THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA TWICE BEFORE. HE TOURED THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA AS MINISTER OF NATURAL RESOURCES IN 1968 AND AGAIN AS CHAIRMAN OF THE NATIONAL PARTY IN 1988.

ASKED IF HE WOULD ATTEND THE PRESIDENTIAL INAUGURATION IN TAIPEI ON MAY 20, CALLEJAS SAID HE WOULD "TRY MY BEST TO GO (TO TAIPEI) MYSELF." IF HE IS UNABLE TO ATTEND, HE ADDED, HE WILL SEND HIS PRESIDENT OF THE NATIONAL CONGRESS, RODOLFO IRIAS NAVAS.

"IF I CANNOT VISIT THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA IN MAY," CALLEJAS SAID, "I WILL MAKE A VISIT TO YOUR COUNTRY BEFORE THE END OF THIS YEAR." MOST LIKELY, HE ADDED, HE WILL PAY A STATE VISIT TO THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA IN NOVEMBER.

IN RETURN, CALLEJAS SAID, "WE WILL BE HONORED TO HAVE YOUR PRESIDENT, PRESIDENT LI, VISIT US."

RELATIONS BETWEEN HONDURAS AND THE REPUBLIC OF CHINA ARE "EXTREMELY CLOSE ONES," CALLEJAS SAID. "AND WE IN HONDURAS HOPE TO FURTHER CEMENT THOSE EXTREMELY GOOD RELATIONS," HE POINTED OUT.

SUCH GOOD RELATIONSHIPS SHOULD NOT BE MONOPOLIZED BY THE GOVERNMENTS, CALLEJAS SAID. "WE NEED MORE CONTACT AMONG THE PEOPLE IN ALL WALKS OF LIFE, ON CULTURAL, SOCIAL AND COMMERCIAL LEVELS, SO THAT WE MAY CONTINUE IMPROVING THE EXTREMELY GOOD RELATIONSHIP THAT HAS EXISTED BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES," HE POINTED OUT.

DEV-MUC3-1091 (UNISYS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 6 FEB 90 (TELEONCE TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [TEXT] THIS MORNING PRESIDENT VINICIO CEREZO HOSTED A NEWS CONFERENCE AT THE PRESIDENT'S PALACE OFFICE. THE PRESIDENT WAS ASKED ABOUT THE HUMAN RIGHTS SITUATION IN OUR COUNTRY. IN ADDITION, [WORDS INDISTINCT] PRESENTED BY THE UNITED NATIONS RAPPORTEUR OF THE UN HUMAN RIGHTS COMMISSION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CEREZO] [WORDS INDISTINCT] OF THE COMMISSION THAT HAS ARRIVED IN GUATEMALA [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WE ALL MUST ADMIT THAT IN 1989 THERE WAS [WORDS INDISTINCT] THAT CREATED AN ATMOSPHERE OF TERRORISM AND [WORDS INDISTINCT]. ON VARIOUS OCCASIONS AND IN SEVERAL CRIMINAL AND POLITICAL CASES, IT WAS DECIDED THAT [WORDS INDISTINCT] THAT CONTINUES PROGRESSING, BUT THERE IS AN EVEN BETTER WAY YET. THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER IS THAT THE INSTITUTIONS THAT ARE GOING TO PROTECT HUMAN RIGHTS ARE MAKING MORE PROGRESS EACH DAY AND BECOMING MORE OPERATIONAL. THE AUTHORITIES ARE BECOMING MORE COOPERATIVE EVERY DAY WITH THE VARIOUS INSTITUTIONS THAT ARE CONCERNED ABOUT THE HUMAN RIGHTS SITUATION.

[WORDS INDISTINCT] TO CREATE A NEW SYSTEM FOR LOCATING MISSING PEOPLE. WE HAVE FOUND A SYSTEM THAT ALLOWS US TO LOCATE MANY MISSING PEOPLE, AND [WORDS INDISTINCT]. [PASSAGE INDISTINCT].

FRANKLY SPEAKING, [NAME INDISTINCT] IS A SERIOUS MAN WHO DESERVES ALL OF MY TRUST AND RESPECT FOR HIS CAPABILITIES. HE HAS SAID THAT WE HAVE PROBLEMS IN CONTROLLING SOME TERRORIST GROUPS, AND WHAT WE NEED IS ASSISTANCE IN IMPROVING OUR EFFICIENCY. HE HAS POINTED OUT SOME DEFECTS IN OUR PENAL PROCEDURES WHICH MAKE IT DIFFICULT FOR US TO KEEP THESE PEOPLE IN PRISON.

HOWEVER, HIS CONCLUSIONS DO NOT NECESSARILY MEAN THAT WE ARE GETTING WORSE. THAT HAS NOT BEEN MENTIONED IN THE NEWS. HIS CONCLUSIONS NOTES THAT IN SPITE OF THESE OBSERVATIONS THAT HE HAD TO MAKE AS UNITED NATIONS OBSERVER FOR GUATEMALA, THE SITUATION IN OUR COUNTRY HAS OBVIOUSLY IMPROVED, COMPARED TO THE PREVIOUS YEARS. WE ARE TAKING ALL OF THIS INTO CONSIDERATION. THIS HAS BEEN INCLUDED IN A WRITTEN REPORT THAT WILL BE NOTED IN GENEVA IN ORDER TO CONSIDER TREATMENT FOR GUATEMALA. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1092 (UNISYS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 24 JAN 90 (EL GRAFICO) -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] A SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL MISSION, MADE UP OF PROMINENT LEADERS OF THAT ORGANIZATION, ARRIVED IN THE COUNTRY ON 23 JANUARY TO "DEMAND" THAT THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT CONDUCT AN EXHAUSTIVE INVESTIGATION INTO THE MURDER OF SALVADORAN OPPOSITION LEADER HECTOR OQUELI COLINDRES AND GUATEMALAN GILDA FLORES. THEIR KIDNAPPING AND SUBSEQUENT MURDER TOOK PLACE IN OUR COUNTRY AND THUS, GUATEMALAN AUTHORITIES, WITHOUT ANY KIND OF MEDDLING, SHOULD SOLVE THIS CASE. GUATEMALAN COURTS OF JUSTICE HAVE THE DUTY TO REQUEST, AS PART OF THE INVESTIGATION, THE TESTIMONIES OF WITNESSES AND CONCLUSIONS OF EXPERTS INVOLVED IN THE CASE. ACCORDING TO GUATEMALAN LAW, THERE IS A PERIOD ALLOTTED FOR INITIAL INVESTIGATIONS DURING WHICH NO PUBLIC STATEMENTS CAN BE MADE OR PRESSURES EXERTED WHICH MIGHT HAMPER THE COURSE OF JUSTICE.

THIS IS WHY THE FACT THAT A DELEGATION, WHICH IS MADE UP OF RESPECTABLE PEOPLE WHO DESERVE OUR ADMIRATION, NOT ONLY BECAUSE OF THEIR OUTSTANDING POLITICAL VIRTUES, BUT ALSO BECAUSE OF THEIR HONEST BEHAVIOR AS CITIZENS, IS COMING TO "DEMAND" THAT OUR AUTHORITIES INVESTIGATE THE CRIME, AS IF THEY WERE NOT ALREADY OFFICIALLY DOING SO, IS TO A CERTAIN EXTENT HAMPERING JUSTICE. IT HAPPENS THAT THE ILLUSTRIOUS VISITORS CAME HERE WITH THE EVIDENT GOAL OF ACCUSING THE ALLEGED AUTHORS OF THE DOUBLE CRIME. IN PUBLIC STATEMENTS, THEY HAVE ALREADY SAID THAT "FORCES OF THE GUATEMALAN AND SALVADORAN EXTREME RIGHT" MURDERED THEM. THESE STATEMENTS ARE AS UNCALLED FOR AS THOSE UTTERED BY PRESIDENT CRISTIANI IN EL SALVADOR WHEN HE SAID THAT THE MURDERERS OF THE SIX UCA [CENTRAL AMERICAN UNIVERSITY] JESUITS WERE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] GUERRILLAS AND WAS LATER FORCED TO RETRACT, WHEN THE INVESTIGATIONS REVEALED THAT MEMBERS OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES CARRIED OUT THE MURDER.

IN THE FACE OF DOMESTIC AND INTERNATIONAL PRESSURE, AND THE COMDEMNATION OF THE BRUTAL MURDER OF THE SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC LEADERS, PRESIDENT CEREZO DECIDED TO ESTABLISH AN INVESTIGATIVE COMMISSION TO WHICH HE PLANS TO ADD A REPRESENTATIVE OF AN INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION. ON 23 JANUARY THE SOCIALIST DELEGATE WHO IS IN THE COUNTRY (WITHOUT NAMING IT) CLEARLY REFERRED TO A LEGALLY REGISTERED GUATEMALAN POLITICAL PARTY, WHICH ENJOYS FULL POLITICAL RIGHTS, AS THE "NANNY" PARTY OF THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE, ARENA, OF EL SALVADOR. HE IS LEVELLING SERIOUS CHARGES, WHICH COULD EVEN CREATE LEGAL AND POLITICAL CONFLICTS BETWEEN GUATEMALA AND EL SALVADOR, BY INSISTING THAT THE CRIME WAS POLITICALLY MOTIVATED, WHICH SEEMS TO BE EVIDENT, AND BY LINKING THE CRIME TO POLITICAL PARTIES OF THE TWO COUNTRIES. WITH THE DUE RESPECT THAT THE PRESIDENTIAL COMMISSION DESERVES, THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE SHOULD BE CONSULTED ABOUT WHAT SHOULD BE DONE NEXT BECAUSE THE CASE IS UNDER THE PURVIEW OF GUATEMALAN COURTS, ESPECIALLY THOSE IN JUTIAPA JURISDICTION. THOSE COURTS SHOULD BE THE ONES TASKED WITH COLLECTING THE EVIDENCE, ISSUING THE SUMMONS, AND MAKING THE NECESSARY STATEMENTS. ANYTHING ELSE CONSTITUTES INTERFERING WITH JUSTICE. IN THIS REGARD, THE FACT THAT PRESIDENT CEREZO IS GUESSING ABOUT WHO MIGHT BE THE AUTHOR OF THIS REPUDIABLE BLOODY MURDER IS INAPPROPRIATE BECAUSE IT IS NOT HIS DUTY TO DO SO, EVEN IF THE SOCIALISTS THREATEN TO SEEK CONDEMNATION AGAINST GUATEMALA AT THE UNITED NATIONS FOR VIOLATIONS OF HUMAN RIGHTS WHICH ARE LOOMING OVER HIS GOVERNMENT.

DEV-MUC3-1094 (UNISYS)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 5 FEB 90 (LA PRENSA) -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] DURING THE LAST FEW DAYS, THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE FOR CONTINUISM, DANIEL ORTEGA, HAS BEEN INSISTING ON HIS INTENTION OF A QUICK RECONCILIATION WITH THE U.S. GOVERNMENT. NEVERTHELESS, HE SAYS SO AMID SLANDER AND THREATS THAT INVALIDATE THE SINCERITY OF HIS REMARKS.

FOR ORTEGA AND HIS SPOKESMEN, TO BE RESPECTED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT AND TO MANAGE AN AGREEMENT WITH THE UNITED STATES IS NOW HIS PARTY'S "BEST GUARANTEE," THAT PARTY'S GREAT ELECTORAL OFFER. THE ONLY POSSIBLE EXPLANATION FOR THIS INCOHERENT AND CONTRADICTORY ATTITUDE IS AS A REELECTION STRATEGY, REALIZING THE POPULARITY OF THE IDEA OF NORMALIZING FRIENDLY RELATIONS WITH THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION. ORTEGA HAS NOT WANTED TO REMAIN DISTANCED FROM THAT ASPIRATION, WHICH THE PEOPLE JUDGE AS INDISPENSABLE TO IMPROVE THE CRISIS THEY ARE IN.

THE TRUTH IS THAT ANY UNNECESSARY DISTANCING OF RELATIONS BETWEEN THE U.S. GOVERNMENT AND THE SANDINISTS WAS DUE TO THE LATTER'S INITIATIVE.

EVERYONE KNOWS THE EFFORTS MADE BY BOTH MR BOWDLER AS WELL AS LAWRENCE PEZULLO TO ATTAIN CORDIAL RELATIONS WITH THE SANDINIST GOVERNMENT THAT FOLLOWED SOMOZA DEBAYLE'S. THE STRONG PRESSURES ON THE DICTATOR TO RESIGN WERE DECISIVE IN HIS DEPARTURE. THE CARTER GOVERNMENT'S MASSIVE AND EARLY AID WAS DECISIVE IN STABILIZING THE REVOLUTIONARY REGIME.

THE FSLN [SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] NATIONAL DIRECTORATE, HOWEVER, HAD OTHER INSTRUCTIONS FROM HAVANA. AS SOON AS THEY GOT OUT OF THE AIRPLANE, THEY TOOK IT OUT ON THE "YANKEES, ENEMY OF HUMANITY," WHICH WERE ONLY SEEKING AN UNPREJUDICED RELATIONSHIP WITH THE NEW LEADERS. THAT RHETORIC WOULD HAVE BEEN LESS OBVIOUS IF IT HAD NOT BEEN THAT THE TRUE PURPOSE OF THAT CONFRONTATION CAMPAIGN WAS TO JUSTIFY ITS MISSION OF SETTING CENTRAL AMERICA ON FIRE AND THUS DISTRACTING THE UNITED STATES WITH A STRATEGY OF DESTABILIZING THE AREA, WHICH IS CONVENIENT TO USSR INTERESTS.

THE FMLN'S [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] GENERAL STAFF MOVED TO NIACARAGUA, AND THE CLANDESTINE RADIO STATION VENCEREMOS BEGAN BROADCASTING FROM MANAGUA WHILE THE WHOLE COUNTRY BECAME A SANCTUARY FOR SALVADORAN TERRORISTS AND A LOGISTICS RESUPPLY BASE.

THE U.S. ADMINISTRATION MADE ONE LAST EFFORT AT MANZANILLO, BUT DEPUTY FOREIGN MINISTER TINOCO ONLY WENT TO READ A PREPARED TEXT, USING THAT BRILLIANT OPPORTUNITY AS A CENTER STAGE FOR PROPAGANDA AND DISTURBANCE.

MENAWHILE, THE SLOGAN "IF NICARAGUA WON, SO WILL EL SALVADOR," FLOODED RADIO STATIONS, BANNERS, WATCHWORDS, GRAFFITI, AND BOASTFUL SPEECHES, WHILE THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLAS MADE EVERY EFFORT TO OVERTHROW THE GOVERNMENT AND THE GUATEMALAN REVOLUTIONARY BANDS DID LIKEWISE, DEVASTATING EL PETEN.

DEPUTY SECRETARY OF STATE ENDERS CAME HIMSELF TO HOLD TALKS WITH THE FSLN'S GENERAL DIRECTORATE, PROPOSING AN ARRANGEMENT THAT WOULD GUARANTEE STABILITY IN EXCHANGE FOR THEIR MESSIAH-LIKE PROJECT OF SUBVERTING THE REGION.

WHEN THESE TALKS FAILED, WHAT FOLLOWED WAS INEVITABLE AND IS REGRETTABLE.

NOW, EVEN THOUGH THE SANDINISTS MAY TRY AFTER 10 YEARS TO MAKE UP FOR LOST TIME, TRYING TO PUT THINGS RIGHT, THE RECIPE CONTINUES TO BE THE SAME: ONE, "GENUINELY FREE AND JUST" ELECTIONS IN NICARAGUA, AND TWO, THE REMOVAL OF THEIR INCITING HANDS FROM CENTRAL AMERICA. ON THESE LINES, SECRETARY OF STATE JAMES BAKER'S DECLARATION LAST WEEK WAS CLEAR AND CATEGORICAL: CONVINCING PROOF THAT THE ELECTIONS WERE HONEST, "SOMETHING VERY HARD TO DETERMINE, UNLESS ORTEGA ALLOWS CONGRESSINAL OBSERVERS," AND CONVICING PROOF THAT NICARAGUA HAS STOPPED SENDING ARMS TO EL SALVADOR. IF THE ELECTIONS ARE FRAUDULENT, SENTENCE HAS ALREADY BEEN PASSED: "THE UNITED STATES COULD MAKE NICARAGUA'S SITUATION TOUGHER." IN OTHER WORDS, ORTEGA WOULD CONFIRM HIMSELF ONLY AS A GUARANTOR OF WAR AND MISERY.

DEV-MUC3-1095 (UNISYS)

SANTIAGO, 10 FEB 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [REPORT] [GRACIELA CONTRERAS] [TEXT] PRESIDENT AUGUSTO PINOCHET SAID HERE THAT THIS IS THE LAST CITY HE WILL VISIT DURING THE FIRST PART OF HIS NATIONWIDE TOUR TO BID TAKE LEAVE OF THE CITIZENRY AS CHIEF OF STATE. HE ALSO THANKED THE CHILEAN PEOPLE FOR THEIR HARD WORK TO MAKE PROGRESS.

THE PRESIDENT SAID HE WAS PLEASED TO OBSERVE OPTIMISM AMONG THE PEOPLE IN THE NORTHERN REGION AS IN THE REST OF THE COUNTRY. PINOCHET SAID IN COPIAPO THAT THOSE WHO TRY TO TARNISH THE HONOR OF THE ARMED FORCES AND FORCES OF ORDER ARE AGAINST CHILE. HE MADE THESE STATEMENTS DURING A PUBLIC CEREMONY AT THE ALHAMBRA THEATRE IN COPIAPO, WHERE HE WAS HONORED FOR HIS GOVERNMENT WORK IN THE PAST 16 YEARS. AFTER ENUMERATING THE ACHIEVEMENTS IN THE THIRD REGION, THE PRESIDENT REFERRED TO HIS COMPLETED MISSION.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PINOCHET] WE HAVE COMPLETED OUR MISSION BECAUSE WE HAVE BEHAVED IN KEEPING WITH THE ARMED FORCES TRADITION. WE MAINTAINED THE HONOR WE INHERITED FROM OUR HISTORIC HEROES. THOSE WHO IGNORE THE GREAT WORK CARRIED OUT BY THE NATIONAL DEFENSE INSTITUTIONS ARE BEING IRRESPONSIBLE WITH HISTORY.

THOSE WHO TRY TO TARNISH THE HONOR OF THE ARMED FORCES AND FORCES OF ORDER ARE AGAINST CHILE AND ITS ESSENTIAL INSTITUTIONS. THIS IS NOT ACCEPTABLE, LADIES AND GENTLEMEN. [APPLAUSE] [END RECORDING]

BEFORE MEETING WITH THE COPIAPO CITIZENRY, THE PRESIDENT ALSO REFERRED TO THE VIOLENT ATTACKS THAT TOOK PLACE IN SANTIAGO. HE SAID THAT THESE ATTACKS WILL NOT HINDER THE TALKS ON THE TRANSFER OF POWER. HE ADDED THAT HE DID NOT HAVE FULL REPORTS ON THE SUBVERSIVE ATTACK.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [PINOCHET] I THINK IT IS NORMAL, A SITUATION IN KEEPING WITH THE DYNAMICS OF CURRENT POLITICS. I DO NOT FORESEE GREATER CONSEQUENCES TO IT. WHEN I GET BACK THERE POSSIBLY [PASSAGE INDISTINCT]

[UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, THERE HAS BEEN A TERRORIST ATTACK IN THE CAPITAL, WHAT DO YOU KNOW ABOUT IT?

[PINOCHET] I CANNOT TELL YOU, I HAVE BEEN TOLD OVER THE PHONE, BUT IT IS CONFIDENTIAL INFORMATION WHICH I CANNOT REPEAT, BUT I DO NOT THINK IT IS TOO SERIOUS.

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, THAT DOES NOT BREAK AWAY [PASSAGE INDISTINCT].

[PINOCHET] ACCORDING TO WHAT I KNOW SO FAR, NOTHING HAS HAPPENED THAT COULD TURN INTO ANYTHING MORE SERIOUS. THINGS ARE GOING ALONG JUST THE SAME, WITH THE SMALL PROBLEMS THAT ARISE DAILY WITHIN THE DYNAMICS OF POLITICS, BUT AS I JUST SAID, I DO NOT THINK [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] MR. PRESIDENT, DO YOU THINK THAT THIS ATTACK WAS COMMITTED BY THOSE WHO ESCAPED FROM THE SANTIAGO PRISON?

[PINOCHET] THAT IS WHAT I MEAN; I DO NOT THINK IT IS VERY IMPORTANT SINCE REACTIONS OF VIOLENCE HAVE INCREASED. IT COULD HAVE BEEN THEM. ACCORDING TO THE INFORMATION I GOT, IT COULD BE SERIOUS BUT NOT AS MUCH AS TO THINK THAT THIS IS THE END OF THE WORLD. [END RECORDING]

FINALLY, PRESIDENT PINOCHET SAID HE STILL HAD NO FURTHER REPORTS ON THE TERRORIST ATTACK IN WHICH ANOTHER CARABINERO WAS SLAIN, AND HE REGRETTED THE DISSOLUTION OF THE CNI [NATIONAL INTELLIGENCE CENTER] WHICH WAS A SPECIALIZED ORGANIZATION WELL ACQUAINTED WITH THE TERRORIST CELLS.

THE CHIEF OF STATE WILL END HIS TOUR OF NORTHERN CHILE IN SERENA. HE WILL RETURN TO SANTIAGO TODAY.

DEV-MUC3-1096 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 7 FEB 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] COL. RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHIEF OF THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES GENERAL STAFF, SAID TODAY THAT 145 GUERRILLAS AND 53 SOLDIERS HAD BEEN KILLED IN 386 CLASHES IN JANUARY WITHIN THE FRAMEWORK OF THE COUNTERINSURGENCY OPERATION "VICTORIA."

COL. PONCE SAID THAT THE ARMY HAD DESTROYED 61 CAMPS AND THWARTED 48 LOGISTICAL GUERRILLA OPERATIONS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY IN JANUARY, WHILE THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] SAID IT HAD INFLICTED 532 ARMY CASUALTIES, INCLUDING 10 OFFICERS, IN ARMED CONFRONTATIONS DURING THE MONTH.

COL. PONCE HELD THE GUERRILLA MOVEMENT RESPONSIBLE FOR THE "MURDER" OF 19 PEOPLE AND ADDED THAT 22 REBELS HAD DESERTED FROM THE FMLN RANKS. HE STATED THAT THE REBELS HAD CONDUCTED 235 SABOTAGE OPERATIONS AGAINST THE TELEPHONE, ENERGY, AND TRANSPORTATION SYSTEMS, AS WELL AS THE GOVERNMENT INFRASTRUCTURE AND PRIVATE PROPERTY.

OPERATION "VICTORIA," WHICH BEGAN IN JANUARY, WAS AIMED AT ATTACKING THE GUERRILLA GROUPS THAT STAYED BEHIND IN THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR AND THE COUNTRY'S MAIN CITIES AFTER THE REBEL OFFENSIVE OF 11 NOVEMBER 1989.

PONCE SAID THAT 45 PERCENT OF THE SALVADORAN ARMY (APPROXIMATELY 30,000 SOLDIERS) IS PARTICIPATING IN THE NATIONWIDE OPERATION "VICTORIA."

THE ARMY CONFISCATED 186 WEAPONS OF VARIOUS CALIBERS DURING THE CONFRONTATIONS IN JANUARY.

PONCE ADDED THAT 1,980 PEOPLE, MOST OF THEM YOUTHS, HAVE BEEN KIDNAPPED BY THE REBELS SINCE 11 NOVEMBER AND ARE RECEIVING GUERRILLA TRAINING IN CHALATENANGO, MORAZAN, AND USULUTAN DEPARTMENTS.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES, IN THE LAST DECADE THE SALVADORAN GUERRILLA MOVEMENT HAS CAUSED ECONOMIC LOSSES TO THE COUNTRY OF APPROXIMATELY $430 MILLION AS A RESULT OF TELECOMMUNICATION AND ENERGY SABOTAGE OPERATIONS.

DEV-MUC3-1098 (UNISYS)

BOGOTA, 11 FEB 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS SAID HE WILL ASK U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH -- DURING THE 15 FEBRUARY DRUG SUMMIT TO BE HELD IN CARTAGENA -- FOR GREATER ASSISTANCE TO BOLIVIA AND PERU, THE WORLD'S BIGGEST PRODUCERS OF COCA LEAVES.

DURING AN INFORMAL TALK WITH NEWSMEN, BARCO SAID THAT AT THE SUMMIT HE WILL ASK PRESIDENT BUSH TO PROVIDE ECONOMIC AND MILITARY ASSISTANCE TO FIGHT THE "WAR" HE HIMSELF DECLARED ON DRUG- TRAFFICKING MAFIAS AFTER VARIOUS TERRORIST ACTIONS LAST AUGUST.

ALTHOUGH HE DID NOT SPECIFY THE KIND OF AID OR HOW IT SHOULD BE PROVIDED, BARCO VARGAS SAID THE ECONOMIC MEASURES HE WILL ASK FOR WOULD CONCENTRATE ON A GREATER OPENING OF THE U.S. MARKET TO EXPORTS FROM ANDEAN COUNTRIES AFFECTED BY PRODUCTION AND CHEMICAL PROCESSING OF COCAINE.

IN ADDITION TO PRESIDENTS BUSH AND BARCO, BOLIVIAN PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA AND PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA WILL ALSO ATTEND THE SUMMIT. THEY ARE EXPECTED TO PRESENT PROPOSALS ON THE SUBSTITUTION OF OTHER CROPS FOR COCA LEAVES -- THE BASE FOR MAKING COCAINE -- WHILE BEARING IN MIND THE ECONOMIC WELL-BEING AND SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT OF PEASANTS ENGAGED IN THIS ACTIVITY.

THE FOUR PRESIDENTS WILL MEET FOR NO LONGER THAN FIVE HOURS AND WILL SIGN A DOCUMENT IN WHICH THEY WILL DEFINE STRATEGIES TO DEVELOP AN OVERALL STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING.

ACCORDING TO UNOFFICIAL REPORTS, THE POINTS THAT WILL BE INCLUDED IN THE JOINT DOCUMENT INCLUDE STRENGTHENING ANDEAN ECONOMIES BY INCREASING EXPORTS, AND THE "TOTAL STRUGGLE" AGAINST INTERNATIONAL DRUG-TRAFFICKING GANGS BY REDUCING DEMAND, CONSUMPTION, AND SUPPLY OF HALLUCINOGENIC DRUGS.

BARCO VARGAS SAID INDUSTRIALIZED NATIONS SHOULD "ESPECIALLY HELP THE FRATERNAL COUNTRIES OF BOLIVIA AND PERU, WHICH HAVE GREAT NEEDS."

ONE OF THE COLOMBIAN OBJECTIVES AT THE ANTIDRUG SUMMIT WILL BE TO MAKE THE UNITED STATES UNDERSTAND ITS CORESPONSIBILITY FOR THE SERIOUS COCAINE-TRAFFICKING PROBLEM BECAUSE OF ITS ALMOST 14.5 MILLION DRUG ADDICTS AND BECAUSE OF ITS SALES OF WEAPONS AND CHEMICAL COMPONENTS -- WHICH SEEM TO HAVE NO OFFICIAL CONTROL -- TO MAFIAS.

AT LEAST 5,000 MEN FROM COLOMBIAN SECURITY CORPS ARE ALREADY PATROLLING STRATEGIC SITES IN CARTAGENA TO PREVENT ANY ACT OF TERRORISM THAT COULD BE PERPETRATED BY THE DRUG CARTELS DURING THE SUMMIT.

DEV-MUC3-1101 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 FEB 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES DENIED TODAY THAT THEIR PLANES HAD BOMBED A REFUGEE CAMP AND CIVILIAN SETTLEMENTS IN THE DEPARTMENTS OF CHALATENANGO AND MORAZAN, LOCATED NORTH AND NORTHEAST OF SAN SALVADOR, AS RELIGIOUS SOURCES HAD REPORTED YESTERDAY.

A COMMUNIQUE RELEASED BY THE ARMED FORCES STATES THAT FIVE PERSONS, INCLUDING FOUR MINORS, WERE KILLED, NOT AS A RESULT OF THE BOMBINGS, "BUT AS A RESULT OF THE CLASHES" BETWEEN SOLDIERS AND GUERRILLAS AT THE "CORRAL DE LAS PIEDRAS" REFUGEE CAMP IN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT.

THE ARMED FORCES ACCUSED THE GUERRILLAS OF FIRING ROCKETS "THAT HIT SEVERAL HOUSES," AND IT REPORTED THAT A SOLDIER AND SIX GUERRILLAS WERE KILLED IN THE CLASHES, WHICH LASTED BETWEEN 0600 AND 1400.

HOWEVER, EDUARDO ALAS, THE BISHOP OF CHALATENANGO, TOLD THE MEDIA TODAY THAT FIVE PEOPLE WERE KILLED AND AT LEAST 14 CIVILIANS WERE WOUNDED WHEN THE CAMP WAS ATTACKED FROM THE AIR.

"ACCORDING TO THE ENTIRE COMMUNITY," ALAS SAID, "A ROCKET OR A GRENADE-TYPE DEVICE FELL ON ONE OF THE HOUSES WITH MANY PEOPLE INSIDE, INCLUDING CHILDREN. I SAW THE MUTILATED BODIES OF THE CHILDREN AND HOLES IN THE ROOF. THERE WAS A LOT OF MACHINEGUN FIRE."

MOREOVER, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) CONDEMNED THE "COWARDLY ATTACK" ON THE REFUGEE HOMES, WHICH, HE SAID, WERE "HIGLY VISIBLE AND IDENTIFIED AS CIVILIAN HOUSING."

"THIS INCIDENT SHOWS A TOTAL LACK OF COMMITMENT BY THE ARMED FORCES TO REACH A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION, AND IT REAFFIRMS THE NEED TO MAINTAIN THE ARMED STRUGGLE AND TO USE MILITARY POWER TO REACH A NEGOTIATED SOLUTION SO THAT HUMAN RIGHTS ARE RESPECTED," THE FMLN SAID IN A COMMUNIQUE RELEASED TODAY.

THE FMLN ALSO CONDEMNED AN ALLEGED BOMBING OF THE TOWN OF CACAOPERA, IN MORAZAN DEPARTMENT, WHICH THE ARMED FORCES HAVE DENIED.

ACCORDING TO THE GUERRILLAS, A WOMAN WAS WOUNDED AND A SUGAR CANE HARVEST WAS DESTROYED BY THE BOMBS, BUT ACCORDING TO COL MAURICIO VARGAS, MILITARY CHIEF OF THE REGION, "THERE WAS NO BOMBING, BUT CLASHES WITH A GROUP OF GUERRILLAS WITH THE SUPPORT OF HELICOPTERS."

THE MILITARY CHIEF PROMISED, HOWEVER, TO CARRY OUT THE "PERTINENT INVESTIGATIONS TO LEARN WHAT HAPPENED IN THE REGION."

DEV-MUC3-1102 (UNISYS)

BOGOTA, 13 FEB 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] THE NATIONAL POLICE'S DIJIN [DIRECTORATE OF JUDICIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS] HAS REVEALED A TERRORIST PLAN THAT THE NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY, ELN, WAS PLANNING TO CARRY OUT IN NORTHERN AND EASTERN COLOMBIA IN MARCH, AND ADDED THAT THIS SUBVERSIVE GROUP IS DIVIDED BY DIFFERENCES BETWEEN ITS LEADERS.

A COMMUNIQUE ISSUED BY THIS SECURITY ORGANIZATION STATES THAT, FOLLOWING AN EXHAUSTIVE INTELLIGENCE INVESTIGATION, IT WAS CONCLUDED THAT THIS GUERRILLA MOVEMENT IS DIVIDED, BECAUSE AN ELN FACTION REFUSES TO ACCEPT THE DECISIONS OF FORMER SPANISH PRIEST MANUEL PEREZ MARTINEZ.

IT ALSO STATES THAT THE DISSIDENT GROUP HAS ACCUSED THE FORMER SPANISH CLERGYMAN AND TOP ELN LEADER OF MONOPOLIZING ECONOMIC RESOURCES, PREVENTING THE MODERNIZATION OF THE RANK AND FILE, MAINTAINING A SECURITY GROUP MADE UP OF CRIMINALS, ASSUMING PATERNALISTIC ATTITUDES, AND USING THE MARXIST IDEOLOGY FOR HIS OWN BENEFIT.

THE REPORT ALSO REVEALED THAT THE INSURGENT ORGANIZATION WAS PLANNING TO CARRY OUT A SO-CALLED KEY OPERATION IN NORTHERN AND EASTERN COLOMBIA THAT WOULD HAVE INCLUDED THE KIDNAPPING OF PERSONALITIES, THE OCCUPATION OF TOWNS, AND THE ASSASSINATION OF TOP ARMED FORCES OFFICERS.

MEANWHILE, TROOPS OF THE NATIONAL ARMY'S 5TH BRIGADE HAVE INTENSIFIED SEARCH AND CONTROL OPERATIONS IN A RURAL AREA OF SAN VICENTE DE CHUCURI MUNICIPALITY, MIDDLE MAGDALENA, SANTANDER DEPARTMENT, AFTER KILLING SIX ELN SUBVERSIVES AND SEIZING ABUNDANT WAR MATERIEL.

ACCORDING TO THE DEFENSE MINISTRY'S ADMINISTRATIVE REPORT, THERE WAS A CLASH BETWEEN UNITS OF THE (LUCIANO DE LUGER) BATTALION AND GUERRILLAS OF THE ELN'S CAPTAIN PARMENIO FRONT IN LA TEMPESTUOSA PATH, SAN VICENTE DE CHUCURI MUNICIPALITY, SANTANDER DEPARTMENT. SIX UNIDENTIFIED INSURGENTS WERE KILLED AND WEAPONS OF VARIOUS CALIBERS, AMMUNITION, UNIFORMS, DOCUMENTS, AND SUBVERSIVE PROPAGANDA WERE SEIZED.

MEMBERS OF THE 5TH BRIGADE ARE PATROLLING VARIOUS MUNICIPALITIES OF SANTANDER DEPARTMENT TO GUARANTEE NORMAL ELECTIONS AND ACTIVITIES OF THE NATIONAL CIVIL REGISTRY.

DEV-MUC3-1103 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 13 FEB 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT HAS PUBLICLY ANNOUNCED ITS REGRET OVER THE DEATH OF SEVERAL CHILDREN AND CIVILIANS IN THE GUANCORITA CANTON, CHALANTENGO DEPARTMENT, ON 11 FEBRUARY, AND HAS ORDERED AN INVESTIGATION TO CLARIFY THE CASE, WHICH IS BEING BLAMED ON THE AIR FORCE. THE MASSACRE TOOK PLACE AT A CAMP OF SALVADORAN REFUGEES WHO HAD BEEN IN HONDURAS. ACCORDING TO RESIDENTS, SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS STRAFED THE CAMP FOLLOWING A CLASH BETWEEN GOVERNMENT TROOPS AND GUERRILLAS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT.

MEANWHILE, AIR FORCE COMMANDER GENERAL RAFAEL VILLAMARIONA DENIED THE ACCUSATIONS BUT ADMITTED SOLDIERS BELONGING TO A DETACHMENT STATIONED IN CHALANTENANGO HAD RECEIVED AIR SUPPORT. "THE PARTICIPATION OF THE AIR FORCE IS EFFECTED ACCORDING TO REGULATIONS, WHICH IS WHY IT COULD NOT HAVE BOMBED CIVILIANS," VILLAMARIONA SAID.

IN THE WAKE OF THIS GRAVE INCIDENT, CHALANTENANGO DIOCESE BISHOP MSGR. EDUARDO ALAS HELPED TO PROVIDE RELIEF TO THE WOUNDED AND HEARD TESTIMONIES FROM RESIDENTS. THEY SAID THAT THE HELICOPTERS HAD DROPPED "ROCKETS," ACCORDING TO THE BISHOP.

ON MONDAY, MILITARY SOURCES CONFIRMED HEAVY FIGHTING HAD TAKEN PLACE IN THE AREA KNOWN AS CORRAL DE PIEDRA, GUANCORITA CANTON, SOME 80 KM NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR, AND THAT SEVERAL CIVILIANS WERE KILLED AND AT LEAST 15 WOUNDED AS A RESULT OF THE FIGHTING. MASS GROUPS HAVE DEMANDED PUNISHMENT FOR THE PERSONS RESPONSIBLE, SINCE THE VICTIMS, MOST OF THEM MINORS, WERE REPATRIATES FROM HONDURAS WHO HAD SETTLED BETWEEN GUARJILA AND SAN JOSE LAS FLORES, WHICH IS WHERE THEY HAD COME FROM.

THE ARMY STATES THAT IT ALSO CAPTURED A REBEL IDENTIFIED AS ABEL DUBON CHEVARRIA, WHO ACCORDING TO THE OFFICIAL REPORT DISCLOSED THAT THE REBELS HAD USED THEIR CATAPULTS AGAINST THE HOUSES IN THE TOWN. HOWEVER, THE AREA RESIDENTS DENY THIS REPORT.

DEV-MUC3-1111 (UNISYS)

LONDON (UK), 15 FEB 90 (LONDON PRESS ASSOCIATION) -- [ARTICLE] [TOM MCMULLAN, PRESS ASSOCIATION DIPLOMATIC CORRESPONDENT] [TEXT] BRITAIN AND ARGENTINA TONIGHT AGREED TO RESUME FULL DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WHICH WERE BROKEN OFF IN 1982 AFTER THE INVASION OF THE FALKLAND ISLANDS. THE ANNOUNCEMENT WAS MADE TONIGHT IN LONDON, BUENOS AIRES AND MADRID, WHERE TWO DAYS OF TALKS BETWEEN SENIOR OFFICIALS HAVE HAMMERED OUT THE DEAL. THE FOREIGN OFFICE STRESSED THE DECISION WOULD HAVE NO EFFECT ON BRITISH SOVEREIGNTY OF THE FALKLANDS, WHERE 1,000 BRITONS WERE KILLED AND WOUNDED DURING THE WAR.

BRITAIN HAS AGREED TO LIFT THE 150-MILE MILITARY PROTECTION ZONE AROUND THE FALKLANDS FROM MARCH 31. AT THE SAME TIME NEW MUTUALLY AGREED SECURITY ARRANGEMENTS WILL COME INTO FORCE. THESE WILL INVOLVE 25 DAYS ADVANCE NOTIFICATION BY EACH SIDE OF MILITARY MANOEUVRES IN CERTAIN AREAS. IT HAS ALSO BEEN AGREED THERE SHOULD BE 48-HOURS NOTICE FOR NAVAL SHIPS WHICH WANT TO APPROACH CLOSER TO THE COAST THAN 50 NAUTICAL MILES AND 70 NAUTICAL MILES FOR AIRCRAFT.

FULL DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WILL COME INTO FORCE AS SOON AS THE PROTECTING POWERS FOR THE TWO COUNTRIES HAVE BEEN INFORMED. BRITAIN'S INTERESTS IN ARGENTINA HAVE BEEN REPRESENTED BY SWITZERLAND SINCE 1982. ARGENTINA'S INTERESTS IN LONDON HAVE BEEN REPRESENTED BY BRAZIL FROM THE SAME PERIOD.

TALKS ON FISHERIES AROUND THE FALKLANDS WILL CONTINUE. A WORKING GROUP ON SOUTH ATLANTIC AFFAIRS IS TO BE SET UP. ITS FIRST MEETING WILL TAKE PLACE WITHIN THE NEXT 12 MONTHS. AN ARGENTINE VISIT TO WAR CEMETERIES IN THE FALKLANDS WILL BE ALLOWED TO GO AHEAD. THIS WILL BE WORKED OUT THROUGH THE INTERNATIONAL RED CROSS.

BOTH SIDES HAVE ALSO AGREED THAT VISAS REQUIREMENTS WILL BE ABOLISHED. BRITAIN AND ARGENTINA HAVE ALSO AGREED TO COOPERATE ON DRUGS AND THE ENVIRONMENT.

THE BRITISH DELEGATION TO THE TALKS WAS LED BY SIR CRISPIN TICKELL, AMBASSADOR TO THE UNITED NATIONS AND THE ARGENTINE DELEGATION BY SENOR GARCIA DEL SOLAR, SPECIAL REPRESENTATIVE OF PRESIDENT CARLOS MENEM.

THE AGREEMENT IS THE OUTCOME OF A SERIES OF CONTACTS BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES OVER THE PAST FEW MONTHS. IN OCTOBER, IT WAS AGREED TO ESTABLISH CONSULAR RELATIONS. AIR LINKS BETWEEN BUENOS AIRES AND LONDON RESUMED A FEW WEEKS AGO. A PARTY OF BRITISH MPS AND PROMINENT PUBLIC FIGURES HAVE JUST RETURNED FROM BUENOS AIRES AFTER THE INAUGURAL FLIGHT BY BRITISH AIRWAYS. AN OBSTACLE TO THE RESUMPTION OF RELATIONS OVER THE PAST FEW YEARS WAS THE ARGENTINE REFUSAL TO DECLARE THAT HOSTILITIES BETWEEN THE TWO COUNTRIES WERE AT AN END. HOWEVER, THE NEWLY-ELECTED ARGENTINE GOVERNMENT MADE CLEAR LAST YEAR THAT SUCH HOSTILITIES COULD NOW BE CONSIDERED AT AN END. BRITAIN, AFTER TALKS LAST OCTOBER, AGREED TO RAISE NO OBSTACLES TO ARGENTINE EFFORTS TO ESTABLISH CLOSER TRADING RELATIONS WITH THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITY. THE ARGENTINE ECONOMY IS NOW SEEN TO BE IN A SEVERE PLIGHT. PRESIDENT MENEM HAS WATCHED HIS POPULARITY DECLINE AS ARGENTINA INFLATION HAS REMAINED AT A HIGH LEVEL.

BRITAIN AND ARGENTINA WILL ALSO ESTABLISH A DIRECT COMMUNICATION LINK BETWEEN THEIR RESPECTIVE MILITARY AUTHORITIES. THE PURPOSE IS TO REDUCE THE POSSIBILITY OF INCIDENTS AND TO LIMIT THEIR CONSEQUENCES IF SUCH INCIDENTS SHOULD OCCUR. ACCORDING TO THE STATEMENT, THIS HOTLINE WILL INCREASE COMMON KNOWLEDGE OF MILITARY ACTIVITIES IN THE SOUTH ATLANTIC. THE LINK WILL BE UNDER THE SUPERVISION OF THE ARGENTINE AND BRITISH FOREIGN MINISTRIES. BRITISH MINISTERS HAVE MADE CLEAR THAT ADEQUATE DEFENCE ARRANGEMENTS WILL BE MAINTAINED FOR THE FALKLANDS.

FOREIGN OFFICE MINISTER TIMOTHY SAINSBURY RETURNED TO LONDON LAST WEEKEND AFTER A VISIT TO THE FALKLANDS WHERE HE REASSURED ISLANDERS THERE WAS NO WEAKENING IN BRITAIN'S COMMITMENT TO THEIR DEFENCE.

FOREIGN SECRETARY DOUGLAS HURD TONIGHT DESCRIBED THE AGREEMENT WITH ARGENTINA AS "VERY SATISFACTORY" AND THAT IT "UNDERLINES THE FACT THAT WE HAVE NO QUARREL WITH ARGENTINA". HE SAID: "THIS HAS BEEN ACHIEVED WITHOUT ANY SACRIFICE OF SOVEREIGNTY. I HOPE IT IS A TURNING POINT THAT WILL LEAD TO A NEW RELATIONSHIP BETWEEN BRITAIN AND ARGENTINA." MR HURD TOLD REPORTERS AT THE FOREIGN OFFICE: "I HOPE THAT TRADE BETWEEN BRITAIN AND ARGENTINA CAN BE ACCELERATED. IT IS FOR THE FALKLAND ISLANDERS TO DECIDE ON THEIR OWN CONTACTS WITH THE MAINLAND."

ASKED IF THE INSTABILITY IN ARGENTINA MIGHT LEAD TO A NEW ATTEMPT TO SEIZE THE FALKLANDS, HE SAID: "I THINK THAT IS BECOMING LESS AND LESS LIKELY." HE EXPRESSED APPRECIATION THAT THE READINESS OF THE GOVERNMENT IN ARGENTINA TO MAKE THIS ADVANCE WHICH BRITAIN HAD RECIPROCATED. "THE OUTCOME IS VERY SATISFACTORY," HE SAID. THE BRITISH PROTECTION ZONE HAD BEEN REPLACED "WITH SOMETHING FROM A SECURITY POINT OF VIEW THAT IS BETTER. WE HAVE REPLACED IT WITH AN ADVANCE NOTIFICATION SYSTEM ON THE APPROACH OF SHIPS AND AIRCRAFT. THAT FROM A SECURITY VIEWPOINT IS AN IMPROVEMENT." HE HOPED THAT THE AGREEMENT WOULD BE WELL RECEIVED IN THE FALKLANDS AND NOTED THAT THE FALKLAND ISLANDERS HAD ALREADY BEEN GIVEN AN ASSURANCE OF BRITAIN'S CONTINUED COMMITMENT.

THE EXCHANGE OF AMBASSADORS AND THE ENDING OF VISAS WOULD TAKE PLACE QUITE SOON.

ASKED IF SOVEREIGNTY OF THE FALKLANDS COULD EVER BE DISCUSSED WITH ARGENTINA HE SAID: "I DO NOT SEE HOW THAT CAN BE DISCUSSED BY US GIVEN THE HISTORY AND PRINCIPLE THAT IS INVOLVED."

LABOUR WELCOMED THE MOVE TO RESUME FULL DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS. MR GEORGE FOULKES, A FRONT BENCH SPOKESMAN ON FOREIGN AFFAIRS, SAID IT MEANT THE TWO COUNTRIES WERE NOW ALMOST BACK TO THEIR RESPECTIVE POSITIONS BEFORE THE 1982 CONFLICT. BUT HE ADDED: "WE MUST NOW PULL OUT ALL THE STOPS IN DEVELOPING TRADE RELATIONS BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES." THIS INCLUDED CONSIDERING ALL OPPORTUNITIES FOR BRITISH INVESTMENT IN ARGENTINA AND THE DEVELOPMENT OF CULTURAL, SPORTING AND OTHER LINKS.

DEV-MUC3-1112 (UNISYS)

LA PAZ, 9 FEB 90 (PRESENCIA) -- [ARTICLE] [GREGORIO LANZA] [TEXT] THE SANTA CRUZ PREPARATORY MEETING WAS HELD UNDER STRICT SECURITY MEASURES AND ITS CONCLUSIONS HAVE BEEN KEPT UNDER STRICT SECRECY. THIS VEIL OF SECRECY SEEMED TO HAVE BEEN LIFTED WHEN THE MORNING NEWSPAPER HOY PUBLISHED A LONG AGENDA UNDER THE HEADING "TOTAL WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING." THE GOVERNMENT, HOWEVER, HAS NEITHER CONFIRMED NOR REJECTED THE AUTHENTICITY OF THE REPORT. (SILENCE IS GOLDEN). AT A MEETING AT THE INTERIOR MINISTER'S OFFICE ON 31 JANUARY, THE MINISTER TOLD COCA PRODUCERS THAT HOY DID NOT REPORT THE PRELIMINARY AGENDA... AND THAT THE PRESIDENT'S CRITERION OF "COCA IN RETURN FOR DEVELOPMENT" HAS PREVAILED. IF THIS IS THE CASE, AND IF THERE IS CONSENSUS ON THIS POSITION, WHY HASN'T THE COUNTRY BEEN INFORMED?

THE SITUATION HAS BEEN FURTHER COMPLICATED BY THE REMARKS BY PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA, WHO SAID THAT "WHEN EVERYTHING SEEMED TO HAVE BEEN AGREED UPON" ONE OF THE COUNTRIES INTRODUCED CHANGES THAT HAVE "CHANGED THE STRUCTURAL FEATURES OF THE ISSUE." WHAT IS THIS NEW CONCEPT? IS IT ABOUT SOVEREIGNTY OR INDEPENDENCE?

THE PROGOVERNMENT PROPAGANDA HAS MONOTONOUSLY REITERATED OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS THAT TO GOVERN MEANS TO INFORM. FINE. WE AGREE THAT TO INFORM IS PART OF THE ART OF GOVERNING. TO INFORM, HOWEVER, ALSO MEANS TO TELL THE TRUTH, ESPECIALLY IF IT DEALS WITH AN ISSUE THAT IS FUNDAMENTAL TO THE FUTURE OF BOLIVIANS. THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE CONSISTENT, AT LEAST WITH THIS PRINCIPLE.

PRESIDENT JAIME PAZ ZAMORA HAS REPEATEDLY PROPOSED THE REPLACEMENT OF COCA PRODUCTION THROUGH DEVELOPMENT PROGRAMS. YET THE REMARKS BY U.S. EMBASSY DEPUTY CHIEF OF MISSION MARILYN MCAFEE HAVE DEALT AN ANTICIPATED BLOW THAT HAS CAUSED SOME OFFICIALS TO HESITATE. "THERE IS $15 MILLION FOR REPLACEMENT," SHE SAID. (THERE IS $60 MILLION FOR REPRESSION). BARELY RECUPERATED FROM HIS SURPRISE, THE FOREIGN MINISTER SAID THAT THE U.S. HELP IS A "BILATERAL ISSUE AND, CONSEQUENTLY, IT WILL NOT BE DIRECTLY ADDRESSED" AT THE CARTAGENA SUMMIT. THE INTERIOR MINISTER, WHO HAS MORE EXPERIENCE IN THIS TYPE OF SITUATION, DID NOT ATTACH MUCH IMPORTANCE TO MCAFEE'S STATEMENT AND STRESSED THAT "MORE EXACT FIGURES WILL BE MENTIONED AT THE CARTAGENA SUMMIT." WHO IS TELLING THE TRUTH? WILL THE CARTAGENA SUMMIT ADDRESS THE ECONOMIC AID?

AFTER THIS PECULIAR SITUATION, THE UNITED STATES SEEMS TO HAVE CHOSEN INTERDICTION AND ERADICATION -- REPRESSION -- TO FIGHT DRUG TRAFFICKING. THE STRATEGY OF "WAR AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING TERRORISTS" HAS PREVAILED. THIS STRATEGY LENDS ITSELF TO INTERVENTIONIST MILITARY POLICIES, SIMILAR TO THE PRESENCE OF U.S. MARINES IN BOLIVIA IN THE PAST, OR, IN THE FUTURE, THE CREATION OF A MULTINATIONAL MILITARY FORCE THAT WOULD JEOPARDIZE REGIONAL POLITICAL AND MILITARY STABILITY.

WHEN THE TRAFFICKING OF COCAINE WAS CARRIED OUT AS A COVERT OPERATION (1984-87) INVOLVING THE CIA AND THE U.S. ARMY -- FOR THE PURPOSE OF PROVIDING MILITARY SUPPLIES TO THE CONTRAS -- COCAINE TRAFFICKING WAS NOT A CRIME. THE LINKS BETWEEN NORIEGA AND DRUG TRAFFICKING WERE A MATTER OF SECONDARY IMPORTANCE AS LONG AS HE PROVIDED INFORMATION AND SUPPORT FOR THEIR WAR AGAINST NICARAGUA. BUT NOW THE UNITED STATES DOES NOT MIND INVADING PANAMA OR TURNING COLOMBIA INTO AN INFERNO TO CAPTURE NORIEGA OR SOME OF THE MAJOR COLOMBIAN TRAFFICKERS ON THIS CRUSADE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING. THAT IS THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S DOUBLE-FACED MORALITY.

ANOTHER SCANDAL HIT U.S. SOCIETY LAST WEEK. MARION BARRY, THE MAYOR OF WASHINGTON, THE CAPITAL OF THE EMPIRE AND ALSO THE CAPITAL OF CRIME, WAS CAUGHT IN AN FBI TRAP. HE WAS FILMED CONSUMING COCAINE. HIS FOLLOWERS CLAIM THAT IT IS A WHITE CONSPIRACY TO PREVENT A BLACK MAYOR FROM RUNNING FOR ANOTHER TERM.

BUT THE INTERESTING POINT FOR US IS THE CONTROVERSY BETWEEN BENNETT, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT STRATEGIST FOR THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING (THE BENNETT PLAN), AND WASHINGTON POLICE CHIEF FULWOOD. WHILE BENNETT HAS QUESTIONED THE EFFICIENCY OF THE WASHINGTON POLICE, CLAIMING THAT THIS AREA RECEIVES THE LARGEST AMOUNT OF FEDERAL SUPPORT FOR THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, FULWOOD HAS SAID THAT BENNETT IS WASTING TIME "TALKING WITHOUT DOING ABSOLUTELY ANYTHING" (NEWSWEEK, 29 JANUARY). THE NEWSWEEK JOURNALIST SAID THAT EVEN BEFORE THE BARRY SCANDAL IT WAS POSSIBLE TO SEE THAT THE BENNETT PLAN HAD BECOME "ONLY A DIRTY BATTLE OF WORDS." BENNETT'S STRATEGY FOR THE PREVENTION AND REPRESSION OF DRUG ABUSE IN THE UNITED STATES HAS BEEN A TOTAL FAILURE. BENNETT THEREFORE BELIEVES THAT THE BEST WAY TO COVER HIS FAILURE IS TO TURN TOWARD LATIN AMERICA TO RELIEVE THE FURY OF HIS IMPOTENCE, ORDERING WARSHIPS AND PLANES TO CONTROL MARITIME AND AIR TRAFFIC. AS USUAL, THOSE OF US WHO LIVE IN THE "BACKYARD" HAVE TO PAY FOR THE MISTAKES OF U.S. POLICY.

THIS IS NOT A STORY OF SUSPENSE. THE SUSPENSE HAS BEEN CREATED BY THE ATTITUDE OF THE GOVERNMENT. THE COUNTRY NEEDS TO KNOW THE CONCLUSIONS OF THE SANTA CRUZ SUMMIT. OTHERWISE WE WILL HAVE TO ACCEPT THAT A SMOKE SCREEN HAS BEEN DEPLOYED OVER THE CARTAGENA SUMMIT.

DEV-MUC3-1113 (UNISYS)

NO CITY, NO DATE -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PERUVIAN PRESIDENT GARCIA BY AMAT AND AN UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [GARCIA] THE DEBT AND ITS INTEREST HAVE STEADILY GROWN, BUT THE VALUE OF OUR PRODUCTION HAS DECREASED, SO IT HAS BECOME INCREASINGLY IMPOSSIBLE TO PAY THE DEBT. THEREFORE, WE ARE FACED WITH THE SAME OLD STORY: LEND ME 100 MILLION AND I WILL PAY YOU 110 MILLION AND STILL OWE YOU 120 MILLION WITH THE NEW INTEREST. THIS ROTATION OF CREDIT DOES NOT PRODUCE ANY MATERIAL ASSETS LIKE RAW MATERIALS AND ASSEMBLY PLANTS DID IN THE PAST.

CONSEQUENTLY, THIS RELATION IS NO LONGER FEASIBLE; IT IS USELESS. WE HAVE BECOME INCREASINGLY POOR, AND WE OWE MORE AND MORE. WHY NOT CHANGE TO MORE RATIONAL RELATIONS LIKE IS BEING DONE BY CIVILIZED PERSONS WHO KNOW HOW TALK MULTILATERALLY? WE WOULD THUS ELIMINATE THE FOREIGN DEBT PROBLEM, WHICH NO ONE WILL BE ABLE TO PAY AND, CONSEQUENTLY, NO ONE WILL BE ABLE TO COLLECT. THAT IS WHAT WE ARE TALKING ABOUT.

FINANCIAL CAPITALISM NO LONGER PRODUCES MATERIAL ASSETS AND DOES NOT GENERATE ANYTHING -- BUT IT CERTAINLY CONTINUES TO IMPOVERISH US -- SO AN ENORMOUS FINANCIAL AND TECHNOLOGICAL FORCE IS ACCUMULATING IN THE UNITED STATES, EUROPE, AND JAPAN. THEY HAVE NO ONE TO SELL IT TO BECAUSE WE HAVE BECOME INCREASINGLY POOR. SUDDENLY THEY HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY IN EASTERN EUROPE AND THEY ARE THERE, FULL OF ILLUSIONS ABOUT CREATING NEW MARKETS IN THAT AREA -- AND THEY HAVE FORGOTTEN ABOUT LATIN AMERICA, WHICH PURCHASED MACHINERY FROM THE UNITED STATES AND EUROPE FOR 50 YEARS.

I THINK THAT IS UNJUST AND SHOULD BE DISCUSSED AS A WHOLE. THE UNITED STATES HAS... CHANGES THOUGHT WHAT MORE DOES IT WANT, IF IT HAS THE RESOURCES THAT IT NO LONGER SPENDS ON ATOMIC BOMBS OR ON MEN AND WEAPONS IN EUROPE? IT HAS TO INVEST THOSE RESOURCES SO THAT THEY MAY YIELD SOMETHING. WHERE? IN POLAND? IN CZECHOSLOVAKIA? WHY? WHY NOT IN LATIN AMERICA? WE ARE HERE AND WE HAVE COMMON PROBLEMS LIKE DRUG TRAFFICKING. THAT IS WHAT WE HAVE TO DISCUSS.

[AMAT] WHAT ARE PERU'S REVENUES, IN DOLLARS, FOR THE COCA CROPS?

[GARCIA] THE MOST CONSERVATIVE ESTIMATE IS APPROXIMATELY $700 MILLION.

[AMAT] WITH WHAT ARE YOU GOING TO REPLACE THAT $700 MILLION IF THE COCA CROPS ARE ABOLISHED?

[GARCIA] THAT IS THE CRUX OF THE PROBLEM AND THAT IS WHY WE CAME TO TALK. IT IS OBVIOUS, IT IS TRUE THAT I HAVE AN ETHICAL AND MORAL OBLIGATION TO END IT, BUT IT IS ALSO TRUE THAT I HAVE TO ELIMINATE THE PEASANTS' COCA CROPS TO ACHIEVE THIS.

[AMAT] MR. PRESIDENT, WHAT ABOUT THE PEASANTS OF PERU AND BOLIVIA? COLOMBIA'S CASE IS DIFFERENT BECAUSE COCA IS PROCESSED HERE. WOULD THE PEASANTS BE WILLING TO CHANGE THOSE CROPS FOR OTHERS?

[GARCIA] IF THEY ARE GIVEN A LONG-TERM GUARANTEE, YES.

[AMAT] BUT WOULD THEY CHANGE COCA FOR TOMATOES, ORANGES, AND CACAO?

[GARCIA] IT IS NOT EASY TO CHANGE IT FOR COFFEE, TOBACCO, CACAO, ANNATTO, OR PALM TREES. THE U.S. GOVERNMENT HAS STUDIED ALL THIS. I HAVE A 600-PAGE REPORT FROM THE U.S. GOVERNMENT THAT DISCUSSES THE ALTERNATIVES FOR REPLACING THE 80,000 HECTARES IN THE GUAYAGA VALLEY -- WHICH IS THE LARGEST COCA-PRODUCING AREA IN THE COUNTRY. IT WOULD COST $600 MILLION TO INDUSTRIALIZE THE AREA ON A LONG-TERM BASIS.

[AMAT] BUT, MR. PRESIDENT, COCA PRACTICALLY GROWS WILD; IT DOES NOT REQUIRE MUCH WORK IN THE COUNTRYSIDE. HOW CAN A GOVERNMENT LIKE YOURS CONVINCE A FARMER TO INVEST MUCH MORE MONEY IN A PRODUCT THAT WOULD BE MUCH LESS PROFITABLE?

[REPORTER] LET ME ADD SOMETHING TO THAT...

[GARCIA, INTERRUPTING] EXCUSE ME. IT IS A VICIOUS CIRCLE. THE PEASANT PRODUCES COCA BECAUSE HE HAS NO MONEY. I WILL NOT ASK HIM TO INVEST MONEY HE DOES NOT HAVE TO CHANGE THE PRODUCT. THE UNITED STATES HAS TO BUY THE NEW PRODUCT TO ACHIEVE THIS. THE UNITED STATES HAS TO GUARANTEE THAT IT WILL BUY THE PRODUCT. LOOK, HOW MANY TRILLIONS DOES THE UNITED STATES BUY AS IMPORTS IN OTHER COUNTRIES? A FRACTION OF THIS WOULD CHANGE THE DESTINY OF COLOMBIA, PERU, AND BOLIVIA.

THE UNITED STATES SHOULD SAY: IF I BUY $600 BILLION IN PRODUCTS ABROAD, I WILL BUY $10 BILLION -- OF ANYTHING -- IN PERU, COLOMBIA, AND BOLIVIA. IT COULD BE TOMATOES, PALM OIL, COFFEE, CHOCOLATE BARS, ANYTHING. THIS WOULD CHANGE THE HISTORY OF THESE COUNTRIES. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1114 (UNISYS)

NO CITY, NO DATE -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PERUVIAN PRESIDENT GARCIA BY AMAT AND AN UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [GARCIA] I HAVE SPENT THE LAST SIX YEARS OF MY POLITICAL LIFE SAYING THINGS CLEARLY. MANY PEOPLE DESCRIBE THAT ATTITUDE AS VEHEMENCE OR RADICALISM. I DISAGREE WITH THAT VIEW.

WHEN THE UNITED STATES INVADED PANAMA -- AND I WAS AWARE OF WHAT NORIEGA WAS -- I SAID THAT DESPITE THAT FACT, THE INVASION HAD BEEN A CRIME. WE DEMANDED THE IMMEDIATE WITHDRAWAL OF THE U.S. TROOPS. I SAID THAT IF THE IMMEDIATE WITHDRAWAL DID NOT TAKE PLACE, I WOULD NOT ATTEND THE CARTAGENA SUMMIT, BECAUSE I COULD NOT SIT AT THE SAME TABLE WITH THE U.S. PRESIDENT WHILE A LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRY REMAINED INVADED. AND IT HAPPENED. IT HAPPENED. THE TROOPS HAD TO WITHDRAW. AND WE HAVE HELD A CORDIAL MEETING FOR THAT REASON.

[AMAT] MR PRESIDENT, YOU HAVE CONVINCED US [WORDS INDISTINCT] THINGS THE WAY YOU SEE AND FEEL ABOUT THEM. WILL YOU TELL US FRANKLY -- FRANKLY -- WHAT IS YOUR OPINION OF THE SUMMIT? WHAT HAPPENED AT THE SUMMIT? WHAT IMPORTANT CONCLUSIONS WERE REACHED AT THE SUMMIT?

[GARCIA] FRANKLY, AND IN A NUTSHELL, IT WAS POSITIVE. IT CREATED A MULTILATERAL ATMOSPHERE, AND WE TALKED VERY CANDIDLY. AS FOR ME PERSONALLY, I HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO MEET A CONTINENTAL POLITICIAN LIKE BUSH, AND I FOUND HIM TO BE A PRAGMATIC PERSON. I PROBABLY DISAGREE WITH HIM ON MORE THAN HALF OF THE THINGS HE THINKS, BUT I DO NOT THINK THAT HUMAN BEINGS ARE OBLIGED TO BE IDENTICAL. WHAT IS IMPORTANT IS TO LOOK AT EACH PERSON FOR HIS GOOD POINTS -- HOWEVER FEW OR MANY THEY MAY BE -- TO ESTABLISH A RAPPORT ON THAT BASIS.

[REPORTER] WHAT IS BEING PLANNED? WHAT IS NEXT? WHAT IS GOING TO BE DONE TO CONTINUE... [CHANGES THOUGHT] IN ORDER FOR THE PRESIDENTS TO KEEP IN CONSTANT TOUCH TO FULFILL WHAT THEY SIGNED?

[GARCIA] WELL, THERE WILL BE CONSTANT COMMUNICATION. IT IS EASY TO TALK WITH THE U.S. PRESIDENT, WHO IS NOT GOD. THERE ARE TELEPHONES TO DO THAT. MR. BELL INVENTED A LITTLE GADGET OVER A CENTURY AGO CALLED THE TELEPHONE AND WE, THE PRESIDENTS, COMMUNICATE WITH EACH OTHER -- WITH BARCO, PAZ ZAMORA, AND PRESIDENT BUSH, TO ASK: WILL WE OR WILL WE NOT DO WHAT WE PLEDGED TO DO? IF WE DO NOT, AT LEAST IT WILL NOT BE MY FAULT OR THAT OF THE LATIN AMERICANS.

[AMAT] WE ARE IN THE MIDST OF AN ELECTORAL PROCESS IN COLOMBIA, AND THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENT IS ALSO FACING AN ELECTORAL PROCESS...

[GARCIA, INTERRUPTING] AND YOU KNOW THE CANDIDATE, FORTUNATELY. [CHUCKLES]

[AMAT] MR. PRESIDENT, IT LOOKS LIKE THE OPPOSITION IS GOING TO DEFEAT YOU IN YOUR COUNTRY?

[GARCIA] IT IS A POSSIBILITY, IT IS TRUE.

[AMAT] WHY?

[GARCIA] LOOK, ANYONE WHO LISTENS TO YOUR QUESTION WOULD THINK THAT FIVE YEARS AGO, WHEN I ASSUMED POWER, PERU WAS A COUNTRY FULL OF GOLD, VERY RICH, THE WAY IT WAS BEFORE THE SPANISH CONQUEST -- ORDERLY, AND WITHOUT PROBLEMS. FIVE YEARS AGO IT HAD A DEVELOPED TERRORIST PROBLEM. IT HAD A FOREIGN DEBT OF 14.5 BILLION AND WAS EXTREMELY POOR. FIVE YEARS HAVE ELAPSED. I EXPLAINED TO YOU ONCE THAT I TRIED TO MAKE IT GROW AT GREAT SPEED AND MANAGED TO DO SO. THEN WE FACED A DECLINE, AND WE ARE NOW STABILIZING THE SITUATION.

HOWEVER, MANY PEOPLE FEEL THAT A PERSON CAN SOLVE MANY THINGS BECAUSE OF THE IMPETUOSITY IN HIS PERSONALITY. SOMETIMES THIS IS THE PROBLEM OF BEING HONEST OR HAVING AN IMPETUOUS PERSONALITY OR HARBORING MANY HOPES -- OR SELLING THEM.

THE TRUTH IS THAT -- LIKE FIVE YEARS AGO -- WE HAVE A POOR COUNTRY, A COUNTRY THAT OWES MONEY, A COUNTRY THAT HAS JUST AS MUCH OR MORE SUBVERSIVE TERRORISM, AND THIS MAKES PEOPLE UNCOMFORTABLE. I CANNOT UNDERSTAND IT. HOWEVER, THAT IS WHAT WE POLITICIANS ARE FOR -- TO BURN OUT IN OUR WORK FOR DEMOCRACY TO SURVIVE. I WILL BE REPLACED BY SOMEONE ELSE WHO THINKS LIKE ME OR TOTALLY DIFFERENT FROM ME. HE WILL REPLACE ME AND DEMOCRACY WILL STAY, A CIVILIZED SYSTEM. THIS IS THE MOST IMPORTANT THING. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1116 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 FEB 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] MILITARY AND CIVILIAN SOURCES HAVE REPORTED THAT EARLY THIS MORNING THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN, SET ON FIRE TWO COTTON PROCESSING PLANTS IN SAN MIGUEL, SOME 142 KM EAST OF SAN SALVADOR, CAUSING GREAT PROPERTY DAMAGE, ACCORDING TO MILITARY AND CIVILIAN SOURCES.

ACCORDING TO REPORTS, FMLN MEMBERS ATTACKED THE "CANESSA" AND "EL OBRAJUELO" COTTON PLANTS IN SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT, DESTROYING HEAVY EQUIPMENT, WAREHOUSES WHERE HUNDREDS OF QUINTALES OF COTTON WERE STORED, AND THE MAIN BUILDINGS. FORTUNATELY, NO ONE WAS HURT.

SPOKESMEN REPRESENTING THE OWNERS REPORTED MUCH PROPERTY DAMAGE AND NOTED THAT THE INCIDENT IS PART OF THE FMLN'S CAMPAIGN OF SABOTAGE AGAINST THE ECONOMY.

HEAVY CLASHES WERE ALSO REPORTED IN MORAZAN DEPARTMENT, IN THE COUNTRY'S NORTHEASTERN REGION, DURING WHICH AT LEAST TWO SOLDIERS WERE KILLED. HOWEVER, THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE HAS NOT REPORTED THE INCIDENTS THAT OCCURRED LAST NIGHT AND EARLY THIS MORNING.

SEVERAL TOWNS IN EASTERN EL SALVADOR ARE WITHOUT POWER SINCE 14 FEBRUARY DUE TO SABOTAGE ACTIONS. ELECTRICITY IS ALSO BEING RATIONED IN VARIOUS SECTORS OF SAN SALVADOR, FOLLOWING THE DESTRUCTION OF FIVE HIGH TENSION LINES, ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL SOURCES.

HOWEVER, BOMB ATTACKS ON SHOPPING CENTERS IN SAN SALVADOR ARE LESS FREQUENT. RECENT ATTACKS HAD CAUSED GREAT CONCERN AND PROMPTED A STRONG PROTEST FROM THE CHAMBER OF COMMERCE AND INDUSTRIES OF EL SALVADOR, WHICH DEMANDED AN END TO THE WAVE OF ATTACKS AGAINST NONMILITARY TARGETS.

DEV-MUC3-1118 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 12 FEB 90 (EL MUNDO) -- [TEXT] TERRORIST ACTIONS AGAINST SAN SALVADOR'S COMMERCIAL ESTABLISHMENTS CONTINUE, CREATING ALARM AND CONCERN AMONG PRIVATE ENTERPRISE GROUPS. COPREFA [ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE] REPORTS TODAY THAT AT 0620 FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] URBAN CELLS PLACED DYNAMITE STICKS IN FOUR COMMERCIAL ESTABLISHMENTS IN MID-TOWN SAN SALVADOR; NAMELY, A BANK, A HOTEL, A CAR DEALERSHIP, AND A STORE.

THE REPORT ADDS THAT THE BANCO CUSCATLAN, LOCATED ON 6TH WEST STREET AND CUSCATLAN AVENUE; THE RITZ HOTEL, LOCATED ON 7TH SOUTH AVENUE AND RUBEN DARIO STREET; THE NASA CAR DEALERSHIP, LOCATED BETWEEN 25TH NORTH AVENUE AND 3D WEST STREET; AND THE MIKE-MIKE STORE, LOCATED ON PASAJE MONTALVO AND 1ST NORTH AVENUE, SUFFERED PARTIAL DAMAGE. THERE WERE NO VICTIMS.

COPREFA ALSO REPORTS THAT 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE SOLDIERS DISCOVERED THE BODIES OF FIVE GUERRILLAS INSIDE A CACHE DURING A COMBING OPERATION CONDUCTED ON SATURDAY, 10 FEBRUARY. IT WAS ESTABLISHED THE FIVE MEN HAD BEEN LEFT BEHIND AFTER THE SO-CALLED "OFFENSIVE TO THE TOP," AND PERISHED WHEN THEIR OTHER COMRADES LEFT THEM "COVERING THE WITHDRAWAL."

NINE EXTREMISTS WERE KILLED THE PAST WEEKEND DURING FIGHTING WITH MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 4 IN THE CORINTO AREA, MORAZAN DEPARTMENT. IT IS SAID THE FMLN GUERRILLAS WERE TAKEN BY SURPRISE WHEN THEY TRIED TO ENTER THE TOWN. TWO SOLDIERS DIED IN THE FIGHTING. COPREFA REPORTS THAT THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE PROVIDED SUPPORT. IN ADDITION, THE COMMAND OF EL PARAISO'S 5TH BRIGADE, IN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, REPORTS THE DEATH OF ONE OF ITS SOLDIERS DURING FIGHTING WITH SUBVERSIVE GROUPS IN THE VILLAGE OF EL ZUNGARO, IN CHALATENANGO, ON SATURDAY. IN ADDITION, THE ATONAL BATTALION STATES THAT ONE OF ITS SOLDIERS WAS KILLED IN COMBAT WITH REBELS IN THE AREA AROUND AVALOS FARM IN SANTA ELENA, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT.

THIRD INFANTRY BRIGADE TROOPS REPORT SEIZING 22 AR-15 RIFLES, EIGHT M-16 RIFLES, AND FOUR FAL RIFLES, AS WELL AS TWO SOVIET-MADE AK-47 RIFLES. IN ADDITION, 17 STEYR BRAND SUBMACHINE GUNS, ONE RPG-18 GRENADE LAUNCHER, THREE SOVIET-MADE PISTOLS, 3,800 CARTRIDGES OF DIFFERENT CALIBERS, 94 CARTRIDGE CLIPS, SEVERAL TNT STICKS, 75 POUNDS OF ALUMINUM POWDER, AND A LARGE QUANTITY OF MATERIAL TO MAKE EXPLOSIVES WERE CONFISCATED. THE ARSENAL WAS FOUND IN A CACHE IN LA ESCONDIDA JURISDICTION, SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT, BY TROOPS OF THE 3D BRIGADE, LEON BATTALION. THIS UNIT REPORTS A CLASH WITH THE EXTREMISTS ON THE OUTSKIRTS OF SAN MIGUEL, DURING WHICH WAR MATERIEL WAS SEIZED.

DEV-MUC3-1119 (UNISYS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 7 FEB 90 (TELEONCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] DEFENSE MINISTER GEN. HECTOR ALEJANDRO GRAMAJO SPOKE ON 7 FEBRUARY AT A NEWS CONFERENCE JUST A FEW HOURS AFTER LEARNING OF A NEW GUERRILLA ATTACK THAT TOOK PLACE AT DAYBREAK ON 7 FEBRUARY, AGAINST THE TECPAN, CHIMALTENANGO POLICE GARRISON. THE GUERRILLAS STOLE FOUR .38 CALIBER REVOLVERS, FOUR M-1 CARBINES, AND .30 CALIBER AMMUNITION AND TOOK POLICE PATROL CAR NO. CH-02.

DURING WEDNESDAY'S NEWS CONFERENCE, THE ARMY RELEASED A SUMMARY OF GUERRILLA ACTIVITIES STARTING IN EARLY DECEMBER, WHEN SUBVERISVE COMMANDOS DESTROYED THE BRIDGE SPANNING THE COYOLATE RIVER. DURING A FOUR-DAY PERIOD IN DECEMBER, THE GUERRILLAS SABOTAGED AN ELECTRICAL TOWER OUTSIDE THE CAPITAL AND SET FIRE TO A VEHICLE BELONGING TO THE TECHNICAL-AGRICULTURAL TRAINING INSTITUTE ON THE ROAD TO SOLOLA.

TWO MORE ACTS OF SABOTAGE AGAINST ELECTRICAL INSTALLATIONS TOOK PLACE THE FIRST WEEK IN JANUARY. A FEW DAYS LATER, THREE GOVERNMENT-OWNED VEHICLES WERE SET ON FIRE -- ONE BELONGING TO BANDESA [NATIONAL AGRICULRURAL DEVELOPMENT BANK] AND TWO BELONGING TO THE PUBLIC HEALTH MINISTRY, WHICH WERE TRANSPORTING VACCINES TO A CLINIC. DURING THE LAST DAYS OF JANUARY, THERE WAS ANOTHER ACT OF SABOTAGE AGAINST THE ELECTRICAL SYSTEM IN QUEZALTENANGO AND AN ATTACK ON THE VILLAGE OF POCHUTA THAT CAUSED PERSONAL INJURIES AND PROPERTY DAMAGE.

SINCE THE WEEKEND, A POST AT THE KILOMETER 42 ROAD MARK ALONG ROUTE CA-9 WAS ATTACKED AND A CIVILIAN WAS KILLED. AT DAYBREAK ON 14 FEBRUARY, THE NATIONAL POLICE GARRISON AT TECPAN, CHIMALTENANGO WAS ATTACKED, BUT NO CASUALTIES WERE REPORTED.

ACCORDING TO THE MINISTER OF DEFENSE, THE LEFTIST GUERRILLAS' NEW DIRECTIVES CAME FROM A RECENT MEETING HELD IN A CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRY, WHICH THE MILITARY COMMANDER DID NOT IDENTIFY.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GRAMAJO] THEY ASK ME [WORDS INDISTINCT] INTERNATIONALISTS. WE HAVE CONFIRMED INFORMATION THAT A MEETING WAS HELD IN ONE OF THE CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES IN OCTOBER 1989. NORTH VIETNAMESE ADVISERS -- ONE OF THEM IS NOW A VIETNAMESE GENERAL, BUT THE MEETING WAS ATTENDED BY VIETNAMESE AND CUBAN GENERALS BASICALLY -- MET WITH SUBVERSIVE LEADERS AND DISCUSSED THE STRATEGIC PLAN FOR THE CENTRAL AMERICAN AREA UNDER THE CURRENT SITUATION THEY ARE SUFFERING. THUS THEY DECIDED ON A DESPERATE PLAN WHERE THE REVOLUTIONARY PEOPLE'S WAR WAS GOING TO FOCUS ON TAKING TO ITS OWN AND ONLY COMING TO TOWNS TO MAKE ITS [WORD INDISTINCT]. EVENTUALLY, THEY WOULD GET THE POPULATION TO GO AGAINST THE STATE AND THEN TAKE OVER POWER THAT HAS BEEN ABANDONED. THIS PLAN WAS ADOPTED BECAUSE TIME IS AGAINST THEM; THE PLAN IS NO LONGER FOR A REVOLUTIONARY PEOPLE'S WAR, BUT BASED ON PURE TERRORISM BECAUSE THE INTERNATIONAL [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND ALSO TO PROMOTE ACTIVITIES WITHIN GUATEMALA, MAINLY RELATED TO THE UPCOMING ELECTIONS. [END RECORDING]

ACCORDING TO GEN. GRAMAJO, SOME RIVALRIES HAVE STARTED AMONG THE DIFFERENT GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY UNITY [URNG] GROUPS, SUCH IS THE CASE OF THE REBEL ARMED FORCES [FAR] WHO HAVE PENETRATED AREAS WERE THE REVOLUTIONARY ORGANIZATION OF THE PEOPLE IN ARMS [ORPA] OPERATED, SUCH AS THE AREAS OF PACHLUM, PETEN, AND GODINEZ. ORPA NOW MAINTAINS ITSELF SOUTH OF CHIMALTENANGO, IN THE NORTHERN AREA OF ESCUINTLA AND SACATEPEQUEZ. THE POOR PEOPLE'S GUERRILLA ARMY [EGP] CENTERS ITS ACTIONS AGAINST BASES.

THE DEFENSE MINISTER ALSO EXPLAINED THE ARMY'S POSITION CONCERNING THE POSSIBILITY OF REINITIATING TALKS WITH GUERRILLA REPRESENTATIVES.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GRAMAJO] AS YOU MAY HAVE NOTICED, WE ONLY REFER TO THE THREE GROUPS IN WHICH THEY OPERATE. HOWEVER, WE ARE ONLY TALKING ABOUT ARMED ACTIVITIES. THE CONSTITUTION SAYS THAT THERE CANNOT BE ARMED BANDS AND [WORDS INDISTINCT] IN COMBAT ZONES. [WORDS INDISTINCT] EUPHEMISMS: DIALOGUE, TALKS, AND CONFERENCES. THIS, HOWEVER, IS NOT A MATTER THAT CONCERNS US. WE HAVE BEEN VERY CLEAR IN THIS SENSE. WE HAVE SERIOUS RESERVATIONS ABOUT THE VALIDITY OF A CONFERENCE, OR TALKS, OR WHATEVER THAT HAS ONLY BEEN USED AS A TACTICAL INSTRUMENT AT A SPECIFIC MOMENT. EL SALVADOR HAS SUFFERED MUCH IN THIS REGARD. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1122 (UNISYS)

BOGOTA, 17 FEB 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] OFFICIAL SPOKESMEN REPORTED HERE TODAY THAT THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT AND M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] WILL SIGN A FINAL PEACE AGREEMENT ON 19 FEBRUARY.

THE SOURCES ADDED THAT, THIS WEEKEND, INTERIOR MINISTER CARLOS LEMOS AND M-19 LEADER CARLOS PIZARRO WILL AGREE ON THE TIME FOR THE CEREMONY, WHICH WILL BE HELD AT THE NATIONAL CAPITOL.

THE SIGNING OF THE AGREEMENT--WHICH INVOLVES THE DEMOBILIZATION OF M-19, THE DELIVERY OF ITS WEAPONS TO A COMMISSION FROM THE SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL, AND THE REINCORPORATION OF ITS MEMBERS INTO CIVILIAN LIFE--HAS BEEN REPEATEDLY POSTPONED.

GOVERNMENT SPOKESMEN ADDED THAT AFTER THE SIGNING OF THE DOCUMENT, PIZARRO AND HIS DEPUTY AND IDEOLOGIST ANTONIO NAVARRO WILL HOLD A NEWS CONFERENCE TO EXPLAIN THE PROGRAM THAT THE ORGANIZATION, WHICH IS IN THE PROCESS OF BECOMING LEGAL, WILL CARRY OUT TO PARTICIPATE IN THE 11 MARCH LEGISLATIVE ELECTIONS.

IN SOME AREAS OF THE COUNTRY, M-19 WILL PRESENT ITS OWN LIST OF CANDIDATES, WHILE IN OTHERS IT WILL PARTICIPATE IN COALITION WITH TRADITIONAL PARTIES AND LEFTIST GROUPS.

THE PEACE TALKS, RECENTLY SEALED WITH AN AMNESTY FOR THE SUBVERSIVES, BEGAN BETWEEN THE ADMINISTRATION OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO AND M-19, AN EXTREME LEFTIST AND NATIONALIST GROUP STRUGGLING FOR ALMOST 20 YEARS, IN EARLY 1989.

THE M-19 OCCUPIED THE DOMINICAN EMBASSY IN BOGOTA FOR TWO MONTHS. THE GROUP HELD APPROXIMATELY 20 FOREIGN DIPLOMATS HOSTAGES. IN ADDITION, THE M-19 STOLE 5,000 WEAPONS FROM A MILITARY GARRISON AND CARRIED OUT THE BLOODY TAKEOVER OF BOGOTA'S JUSTICE PALACE, AN ACTION THAT CLAIMED THE LIVES OF 100 PEOPLE.

DEV-MUC3-1123 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 18 FEB 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI TODAY SAID THE GOVERNMENT IS AWAITING A REPLY FROM THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) REGARDING A POSSIBLE RESUMPTION OF THE DIALOGUE.

CRISTIANI HELD A NEWS CONFERENCE AT THE COMALAPA AIRPORT THIS MORNING PRIOR TO TRAVELING TO TAIWAN ON A TOUR WHICH, HE SAID, WILL LAST UNTIL 3 MARCH.

CRISTIANI DISCLOSED THAT AS PART OF HIS MEDIATION EFFORTS, THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL HAS TWICE SENT HIS PERSONAL DELEGATE, ALVARO DE SOTO, WHO HAS BEEN TOLD THAT THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT DEMANDS THAT THE FMLN HALT ITS HOSTILITIES AND SABOTAGE ACTIVITY AIMED AT DISRUPTING NATIONAL COMMERCE.

"WE KNOW," PRESIDENT CRISTIANI SAID, "THAT THE FMLN HAS ASKED FOR TWO WEEKS TO STUDY AND RESPOND TO OUR LATEST PROPOSAL."

THE PRESIDENT REFERRED TO AN ATTACK LAST NIGHT AND EARLY THIS MORNING ON AN ELECTRIC POWER SUBSTATION IN NORTHWESTERN SAN SALVADOR, DESCRIBING IT AS "A PUBLICITY PLOY TO IMPRESS THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL."

"WE ARE INSISTING ON A HALT TO HOSTILITIES" BECAUSE OF SUCH ACTIONS, WHICH "CONSTITUTE ONLY TERRORISM AND DO NOT REPRESENT A MILITARY THREAT," THE PRESIDENT SAID.

THE PRESIDENT DENIED THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS LOOKING FOR ECONOMIC AID IN OTHER REGIONS BECAUSE OF THE SUSPENSION OF FRG AID AND BECAUSE OF THE POSSIBILITY OF U.S. AID CUTS.

"THIS VISIT TO TAIWAN HAD BEEN SCHEDULED SINCE BEFORE THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE IN NOVEMBER. I RECEIVED THE INVITATION FROM THE TAIWAN GOVERNMENT WHEN I TOOK OFFICE IN JUNE," CRISTIANI SAID.

HE ADDED THAT THE OBJECTIVE OF THE VISIT IS TO STRENGTHEN RELATIONS AND TRADE WITH A FRIENDLY GOVERNMENT AS WELL AS TO EXPRESS THANKS FOR THE TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE TAIWAN HAS PROVIDED.

REGARDING AID FROM THE FRG, HE SAID "EFFORTS ARE BEING MADE TO REESTABLISH IT. THE FRG GOVERNMENT IS CONDITIONING ITS AID ON RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS AND THE DEVELOPMENT OF THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IN THE COUNTRY."

REFERRING TO U.S. AID, THE SALVADORAN PRESIDENT SAID HE IS NOT AWARE THAT OFFICIAL DECISIONS OR PLANS EXIST. INSTEAD, THERE ARE PERSONAL POSITIONS OF CONGRESSMEN OR SPECIAL-INTEREST GROUPS, BUT THIS MUST BE FULLY DISCUSSED AT THE TIME OF THE VOTE FOR THE NEXT FISCAL YEAR, WHICH IN THE UNITED STATES BEGINS IN OCTOBER.

THE PRESIDENT ALSO DEFENDED THE RECENT ECONOMIC MEASURES, WHICH HAVE LED TO PROTESTS AGAINST THE GENERAL INCREASE IN PRICES OF STAPLES. HE SAID THESE MEASURES WERE NECESSARY FOR THE COUNTRY'S ECONOMY, WHICH WAS AFFECTED LAST YEAR, FIRST, BY THE OVERALL CUTS IN U.S. AID TO THE REGION, A REDUCTION OF $55 MILLION FOR EL SALVADOR; SECOND, BY THE DROP IN INTERNATIONAL COFFEE PRICES, WHICH CAUSED $150 MILLION IN LOSSES FOR EL SALVADOR; AND THIRD, BY THE DAMAGE FROM THE GUERRILLA OFFENSIVE IN NOVEMBER.

BEFORE LEAVING ON HIS TRIP AND IN RESPONSE TO NEWSMEN'S QUESTIONS, PRESIDENT CRISTIANI ALSO DEFENDED THE ARMED FORCES, STATING THAT THE ACTIONS IN WHICH THEY HAVE BEEN INVOLVED RECENTLY HAVE NOT WEAKENED THEM AND, ON THE CONTRARY, HAVE STRENGTHENED THE ARMED FORCES BECAUSE ERRORS HAVE BEEN ADMITTED AND THOSE RESPONSIBLE ARE BEING PROSECUTED, SUCH AS IN THE CASES OF THE JESUITS AND THE CIVILIANS WHO WERE KILLED ON 11 FEBRUARY IN CHALATENANGO.

CRISTIANI SAID THAT IN THE LATTER CASE THERE HAVE BEEN NO PRESSURES AND THAT FROM THE MOMENT THAT THERE WAS NEWS ABOUT THE TRAGEDY, THE COMMISSION THAT INVESTIGATES CRIMINAL ACTS WAS ORDERED TO UNDERTAKE THE APPROPRIATE INVESTIGATION TO DETERMINE THE CAUSE OF THE TRAGEDY. HE SAID IT CONCLUDED THAT THE TRAGEDY WAS CAUSED BY A HELICOPTER ROCKET, BUT THERE WAS NO BOMBING, ALTHOUGH THE CIVILIANS WERE VICTIMS OF WAR ACTIONS.

CRISTIANI CRITICIZED THE FMLN FOR WAGING BATTLES IN POPULATED AREAS BECAUSE THIS ENDANGERS CIVILIANS.

IN CONCLUSION, CRISTIANI SAID THE FMLN WILL NEVER GIVE UP ITS ATTEMPTS TO WEAKEN OR DIVIDE THE ARMED FORCES, BUT HE ADDED THAT THE ARMED FORCES ARE BECOMING MORE PROFESSIONAL EVERY DAY.

DEV-MUC3-1124 (UNISYS)

BOGOTA, 18 FEB 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE COMMUNIST REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA'S (FARC) GENERAL STAFF STATED THAT ALL THE COLOMBIAN GUERRILLA MOVEMENTS AGREE THAT THE CATHOLIC CHURCH SHOULD SERVE AS MEDIATOR IN A BROAD PEACE PROCESS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS.

THE FARC'S STATEMENTS ARE CONTAINED IN A LETTER RELEASED TODAY THAT WAS SENT TO CARDINAL ALFONSO LOPEZ TRUJILLO, PRESIDENT OF THE EPISCOPAL CONFERENCE, IN WHICH THE GUERRILLAS RESPOND TO RECENT STATEMENTS BY THE PRELATE, INTERPRETED BY THE FARC AS A MEDIATION OFFER.

ALTHOUGH THE DECLARATION IS ONLY SIGNED BY THE FARC COMMANDERS, IN CERTAIN PARAGRAPHS THEY EXPRESS THEMSELVES AS IF THEY WERE SPEAKING FOR THE SIMON BOLIVAR GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD, FOUNDED IN SEPTEMBER 1987.

IN ADDITION TO THE FARC, THE SIMON BOLIVAR GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD IS MADE UP OF THE PRO-MAO POPULAR LIBERATION ARMY (EPL), THE PRO-CASTRO CAMILISTA UNION OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (UC-ELN), THE PRO-TROTSKY REVOLUTIONARY WORKERS' PARTY (PRT), AND THE INDIAN GROUP QUINTIN LAME.

THE 19 APRIL MOVEMENT (M-19), WHICH HAS A LEFTIST - NATIONALIST ORIENTATION AND WHICH WAS PART OF THE SIMON BOLIVAR GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD, BEGAN 16 MONTHS AGO, OF ITS OWN ACCORD, A PEACE PROCESS WITH VIRGILIO BARCO'S LIBERAL PARTY GOVERNMENT.

THIS PEACE PLAN, WHICH HAS STUMBLED ACROSS SEVERAL POLITICAL OBSTACLES THAT HAS PRECLUDED TOTAL COMPLIANCE, COULD END ON 28 FEBRUARY WITH THE M-19 HANDING OVER THEIR WEAPONS TO A SOCIALIST INTERNATIONAL (IS) COMMISSION, THE FINAL PHASE BEING POSTPONED ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS SINCE LAST DECEMBER.

"YOUR RECENT STATEMENTS, CARDINAL, ON OPENING NEW ROADS TOWARD PEACE SEEM IMPORTANT TO US," THE FARC COMMANDERS STATE IN THEIR LETTER TO CARDINAL LOPEZ TRUJILLO.

"YOUR EMINENCE SAYS THAT IT WOULD MEAN GREAT PROGRESS FOR THE COUNTRY IF THE FARC WERE TO TAKE PART IN A COHERENT PEACE PROCESS," THE NOTE GOES ON, ADDING: "YOUR EMINENCE SHOULD KNOW THAT WE HAVE BEEN INVOLVED IN THIS EFFORT EVER SINCE BELISARIO BETANCUR'S (FORMER COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT) AMNESTY, WHICH STOPPED A 25-YEAR WAR."

IN 1984, UNDER BELISARIO BETANCUR'S SOCIAL - CONSERVATIVE GOVERNMENT (1982 - 1986), A PEACE PROCESS BEGAN THAT RESULTED IN THE CREATION OF THE LEGAL LEFT-WING PATRIOTIC UNION (UP) MOVEMENT -- INITIALLY COMPRISED OF FORMER FARC GUERRILLAS -- AND AN AGREEMENT RENDERING THE GUERRILLA GROUP'S GENERAL STAFF CAMP INVIOLABLE.

THE FARC LEADERS SAY IN THEIR LETTER TO THE CARDINAL THAT THE BARCO GOVERNMENT "DID NOT WANT OR COULD NOT CONTINUE BETANCUR'S POLICY OF PEACE AND RECONCILIATION."

"IF THE COLOMBIAN CHURCH, JUDGING BY THE CARDINAL'S STATEMENTS, SERVES AS AN ITERMEDIARY BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE REBELS, WE APPLAUD THAT HUMANISTIC AND PATRIOTIC DECISION," THE FARC GENERAL STAFF'S LETTER SAYS.

THE GUERRILLA GROUP ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE YESTERDAY PROPOSING THAT THE BARCO GOVERNMENT DECLARE A GENERAL CEASE-FIRE FOR THE 11 MARCH LEGISLATIVE AND 27 MAY PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS, TO WHICH THE GOVERNMENT HAS NOT YET RESPONDED.

HOWEVER, WITH PREVIOUS REQUESTS, THE GOVERNMENT HAS LIMITED ITSELF TO ASKING THE GUERRILLAS FOR UNILATERAL TRUCES TO PROVE THEIR DESIRE FOR PEACE, WHICH HAS ONLY WORKED OUT IN THE CASE OF THE M-19.

ALL THE MEMBERS OF THE SIMON BOLIVAR GUERRILLA COORDINATING BOARD, WITH THE EXCEPTION OF THE UC-ELN, DECLARED UNILATERAL TRUCES DURING THE LAST FEW WEEKS.

THE PRO-CASTRO GROUP IS THE ONLY ONE DETERMINED TO CONTINUE A SABOTAGE CAMPAIGN AGAINST THE ELECTIONS, CHARACTERIZED BY KIDNAPPINGS, ATTACKS ON RURAL VILLAGES, THREATS TO OFFICIALS, AND POLICE AND ARMY AMBUSHES.

DEV-MUC3-1125 (UNISYS)

LIMA, 18 FEB 90 (TELEVISION PERUANA) -- [SPEECH] [PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA] [EXCERPT] PERU HAS FACED THE GREAT ADVERSITY OF FOREIGN IMPERIALISM. PERU, A POOR AND WEAK BUT SOVEREIGN COUNTRY, HAS RAISED ITS VOICE TO FACE THE POWER AND GREED OF THE INTERNATIONAL BANKING SECTORS. PERU AND THE PERUVIAN STATE HAVE REFUSED TO PAY AN UNJUST DEBT. THIS WILL BE FOREVER REGARDED AS THE PIONEER AND VANGUARD ATTITUDE OF THE THIRD WORLD.

NO ONE WILL EVER FORGET THAT, IN THE FIRST TWO MONTHS OF MY ADMINISTRATION, THE PERUVIAN RESOURCES THAT WERE SCHEDULED TO BE USED TO PAY THE FOREIGN DEBT WERE INSTEAD USED FOR THE BENEFIT OF PERU. ALL PERUVIANS ADMITTED AT THE TIME THAT WE HAD BEGUN A PROCESS OF CAPITALIZATION AND DEVELOPMENT.

I HAVE COME HERE TODAY TO DELIVER SOME TRACTORS. BUT I WANT TO TELL YOU THAT DURING THE APRA [AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE] ADMINISTRATION THE NUMBER OF TRACTORS HAS DOUBLED. WHEN THE APRA ASSUMED POWER IN 1985, THERE WERE 5,060 TRACTORS IN PERU. BUT AFTER I DELIVER THESE ITALIAN TRACTORS, THERE WILL BE 11,200. THIS MEANS THAT THE AMOUNT OF LAND BEING FARMED MECHANICALLY IN PERU HAS DOUBLED. APPLAUSE, CHEERS OF "ALAN, ALAN"

THE HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS THAT HAS BEEN INVESTED IN EQUIPMENT OPERATING IN PERU TODAY IS THE SAME MONEY THAT, IN A SOVEREIGN DECISION, THE FATHERLAND REFUSED TO SEND ABROAD TO FOREIGN INTERNATIONAL BANKS. SHOUTS OF "WELL DONE" THE ANTI-IMPERIALISTIC IDEAL THAT WE UPHOLD IS BASED ON THIS MAIN PRINCIPLE: TO RETAIN OUR RESOURCES WITHIN PERU.

WE HAVE ALSO RAISED OUR VOICES TO DEFEND THE SOVEREIGNTY AND INTEGRITY OF OUR CONTINENT, BECAUSE WE ARE A PROUD AND FREE CONTINENT. WHEN WE SAW MILITARISTIC IMPERIALISM THREATEN AND INVADE A BROTHER COUNTRY, WE HAD THE HONOR -- THE SAD HONOR -- OF BEING THE ONLY ONE TO RAISE ITS VOICE AND TO MAKE IMPERIALISM, DUE TO THE FIRMNESS OF THE PERUVIAN STANCE, HEED OUR DEMANDS AND WITHDRAW ITS INVADING TROOPS FROM PANAMA."

I REMEMBER THE NIGHT OF 20 DECEMBER 1989, WHEN AT 0500 GMT I WAS INFORMED FROM WASHINGTON THAT 24,000 AMERICAN SOLDIERS HAD OCCUPIED PANAMA. I RECEIVED MANY PHONE CALLS FROM PEOPLE WHO TOLD ME: IT IS A DONE DEED. LET THEM INVADE THE COUNTRY. WE DO NOT NEED TO CONFRONT THEM. I RECEIVED PHONE CALLS FROM PEOPLE IN PERU AND ABROAD TELLING ME THAT WE COULD NOT CONFRONT THEM, THAT WE COULD NOT MAKE ANY DEMANDS. THEY SAID FOR US TO ACT AS IF NOTHING HAD HAPPENED. LET US RECOGNIZE THE GOVERNMENT THAT THEY HAVE PUT IN POWER. BUT I SAID NO. PEOPLE SHOUT "WELL DONE" I WAS TOLD: IF YOU KEEP SILENT, YOU CAN SOLVE YOUR PROBLEM WITH THE IMF. BUT I SAID NO, BECAUSE THE DIGNITY OF A NATION IS NOT FOR SALE. NO, BECAUSE THE DIGNITY OF LATIN AMERICA CANNOT BE BOUGHT. APPLAUSE, CHEERS OF "ALAN, ALAN"

CAUSING FEAR AND ASTONISHMENT FOR MANY PEOPLE IN PERU AND THROUGHOUT LATIN AMERICA, I SAID: WE ARE POOR. WE HAVE NO GREAT MILITARY POWER. WE HAVE NO PLANES OR BOMBS. WE HAVE NO BANKS FILLED WITH MILLIONS. BUT WE HAVE THE POWER OF REASON, WHICH IS MORE POWERFUL. WE HAVE THE POWER OF JUSTICE, WHICH IS GREATER. WE HAVE THE POWER OF FREEDOM, WHICH IS MORE IMPORTANT. I SAID THAT WE WOULD RECALL THE PERUVIAN AMBASSADOR FROM WASHINGTON. WE WOULD WITHDRAW FROM THE MILITARY ALLIANCE THAT WE HAVE WITH THE UNITED STATES, WHICH ALLOWED IT TO PERPETRATE THIS INVASION. WE WOULD TELL THE UNITED STATES THAT UNTIL THE LAST SOLDIER WAS WITHDRAWN, WE WOULD NOT SIT AT ANY NEGOTIATING TABLE, NOT ON DRUGS OR ON ANY OTHER SUBJECT.

BUT THE PERUVIAN RIGHTIST SECTORS DESCRIBED EVERYTHING I SAID ON 21 DECEMBER, EIGHT HOURS AFTER THE PANAMANIAN INVASION, AS INSANE. THEY DESCRIBED IT AS DEMAGOGIC THEATRICS. THEY SAID WE SHOULD COMPLY WITH THE U.S. ACTIONS. BUT I SAID NO. ALTHOUGH WE RESPECT THE UNITED STATES AND ITS PEOPLE, WE DO NOT TOLERATE IMPERIALISTIC IMPOSITIONS. WE DO NOT TOLERATE OTHER COUNTRIES INTERVENING IN THE SOVEREIGN AFFAIRS OF SISTER-NATIONS.

I CAN STATE WITH GREAT SATISFACTION THAT, 24 HOURS BEFORE THE CARTAGENA SUMMIT AND 2 MONTHS AFTER THE INVASION, THE LAST U.S. SOLDIER WITHDREW FROM PANAMA. THIS WAS THE SINE QUA NON CONDITION FOR MY ATTENDANCE AT THE SUMMIT. APPLAUSE, CHEERS

THIS PROVES THAT YOU CAN BE POOR AND ECONOMICALLY WEAK, BUT THAT YOU CAN HAVE THE STRENGTH THAT COMES FROM REASON, FROM MORAL PRINCIPLES; THAT YOU CAN HAVE JUSTICE ON YOUR SIDE; THAT YOU CAN SUCCEED, THAT SOONER OR LATER YOU WILL BE SUCCESSFUL. PERHAPS JUSTICE MAY COME LATE, BUT IT COMES. WHEN I SEE THE OLIGARCHIC ATTACK OF THE PREPOTENT ECONOMIC POWER HITTING PERU, I TELL THE PEOPLE THAT THE RIGHTIST SECTORS MAY BE VICTORIOUS. BUT IT WILL BE AN EPHEMERAL, TEMPORARY, AND MOMENTARY VICTORY BECAUSE IT IS THE PEOPLE WHO WILL SUCCEED, THE PEOPLE WHO WILL CONQUER, BECAUSE THE PEOPLE ARE RIGHT, THE PEOPLE HAVE JUSTICE ON THEIR SIDE, AND BECAUSE PERU BELONGS TO THE PEOPLE. APPLAUSE, CHEERS [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1128 (UNISYS)

BOGOTA, 20 FEB 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] AS A RESULT OF AN OFFENSIVE LAUNCHED BY ELN [ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION], EPL [POPULAR LIBERATION ARMY], AND FARC [REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA] REBELS, FIVE PEASANTS AND FOUR GUERRILLAS HAVE DIED, FIVE POLICEMEN HAVE BEEN WOUNDED, AND PROPERTY LOSSES IN THE MILLIONS HAVE OCCURRED. THE REBEL ACTIONS TOOK PLACE IN THE DEPARTMENTS OF BOLIVAR, META, SANTANDER, NORTHERN SANTANDER, CORDOBA, ANTIOQUIA, AND IN THE ARAUCA INTENDANCY.

ACCORDING TO THE AUTHORITIES' PRELIMINARY REPORT, ELN GUERRILLAS APPARENTLY BLEW UP A POWER TOWER IN CARTAGENA CAUSING A BLACKOUT IN MOST PARTS OF CARTAGENA CITY. SUBSEQUENTLY, THE ELN REBELS SHOT AT THREE EMERGENCY MEDICAL CARE CENTERS WOUNDING FIVE POLICEMEN.

SIMILARLY, TWO BOMB ATTACKS ON THE CANO LIMON-COVENAS AND CENTRAL DE LOS LLANOS ORIENTALES OIL PIPELINES CONDUCTED BY ELN REBELS HAVE RESULTED IN PROPERTY DAMAGE IN THE MILLIONS. THE TWO ATTACKS OCCURRED IN THE DEPARTMENTS OF NORTHERN SANTANDER AND META, RESPECTIVELY.

TWO REBELS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND FOUR OTHERS HAVE BEEN ARRESTED AFTER VARIOUS CLASHES BETWEEN COLOMBIAN ARMY TROOPS AND ELN AND FARC REBELS IN THE DEPARTMENTS OF SANTANDER, META, AND ARAUCA INTENDANCY.

IN ADDITION, TWO EPL REBELS HAVE BEEN KILLED IN A RURAL AREA IN CORDOBA DEPARTMENT IN CLASHES WITH A CARTAGENA BATTALION MILITARY PATROL. THE MILITARY PATROL WAS CONDUCTING SEARCH AND COMBING OPERATIONS IN THE AREA. ONE SOLDIER WAS ALSO WOUNDED IN THE CLASHES.

SIMILARLY, THREE PEASANTS HAVE BEEN SHOT TO DEATH BY ALLEGED EPL MEMBERS IN A RURAL AREA OF TIERRA ALTA MUNICIPALITY, CORDOBA DEPARTMENT. MEANWHILE, TWO OTHER PEASANTS, WHO WERE ACCUSED OF HELPING THE POLICE, HAVE BEEN SHOT TO DEATH BY ALLEGED ELN MEMBERS IN BARBACOAS, YONDO MUNICIPALITY, ANTIOQUIAN MIDDLE MAGDALENA.

FINALLY, ELN GUERRILLAS BLEW UP A PRIVATE PLANE CAUSING PROPERTY DAMAGE IN THE MILLIONS IN NUEVA FLORIDA, MIRAFLORES MUNICIPALITY, BOLIVAR DEPARTMENT.

DEV-MUC3-1129 (UNISYS)

SANTIAGO, 5 FEB 90 (HOY) -- [ARTICLE] [GILBERTO VILLARROEL] [TEXT] ON THE EVENING OF 20 MAY 1986, THE JENKA, A DANISH CARGO SHIP WITH AN EMPTY HOLD, WAS ANCHORED IN VALPARAISO BAY.

THE SHIP, WHICH WAS SPECIALLY FITTED TO CARRY WEAPONS, HAD BEEN "WAITING INTO LINE" FOR 120 DAYS, MEANING -- IN PORT OPERATION JARGON -- THAT IT WAS WAITING FOR ITS TURN OR FOR THE ARRIVAL OF ITS CARGO.

THE FIVE-MAN CREW WAS UNEASY. THEY WERE WAITING FOR A SHIPMENT OF 400 "WASP" CLUSTER BOMBS PRODUCED BY FERRIMAR [EXPANSION UNKNOWN] -- A SUBSIDIARY OF FAMAE (ARMY ORDNANCE) -- AND BOUND FOR THE MIDDLE EAST. THE DESTINATION OF THE SHIPMENT WAS IRAN. THE USERS: THE ARMED FORCES OF IMAM RUHOLLAH KHOMEINI.

THE SECRET SHIPMENT WAS HAVING PROBLEMS ON LAND.

THE FIVE CREW MEMBERS MADE A DECISION THAT NIGHT, TAKING ON FUEL AND FOOD AND FLEEING TOWARD PANAMA. IN THE DARK NO ONE NOTICED THE SHIP'S DEPARTURE, NOT THE SHIPPING COMPANY THAT WAS IN CHARGE OF THE SHIP NOR THE PORT'S CAPTAIN -- A NAVY OFFICER WHO WAS SUPPOSED TO AUTHORIZE THE MOVE. THE JENKA LEFT AN UNPAID DEBT OF $30,000 OWED TO THE SHIPPING COMPANY.

THE CASE WAS REPORTED BY THE PRESS AND FERRIMAR RUSHED TO SAY THAT IT WAS SELLING WEAPONS TO PAKISTAN AND NIGERIA. IT WAS ALSO SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT, FOR ETHICAL REASONS, WOULD NOT ALLOW THE ENTERPRISE TO OFFER THE "WASP" BOMBS TO IRAN. IN FACT, CHILEAN BUSINESSMAN CARLOS CARDOEN WAS ALREADY SELLING "CLUSTERS" [PRECEDING WORD IN ENGLISH] TO IRAQ. DOING BUSINESS AT THE EXPENSE OF THE TWO SIDES CONFRONTING EACH OTHER IN THE LONG PERSIAN GULF WAR WAS NOT CONSIDERED APPROPRIATE.

THE DEAL, HOWEVER, WAS ATTRACTIVE BECAUSE THERE COULD BE MILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN PROFITS. COUNTRIES LIKE BRAZIL AND THE USSR WERE KNOWN TO BE SELLING WEAPONS TO BOTH IRAN AND IRAQ. THE USSR WAS DIRECTLY SELLING WEAPONS TO IRAQ AND SUPPLYING IRAN THROUGH MIDDLEMEN. CHILE KNEW OF A SIMILAR EXAMPLE: DURING THE BEAGLE CHANNEL CONFLICT, WHICH ALMOST ENDED IN A WAR WITH ARGENTINA, ISRAEL SOLD MISSILES TO BOTH SIDES.

THEREFORE, IN A CAREFULLY PLANNED OPERATION, FERRIMAR AND FAMAE WERE ABLE TO SELL CLUSTER BOMBS TO IRAN.

THE MIDDLEMAN WOULD BE FRENCHMAN BERNARD STROIAZZO, THE SAME PERSON WHO THREE YEARS LATER WOULD CAUSE THE "IRAN-CORFO" [PRODUCTION DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION] SCANDAL (HOY, NO. 655).

IT IS ONLY NOW THAT STROIAZZO'S HISTORY HAS BEEN MADE PUBLIC. AN ENGINEER HIRED BY IRAN'S NATIONAL PETROLEUM COMPANY, HE SERVED AS A REPRESENTATIVE OF FERRIMAR AND FAMAE TO THE IRANIAN GOVERNMENT IN THE SALE OF CLUSTER BOMBS IN 1986. AFTER TWO SHIPMENTS OF DEFECTIVE BOMBS, THE IRANIANS DECIDED THAT THEY COULD CAUSE MORE CASUALTIES AMONG THEIR OWN MEN THAN AMONG ENEMY TROOPS. STROIAZZO WAS TAKEN HOSTAGE FOR 18 MONTHS.

HE MANAGED TO LEAVE AND TRAVELED TO CHILE. WITH THE HELP OF CNI [NATIONAL INTELLIGENCE CENTER] DIRECTOR BRIGADIER GENERAL HUGO SALAS, HE CONTACTED CORFO OFFICIALS WHO HELPED HIM ARRANGE COMPENSATION. HE ARRANGED A PRELIMINARY ACCORD FOR ESTABLISHING A TOXIC WASTE RECYCLING PLANT IN CHILE, BUT THE DEAL FAILED. HE THEN FILED A LAWSUIT AGAINST CORFO IN THE 19TH CIVIL COURT OF SANTIAGO. CORFO HAS NOT YET BEEN NOTIFIED OF THE LAWSUIT. THE PROBLEM, AT LEAST AS FAR AS THE TOXIC WASTE PLANT IS CONCERNED, WILL BE INHERITED BY THE NEW GOVERNMENT -- WHICH WILL TAKE OVER ON 11 MARCH -- AND BY CORFO.

DID FERRIMAR LIE TO THE CHILEAN GOVERNMENT?

THIS ENTERPRISE WAS KNOWN TO HAVE GOOD CONTACTS WITH THE AUTHORITIES. AMONG THE PARTNERS OF FERRIMAR OWNER ALDO PESCE WERE RETIRED GENERAL MANUEL CONTRERAS SEPULVEDA, FORMER CHIEF OF THE NATIONAL INTELLIGENCE DIRECTORATE, DINA; GENERAL RAUL REYES, FAMAE DIRECTOR, AND COLONEL CARLOS CARRENO, WHO WAS A FAMAE EXECUTIVE AND AN ADVISER TO FERRIMAR ON THE PRODUCTION OF THE "WASP" BOMBS. (A LAWSUIT FILED WITH THE 14TH CRIMINAL COURT OF SANTIAGO UNDER "ROBBERY OF INDUSTRIAL SECRETS" CHARGES CLAIMS THAT THE BOMBS WERE BUILT WITH PLANS STOLEN FROM CARLOS CARDOEN BY ONE OF CARDOEN'S TRUSTED MEN.)

TO EXPORT ITS BOMBS, FERRIMAR NEEDED THE AUTHORIZATION OF THE DEFENSE AND FOREIGN MINISTRIES. THE COMPANY HAD TO PROVIDE WHAT IS KNOWN IN THE INTERNATIONAL WEAPONS MARKET IS KNOWN AS AN "END-USER CERTIFICATE" OR "FINAL-USER CERTIFICATE." FERRIMAR GOT ONE. IT WAS SIGNED IN AUGUST 1985 BY A NIGERIAN ARMY OFFICER WHO, ACCORDING TO SOURCES CLOSE TO THE CASE, HAD RETIRED A LONG TIME AGO. A "TRIANGLE OPERATION" WAS CARRIED OUT TO CONCEAL THE TRUE OPERATION. IT IS NOT KNOWN WHETHER THE DEFENSE MINISTRY HAS INDICTED ANYONE OVER THE DECEPTION BY WHICH IT WAS VICTIMIZED.

AT THE END OF JANUARY 1986, THE FIRST 100 BOMBS WERE SHIPPED BY PLANE TO BANDAR ABBAS AIRPORT IN IRAN. EACH BOMB WEIGHED 227 KG AND CONTAINED 248 AMMUNITION PACKAGES, SOME OF THEM FOR IMMEDIATE DISCHARGE AND OTHERS FOR DELAYED ACTION. THESE WERE CAPABLE OF MINING LARGE AREAS FOR UP TO 72 HOURS AFTER A BATTLE.

THE FIRST SHIPMENT WAS WORTH $7 MILLION; $1 MILLION WAS FOR STROIAZZO AND $1.5 MILLION WENT FOR THE COST OF THE BOMBS. THE PRICE OF THE BOMBS ABROAD WAS $14,000 EACH, BUT THEIR REAL COST WAS ONLY $3,000. THE CHILEAN CONTACT IN THIS OPERATION, FERNANDO PEREZ, WAS TO HAVE RECEIVED $4.5 MILLION.

A TEST WAS PERFORMED IN IRAN AND THE BOMBS DID NOT WORK. THE IRANIAN DEFENSE MINISTRY ASKED THAT NEW TESTS BE CARRIED OUT IN CHILE. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1132 (UNISYS)

VALLELUPAR (COLOMBIA), 21 FEB 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] IN THE PAST FEW HOURS, THE SO-CALLED CAMILIST UNION ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION (UC-ELN) MURDERED A POLICE INSPECTOR AND TWO OF HIS BROTHERS, WHO WERE PEASANTS. THE INSPECTOR AND HIS BROTHERS WERE MURDERED BY THE UC-ELN WHO ACCUSED THEM OF BEING ARMY AND POLICE INFORMERS. THE TRIPLE CRIME OCCURRED ON THE EL LIMONCITO PATH, IN GUACHICA MUNICIPALITY, SOUTHERN CESAR DEPARTMENT. A POLICE SPOKESMAN SAID THAT THE REBELS HAD IDENTIFIED THEMSELVES AS UC-ELN MEMBERS. THESE THREE NEW VICTIMS OF THE REBEL OFFENSIVE WERE TAKEN BY FORCE FROM THEIR HOMES BEFORE THEY WERE KILLED. THE MURDERED INSPECTOR WAS IDENTIFIED AS GUSTAVO ROPERO NAVARRO, 22, FROM GUACHICA. HIS BROTHERS WERE IDENTIFIED AS MARIANO AND FELIX ROPERO NAVARRO, 26 AND 24, RESPECTIVELY. AFTER THE CRIME, THE REBELS FLED INTO THE EASTERN MOUNTAIN RANGE. THE ELN HAS STARTED A NEW WAVE OF VIOLENCE IN THE PAST HOURS. IT HAS MURDERED THREE PEASANTS IN GUACHICONO, SOUTHERN CAUCA DEPARTMENT, TWO IN ANTIOQUIA, AND THREE IN CORDOBA. THESE PEOPLE WERE KILLED AFTER BEING ACCUSED BY THE ELN OF BEING INFORMANTS.

DEV-MUC3-1134 (UNISYS)

MOSCOW (USSR), 18 FEB 90 (PRAVDA) -- [ARTICLE] [PAVEL BOGOMOLOV] [TEXT] THE ANNALS OF THE COLOMBIAN PORT OF CARTAGENA LIST THREE EXTREMELY FIERCE SIEGES. BACK IN 1586, THE "JEWEL OF THE CARIBBEAN" WAS CAPTURED BY SIR FRANCIS DRAKE, WHO DID NOT BURN THE CITY TO THE GROUND ONLY BECAUSE HE RECEIVED A RANSOM OF 10 MILLION PESOS. A CENTURY LATER CARTAGENA WAS OCCUPIED BY THE FRENCH. FINALLY, IN 1741, THE CITY'S DEFENDERS SUCCESSFULLY FOUGHT OFF AN ASSAULT BY A HOST OF 27,000 PIRATES HEADED BY SIR EDWARD VERNON...

THE WESTERN PRESS DESCRIBED THE MEETING BETWEEN THE PRESIDENTS OF THE UNITED STATES, BOLIVIA, COLOMBIA, AND PERU HELD A FEW DAYS AGO IN CARTAGENA AS A KIND OF ASSAULT. DESPITE SOME EXAGGERATION, THIS GRAPHIC DESCRIPTION WAS BASED ON PERFECTLY SERIOUS GROUNDS. AFTER ALL, THE CONFERENCE DID DISCUSS IMMEDIATE TASKS AND EVEN A DETAILED SCHEDULE FOR A JOINT OFFENSIVE BY THE GOVERNMENTS OF THESE COUNTRIES AGAINST CRIMINAL DRUG TRAFFICKING, WHICH RANKS FIRST IN THE PECKING ORDER OF CRIME.

IT IS INDEED NECESSARY TO LAUNCH AN ASSAULT AGAINST THE DRUG MAFIA'S STRONGHOLDS, WHETHER IN MEDELLIN, "FAMOUS" FOR UNBRIDLED GANGSTERISM, OR IN CARTAGENA ITSELF, WHOSE STATUS AS A RESORT IS THREATENED BY THE SELFSAME "COCAINE BARONS." AS A MATTER OF FACT, THIS TOURIST CENTER HAS BEEN REPEATEDLY SHAKEN IN RECENT MONTHS BY THE EXPLOSIONS OF BOMBS PLANTED BY TERRORISTS IN THE "HILTON" HOTEL, IN STORES, OR AT ITS MARINAS. IT IS NO WONDER, AS REUTER REPORTS, THAT NOT A SINGLE CRUISE SHIP HAS DROPPED ANCHOR THERE THIS SEASON.

YES, THE SITUATION IS HIGHLY ALARMING, AND THIS APPLIES TO THE WHOLE OF COLOMBIA AND EVEN TO THE ENTIRE REGION. IN THESE CONDITIONS THE FIRM RESOLVE DISPLAYED BY THE PARTICIPANTS IN THE CARTAGENA MEETING DESERVES UNDERSTANDING AND SUPPORT: THE RESOLVE TO FINALLY POOL THEIR EFFORTS IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST ORGANIZED CRIME AND TO JOINTLY PLACE A RELIABLE BARRIER IN ITS PATH. THESE ARE THE INTENTIONS SHOWN IN THE JOINT STATEMENT SIGNED BY THE FOUR PRESIDENTS AND BY THE SERIES OF SPECIAL DOCUMENTS.

THE AIM OF THESE AGREEMENTS IS NOBLE INDEED: TO BESIEGE THE DRUG MAFIA IN ITS NESTS, TO CUT OFF THE "LAUNDERING" OF DRUG DOLLARS, AND TO DEPRIVE THE MERCHANTS OF "SLOW DEATH" OF BROAD ACCESS TO THE "BLACK MARKET" IN THE UNITED STATES, WHERE, AS A MATTER OF FACT, THE LION'S SHARE OF SOUTH AMERICA'S POISONOUS EXPORT IS CONSUMED. IN OTHER WORDS, AN IMPORTANT STEP HAS BEEN TAKEN TO COMBAT ONE OF THE MAIN "EVILS OF THE 20TH CENTURY," AND IT WAS NOT FOR NOTHING THAT THE MEETING'S RESULTS WERE POSITIVELY APPRAISED BY UN SECRETARY GENERAL J. PEREZ DE CUELLAR.

HERE IS A DIFFERENT QUESTION: EMPHASIS IN CARTAGENA WAS PLACED ON ADMINISTRATIVE AND POLICE MEASURES AND ON WASHINGTON'S PRIMARILY MILITARIZED FORMS OF COOPERATION WITH THE ANDEAN STATES, BUT DOES THIS CONFORM WITH THEIR LONG-TERM NATIONAL INTERESTS, WITH THEIR DESIRE TO PUT AN END TO BACKWARDNESS AND ATTAIN A QUALITATIVELY NEW LEVEL OF SOCIOECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT? AFTER ALL, A RADICAL SOLUTION OF THE DRUG PROBLEM PRIMARILY DEMANDS NEITHER COMBAT AIRCRAFT NOT ARMORED PERSONNEL CARRIERS, BUT SOMETHING QUITE DIFFERENT. IT IS NECESSARY TO CHANGE THE ECONOMIC PROFILE OF VAST PROVINCES WHERE THE CULTIVATION OF COCA AND MARIJUANA IS THE SOLE SOURCE OF THE POPULATION'S EXISTENCE.

TRUE ENOUGH, THE UNITED STATES HAS NOW EXPRESSED READINESS TO ASSIST ALSO IN THIS SPHERE. ON THE OTHER HAND, THERE IS AN ALMOST TOTAL LACK OF READINESS TO IMPORT FROM SOUTH AMERICA THE CROPS WHICH COULD, IN PRINCIPLE, SQUEEZE OUT COCA AND MARIJUANA. IT WAS NOT FOR NOTHING THAT COLOMBIA'S PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO, THE WHITE HOUSE'S CLOSEST ALLY IN THE STRUGGLE AGAINST DRUGS, WAS FORCED TO DECLARE IN CARTAGENA THAT THE U.S. GOVERNMENT'S RIGID PROTECTIONIST MEASURES ARE JEOPARDIZING THE VERY FUTURE OF "ALTERNATIVE" SECTORS OF TROPICAL CROP FARMING -- THE CULTIVATION OF COFFEE, FLOWERS, AND SUGAR CANE. AND SO THE "SENIOR PARTNER" APPEARS TO BE TIGHTENING WITH THE ONE HAND THE VISE IN WHICH THE DRUG MAFIA NOW FINDS ITSELF, WHILE USING THE OTHER HAND TO PROTECT ITS MARKET FROM LEGAL LATIN AMERICAN EXPORTS.

FINALLY, THE LAST BUT, I THINK, MOST SUBSTANTIVE ARGUMENT. ACTUALLY, IT ALSO CASTS AN UNFAVORABLE LIGHT ON THE ROLE OF CONSISTENT FIGHTER AGAINST THE DRUG MAFIA WHICH WASHINGTON HAS NOW ASSUMED. THIS ARGUMENT IS PERFECTLY ENCAPSULATED IN JUST ONE SHORT WORD: "PANAMA." INDEED, DID THE RECENT AGGRESSION AGAINST THIS SOVEREIGN STATE, ONE OF WHOSE MAIN MOTIVES WAS ACTUALLY "TO PUNISH THE DRUG BUSINESS BOSSES," NOT DEMONSTRATE ALL THE FLAWS OF WASHINGTON'S "STRONGARM APPROACH" TOWARD LATIN AMERICA? AND ARE THERE ANY GUARANTEES THAT THE PENTAGON WILL NOT START "COPYING" ITS PANAMANIAN EXPERIENCE IN OTHER COUNTRIES IN THE CONTINENT ON THE PRETEXT OF PURSUING THE "COCAINE BARONS"?

THESE ARE FAR FROM RHETORICAL QUESTIONS, AND IT IS A PITY THAT CARTAGENA SIMPLY FAILED TO PROVIDE EVEN THE SLIGHTEST CLEAR-CUT ANSWERS TO THEM.

DEV-MUC3-1140 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 26 FEB 90 (LA VOZ PANAMERICANA) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH MSGR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ, AUXILIARY BISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR, WITH UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [ROSA CHAVEZ] WE BELIEVE THAT THE ELECTIONS IN NICARAGUA WILL MARK A NEW PHASE IN THE CENTRAL AMERICAN SITUATION. THINGS WILL NOT BE THE SAME IN THAT NEIGHBORING NATION AND I BELIEVE THAT THE EVOLUTION WILL FAVOR THE ACHIEVEMENT OF PEACE AT THE REGIONAL LEVEL. MOREOVER, THERE ARE OTHER ELEMENTS AT THE WORLD LEVEL THAT ALSO ALLOW US TO HAVE HOPE. LET US NOT FORGET THAT THE UNITED NATIONS PARTICULARLY IS STRIVING TO ORGANIZE A NEW ROUND OF TALKS. THEREFORE, WE BELIEVE THAT THE CONDITIONS ARE BEING SET SO THAT PEACE MAY BE ACHIEVED THIS YEAR. THE CHURCH URGES THOSE WHO HAVE ANYTHING TO DO WITH THIS DECISION TO DO IT AND THUS PAY HOMAGE TO OUR ARCHBISHOP MSGR [OSCAR ARNULFO] ROMERO, WHO DIED 10 YEARS AGO, AND A MAN WHO STRUGGLED FOR PEACE, ENGINEER [JOSE NAPOLEON] DUARTE. THAT WAS OUR PROPOSAL IN TODAY'S HOMILY.

[REPORTER] WILL THERE BE ANY DEMAND FOR AN INVESTIGATION OR RESOLUTION OF THIS CASE EVEN THOUGH MSGR ROMERO WAS ASSASSINATED 10 YEARS AGO?

[ROSA CHAVEZ] WE ARE CONVINCED THAT THE SOLUTION OF THIS CASE BASICALLY DEPENDS ON A POLITICAL DECISION TO DO IT. THEREFORE, IT COULD REMAIN UNSOLVED OR IT COULD BE QUICKLY SOLVED. WE WOULD LIKE TO THINK THAT A POLITICAL DECISION WOULD BE ADOPTED, BUT WE HAVE NO INFORMATION TO INDICATE THAT THIS WILL BE SO. INSTEAD, IT IS MORE A WISH, I BELIEVE IT IS A LEGITIMATE WISH, OF ALL THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. THEY WANT THE CASE TO BE SOLVED AND, ABOVE ALL, THEY WANT JUSTICE. THIS BLOOD SHOULD BEAR FRUIT BY ACHIEVING PEACE AND RESPECT AMONG MEN, AS A NEW FORM OF SOCIAL COEXISTENCE IN EL SALVADOR. VIOLENCE SHOULD NO LONGER EXIST AMONG US AND RECONCILIATION SHOULD QUICKLY BECOME A REALITY AMONG SALVADORANS.

[REPORTER] A WASHINGTON POST ARTICLE REVEALED THAT COL. [GUILLERMO ALFREDO] BENAVIDES HAS RECENTLY BEEN SEEN AT A SEASIDE [WORDS INDISTINCT]. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION ABOUT THIS?

[ROSA CHAVEZ] WE BELIEVE THAT THE TRIALS CURRENTLY UNDERWAY WILL BE ANOTHER TEST [PRECEDING WORD IN ENGLISH] FOR SALVADORAN JUSTICE. IT HAS FAILED ALMOST ALL OTHER TESTS [PRECEDING WORD IN ENGLISH]. LET US SEE HOW IT FARES THIS TIME, NOT ONLY FOR THE SAKE OF ITS PRESTIGE, BUT ALSO FOR THE SAKE OF THE HONOR OF SUCH A MUCH-SACRIFICED PEOPLE AND THE NEED TO GIVE THE PEOPLE HOPE. I BELIEVE THAT IMPORTANT STEPS HAVE BEEN TAKEN, BUT THE TIME HAS COME TO PROVE THAT THESE STEPS WILL LEAD TO A TRULY JUST CONCLUSION -- OR IF THEY WILL ONCE AGAIN BE CUT SHORT. LET US HOPE THAT PROGRESS WILL BE ACHIEVED AND, AS WE HAVE STATED ON OTHER OCCASIONS, THAT THE NAMES OF THE INTELLECTUAL AUTHORS OF THIS CRIME WILL ALSO BE KNOWN. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1141 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, 26 FEB 90 -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH MSGR GREGORIO ROSA CHAVEZ, AUXILIARY BISHOP OF SAN SALVADOR, WITH UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] MONSIGNOR, REFERRING TO THE WEEK'S EVENTS, YOU DID NOT TALK ABOUT THE CORRUPTION CASE MENTIONED BY THE GOVERNMENT. WHAT IMPLICATIONS MIGHT THIS CASE HAVE?

[ROSA CHAVEZ] I THINK IT IS TOO SOON TO HAVE A CLEAR IDEA OF WHAT MAY BE BEHIND THIS NEW SITUATION. WE MUST WAIT AWHILE FOR SOME TIME AND LEARN THE DETAILS. WE BELIEVE THAT THERE ARE WORSE THINGS WHICH SHOULD BE SOLVED. WE WOULD NOT LIKE TO EXPAND ON THIS. ALL WE WOULD LIKE TO SAY IS THAT WE THINK THERE ARE STILL THINGS WE SHOULD KNOW TO HAVE A CLEAR IDEA OF WHAT IS BEHIND THE ANNOUNCEMENT MADE THIS WEEK.

[REPORTER] DO YOU THINK A FRAUD CAN BE PERPETRATED IN THE NICARAGUAN ELECTIONS?

[ROSA CHAVEZ] WE THINK THAT, REGARDLESS OF WHO WINS IN NICARAGUA, IT WILL REPRESENT A POSITIVE STEP FOR THAT COUNTRY AND ALL OF THE REGION. THE NICARAGUAN CHURCH SHARES OUR VIEWS, MEANING THE PASTORS OF THAT NATION. THAT IS WHY WE BELIEVE THAT THE ACHIEVEMENT OF PEACE COULD BE NEAR FOR EL SALVADOR. HOW NICE IT WOULD BE IF WE AVAILED OURSELVES OF THIS OPPORTUNITY.

[REPORTER] MONSIGNOR, THE ARCHBISHOPRIC'S LEGAL ASSISTANCE HAS HELPED CLEAR MANY DEATHS IN EL SALVADOR. MONSIGNOR ROMERO WAS KILLED 10 YEARS AGO. DOES THE CATHOLIC CHURCH AND THE LEGAL ASSISTANCE OFFICE HAVE ANY IDEA OF WHO MIGHT BE BEHIND THIS DEATH?

[ROSA CHAVEZ] WE HAVE SAID MANY TIMES THAT THERE ARE MANY CLUES WHICH LEAD TO CERTAIN CONCLUSIONS BUT, ACCORDING TO OUR CURRENT LEGAL SYSTEM, THOSE CLUES CANNOT BE USED AS EVIDENCE. THUS, ONE CAN BE CERTAIN OF WHO THE KILLERS ARE AND STILL NOT BE ABLE TO PROVE IT. THAT IS ONE OF THE GREAT FRUSTRATIONS CREATED BY OUR LEGAL SYSTEM. IT IS OBVIOUS THAT WE HAVE SEVERAL IDEAS, WHICH WE HAVE COMMENTED ON MANY TIMES, OF WHO THE MONSIGNOR'S KILLERS MAY BE. ONCE MORE I SAY THAT THIS IS A MATTER OF MAKING A POLITICAL DECISION, PARTICULARLY TO CLEAR THE CASE OR LET IT REMAIN UNSOLVED.

[REPORTER] MONSIGNOR, FORMER PRESIDENT DUARTE HAS DIED. WHAT IS YOUR OPINION OF DUARTE'S ROLE CONCERNING THE CHURCH?

[ROSA CHAVEZ] WE WILL STATE IT THIS AFTERNOON DURING THE SPECIAL MASS WITH ALMOST ALL THE BISHOPS OF EL SALVADOR. THAT ANSWERS YOUR QUESTION. I BELIEVE WE SHOULD SEE THREE LEVELS: THE MAN, THE CHRISTIAN, AND THE POLITICIAN. THE LETTER THAT THE ARCHBISHOP SENT TO DUARTE'S WIDOW, MRS. INES, STATES SOME IDEAS ON THE MAN, THE CHRISTIAN, AND THE POLITICIAN. THIS AFTERNOON THE ARCHBISHOP WILL HAVE A SPECIAL HOMILY AND HE WILL UNDOUBTEDLY GIVE A MORE COMPLETE DESCRIPTION OF THE CHURCH'S VIEWS. WE CAN ADD THAT HE WAS A MAN WHO TRIED TO BE CONSISTENT WITH HIS CHRISTIAN FAITH. HE WAS A MAN WHO WAS OPEN TO THE CHURCH'S PROPOSAL.

DEV-MUC3-1142 (UNISYS)

BOGOTA, 26 FEB 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] SEVERAL COLOMBIAN PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFULES, LIBERALS ERNESTO SAMPER PIZANO AND HERNANDO DURAN AND CONSERVATIVE RODRIGO LLOREDA CAICEDO, EXPRESSED THEIR WILLINGNESS TODAY TO HOLD A DIALOGUE WITH THE EXTRADITABLES, THE ARMED WING OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, AFTER THE EXTRADITABLES VOICED THEIR DESIRE FOR SUCH TALKS.

THE EXTRADITABLES ASKED THE COLOMBIAN GOVERNMENT TODAY TO COME UP WITH THE MECHANISMS TO MAKE IT POSSIBLE FOR THEM TO TURN THEMSELVES IN TO THE JUSTICE SYSTEM, SUCH AS SURRENDERING THEIR WEAPONS, AMMUNITION, AND EXPLOSIVES, ACCORDING TO A LETTER DELIVERED TO THE GROUP OF NOTABLES, A GROUP OF MEDIATORS.

GOVERNMENT MINISTER CARLOS LEMOS AND OTHER AUTHORITIES REJECTED THE PROPOSALS MADE BY THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS.

THERE WILL BE NO MECHANISMS AND NO COMMISSIONS OTHER THAN THE COURTS, LEMOS SAID WHEN HE HEARD ABOUT THE PROPOSAL SENT TO THE GROUP OF NOTABLES FROM MEDELLIN.

THE GROUP OF NOTABLES IS COMPOSED OF FORMER LIBERAL PRESIDENTS ALFONSO LOPEZ AND JULIO CESAR TURBAY, FORMER SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE PRESIDENT MISAEL PASTRANA, BOGOTA ARCHBISHOP AND CARDINAL MARIO REVOLLO, AND DIEGO MONTANA, PRESIDENT OF THE LEFTIST PATRIOTIC UNION (UP).

LIBERAL SENATOR SAMPER PIZANO, AFTER LEARNING OF THE GOVERNMENT'S REFUSAL TO ACCEPT THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS' PROPOSAL, SAID THAT THERE ARE CERTAIN WARMONGERING SPIRITS IN THE GOVERNMENT, WHO MUST CHANGE THEIR ATTITUDE SO AS TO PUT AN END TO THE WAR.

THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE ADDED THAT THE OFFERS MADE BY THE EXTRADITABLES COULD BE ACCEPTED WITHOUT DISMANTLING THE DE JURE STATE OR THE COUNTRY'S INSTITUTIONS.

HERNANDO DURAN DESCRIBED THE PROPOSAL AS A STEP FORWARD IN THE EFFORTS BEING MADE TO NORMALIZE THE SITUATION OF THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS, AND HE WARNED THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND ITS OFFICERS MUST RESPOND TO THIS PROPOSAL.

I BELIEVE THE NEW OFFER TENDS TO CREATE A CLIMATE OF DETENTE BETWEEN THOSE INVOLVED IN DRUG TRAFFICKING ACTIVITIES AND THE GOVERNMENT ITSELF, DURAN SAID.

SOCIAL CONSERVATIVE CANDIDATE RODRIGO LLOREDA SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS THE OBLIGATION TO RESPOND TO THE EXTRADITABLES, AND HE ADDED THAT WHEN HE BECOMES PRESIDENT HE WILL DO SO.

HOWEVER, LLOREDA CAICEDO SAID THAT THE BASIC CONDITIONS FOR REACHING AN AGREEMENT ON THEIR SURRENDER IS TO HAVE THOSE WHO COMMITTED CRIMES TURN THEMSELVES IN AND BE JUDGED BY THE COLOMBIAN JUSTICE SYSTEM. HE ADDED: IT IS ALSO NECESSARY FOR THEM TO COMPENSATE THE VICTIMS OF THEIR TERRORIST ACTIONS; THERE SHOULD BE GUARANTEES FOR THE DISMANTLING OF THEIR PRODUCTIVE APPARATUS; THERE SHOULD BE A SUSPENSION OF THE PROCESSING AND SHIPMENT OF COCAINE ABROAD; AND INTERNATIONAL OBSERVERS SHOULD BE BROUGHT IN TO VERIFY THE PROCESS.

DEV-MUC3-1143 (UNISYS)

AYACUCHO, 26 FEB 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] IT WAS REPORTED TODAY IN AYACUCHO THAT AT LEAST 16 MEMBERS OF THE "PEASANT DEFENSE PATROL" (THE CIVILIAN MILITIA THAT FIGHTS SUBVERSION) DIED AND ANOTHER 30 WERE WOUNDED DURING AN ATTACK BY A "SHINING PATH" COLUMN.

TRUCK DRIVERS WHO TRANSPORT FREIGHT TO THE ZONE AND WHO ARRIVED TODAY FROM MACHENTE (LA MAR PROVINCE), 196 KM NORTHEAST OF AYACUCHO, HAVE REPORTED THAT THE SHINING PATH ATTACK TOOK PLACE UNEXPECTEDLY ON FRIDAY NIGHT. THE DRIVERS REPORTS HAVE NOT BEEN DENIED NOR CONFIRMED BY MILITARY AND POLICE AUTHORITIES. THEY REPORTED THAT THEY SAW AMBULANCES CARRYING THE WOUNDED TO THE HOSPITAL IN SAN FRANCISCO, LA MAR PROVINCE.

THE NUMBER OF VICTIMS OF POLITICAL VIOLENCE IN PERU NOW STANDS AT MORE THAN 600 THIS YEAR, AND THE TOTAL NUMBER OF PEOPLE KILLED SINCE THE "SHINING PATH" BEGAN ITS ARMED STRUGGLE IN 1980 NOW TOTALS 18,000 ACCORDING TO A CONGRESS COMMISSION WHICH IS STUDYING THE CAUSES OF VIOLENCE IN PERU.

POLICE SOURCES TODAY REPORTED IN AYACUCHO, 575 KM SOUTHEAST OF LIMA, THAT ACCORDING TO REPORTS BY RELATIVES, OVER THE PAST WEEK 30 YOUNG MEN WERE ABDUCTED BY SHINING PATH COLUMNS THAT INTERCEPT PASSENGER BUSES AND PRIVATE VEHICLES ON THE HIGHWAYS IN THE DEPARTMENT.

THE SOURCES ADDED THAT THE MAOIST GROUP IS RECRUITING PEOPLE LIKE THAT FOR THEIR ORGANIZATION, UNDER THREATS OF DEATH.

THE GOVERNMENT TODAY EXTENDED THE STATE OF EMERGENCY FOR 60 DAYS IN NINE OF THE 24 DEPARTMENTS INTO WHICH PERU IS POLITICALLY DIVIDED, AMONG THEM AYACUCHO, BECAUSE OF THE TERRORIST ACTION THAT PERSISTS IN THOSE AREAS.

THIS MEASURE WILL BE IMPLEMENTED UNTIL 2 WEEKS AFTER THE GENERAL LEGISLATIVE ELECTIONS THAT ARE SCHEDULED FOR 8 APRIL 1990.

DEV-MUC3-1144 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [MODERATOR] MARIA DE DOLORES ARJAC.

[ARJAC] IT IS SAID THAT AID TO EL SALVADOR WAS STOPPED [WORD INDISTINCT] FOR AID TO PANAMA. COULD IT NOT HAPPEN -- WITH MRS. CHAMORRA'S VICTORY -- THAT READJUSTMENTS ARE MADE IN AID TO SEVERAL CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRIES, INCLUDING EL SALVADOR? IN THIS RESPECT, THE FRG GOVERNMENT HAS ALREADY RENEWED AID TO EL SALVADOR, BUT NOT TO OTHER COUNTRIES. HOW DO YOU SEE THIS SITUATION?

[CRISTIANI] WELL, THIS COULD WELL HAPPEN, AS, OBVIOUSLY, THE U.S. GOVERNMENT AND THE SENATE AND HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES ARE FREE TO GIVE AID TO WHATEVER COUNTRY THEY BELIEVE IT IS ADVISABLE TO DO SO. CERTAINLY THERE IS A NEW SITUATION, AND MANY HAVE EXPRESSED TODAY THAT THEY ARE WILLING TO HELP NICARAGUA, AS WELL AS PANAMA AND OTHERS. THIS SITUATION COULD PERFECTLY WELL LESSEN THE AMOUNT OF AID TO EL SALVADOR. THIS IS A POSSIBILITY.

[MODERATOR] JUAN BURGOS OF INTERPRESS SERVICE.

[BURGOS] [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] UN SECRETARY GENERAL THAT ARE INTERPRETED AS THAT PRESSURE WAS APPLIED TO YOU AND TO THE ARMED FORCES COMMANDERS BY SOME POLITICAL LEADERS.

[CRISTIANI] I CAN TELL YOU VERY CLEARLY, AND I BELIEVE THAT THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL CAN TESTIFY TO MY STATEMENTS, THAT OUR POSITION HAS BEEN FITTING AND CONSISTENT AND THAT WE MAINTAIN THE POSITION WE EXPRESSED TO HIM AT PRESENT. WE DID PLACE AS A PRE-CONDITION THAT THE FMLN STOP ALL TERRORIST ACTIONS. IT IS HARD TO UNDERSTAND THAT THE UNITED NATIONS, AN ORGANIZATION THAT HAS CONDEMNED TERRORISM, CANNOT BACK OUR POSITION, AS WE ARE TRYING TO ELIMINATE FMLN TERRORIST ACTIONS. BUT WE HAVE NOT CHANGED OUR POSITION, AND IT IS THE SAME ONE WE EXPRESSED TO THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL.

[MODERATOR) MARGARITA ARTEGA OF ACAN-EFE.

[ARTEAGA] MR. PRESIDENT, I WOULD LIKE TO ASK YOU IF THE MOBILIZATION OF PEASANTS TODAY [WORDS INDISTINCT] COULD BE AN ANNOUNCEMENT THAT THE STATE OF SIEGE IS ABOUT TO LIFTED, AS, SUPPOSEDLY, CONCENTRATIONS AND MOBILIZATIONS ARE PROHIBITED?

[CRISTIANI] IT DEPENDS ON THE SECURITY SITUATION. THE STATE OF SIEGE IS NOT PERMANENT. WE MUST ANALYZE THE CONTEXT OF THE THREAT THAT MIGHT EXIST WITH REGARD TO SECURITY. WE HAVE READ SOME REPORTS, THOUGH WE HAVE NOT YET CONFIRMED THEM, CLAIMING THAT THE FMLN HAS SAID THAT IT DOES NOT INTEND TO LAUNCH ANY MORE OFFENSIVES. IT IS A GOOD SIGN THAT THE FMLN IS LOOKING FOR A WAY TO A DIALOGUE, AND THIS COULD PRODUCE THE LIFTING OF THE STATE OF SIEGE. AS YOU KNOW, THE STATE OF SIEGE HAS BEEN GREATLY REDUCED. IT IS NOT THE SAME. WE HAVE BEEN REDUCING IT PROGRESSIVELY AND IT IS NOW STRICTLY WHAT IS NECESSARY FOR NATIONAL SECURITY.

[MODERATOR] FRANCISCO ESPINOSA FOR ABC NEWS.

[ESPINOZA] [PASSAGE INDISTINCT]

[CRISTIANI] WELL, I DO NOT KNOW. I BELIEVE THAT FOR A DIALOGUE TO TAKE PLACE, THE PRE-CONDITION HAS TO BE MET, REGARDLESS OF NICARGUAN ELECTION RESULTS AND WHAT IT MEANS FOR THE FMLN. OUR POSITION IS BASED ON PRINCIPLES, ON THE PRINCIPLE THAT THE PEOPLE NOT CONTINUE TO SUFFER THE VIOLENCE GENERATED BY FMLN TERRORISM. THUS, THIS IS SOMETHING THAT HAS TO BE MET, REGARDLESS OF THE ELECTIONS. OBVIOUSLY, I BELIEVE THE RESULTS OF THE NICARAGUAN ELECTIONS WILL AFFECT THE FMLN IN SOME MEASURES, AND THIS COULD INCLUDE... [CHANGES THOUGHT] I DO NOT KNOW. WE WOULD HAVE TO SEE WHAT POSITION THEY WILL TAKE IN THE FUTURE, BUT IT COULD BE. OBVIOUSLY A CHANGE HAS OCCURRED AND WILL HAVE AN IMPACT AND COULD MOVE THE FMLN TO CHANGE ITS POSITION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1145 (UNISYS)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] AND, THEREFORE, IT DOES NOT SEEM LIKE IT IS A TOTAL ADVANCEMENT IN A DEMOCRATIC PROCESS, BECAUSE OBVIOUSLY IT IS NOT VERY DEMOCRATIC TO HAVE THE ARMED FORCES OF A COUNTRY UNDER THE CONTROL OF ONE OF ITS POLITICAL PARTIES. THE ARMED FORCES OF A COUNTRY SHOULD RESPOND TO THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS AND TO THE GOVERNMENT THAT IS LEGITIMATELY ELECTED BY THE PEOPLE. AND THEREFORE, THIS WOULD CURTAIL THE FREEDOM OF CHOICE OF THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE IN TRYING TO CONTROL AND GOVERN THE COUNTRY, EVEN THOUGH IT IS NOT FROM THE POSITION OF BEING PRESIDENT OF THE COUNTRY. SECONDLY, I THINK THAT I HAVE MENTIONED BEFORE THAT IT IS NOT THE RESULT OF THE ELECTION THAT WILL CHANGE OUR ATTITUDE WITH RESPECT TO OUR DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH NICARAGUA, BUT RATHER THE ATTITUDE OF THE NICARAGUAN GOVERNMENT WITH RESPECT TO AID TO THE FMLN, TO THE MARXIST GUERRILLAS IN EL SALVADOR. AND IN THIS CASE WE STILL HAVE NOT SEEN THAT CHANGE TAKING PLACE. OBVIOUSLY, WE FEEL THAT WITH MRS CHAMORRO AS PRESIDENT OF NICARAGUA THAT THIS AID WILL STOP AND THEREFORE MAKE IT EASIER FOR THE RESUMPTION OF NORMAL RELATIONS BETWEEN EL SALVADOR AND NICARAGUA, BUT IT IS THAT ATTITUDE THAT WOULD MAKE A CHANGE AND NOT NECESSARILY THE RESULT IN ITSELF.

WITH RESPECT TO THE THIRD QUESTION, OBVIOUSLY I THINK THAT IF MRS CHAMORRO REALLY IS IN CONTROL, IN TOTAL CONTROL, ESPECIALLY OF THE SANDINISTA ARMY, THAT THERE WILL BE A STOP IN AID, AND THEREFORE THE FMLN WOULD NOT HAVE NICARAGUA'S LOGISTICAL AND MILITARY SUPPORT FOR THEM. AND THEREFORE, THIS CERTAINLY AFFECTS THEM.

[REPORTER, IN ENGLISH] I THINK THAT ABOUT ONE WEEK AGO OR TWO WEEKS AGO IN THE WASHINGTON POST THERE WAS A REPORT THAT COLONEL BENAVIDES WAS LIVING A RATHER LUXURIOUS LIFE. I DO NOT KNOW IF YOU HAVE SEEN THAT PIECE. AND ALSO THE U.S. AMBASSADOR WILLIAM WALKER HAS SAID THAT HE FELT THAT IT WAS TIME THAT, WELL, THE ARTICLE IMPLIES THAT THERE WAS SOME PRESSURE, OR THERE WAS SOME PROTECTION COMING FROM THE TANDONA [REFERENCE TO THE 1966 GRADUATING CLASS OF THE CAPTAIN GENERAL GERARDO BARRIOS MILITARY ACADEMY] TO PROTECT BENAVIDES, BECAUSE HE [WORDS INDISTINCT] THEIR MEN AND THAT SOME LOWER LIEUTENANTS WERE NOT GOING TO BE RECEIVING ANY SORT OF PROTECTION AND THEY MAY HAVE TO TAKE THE FAULT FOR WHAT HAS HAPPENED. AND ALSO WILLIAM WALKER HAD SAID THAT HE FELT THAT IT WAS TIME FOR SOME OF THE PEOPLE IN THE TANDONA TO STEP DOWN AND FOR OTHER OFFICERS TO MOVE UP. WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT THAT [WORD INDISTINCT]? SHOULD THERE BE THAT KIND OF PRESSURE? SHOULD SOME OF THE GUYS IN THE TANDONA STEP DOWN FROM THEIR POSTS?

[CRISTIANI, IN ENGLISH] WELL, I THINK THAT IT IS NOT REALLY THE DETERMINING FACTOR WHETHER YOU BELONG TO A SPECIFIC GRADUATING CLASS WITHIN THE ARMED FORCES THAT SHOULD BE WHAT DETERMINES WHETHER YOU CONTINUE OR NOT, OR BE REMOVED OR NOT FROM THE ARMED FORCES. IT IS YOUR OWN PERFORMANCE AND YOUR OWN BEHAVIOR THAT SHOULD BE THE DETERMINING FACTOR.

SO, THEREFORE, IT IS NOT NECESSARILY THAT THE TANDONA PEOPLE, JUST FOR BEING MEMBERS OF THE GRADUATING CLASS, [CHUCKLES] THAT ACTION SHOULD BE TAKEN AGAINST THEM. SO I THINK THAT IN THAT CASE THAT IS NOT REALLY THE POINT.

WITH RESPECT TO THE OTHER CASE, I THINK IT IS NOW IN THE HANDS OF THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM IN THE COUNTRY ON HOW IT GOES, WHAT TYPE OF DEFENSE THOSE THAT HAVE BEEN ARRAIGNED HAVE. I THINK THAT THEY ALL ARE RECEIVING THE LEGAL SUPPORT IN THE CASE AND THE OTHER [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER, IN ENGLISH] AS FOR THE DIALOGUE WITH THE GUERRILLAS, BEFORE YOU LEFT FOR TAIWAN YOU CONDITIONED THE DIALOGUE ON A CEASING OF ACTS OF VIOLENCE. TO BE SPECIFIC, DOES THIS MEAN [WORDS INDISTINCT] ALL ACTS OF VIOLENCE? AND ALSO, WHEN DO YOU THINK THAT THIS DIALOGUE CAN ACTUALLY TAKE PLACE?

[CRISTIANI, IN ENGLISH] WELL, IF WE COULD TRY AND PUT INTO ONE BASKET AND CALL THAT BASKET WITH A NAME WITH RESPECT TO THE ACTIONS, WE ARE ASKING THE FMLN TO STOP TERRORIST ACTIVITIES, BECAUSE TERRORIST ACTIVITY IS AFFECTING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. YOU JUST MENTIONED THE FACT ABOUT A POLE THAT THEY USE FOR ELECTRICAL DISTRIBUTION IN THE COUNTRY. JUST LAST NIGHT THEY BLEW UP ONE AND THERE ARE TWO PEOPLE HURT. TWO CIVILIANS THAT WERE PASSING BY WERE HURT BY THAT EXPLOSION. SO THAT IS WHAT HAS TO STOP. THE FMLN HAS TO STOP ALL TERRORIST ACTIVITY, BECAUSE THAT IS THE ACTIVITY THAT HURTS THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. THAT IS NOT MILITARY ACTIVITY. THAT IS SOMETHING GEARED AGAINST OR TO CONFRONT THE ARMED FORCES. SO IT IS THAT VIOLENCE THAT CAN BE SUMMED UP IN WHAT IS CALLED TERRORISM THAT WE ARE ASKING FOR -- THOSE ACTIVITIES THAT REALLY AFFECT THE CIVILIAN POPULATION OF THE COUNTRY. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1148 (UNISYS)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 3 MAR 90 (CIRCUITO RPC TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [JULIO MILLER, DIRECTOR OF RPC NEWS DEPARTMENT] [TEXT] DEAR TELEVISION AUDIENCE, WE BRIEFLY INTERRUPT OUR REGULAR PROGRAMMING TO OFFER YOU A REPORT OF GENERAL INTEREST. THE FILM CLIPS WE WILL SEE IN A FEW MINUTES WERE TAKEN THIS AFTERNOON AND EARLY TONIGHT AT THE RESIDENCY OF THE PERUVIAN AMBASSADOR IN BELLA VISTA CORREGIMIENTO, EL CANGREJO NEIGHBORHOOD, WHEN PEOPLE WERE STAGING A PEACEFUL DEMONSTRATION PROMPTED BY THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT'S DECISION TO GRANT SAFE-CONDUCTS TO SOME OF THE PANAMANIANS CURRENTLY AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY. AMONG THE PANAMANIANS WHO SOUGHT SHELTER AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY AND WHO WERE GRANTED SAFE-CONDUCTS ARE MARCELA TASON, FORMER PRIVATE SECRETARY OF OUSTED PANAMANIAN DICTATOR MANUEL ANTONIO. CAPTAINS HERACLIDES SUCRE, AND GONZALO GONZALEZ, INVOLVED IN THE KILLING OF MAJOR MOISES GIROLDI ARE ALSO AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY. THE FILM CLIPS SHOW PART OF THE INTENSE PROTESTS THAT TOOK PLACE NEAR, OR RATHER ON THE GROUNDS OF THE RESIDENCY OF THE PERUVIAN AMBASSADOR IN PANAMA CITY.

DEMONSTRATORS THREW STONES AT THE EMBASSY WINDOWS AND LATER SET FIRE TO PART OF THE RESIDENCY INSTALLATIONS. [CROWD SHOUTS: "THIS DAMNED THING IS ON FIRE!" THREE TIMES] DURING THE PROTEST NOT ONE OF THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY OFFICIALS ATTEMPTED TO LEAVE THE DIPLOMATIC QUARTERS. PERUVIAN DIPLOMATS AND EVEN THE PANAMANIANS WHO SOUGHT SHELTER AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY AND WHO WERE AT THE RESIDENCY REMAINED INSIDE. PANAMANIAN PUBLIC FORCE UNITS UNSUCESSFULLY TRIED TO CONTROL DEMONSTRATORS. DURING THE INCIDENT, A PUBLIC FORCE MEMBER WHO TRIED TO PREVENT THE INCIDENT WAS SLIGHTLY INJURED. THESE SCENES WERE FILMED THIS AFTERNOON AND DURING THE EARLY EVENING HOURS BY OUR CAMERAMAN JOSE CASIS JR. AND SHOW PART OF THE PROTEST ACTIONS AGAINST THE RESIDENCY.

MAJOR EDGARDO LOPEZ GRIMALDO, FORMER DEFENSE FORCES PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICER, AND THE OTHER CAPTAINS WE MENTIONED BEFORE ARE CURRENTLY AT THE RESIDENCY. LET US LISTEN TO PART OF THE STATEMENTS BY THE WIDOW OF MAJOR MOISES GIROLDI.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ADELA DE GIROLDI] HE [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] TOLD US THAT HE WILL TAKE US TO FIRST VICE PRESIDENT AND JUSTICE MINISTER RICARDO ARIAS CALDERON.

[REPORTER] DID YOU AGREE TO THAT?

[GIROLDI] I DO NOT WANT TO SEE ANYONE ELSE KILLED. I THINK THERE HAVE BEEN ENOUGH PEOPLE KILLED. I BELIEVE THE PRESSURE WE HAVE EXERTED IS ENOUGH.

[REPORTER] WHAT WILL BE YOUR POSITION WHEN YOU TALK TO THE MINISTER?

[GIROLDI] I WANT THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT TO TAKE ACTION SO THAT THE PERUVIAN AUTHORITIES TURN THOSE PEOPLE OVER TO THE PANAMANIANS. I THINK IT IS A MATTER OF FIRMLY DEMANDING THAT THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT TURNS THIS PEOPLE OVER TO PANAMA.

[REPORTER] HOWEVER, IF THERE IS NOT A SATISFACTORY RESPONSE TODAY, BY THE AUTHORITIES AND THE GOVERNMENT, WHAT MEASURES WILL YOU ADOPT? WILL YOU CONTINUE PROTESTING?

[GIROLDI] OF COURSE WE WILL CONTINUE PROTESTING. WE WILL CONTINUE PROTESTING BECAUSE THE ONLY THING WE ARE ASKING FOR IS THAT THESE PEOPLE SURRENDER TO PANAMANIAN JUSTICE SO THE LAW CAN BE ENFORCED BECAUSE THEY KILLED....[CHANGES THOUGHT] HERACLIDES SUCRE FIRED AT MY HUSBAND, HAVE YOU HEARD ABOUT IT, HE MACHINEGUNNED MY HUSBAND IN COLD BLOOD. OTHER OFFICERS AND SOLDIERS WHO TOOK PART IN THE 3 OCTOBER COUP WERE TORTURED, CUT WITH MACHETES. [END RECORDING]

THE FOLLOWING FILM CLIPS SHOW A DIALOGUE BETWEEN PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC GUILLERMO ENDARA, VICE PRESIDENT RICARDO ARIAS CALDERON, AND THE WIDOWS OF OFFICERS AND MILITARYMEN MISSING OR KILLED ON 3 OCTOBER 1989 IN THE ATTEMPTED COUP. THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE PRESIDENT, THE VICE PRESIDENT, AND THE DEMONSTRATORS WAS POSITIVE. DEMONSTRATORS PROMISED TO REMAIN CALM AND WAIT UNTIL PANAMANIAN JUSTICE DETERMINES THE RESPONSIBILITY, AND ISSUE SENTENCES FOR THOSE CURRENTLY AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY. LATER ON VICE PRESIDENT RICARDO ARIAS CALDERON, AND PRESIDENT ENDARA MADE STATEMENTS TO THE PRESS. WE WILL LISTEN FIRST TO STATEMENTS BY VICE PRESIDENT RICARDO ARIAS CALDERON. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1149 (UNISYS)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 3 MAR 90 (CIRCUITO RPC TELEVISION) -- [REPORT] [JULIO MILLER, DIRECTOR OF RPC NEWS DEPARTMENT] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [BEGIN RECORDING] [ARIAS] THE PRESIDENT AND MYSELF VIGOROUSLY DEPLORE WHAT TRANSPIRED THIS AFTERNOON AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY. I HAD THE OPPORTUNITY ALONG WITH THE PRESIDENT TO TALK TO MRS. GIROLDI, AND SHE ASSURED US THAT HER ONLY INTENTION WAS TO STAGE A PEACEFUL PROTEST AND AT NO TIME DID THEY PLAN TO INCLUDE ANY VIOLENT ACTS. MRS. GIROLDI SAID THAT SHE IS VERY SURPRISED THAT SOME PEOPLE WHOM SHE DOES NOT KNOW AND HAS NEVER SEEN BEFORE PROMOTED VIOLENT ACTS. SHE TOLD THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC THAT SHE WILL TALK TO THE PEOPLE AND TELL THEM THAT THERE SHOULD BE NO VIOLENCE AND THAT VIOLENCE IS NOT THE AIM.

THE PRESIDENT AND I APPRECIATE WHAT SHE IS DOING; WE UNDERSTAND HER PAIN. WE EXPLAINED TO HER THAT THE PRESIDENT HAS NOT AUTHORIZED ANY SAFE-CONDUCTS FOR INDIVIDUALS WHO HAVE BEEN CHARGED WITH MURDER. THOSE CASES ARE BEING TREATED DIFFERENTLY BY THE PRESIDENT AND THE MINISTER OF FOREIGN RELATIONS.

[REPORTER] IS A BREAK IN RELATIONS EXPECTED BETWEEN PANAMA AND PERU DUE TO THE VIOLENT ACTIONS?

[ARIAS] NOT AT ALL. I TALKED TO THE PERUVIAN CHARGE D'AFFAIRES AFTER OUR FOREIGN MINISTER TALKED TO HIM. HE KNOWS THAT THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT PROFOUNDLY REGRETS WHAT HAS TRANSPIRED; THAT THE PEOPLE WHO WERE PROTESTING THERE, SUCH AS MRS GIROLDI, HAD NO PLANS TO CARRY OUT VIOLENT ACTIONS. UNIDENTIFIED PEOPLE, WHOSE IDENTITY WE WILL TRY TO DETERMINE, URGED THE THROWING OF FIRE BOMBS AGAINST THE EMBASSY. THE FOREIGN MINISTER AND MYSELF EXPRESSED OUR APOLOGIES TO THE PERUVIAN GOVERNMENT FOR ANY INCONVENIENCES OR INSECURITY FELT BY ITS PERSONNEL.

[ENDARA] THESE ARE VERY REGRETFUL INCIDENTS. NOT ONLY A BASIC COURTESY OF CIVILIZED PEOPLE, THAT IS TO RESPECT THE RESIDENCES OF OTHER PEOPLE, AND MORE SO WHEN THEY BELONG TO REPRESENTATIVES OF OTHER COUNTRIES, BUT A PRINCIPLE OF INTERNATIONAL LAW HAS BEEN VIOLATED. THAT PRINCIPLE IS DUE RESPECT FOR DIPLOMATIC MISSIONS.

WHAT REALLY WORRIES US ABOUT THIS INCIDENT IS A REPORT GIVEN TO US BY THE ORGANIZERS OF DEMONSTRATIONS AT THE EMBASSY. SPECIFICALLY, BY THE WIDOWS OF MEN MURDERED BY THOSE WHO ARE REFUGED IN THAT EMBASSY; THE WIDOW OF MAJOR GIROLDI WAS HERE, AND SHE TOLD US THAT ALL HER ACTIONS AT THE EMBASSY HAVE BEEN PEACEFUL.

SHE TOLD US THAT TODAY THEY NOTICED THAT TOTALLY UNFAMILIAR PEOPLE WERE PRESENT AND THESE PEOPLE PROVOKED THE VIOLENCE; THEY INSTIGATED THE VIOLENCE. OBVIOUSLY, THERE CERTAIN GROUPS ARE SEEKING TO SPOIL OUR EFFORTS TO ACHIEVE DEMOCRACY. THEY WANT TO PREVENT THE ESTABLISHMENT OF A DEMOCRATIC SYSTEM WITH JUSTICE AND LIBERTY AT ALL COSTS.

I BELIEVE THAT THIS INCIDENT MUST BE DENOUNCED BEFORE THE ATTORNEY GENERAL OF THE NATION. HE SHOULD INVESTIGATE THESE PROVOCATIONS. NEVERTHELESS, THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH URGES THE CITIZENS TO NOT ALLOW PEOPLE TO PROVOKE THEM INTO PARTICIPATING IN VIOLENT ACTIONS SUCH AS ONE WHICH OCCURRED TODAY. THE CITIZENS MUST NOT ALLOW OTHERS TO EXPLOIT THE FEELINGS THAT ALL PANAMNIANS FEEL TOWARDS CRIMINALS AND PEOPLE WHO HAVE COMMITTED CRIMES AND WHO ARE HOLED UP IN EMBASSIES SUCH AS THIS ONE; WE URGE CITIZENS TO AVOID BEING PROVOKED. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1150 (UNISYS)

BOGOTA, 4 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] THE AUTHORITIES AND SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS HAVE BEEN SURPRISED BY THE SHOCKING WAVE OF KIDNAPPINGS CARRIED OUT THROUGHOUT THE NATIONAL TERRITORY BY THE SELF-STYLED ARMY OF NATIONAL LIBERATION, ELN. OVER THE PAST FEW HOURS, THE GROUP HAS KIDNAPPED 20 PEOPLE.

AMONG THE VICTIMS OF THE ELN'S SO-CALLED CAMILIST UNION ARE FOUR MAYORS, TWO DEPUTIES, SIX EXECUTIVES, CATTLEMEN, BUSINESSMEN, FARMERS, AND A POLICEMAN.

ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL REPORTS, 12 KIDNAPPINGS TOOK PLACE OVER THE PAST 18 HOURS. IN CESAR DEPARTMENT, MEMBERS OF THE CAMILIST UNION KIDNAPPED LIBERAL DEPUTY DARIO QUINTERO PATINO, 42, IN THE DOWNTOWN SECTION OF AGUACHICA MUNICIPALITY. NEWSMAN EMILIANO J. PACHECO, WHO WORKS FOR THE "ADVANCES OF CESAR" NEWSCAST OF THE ONDAS DEL CESAR RADIO STATION, WAS KIDNAPPED ALONG WITH THE POLITICAL LEADER.

EARLY ON SATURDAY MORNING, A GANG OF KIDNAPPERS, APPARENTLY ELN MEMBERS, KIDNAPPED CATTLEMAN MANUEL NARCISO MARTINEZ JAROCA, NEPHEW OF ANIBAL MARTINEZ ZURETA, CANDIDATE FOR MAYOR OF VALLEDUPAR AND FORMER COMPTROLLER GENERAL OF THE REPUBLIC. IN ADDITION, CELINA OSSA DE GOMEZ, CONSERVATIVE PARTY LEADER AND DEPUTY, WAS KIDNAPPED IN DOWNTOWN GRANADA, ANTIOQUIA. IN TIBU, NORTE DE SANTANDER, MAYOR EDUARDO ROLON DIAZ AND MAYORAL CANDIDATE ALVARO SARMIENTO HERRERA WERE ALSO KIDNAPPED BY THE SO-CALLED ELN CAMILIST UNION. THE TWO MEN WERE ON THEIR WAY TO LUNCH WHEN THEY WERE TAKEN BY SURPRISE BY THE REBELS.

AT NOON YESTERDAY, NEAR SAVANA DE TORRES, SANTANDER, ALVARO TORRES, AN EMPLOYEE OF THE AGRARIAN FUND; OSCAR CELIO TORRES GUTIERREZ, A SPOKESMAN FOR INCORA [COLOMBIAN INSTITUTE OF AGRARIAN REFORM]; MIGUEL CACEL, AN IMAT [EXPANSION UNKNOWN] OFFICIAL; AND A WORKER FROM PEDIAROZ WERE KIDNAPPED. THE ELN IS ALSO HOLDING NOEL FRANCISCO ACEVEDO AND JAVIER IGNACIO PENA, THE MAYORS OF EL CARMEN AND CALIFORNIA, SANTANDER, RESPECTIVELY; AND LIBERAL PARTY DEPUTY JUAN CARLOS DUARTE, WHO WAS ABDUCTED BY THE ELN ON TENERIFE ROAD, IN THE MUNICIPAL JURISDICTION OF CONCEPCION. DUARTE IS A DEPUTY FOR THE RENOVATION OF FREE SANTANDER LIBERAL PARTY.

ALONG THE ROAD FROM SAN VICENTE TO EL CARMEN, ALSO IN SANTANDER, GONZALO VASQUEZ ARDILA, MANAGER OF THE LOCAL AGRARIAN FUND, AND OLINDO MANTILLA ARDILA, A DIRECTOR OF THE (COTRAS MAGDALENA) COMPANY, WERE ALSO KIDNAPPED. THE TWO MEN WERE IN AN AUTOMOBILE WITH LICENSE PLATE UF-2171 WHEN THEY WERE ABDUCTED BY THE GUERRILLAS. THE DRIVER, MARCO TULIO GOMEZ, WAS ALSO KIDNAPPED, BUT RELEASED SEVERAL HOURS LATER.

HERNANDO TORRES JAIMES, MAYOR OF HACARI, NORTE DE SANTANDER, IS ALSO IN THE HANDS OF THE ELN. IN CORDOBA, CATTLEMAN GERMAN SIERRA MEDINA WAS KIDNAPPED ALONG THE EL TORO ROAD OF PIEDRA ALTA. IN CANALETE, ALSO IN CORDOBA, CATTLEMAN PEDRO PABLO MEJIA WAS KIDNAPPED. HE WAS AT THE LA CANA ESTATE WHEN THE GUERRILLAS KIDNAPPED HIM.

IN PEDREGALES, ON THE ROAD FROM ZULIA TO SARDINATA, THE ELN KIDNAPPED BUSINESSMAN SERGIO ALARCON. IN EL CENTENARIO, EL CARMEN, SANTANDER, MEMBERS OF THE CAMILIST UNION KIDNAPPED LANDOWNER SAMUEL PLAZAS.

THE AUTHORITIES ALSO ANNOUNCED THAT POLICEMAN EDISON AGUDELO AGUDELO WAS KIDNAPPED BY MEMBERS OF THE CAMILIST UNION AS HE WAS ON HIS WAY TO FRAGUAS CORREGIMIENTO IN REMEDIOS, ANTIOQUIA, TO CASH A CHECK.

THE AUTHORITIES AND SECRET SERVICE ORGANIZATIONS ANNOUNCED THAT INTENSIVE OPERATIONS ARE UNDERWAY IN AN EFFORT TO RESCUE THE HOSTAGES ALIVE. AT THE SAME TIME, THEY URGED LOCAL OFFICIALS AND POLITICAL LEADERS TO REFRAIN FROM TRAVELLING ALONE TO AVOID FALLING INTO THE HANDS OF THE GUERRILLAS.

WITH THIS SHOCKING WAVE OF KIDNAPPINGS, THE NUMBER OF SUCH ACTIONS IN COLOMBIA SO FAR IN 1990 HAS INCREASED TO 120.

DEV-MUC3-1151 (SYNCHRONETICS)

CLANDESTINE, 6 MAR 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [JOINT COMMAND OF THE MODESTO RAMIREZ CENTRAL FRONT] [TEXT] ONE MILITARY HELICOPTER WAS SHOT DOWN TODAY WHILE ANOTHER ONE WAS DAMAGED IN QUEBRANDA HONDA NEAR CHALATENANGO CITY. THEREFORE, THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] WISHES TO INFORM OUR PEOPLE OF THE FOLLOWING:

1. THE ANTI-AIRCRAFT CLASH TOOK PLACE DURING A MILITARY OPERATION WHICH THE DM-1 [MILITARY DETACHMENT 1] IS CARRYING OUT IN THAT SECTOR.

2. EARLY IN THE MORNING WE FOUGHT WITH DM-1 TROOPS, WHO WERE SUPPORTED BY SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS.

3. WITHIN THIS FRAMEWORK, OUR ANTI-AIRCRAFT UNITS FIRED ON TWO MILITARY HELICOPTERS THAT HAD FIRED ROCKETS AND MACHINEGUNNED THE AREA. OUR UNITS SHOT DOWN ONE AND SERIOUSLY DAMAGED ANOTHER HELICOPTER.

4. THESE ACTIONS TOOK PLACE NEAR THE CAPITAL OF CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT, AND NOT NEAR THE GUANCORA LAND SETTLEMENT.

5. LATER, WE LEARNED FROM PUBLIC REPORTS THAT ONE OF THE HELICOPTERS WAS CARRYING A TEAM OF JOURNALISTS AND ATTORNEY GENERAL MAURICIO COLORADO ALONG WITH THE TROOPS. TO THAT EFFECT, WE REGRET THE INJURIES INFLICTED ON THE JOURNALISTS, TO WHOM WE REITERATE OUR RECOMMENDATION THAT THEY SHOULD NOT TRAVEL ON ANY MILITARY VEHICLES OR AIRCRAFT. WE EXTEND THIS WARNING TO ALL CIVILIANS AND GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS.

DEV-MUC3-1153 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 6 MAR 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] MILITARY SOURCES REPORTED TODAY THAT FIGHTING BROKE OUT ON THE NIGHT OF 5 MARCH IN THE WAR-TORN CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT TO THE NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR, WHERE THE GUERRILLAS SUFFERED EIGHT CASUALTIES.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE REPORTED THAT THE CLASHES TOOK PLACE NEAR SAN ISIDRO LABRADOR, WHERE THREE GUERRILLAS WERE KILLED AND FIVE OTHERS WERE WOUNDED.

THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN), WHICH HAS BEEN FIGHTING THE U.S.-BACKED ARMY FOR THE LAST 10 YEARS, HAS TRADITIONALLY MAINTAINED A HIGH PROFILE IN STRATEGIC AREAS OF CHALATENANGO.

MEANWHILE, URBAN GUERRILLA COMMANDOS HARASSED TROOPS BELONGING TO THE 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE LAST NIGHT AT THE MARIONA PENITENTIARY, LOCATED ON THE NORTHERN OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR, APPARENTLY LEAVING NO CASUALTIES.

ATLACATL BATTALION TROOPS, WHICH MAINTAIN A COUNTERINSURGENCY OPERATION AT THE FOOTHILLS OF GUAZAPA HILL, TO THE NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR, CONFISCATED WAR MATERIEL THAT THE GUERRILLAS HAD HIDDEN UNDERGROUND.

IN ANOTHER TURN OF EVENTS, FMLN SAPPERS WHO CONTINUOUSLY SABOTAGE THE ELECTRICAL POWER SYSTEM DESTROYED SEVERAL HIGH-VOLTAGE POSTS IN LA LIBERTAD AND CABANAS DEPARTMENTS IN THE CENTRAL PART OF THE COUNTRY, AND IN USULUTAN DEPARTMENT IN THE SOUTHEASTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY.

THERE WERE WIDESPREAD POWER OUTAGES IN THE THREE DEPARTMENTS WHILE TECHNICIANS OF THE STATE-RUN ELECTRIC POWER COMPANIES REPAIRED THE DAMAGE.

THE ARMY AND SECURITY CORPS DEPLOYED HEAVY PATROLS IN SAN SALVADOR AND IN CITIES IN THE COUNTRY'S INTERIOR TO TRY AND COUNTER THE WAVE OF ATTACKS.

DEV-MUC3-1154 (SYNCHRONETICS)

GUATEMALA CITY, 6 MAR 90 (TELEONCE TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] NOW, JUST LIKE 13 YEARS AGO WHEN A DEMOCRATIC ADMINISTRATION WAS INSTALLED IN THE WHITE HOUSE, THE RELATIONS BETWEEN GUATEMALA AND THE UNITED STATES ARE PARTICULARLY TENSE, AND TODAY, JUST LIKE THEN, THE REASON FOR THE TENSION IN THEIR BILATERAL RELATIONS IS THE HUMAN RIGHTS SITUATION, BECAUSE, ACCORDING TO THE REPUBLICAN ADMINISTRATION OF GEORGE BUSH, THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENT OF VINICIO CEREZO DOES NOT SEEM TO HAVE ENOUGH POLITICAL WILL TO NEUTRALIZE THE PROBLEMS THAT ARE AFFECTING THE SECURITY OF CITIZENS AND INDIVIDUAL GUARANTEES.

IN MARCH 1977, NEWLY INSTALLED U.S. PRESIDENT JIMMY CARTER DEMANDED THAT THE REGIME HEADED BY GENERAL KJELL LAUGERUD RECTIFY A DOMESTIC POLICY THAT, ACCORDING TO THE WHITE HOUSE, WAS CHARACTERIZED BY REPRESSIVE PRACTICES AGAINST THE OPPOSITION AND PEASANT AND LABOR GROUPS. THE GUATEMALAN AUTHORITIES REACTED BY REJECTING U.S. MILITARY AID. THE SAME POSITION WAS ADOPTED, AMID VERY SIMILAR CIRCUMSTANCES, BY THE MILITARY GOVERNMENTS OF JORGE VIDELA IN ARGENTINA AND AUGUSTO PINOCHET IN CHILE.

RELATIONS BETWEEN GUATEMALA AND WASHINGTON CONTINUED TO BE TORTUOUS DURING THE BALANCE OF THE CARTER ADMINISTRATION AND ONLY IMPROVED, RELATIVELY SPEAKING, WHEN REPUBLICAN RONALD REAGAN TOOK OFFICE IN 1981. HOWEVER, ONLY YEARS LATER -- WITH THE COMMITMENT TO DEMOCRATIZATION BY DE FACTO MILITARY GOVERNMENTS THAT LED THE COUNTRY FROM 1982 AND 1985 -- WAS THERE A CONCILIATORY ATTITUDE BETWEEN GUATEMALA AND THE UNITED STATES THAT BROUGHT ABOUT QUITE HARMONIOUS RELATIONS BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENTS OF PRESIDENT CEREZO AND PRESIDENTS REAGAN AND BUSH UNTIL MID-1989.

ON 27 FEBRUARY U.S. AMBASSADOR THOMAS STROOK CRITICIZED THE GUATEMALAN AUTHORITIES' FAILURE TO PURSUE THE AUTHORS OF MURDERS AND OF KIDNAPPINGS OF POLITICAL, STUDENT, AND LABOR LEADERS, AND THUS WORSENED AN ATMOSPHERE OF CONFRONTATION THAT HAD RESURFACED ABOUT SIX MONTHS AGO WHEN AMBASSADOR STROOK, WHO HAD JUST ARRIVED IN GUATEMALA, OBJECTED TO THE APPOINTMENT OF COLONEL HUGO MORAN CARRANZA, FORMER DIRECTOR OF ADMINISTRATIVE CONTROL, TO THE POST OF MANAGER OF THE SANTO TOMAS DE CASTILLA PORT ENTERPRISE. THE AMBASSADOR JUSTIFIED HIS OBJECTION BY CLAIMING THAT ASPECTS RELATED TO INTERNATIONAL DRUG TRAFFICKING HAD TO BE RESOLVED FIRST.

ON 6 MARCH, PRESIDENT CEREZO SAID THAT THE UNITED STATES HAD HARDENED ITS ATTITUDE TOWARD THE GUATEMALAN REGIME AND THAT THIS ATTITUDE CONTRASTS WITH A TOLERANT POSTURE EXHIBITED TOWARD PREVIOUS ADMINISTRATIONS IN GUATEMALA:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [CEREZO] THEY HAVE HARSHLY CRITICIZED THE COURTS SITUATION. THE SUPREME COURT OF JUSTICE [WORDS INDISTINCT] AND AS A RESULT OF THE UN ACTION A DRAFT PROCEDURAL LAW WILL BE SUBMITTED. THIS SHOULD BE APPROVED AND PROCEEDINGS SHOULD IMPROVE IN GUATEMALA IN ABOUT [WORD INDISTINCT] YEARS.

HOWEVER, WE ARE DEALING WITH LONG-TERM EFFORT. WE HAVE MADE INSTITUTIONAL CHANGES FOR ONLY FOUR YEARS. I SINCERELY BELIEVE THAT THE U.S. ATTITUDE TOWARD A COUNTRY THAT IS MAKING EFFORTS TO MOVE FORWARD IS UNFAIR AND OVERLY CRITICAL. IT IS BEING MORE CRITICAL OF THE CURRENT GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT THAN IT EVER WAS TOWARD PAST DICTATORSHIPS. THE UNITED STATES HAS BEEN CONSIDERABLY HARSHER IN CRITICIZING THE CURRENT GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT [WORDS INDISTINCT] DEMOCRACY THAN PAST DICTATORIAL GOVERNMENTS, TO WHICH THE UNITED STATES, IN CERTAIN CASES, WAS AN ACCOMPLICE BY SAYING NOTHING [WORDS INDISTINCT]. [END RECORDING]

ONLY HOURS AFTER THE PRESIDENT MADE THESE STATEMENTS, THE U.S. EMBASSY IN GUATEMALA ISSUED A COMMUNIQUE STATING THAT IF THE UNITED STATES ABSTAINED FROM VOICING ITS CONCERN OVER HUMAN RIGHTS ABUSES, IT WOULD INDEED BE ACTING AS AN ACCOMPLICE. THE COMMUNIQUE CITES STATEMENTS MADE ON 5 MARCH IN WASHINGTON BY STATE DEPARTMENT SPOKESWOMAN MARGARET TUTWILLER THAT U.S. AMBASSADOR STROOK, IN HIS CAPACITY AS PRESIDENT BUSH'S PERSONAL REPRESENTATIVE, HAS ON MANY OCCASIONS TOLD TOP GUATEMALAN OFFICIALS, IN PUBLIC AND PRIVATE, THAT THOSE WHO COMMIT VIOLENT ACTS MUST BE TURNED OVER TO JUSTICE.

STROOK IS CURRENTLY IN WASHINGTON WHERE HE WAS RECALLED BY THE STATE DEPARTMENT FOR CONSULTATIONS. ACCORDING TO THE DIPLOMATIC MISSION, THE AMBASSADOR'S STATEMENTS ACCURATELY REFLECT THE PERMANENT U.S. POSITION OF CONSIDERING HUMAN RIGHTS AS AN ISSUE THAT MUST BE TREATED AT AN INTERNATIONAL LEVEL. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1155 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SANTIAGO, 6 MAR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] CHILEAN PRESIDENT-ELECT PATRICIO AYLWIN TODAY CONDITIONED THE REESTABLISHMENT OF DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH CUBA TO THAT COUNTRY'S SUSPENSION OF ITS MILITARY, POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC SUPPORT TO CHILE'S MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT (FPMR) TERRORIST GROUP. IN REMARKS TO EFE, AYLWIN EXPRESSED HIS SATISFACTION OVER THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENT'S DECISION TO ATTEND THE CHILEAN PRESIDENTIAL INAUGURATION ON 11 MARCH. HE ALSO NOTED THAT LA PAZ MUST FIRST RESTORE DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH CHILE TO HOLD TALKS ON BOLIVIA'S DESIRE FOR AN OUTLET TO THE SEA.

AYLWIN STATED THAT CUBA'S SUSPENSION OF ITS SUPPORT TO THE FPMR IS "A SINE QUA NON CONDITION" FOR RESUMING RELATIONS, WHICH WERE SEVERED IN 1973 IMMEDIATELY AFTER THE MILITARY COUP IN CHILE. "WE WANT TO MAINTAIN RELATIONS WITH EVERY COUNTRY," THE CHILEAN PRESIDENT-ELECT TOLD EFE. HE ADDED: "IT WOULD BE VERY GOOD FOR LATIN AMERICA IF CUBA COULD EFFECTIVELY REJOIN US AT THIS TIME (...) IN WHICH, FOR THE FIRST TIME IN MANY YEARS, PERHAPS IN DECADES, THERE WILL BE DEMOCRATIC GOVERNMENTS THROUGHOUT THE CONTINENT."

AYLWIN ADDED: "WE HAVE THE RIGHT TO ASK CUBA TO MAKE IT QUITE CLEAR THAT IT WILL REFRAIN FROM ANY ACT OF INTERFERENCE AND FROM SUPPLYING ANY AID TO CHILEAN TERRORIST GROUPS."

THE FPMR, WHICH EMERGED IN DECEMBER 1983, IS MADE UP OF MILITANTS FROM COMMUNIST YOUTH GROUPS AND OTHER EXTREME LEFT ORGANIZATIONS AND YOUNG EXILES WHO HAVE RETURNED TO THE COUNTRY. THE FPMR MADE HEADLINES IN AUGUST 1986 WITH THE DISCOVERY OF AN ARSENAL THAT HAD BEEN CLANDESTINELY SHIPPED INTO NORTHERN CHILE. THE FPMR WAS ALSO IN THE NEWS WITH THE UNSUCCESSFUL 7 SEPTEMBER 1986 ATTACK ON CHILE'S CHIEF EXECUTIVE, GENERAL AUGUSTO PINOCHET, WHICH CLAIMED THE LIVES OF FIVE OF PINOCHET'S BODYGUARDS.

AYLWIN ALSO STATED THAT THE REESTABLISHMENT OF DIPLOMATIC TIES WITH BOLIVIA "IS BLOCKED BY THE BOLIVIAN DECISION TO BREAK RELATIONS WITH OUR COUNTRY." COMMENTING ON BOLIVIA'S ASPIRATION FOR AN OUTLET TO THE SEA, AYLWIN SAID: "WE CANNOT ACCEPT CONDITIONS FOR THE REESTABLISHMENT OF RELATIONS. IF WE HAVE RELATIONS, WE CAN TALK ABOUT ANYTHING AND FIND SOLUTIONS TO ALL OF OUR PROBLEMS." AYLWIN CONTINUED: "IF WE DO NOT MAINTAIN RELATIONS, IT IS VERY DIFFICULT TO HOLD A DIALOGUE."

AYLWIN ALSO COMMENTED ON PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA'S DECISION TO ATTEND THE CHILEAN PRESIDENTIAL INAUGURATION. THIS WILL BE THE FIRST TIME IN MORE THAN 100 YEARS (SINCE THE 1879 WAR OF THE PACIFIC IN WHICH CHILE FOUGHT AGAINST PERU AND BOLIVIA) THAT A PERUVIAN PRESIDENT WILL VISIT CHILE, A GESTURE WITH "HISTORIC SIGNIFICANCE" FOR AYLWIN.

THE LEGACY OF THE CHILEAN-PERUVIAN WAR HAS NOT YET DISAPPEARED DESPITE THE FACT THAT THE TWO COUNTRIES SHARE COMMON INTERESTS AND HAVE MAINTAINED FRIENDLY RELATIONS IN RECENT YEARS. AYLWIN DESCRIBED THE PERUVIAN PRESIDENT'S PLAN TO ATTEND HIS INAUGURATION "AS A GESTURE WHICH, IN ADDITION TO GREATLY HONORING ME, I MUST SEE AS VERY PROMISING FOR RELATIONS BETWEEN OUR TWO COUNTRIES."

[PASSAGE INDISTINCT] COUNTRY IS WILLING TO PARTICIPATE "IN EVERY STAGE." COMMENTING SPECIFICALLY ON THE GROUP OF EIGHT, AYLWIN NOTED THAT THIS GROUP MAY BECOME A LARGER LATIN AMERICAN ORGANIZATION. IN AYLWIN'S OPINION, THE GROUP OF EIGHT -- WHICH IS MADE UP OF ARGENTINA, BRAZIL, COLOMBIA, MEXICO, PERU, URUGUAY, VENEZUELA, AND PANAMA (WHICH IS CURRENTLY EXCLUDED BECAUSE OF ITS DOMESTIC POLITICAL SITUATION) -- EMERGED PRIMARILY TO SUPPORT DEMOCRATIC MOVEMENTS IN SOME LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES.

NOW THAT DEMOCRACY HAS SPREAD TO VIRTUALLY ALL LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES, THE GROUP OF EIGHT COULD BECOME "THE SEED FOR A BROADER ORGANIZATION, BECAUSE THE REASONS THAT PREVENTED OTHER COUNTRIES FROM JOINING HAVE GRADUALLY DISAPPEARED."

DEV-MUC3-1157 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 8 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [TEXT] HERE IS AN EXCERPT OF WHAT AN OFFICIAL REPORT BY THE GOVERNMENT AND THE NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE, ARENA, REGARD AS A COMPLETELY RECKLESS PUBLICATION AND WITHOUT ANY CREDIBILITY.

THE COMMUNIQUE IS BY THE SO-CALLED DEATH SQUADS, AND AN EXCERPT OF IT RELEASED A FEW HOURS AGO THROUGH VARIOUS LOCAL AND FOREIGN MEDIA READS AS FOLLOWS:

TO THE NEWS MEDIA, POLITICAL PARTIES, THE CATHOLIC CHURCH, UNIONS, WORKERS, PEASANT ORGANIZATIONS, AND DIPLOMATIC MISSIONS: THE UNDERSIGNED, SUPREME COMMANDERS OF THE DEATH SQUADS WHO MET ON 13 FEBRUARY SOMEWHERE IN SAN SALVADOR IN AN EXTRAORDINARY ASSEMBLY AND WHO REPRESENT ALL OUR CHAPTERS AND CADRES SCATTERED IN THE COUNTRY'S 14 DEPARTMENTS, STRONGLY AND MANFULLLY DECLARE: SENTENCE UNFINISHED AS HEARD

THE DOCUMENT, WITH PARAGRAPHS HIGHLIGHTED BY THE AUTHORS, STATES THAT THE OFFICERS AND ENLISTED MEN INVOLVED IN THE JESUITS' MURDERS MUST BE RELEASED BEFORE HOLY WEEK, OR ELSE THEY WILL PHYSICALLY ELIMINATE ALL CIVILIAN AND RELIGIOUS PERSONNEL, INSIDE AND OUTSIDE THE GOVERNMENT, WHO HAVE ANYTHING TO DO WITH THIS CASE.

THE COMMUNIQUE NOTES: NEVER BEFORE IN THE HISTORY OF EL SALVADOR HAS ANY OFFICER BEEN TRIED, AND AS WE HAVE LEARNED, NO SOLDIER HAS BEEN, AND MUST NOT BE, SUBJECT TO ANY LAW OF THE REPUBLIC. IT ADDS: KEEP IN MIND, LEST WE BEGIN TO CARRY OUT REPRISALS, THAT THROUGHOUT OUR HISTORY WE HAVE ALWAYS GONE UNPUNISHED, A PRIVILEGE THAT WE ARE NOT READY TO LOSE.

A STATEMENT BY THE GOVERNMENT AND ARENA, WHICH ARE MENTIONED IN THE COMMUNIQUE, TOTALLY REJECTED THE DOCUMENT THAT, WE REPEAT, WAS DISTRIBUTED IN SAN SALVADOR A FEW HOURS AGO. IN A WARNING TO THE NEWS MEDIA, THE AUTHORS SAY THAT THE MEDIA ARE OBLIGATED TO MAKE THIS COMMUNIQUE KNOWN, OR ELSE THEIR INSTALLATIONS AND STAFF WILL SUFFER THE CONSEQUENCES OF THEIR DISOBEDIENCE. THE AUTHORS OF THE COMMUNIQUE ALSO REFER TO A NEWSPAPER THAT THEY REGARD AS THEIR OFFICIAL MOUTHPIECE, AND THEY WARN THAT, FOR THE GOOD AND SECURITY OF THE COUNTRY AND THE FATHERLAND, THIS NEWSPAPER MUST BE CLEARER IN IDENTIFYING PEOPLE AND FIGURES WHO HAVE ALREADY BEEN JUDGED AND CONDEMNED IN ORDER TO CAPTURE AND DESTROY THEM.

MEANWHILE, TERMING THE COMMUNIQUE AS RECKLESS AND THE ENTIRE SITUATION AS DESPICABLE, THE GOVERNMENT AND ARENA REJECT ANY TIES TO ANY DEATH SQUADS.

THE COMMUNIQUE BY THE SELF-STYLED DEATH SQUADS IS SIGNED BY AQUILES BAIRES [LEADER OF THE SECRET ANTICOMMUNIST ARMY], THE MAXIMILIANO HERNANDEZ MARTINEZ SQUAD [ESCUADRON MAXIMILIANIO HERNANDEZ MARTINEZ], THE ALLIANCE OF ANTICOMMUNIST ACTION [ALIANZA DE ACCION ANTICOMUNISTA], AND THE COMMITTEE FOR THE SALVATION OF THE FATHERLAND COMITE PRO SALVACION DE LA PATRIA. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1158 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 8 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA YSU) -- [TEXT] GOOD EVENING, LISTENERS. IN ORDER TO BRING CALM TO ALL SAN SALVADOR RESIDENTS, AND ALSO TO PEOPLE LIVING IN THE INTERIOR OF THE COUNTRY, WE INFORM YOU THAT A FEW MINUTES AGO, EXPERTS OF THE ELECTRIC LIGHT COMPANY OF EL SALVADOR, CAES, CONFIRMED THAT DESPITE A FEW ATTACKS ON SOME POWER TOWERS, ENERGY SERVICE IS COMPLETELY NORMAL THROUGHOUT SAN SALVADOR. THE CAES EXPERTS ADDED THAT THERE WAS A SHORT POWER OUTAGE IN LARGE PARTS OF SAN SALVADOR, BUT THAT THE SITUATION IS BACK TO NORMAL NOW. THE EXPERTS SAID THAT THEY ALSO DETECTED SOME DAMAGE IN THE ENERGY SYSTEM.

AS YOU MAY HAVE HEARD ON THIS RADIO STATION EARLIER, HARASSMENT OPERATIONS WERE CARRIED OUT IN SEVERAL PARTS OF SAN SALVADOR AT APPROXIMATELY 2115 TONIGHT.

FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] LEFTIST GUERRILLAS ATTACKED MILITARY POSITIONS IN SAN RAMON, AYUTUXTEPEQUE, MEJICANOS, AND CUSCATANCINGO TONIGHT. IT WAS SAID THAT A NUMBER OF FMLN MEMBERS CONDUCTED LIGHTNING ATTACKS ON THOSE MILITARY POSITIONS AND THEN WITHDREW FROM THE AREA IMMEDIATELY.

IT WAS REPORTED THAT THE ATTACK IN SAN RAMON LASTED APPROXIMATELY 15 MINUTES, AFTER WHICH THE ARMY TOOK CONTROL OF THAT ENTIRE AREA. REPORTS STATE THAT AFTER THE ATTACK IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE THE GUERRILLAS MOVED TOWARD EL CARMEN HILL AND COUNTERINSURGENCY BATTALION MEMBERS WERE PURSUING THE REBEL COLUMNS THERE. IT WAS ALSO REPORTED THAT THE REBELS ATTACKED MILITARY POSITIONS IN CUSCATANCINGO AND ON EL FITO STREET, MEJICANOS JURISDICTION.

A FEW MINUTES AGO IT WAS REPORTED THAT THE SHOOTING ENDED IN AYUTUXTEPEQUE AND IN THE OTHER PARTS OF NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR, AND THAT AN AIR FORCE HELICOPTER IS OVERFLYING THE AREA TO COUNTERACT THE REBELS' MOVEMENT.

IT WAS ALSO CONFIRMED THAT ENERGY HAS BEEN RESTORED IN SOME PARTS OF SAN SALVADOR, BUT NOT IN CUSCATANCINGO AND CIUDAD DELGADO, WHERE THE GUERRILLAS BLEW UP SEVERAL POWER TOWERS.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE [COPREFA] HAS ONLY STATED THAT NO CASUALTIES ARE REPORTED AS A RESULT OF THESE HARASSMENT OPERATIONS, ESPECIALLY IN THE AREA OF AYUTUXTEPEQUE. COPREFA INDICATED THAT 1ST INFANTRY BRIGADE MEMBERS HAVE ALREADY TAKEN STRATEGIC POSITIONS THROUGHOUT NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR AND THAT THESE MEN ARE SUPPORTED BY SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTERS, WHICH ARE LIGHTING THE AREA WITH SPOTLIGHTS AND FLARES.

ACCORDING TO THE OFFICIAL REPORT, THE SITUATION AT THIS TIME IS COMPLETELY NORMAL IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR, DESPITE THE PANIC THAT SPREAD AT APPROXIMATELY 2115 WHEN HEAVY SHOOTING, MACHINEGUN FIRE, AND THE DETONATION OF POWERFUL BOMBS WERE HEARD.

NEITHER COPREFA NOR THE SPECIFIC MILITARY POSITIONS THAT WERE ATTACKED HAVE REPORTED CASUALTIES SO FAR. IT WAS SAID THAT TOMORROW MORNING COPREFA WILL ISSUE AN OVERALL REPORT ON THE RESULTS OF THESE CLASHES. SALVADORAN RED CROSS SOURCES SAID TONIGHT THAT THEY DO NOT KNOW OF ANY CIVILIAN CASUALTY RESULTING FROM THESE ARMED INCIDENTS.

THIS HAS BEEN A REPORT ON THE ATTACKS CARRIED OUT IN NORTHERN SAN SALVADOR TONIGHT. WE INVITE YOU TO JOIN US TOMORROW FOR A REPORT ON THE DEVELOPMENT OF EVENTS.

DEV-MUC3-1159 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 8 MAR 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI HAS ACCUSED THE GUERRILLAS OF MAINTAINING "INFLEXIBLE STANDS" REGARDING RESUMING THE DIALOGUE THAT WILL ALLOW ENDING THE 10-YEAR-OLD ARMED CONFLICT.

IN AN OFFICIAL STATEMENT TODAY, PRESIDENT CRISTIANI SAID THAT "THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) DOES NOT WANT TO LISTEN TO THE CRIES OF THE PEOPLE WHO ARE REJECTING VIOLENCE."

FOR CRISTIANI, THE FMLN "IS THE ONLY PARTY RESPONSIBLE FOR THE TERRORIST ACTIONS, AS IT MAINTAINS INFLEXIBLE STANDS" ABOUT THE PEACE PROCESS.

THE REBELS, WHO ROSE UP IN ARMS 10 YEARS AGO, RECENTLY SAID THAT AS LONG AS THERE IS NO TRUE ATTEMPT TO BRING ABOUT A DEMOCRATIZATION, ITS ARMED STRUGGLE "CONTINUES BEING AS LEGITIMATE AS IT WAS 10 YEARS AGO."

FOLLOWING THE NOVEMBER 1989 OFFENSIVE, THE CRISTIANI GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN ASKED UN SECRETARY GENERAL JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR TO INTERCEDE AND SEEK AN AGREEMENT THAT WILL BRING ABOUT THE PEACE TALKS.

HEEDING THIS REQUEST, PEREZ DE CUELLAR APPOINTED DIPLOMAT ALVARO DE SOTO AS HIS PERSONAL REPRESENTATIVE. AS OF LAST DECEMBER, DE SOTO HAS BEEN MEETING WITH BOTH PARTIES, THE CHURCH, AND SALVADORAN POLITICAL SECTORS.

THE CRISTIANI STATEMENT TERMS AS "FALSE" THE CHARGES RAISED BY THE FMLN TO THE EFFECT THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS RESPONSIBLE FOR HINDERING THE RESUMPTION OF THE PEACE EFFORTS.

"PRESIDENT CRISTIANI HAS REITERATED TO MR. DE SOTO A TRUE WILLINGNESS TO SEEK THROUGH A SERIOUS DIALOGUE AND NOT A TACTICAL OR MUCH LESS PROPAGANDISTIC DIALOGUE THE SOLUTION TO THE ARMED CONFLICT," THE DOCUMENT POINTS OUT.

THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT THANKED DE SOTO'S "INTEREST AND HARD WORK" IN COMPLYING WITH THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL'S COMMITMENT OF SEEKING PEACE IN THE COUNTRY.

DEV-MUC3-1162 (SYNCHRONETICS)

NO CITY, NO DATE (FBIS) -- [TEXT]

COLOMBIA: DRUG KINGPINS SOLE MEMBERS OF 'EXTRADITABLES'

THE 22 JANUARY EDITION OF THE BOGOTA DAILY EL TIEMPO PUBLISHED INFORMATION FROM COLOMBIAN POLICE INTELLIGENCE REPORTS AND STATE SECURITY INTERCEPTS IDENTIFYING DRUG KINGPINS PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA AND JORGE LUIS OCHOA VASQUE AS THE ONLY MEMBERS OF THE SO-CALLED "EXTRADITABLES." THIS PRESS NOTE PROVIDES HIGHLIGHTS OF THE 22 JANUARY ARTICLE.

DRUG BARONS PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA AND JORGE LUIS OCHOA VASQUE, WHO ARE REPUTED TO BE THE BRAINS BEHIND THE MEDELLIN CARTEL'S PLAN TO SURRENDER TO THE GOVERNMENT, HAVE BEEN IDENTIFIED BY THE NATIONAL POLICE AND STATE SECURITY AS THE ONLY ONES RESPONSIBLE FOR THE COMMUNIQUES SENT BY THE SO-CALLED "EXTRADITABLES," ACCORDING TO THE EL TIEMPO ARTICLE.

STATE SECURITY RECOGNI ED ESCOBAR'S VOICE IN A CONVERSATION INTERCEPTED DURING A ROUTINE RADIO SCANNING OPERATION, WHICH REVEALED THAT THE CARTEL WAS PLANNING TO SURRENDER TO THE GOVERNMENT. ESCOBAR WAS ACTING AS THE CARTEL'S INTERMEDIARY IN CHARGE OF CONTACTING LAWYER GUIDO PARRA, THE LIAISON BETWEEN THE CARTEL AND HIGH LEVEL GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS. ESCOBAR DID NOT DISCLOSE THE NAMES OF THE OFFICIALS INVOLVED.

A NATIONAL POLICE INTELLIGENCE REPORT SAYS THAT OCHOA AND ESCOBAR FIND THEMSELVES IN A PRECARIOUS SITUATION BECAUSE OTHER TRAFFICKER GROUPS HAVE WITHDRAWN THEIR SUPPORT AS THEY DO NOT WANT TO BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE FOR KIDNAPPINGS AND OTHER TERRORIST ACTS THEY HAVE NOT PERPETRATED. THE REPORT FURTHER INDICATES THAT ESCOBAR, PRESSURED BY MILITARY OPERATIONS IN ANTIOQUIA, "WAS FORCED TO ORDER THE KIDNAPPINGS OF ALVARO DIEGO MONTOYA, (SON OF THE SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE PRESIDENCY) AND PATRICIA ECHEVARRIA (SISTER OF PRESIDENT BARCO'S SON-IN-LAW) AND HER DAUGHTER." THESE HIGH PROFILE HOSTAGES SERVED AS A "PROTECTIVE SHIELD," ACCORDING TO THE ARTICLE.

SPOKESMEN FOR THE INTELLIGENCE CORPS ARE QUOTED AS SAYING THAT ESCOBAR KNEW THAT BY TAKING HOSTAGE THE SON OF THE SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE PRESIDENCY, HE COULD SUCCESSFULLY EXERT THE PRESSURE HE NEEDED TO ACT IN THE NAME OF THE "EXTRADITABLES." PROBLEMS BEGAN TO SURFACE SOON AFTER THE CARTEL'S SURRENDER, AS MEMBERS AT ODDS WITH ESCOBAR STARTED TO BREAK AWAY FROM THE GROUP. ACCORDING TO MEDELLIN OFFICIALS, THE KIDNAPPINGS OF MONTOYA AND ECHEVARRIA ALSO HAD AN IMPACT ON THE RATE OF ATTRITION AMONG THE "EXTRADITABLES.

THE CARTEL'S SURRENDER IS NOT SEEN AS A SURPRISE: THE 4TH ARMY BRIGADE WAS CONDUCTING AN EXHAUSTIVE SEARCH OF THE ANTIOQUIA DEPARTMENT IN AN EFFORT TO BRING THE KINGPINS TO JUSTICE. MOREOVER, THE ARMY LAUNCHED A PUBLICITY CAMPAIGN AMONG THE LOCALS TO ENCOURAGE THEM TO INFORM AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS. FOLLOWING THE DEATH OF JOSE GON ALO RODRIGUE GACHA, ESCOBAR AND OCHOA WERE CONSTANTLY ON THE MOVE.

A SPOKESMAN FOR STATE SECURITY STATES THAT SOPHISTICATED COMMUNICATIONS EQUIPMENT IN MEDELLIN ENABLED THEM TO LEARN ABOUT ESCOBAR'S INTENTIONS ALMOST ON A DAILY BASIS. IT WAS DIFFICULT TO ESTABLISH THEIR EXACT WHEREABOUTS, HOWEVER, BECAUSE THEY NEVER REMAINED IN ONE PLACE FOR MORE THAN SIX HOURS AT A TIME. THE TWO DRUG BARONS ALWAYS TRAVELED WITH AN ESCORT OF SIX TO EIGHT MEN WHOM THEY TRUSTED IMPLICITLY.

ACCORDING TO A HIGH-RANKING MILITARY OFFICIAL, "WHEN ESCOBAR BEGAN LOSING POWER IN MEDELLIN, HIS CLOSEST AIDES, FEARING PERSECUTION, WENT INTO HIDING." HE ADDS THAT ESCOBAR AND OCHOA TOOK ON THE CAUSE OF TRAFFICKERS WANTED BY THE UNITED STATES, BUT NOTES, "WE ARE WELL AWARE OF THE FACT THAT THE CALI CARTEL MEN DO THINGS DIFFERENTLY."

THE EL TIEMPO ARTICLE NOTES THAT ON 19 JANUARY SEVERAL LEADING COLOMBIAN NEWSPAPERS CIRCULATED A NOTICE POINTING TO ESCOBAR AS THE MAN WHO ACTS IN THE NAME OF THE "EXTRADITABLES." LATER, IT WAS CONFIRMED THAT THE AUTHORSHIP OF THE NOTICE WAS ATTRIBUTED TO A DEMENTED PERSON WHOSE NAME HAD CLEARLY BEEN USED. EL TIEMPO ASKS:. "COULD THIS BE A MESSAGE FROM OTHER DRUG TRAFFICKERS WHO ARE UNWILLING TO PAY FOR PABLO ESCOBAR'S ACTIONS? COULD IT BE A MESSAGE FROM THESE SAME TRAFFICKERS WHO DO NOT WANT TO GIVE UP THIS BUSINESS AND THEREFORE ARE UNWILLING TO HAVE ESCOBAR AND OCHOA SPEAK FOR THEM?"

DEV-MUC3-1163 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SANTIAGO, 9 MAR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] ADMIRAL JOSE TORIBIO MERINO, FORMER COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF THE CHILEAN NAVY, TODAY HARSHLY ATTACKED PERUVIAN PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA AND NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA.

ASKED ABOUT THE FACT THAT ONLY THREE OUT OF 11 PRESIDENTS WHO WILL BE IN CHILE FOR AYLWIN'S INAUGURATION WILL SALUTE CURRENT PRESIDENT GENERAL AUGUSTO PINOCHET ON SATURDAY, MERINO SAID: "WE HAVE ALL KINDS OF THEM. I WILL NOT SHAKE HANDS WITH THAT MAN GARCIA FROM PERU. HE IS FILTHY [MUGRIENTO]." THE ADMIRAL CONTINUED: "NEITHER WILL I SHAKE HANDS WITH A GRIMY PERSON WHO HAS KILLED ANY NUMBER OF PATRIOTS AND WHO IS CREATING TROUBLE FOR THAT LADY...WHAT IS HER NAME?...CHAMORRO." MERINO WAS REFERRING TO ORTEGA, WHO WILL ARRIVE IN SANTIAGO ON SUNDAY.

MERINO, WHO RETIRED AFTER 16 YEARS AS NAVY COMMANDER IN CHIEF, MADE THESE REMARKS AFTER A GOVERNMENT JUNTA FAREWELL SESSION. THE GOVERNMENT JUNTA HAS FUNCTIONED AS A LEGISLATIVE BRANCH SINCE 1973.

MERINO SAID: "SOME PEOPLE WHO DO NOT WANT TO SHAKE THE PRESIDENT'S HAND COME FROM WRETCHED COUNTRIES WHERE PEOPLE ARE DYING OF HUNGER, COUNTRIES EXPERIENCING DESPERATE INFLATION AND ECONOMIC SITUATIONS. THEY ARE PROPERLY REPRESENTED [SON UNOS PUEBLOS TALES POR CUALES]."

MERINO AND PINOCHET ARE THE ONLY MILITARY OFFICERS WHO HAVE REMAINED IN POWER SINCE THE 11 SEPTEMBER 1973 COUP.

DEV-MUC3-1165 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, 11 MAR 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] CESAR GAVIRIA TRUJILLO, A 43-YEAR-OLD ECONOMIST, BECAME THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE OF THE RULING COLOMBIAN LIBERAL PARTY TODAY BY A WIDE MARGIN OF 60 PERCENT IN THE "POPULAR CONSULTATION," AN ELECTION HELD AT THE SAME TIME AS THE LEGISLATIVE AND MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS, THE RADIO STATION NETWORK CARACOL REPORTED TODAY. THE RESULTS WERE REPORTED ONLY A FEW MINUTES AFTER THE ELECTIONS ENDED AT 1600 (2100 GMT) IN A RELATIVELY CALM CLIMATE.

SIMULTANEOUSLY, A PRIVATE POLLING CONCERN THAT CONDUCTED A SURVEY IN NEARLY 90 PERCENT OF THE COUNTRY'S VOTING PRECINCTS ANNOUNCED THAT LIBERAL PARTY CANDIDATE JUAN MARTIN CAICEDO WAS ELECTED THE NEW MAYOR OF BOGOTA AND ANOTHER LIBERAL PARTY MEMBER, OMAR FLOREZ VELEZ, WILL BECOME THE MAYOR OF MEDELLIN, COLOMBIA'S SECOND LARGEST CITY.

THE FIRST RESULTS, WHICH ARE NOT OFFICIAL, WERE RELEASED BY THE ELECTRONIC MEDIA AFTER THE GOVERNMENT FOR THE FIRST TIME IN COLOMBIA'S HISTORY GAVE THEM PERMISSION TO ANNOUNCE ELECTION FIGURES BEFORE THE OFFICIAL ANNOUNCEMENTS OF THE CIVIL REGISTRATION OFFICE, THE STATE AGENCY IN CHARGE OF COUNTING HE VOTES.

ACCORDING TO THE REPORT, GAVIRIA LED HIS OPPONENTS BY A WIDE MARGIN. ERNESTO SAMPER PIZANO RECEIVED 18 PERCENT, HERNANDO DURAN DUSSAN, 15 PERCENT; ALBERTO SANTOFIMIO BOTERO, FOUR PERCENT; WILLIAM JARAMILLO GOMEZ, TWO PERCENT; AND JAIME CASTRO CASTRO, ONE PERCENT.

GAVIRIA, WHO WAS ALWAYS A FAVORITE IN THE POLLS, REPLACED SENATOR LUIS CARLOS GALAN AS THE LIBERAL PARTY'S PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE. GALAN WAS ASSASSINATED BY THE CRIMINAL DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFIAS LAST YEAR.

DEV-MUC3-1166 (SYNCHRONETICS)

MOSCOW (USSR), 11 MAR 11 (TASS) -- [ARTICLE] [GENNADIY PETROV] [TEXT] AFTER STAYING IN POWER FOR 16 YEARS, GENERAL AUGUSTO PINOCHET WAS FINALLY COMPELLED TO LEAVE THE LA MONEDA PRESIDENTIAL PALACE, WHICH HE CAPTURED DURING THE MILITARY COUP OF SEPTEMBER 11, 1973.

LAWYER PATRICIO AYLWIN, 71, LEADER OF THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY, BECAME ITS NEW MASTER TODAY. HE SCORED A SWEEPING VICTORY DURING DECEMBER'S GENERAL ELECTIONS WITH THE SUPPORT OF ALL THE OPPOSITION PARTIES, INCLUDING COMMUNISTS.

THE RESTORATION OF DEMOCRACY IN CHILE WILL BY NO MEANS BE EASY. BOMB EXPLOSIONS SHOOK THE CAPITAL ON THE EVE OF THE INAUGURATION CEREMONY AS MILITANTS REMINDED THE PUBLIC OF THEIR PRESENCE.

ACCORDING TO AYLWIN, IT IS IMPORTANT FOR THE GOVERNMENT TO OVERCOME THE DEEP POLITICAL DIVISION OF CHILEAN SOCIETY. "ONLY THIS," AYLWIN BELIEVES, "WILL ALLOW CHILE TO DO AWAY WITH VESTIGES OF THE TOTALITARIAN SYSTEM AND EVENTUALLY EXPAND PARLIAMENT'S POWERS, TO AMEND THE CONSTITUTION AND THE UNFAIR ELECTORAL SYSTEM AND TO LEGALISE BANNED PARTIES.

ANALYSTS BELIEVE THE REVIVAL OF CHILE, WHICH HAS LONG-STANDING DEMOCRATIC TRADITIONS, WILL BE HELD BACK BY THE FACT THAT, ACCORDING TO THE CONSTITUTION IN FORCE, PINOCHET WILL REMAIN COMMANDER-IN- CHIEF OF THE GROUND FORCES FOR EIGHT MORE YEARS. THIS SUBSTANTIALLY CURTAILS THE PRESIDENT'S RIGHTS AS SUPREME COMMANDER OF THE COUNTRY'S ARMED FORCES. FURTHERMORE, BEFORE STEPPING DOWN, THE FORMER RULER HAS ENSURED HIMSELF AN OBEDIENT MAJORITY IN THE SENATE, THE CHILEAN PARLIAMENT'S UPPER CHAMBER.

IN THE INTERNATIONAL ARENA THE NEW GOVERNMENT WILL HAVE TO OVERCOME THE ISOLATION THAT RESULTED FROM THE YEARS OF DICTATORSHIP, WHEN HUMAN RIGHTS WERE GROSSLY VIOLATED AND THOUSANDS OF FREEDOM FIGHTERS WERE RUTHLESSLY PERSECUTED OR ELIMINATED. THIS TASK IS FACILITATED BY THE FACT THAT RELAXATION PROCESSES ARE GAINING MOMENTUM IN THE WORLD AND EAST-WEST COOPERATION IS ON THE UPSWING.

NUMEROUS FOREIGN GUESTS, INCLUDING A SOVIET DELEGATION, ARRIVED FOR THE INAUGURATION CEREMONY AND THE TRANSFER OF POWER TO A CIVILIAN GOVERNMENT. AN AGREEMENT IS EXPECTED TO BE SIGNED THESE DAYS ON THE RESTORATION OF DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS BETWEEN THE SOVIET UNION AND CHILE AND ON THE OPENING OF THEIR RESPECTIVE EMBASSIES IN MOSCOW AND SANTIAGO.

DEV-MUC3-1168 (SYNCHRONETICS)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), NO DATE (RADIO KW CONTINENTE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH ENDARA BY MONTANER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [ENDARA] THERE WAS NOTHING REMOTELY CLOSE TO A TRIAL HELD, EVEN IF WE HAD THE DEATH PENALTY AS A PUNISHMENT FOR MILITARY CRIMES. THEY WERE ASSASSINS OF THE WORST KIND. THERE WERE OTHER PREVIOUS INCIDENTS, BUT BASICALLY THIS IS THE ACCUSATION.

[MONTANER] OF MAJOR MOISES GIROLDI'S DEATH?

[ENDARA] GIROLDI AND MANY OTHERS. MANY PEOPLE WERE KILLED DURING THOSE DAYS. WE DO NOT EXACTLY KNOW HOW MANY PEOPLE WERE KILLED.

[MONTANER] YOU DO NOT KNOW?

[ENDARA] WE DO NOT KNOW.

[MONTANER] ARE YOU GOING TO LET THEM LEAVE? ARE YOU GOING TO LET THEM ESCAPE TO PERU?

[ENDARA] LOOK, AS A LAWYER I KNOW WHAT LATIN AMERICAN INTERNATIONAL TREATIES SAY -- THOSE THAT HAVE ONLY BEEN SIGNED AND RATIFIED BY THE LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES BECAUSE THE UNITED STATES HAS NOT RATIFIED THEM -- REGARDING THE RIGHT TO ASYLUM. THE HOST COUNTRY DECIDES WHAT CRIME HAS BEEN COMMITTED, NOT THE HOME COUNTRY. THERE ARE RIGHTS ESTABLISHED IN THOSE TREATIES. THE HOME COUNTRY MAY INQUIRE ABOUT THE CHARGES THAT HAVE BEEN FILED AGAINST THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE SOUGHT REFUGE. THE HOME COUNTRY MAY ASK THE HOST COUNTRY NOT TO DETERMINE WHAT CRIMES HAVE BEEN COMMITTED IN EACH CASE. IF THE HOST COUNTRY HAS ALREADY DECIDED ON THE CHARGES, IT MAY BE ASKED BY THE HOME COUNTRY TO RECONSIDER ITS DECISION AND TO PROVIDE EVIDENCE SUPPORTING THOSE CHARGES. WE ARE CURRENTLY EXERCISING THOSE RIGHTS.

WE HOPE PERU DOES NOT INSIST BECAUSE OUR RELATIONS, AS YOU HAVE ALREADY SEEN [CHANGES THOUGHT] THEY ARE NOT ACCEPTING OTHER CASES, WHICH ARE LESS SERIOUS. FOR EXAMPLE, WE HAVE THE CASE OF A MAN LIKE TOTY SUAREZ [PRESIDENT OF THE REVOLUTIONARY PANAMENIST PARTY, PRD]; WE HAVE THE CASE OF GENERAL NORIEGA'S WIFE AND DAUGHTERS; AND A NUMBER OF OTHER CASES WHERE WE CANNOT CALL THESE PEOPLE ASSASINS. WE DID NOT HAVE ANY EVIDENCE AGAINST THEM.

[MONTANER] WHAT ABOUT MANUEL SOLIS PALMA?

[ENDARA] SOLIS PALMA LEFT THE EMBASSY AND NOTHING HAPPENED TO HIM. HIS CASE WAS INTERESTING. HE SOUGHT ASYLUM AND THE VENEZUELAN EMBASSY NEVER, NEVER, OFFICIALLY INFORMED THE PANAMANIAN GOVERNMENT THAT SOLIS PALMA WAS THERE.

[MONTANER] HE WAS THERE AS A GUEST?

[ENDARA] YES. WHEN WE WERE ASKED ABOUT THE FATE OF SOLIS PALMA, WE REPLIED THAT, FOR ALL WE KNEW, HE WAS SPENDING A FEW DAYS WITH THE VENEZUELAN AMBASSADOR. HE HAD EVERY RIGHT TO SLEEP THERE.

[MONTANER] I WILL ASK A FEW MORE QUESTIONS.

[ENDARA] YOU MAY ASK ANYTHING YOU LIKE.

[MONTANER] THERE WERE MANY PEOPLE SAYING THAT THE INVASION WAS A U.S. PRETEXT NOT TO RETURN THE CANAL IN THE YEAR 2000.

[ENDARA] NO, NO. THERE HAS NEVER EVEN BEEN THE SLIGHTEST HINT FROM ANY U.S. GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL, NOT FROM THE STATE DEPARTMENT OR THE ARMY ABOUT THIS. CONGRESSMEN OF ALL IDEOLOGIES HAVE BEEN HERE, EVEN FROM THE EXTREME RIGHT -- I DO NOT THINK THERE ARE ANY EXTREME LEFTIST CONGRESSMEN IN THE UNITED STATES -- AS WELL AS SENATORS. MILITARY OFFICERS HAVE ALSO BEEN HERE. I HAVE HAD LONG TALKS WITH THEM. THEY HAVE NOT EVEN HINTED THAT THEY WANT TO CHANGE THE TREATIES OR THAT THEY WANT TO STAY BEYOND THE YEAR 2000. ALL OF THAT IS NORIEGA'S NONSENSE. NORIEGA WAS THE ONE WHO STARTED THAT CAMPAIGN. THERE HAS NEVER BEEN ANY TALK ABOUT THIS, NOT EVEN ABOUT THE BASES REMAINING BEYOND THE YEAR 2000. THERE HAS BEEN NONE OF THAT AT ALL. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1169 (SYNCHRONETICS)

CLANDESTINE, 16 MAR 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT, FMLN] [TEXT] THE GENERAL COMMAND OF THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] DEEMS AS POSITIVE THE GOVERNMENT'S RECOGNITION OF THE FMLN'S GOOD-WILL GESTURES. HOWEVER, WE VIEW AS A NEGATIVE THAT IN THE GOVERNMENT'S RESPONSE THERE IS NOT A CORRESPONDING ATTITUDE. IN THIS REGARD, WE INFORM:

1. THE GOVERNMENT RESPONSE TRIES TO UNDERMINE OUR GESTURE. THE FMLN HAS NEVER HAD A POLICY TO ATTACK OR HARM THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. OUR GESTURES ARE A CLEAR CONTRIBUTION TO STRENGTHENING THE SPACE OF OTHER POLITICAL AND SOCIAL FORCES TO ALLOW FOR THEIR PARTICIPATION IN THE POLITICAL NEGOTIATION SOLUTION PROCESS AND IN THE EFFORT TO HUMANIZE THE CONFLICT.

2. THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES CONTINUE TO VIOLATE HUMAN RIGHTS, BOMB CIVILIAN POPULATED AREAS, SUBJECT THE COUNTRY TO A PERMANENT STATE OF SIEGE, BE IT LEGAL OR DE FACTO. IN A CONSTANT AND SYSTEMATIC MANNER, THE GOVERNMENT MAINTAINS A POLICY OF CAPTURING AND TORTURING LEADERS OF PEOPLE'S GROUPS; MAINTAINS SIEGES AND RAIDS; HARASSES THE COMMUNITIES OF REPATRIATES; AND SABOTAGES THE PROPERTY OF RESIDENTS IN AREAS UNDER THE FMLN CONTROL.

IN THE MEANTIME, NO STEP HAS BEEN TAKEN TO INVESTIGATE AND PUNISH THE MURDER OF MONSIGNOR ROMERO AND THE MASSACRE OF FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION], WHILE THE TRIAL AGAINST THE MURDERERS OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS HAS STAGNATED AND THE SUSPECTS ARE PROMOTED OR SENT ABROAD.

THE GOVERNMENT INTENDS TO APPOINT AS DEFENSE MINISTER THE PERSON WHO GAVE THE ORDER TO MURDER THE PRIESTS, AND IT ALLOWS THE REPORTED EXECUTIONER TO LIVE IN A LUXURY APARTMENT.

3. WE AGREE WITH THE PERMANENT, SERIOUS, IMPORTANT, AND RESERVED CHARACTER THAT THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS SHOULD HAVE.

4. THE GOVERNMENT IS MORALLY AND POLITICALLY COMPELLED TO IMPLEMENT AS SOON AS POSSIBLE GOODWILL GESTURES THAT WILL PERMIT THE EXERCISE OF CITIZEN'S FREEDOMS AND CEASE THE DAILY HUMAN RIGHTS VIOLATIONS AND ALL FORMS OF AGGRESSION AIMED AT THE CIVILIAN POPULATION.

5. WE WARN THAT IT WOULD BE REGRETTABLE FOR THE PEOPLE'S PEACE AND DEMOCRACY HOPES THAT THE GOVERNMENT AND THE ARMED FORCES TRY TO HARDEN WARMONGERING POSITIONS, BELIEVING IN THE MIRAGE OF AN ALLEGED WEAKNESS OF THE FMLN. OBVIOUSLY, THIS MISTAKE WOULD ONLY LEAD TO A WORSENING OF THE WAR AND WOULD FURTHER DELAY THE POSSIBILITIES OF NEGOTIATIONS, DEMOCRATIZATION, AND PEACE FOR EL SALVADOR.

FMLN GENERAL COMMAND

[SIGNED] COMMANDER SHAFIK JORGE HANDAL, COMMANDER EDUARDO SANCHO, COMMANDER SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, COMMANDER FRANCISCO JOVEL, COMMANDER JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS

[ISSUED IN] EL SALVADOR, 15 MARCH 1990

DEV-MUC3-1170 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, 16 MAR 90 (INRAVISION TELEVISION CADENA 1) -- [REPORT] [SORAYA CAICEDO] [TEXT] PICHINCHA BATTALION TROOPS HAVE SEIZED LETTERS, WHICH WERE GOING TO BE USED FOR EXTORTION, AND LARGE AMOUNTS OF WAR MATERIEL IN CLASHES WITH THE 6TH FARC FRONT IN THE BORDER AREA OF THE DEPARTMENTS OF VALLE DEL CAUCA AND CAUCA. IN THE OPERATIONS THAT TOOK PLACE ON 15 MARCH IN THE JAGUAL AREA IN CORINTO MUNICIPALITY, IN NORTHERN CAUCA, 3RD BRIGADE TROOPS KILLED ALONSO CORTES, CONSIDERED THE FARC'S MOST IMPORTANT LEADER IN THE SOUTHWESTERN PART OF THE COUNTRY. TWO OTHER GUERRILLAS WERE ALSO KILLED.

IN THAT AREA THE PICHINCHA BATTALION TROOPS FOUND A COCAINE PROCESSING LABORATORY AND 35 PACKAGES OF MARIJUANA.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [GENERAL JOSE MANUEL BONNET] WE DEMONSTRATED THAT THE FARC IS INVOLVED IN DRUG TRAFFICKING. AS YOU SAW, THE SEIZURE OF 35 PACKAGES OF MARIJUANA AND OF A COCAINE PROCESSING LABORATORY IN CALOTO, IN THIS SAME OPERATION, SHOWS US THAT WE ARE FACING A SUBVERSIVE GROUP THAT IS ALSO INVOLVED IN THE MARIJUANA BUSINESS ACTIVITY. [END RECORDING]

ON ALONSO CORTES' BODY, THE TROOPS FOUND A LISTING OF PEOPLE WHO WERE SUBJECTED TO [1-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] NOTING THE AMOUNT OF MONEY THAT THEY WERE SUPPOSED TO GIVE TO THE FARC. THEY ALSO FOUND A LETTER THAT CORTES NEVER SENT FOR A [7-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] FOR HAVING IMPLICATED THE M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT]. IN THIS MILITARY OPERATION CALLED "LILIANA," THE ARMY SEIZED SHOTGUNS, PISTOLS, ONE SUB-MACHINE GUN, AND LARGE AMOUNTS OF AMMUNITION, IN ADDITION TO DYNAMITE AND CABLES FOR EXPLOSIVES, COMMUNICATION EQUIPMENT, DENTAL EQUIPMENT, AND CLOTHING FOR THE EXCLUSIVE USE OF THE MILITARY FORCES.

DEV-MUC3-1171 (SYNCHRONETICS)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 16 MAR 90 (BARRICADA) -- [SPEECH] [NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA] [TEXT] IN SEPTEMBER 1970, I WAS IN JAIL WITH OTHER COMRADES. OUR JAILERS DID NOT ALLOW US TO READ THE NEWSPAPERS -- NOT EVEN THE ONES PUBLISHED BY THE SOMOZAS -- BUT WE FOUND WAYS TO GET A RADIO AND WERE ABLE TO LEARN OF SALVADOR ALLENDE'S ELECTION THROUGH THE PEOPLE'S VOTE.

WE WERE JAIL IN 1973 WHEN WE LEARNED OF THE BRUTAL COUP AGAINST THE PEOPLE'S WILL AND DEMOCRACY. RADIO REPORTS SAID THAT PLANES WERE BOMBING LA MONEDA [CHILEAN PRESIDENTIAL HOUSE] AND WE PICTURED PRESIDENT ALLENDE HEROICALLY RESISTING THERE.

WE DID NOT LOSE OUR MORALE. WE BECAME INDIGNANT AND FULL OF COURAGE. WE THOUGHT AND FELT CERTAIN THAT THE CHILEAN PEOPLE WOULD GO ON WINNING BECAUSE IT WAS THEIR WILL TO BE FREE AND SOVEREIGN.

SO MANY YEARS HAD TO PASS FOR US TO BE HERE WITH THE CHILEAN PEOPLE. AFTER THAT CAME THE VICTORY OF THE REVOLUTION IN NICARAGUA. THAT DAY, 19 JULY 1979, WHEN THE VICTORIOUS PEOPLE ENTERED MANAGUA, SALVADOR ALLENDE WAS THERE STRUGGLING SIDE BY SIDE WITH THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE.

I WANT TO OUTLINE SOME VIEWS, BUT WITH THE UNDERSTANDING THAT THE CURRENT INTERNATIONAL POLITICAL PICTURE IS EXTREMELY COMPLEX. FIRST OF ALL, WE RESPECT POLITICAL AND IDEOLOGICAL OPTIONS. WHEN WE WON, WE SANDINISTS THOUGHT THAT THE TIME HAD COME TO DEVELOP A DIFFERENT SYSTEM TO GIVE NICARAGUA WHAT HAD BEEN DENIED TO IT BY THE IMPERIALIST DOMINATION.

SANDINO EPITOMIZED THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE'S ANTI-IMPERIALIST STRUGGLE, THE FIRST MANIFESTATIONS OF WHICH OCCURRED LAST CENTURY. SANDINO ADVOCATED NOT ONLY A STRUGGLE AGAINST NORTH AMERICAN INTERVENTION, BUT SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC CHANGE. HE DID NOT PUT A LABEL ON HIS THOUGHTS, BUT WAS CONVINCED THAT TO BE A [TRUE] NICARAGUAN AND LATIN AMERICAN, ONE HAD TO BE ANTI-IMPERIALIST AND HAD TO ADVOCATE SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC TRANSFORMATIONS IN FAVOR OF THE PEOPLE.

THE SANDINIST FRONT [SANDINIST NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] PICKED UP SANDINO'S BANNERS AND ADOPTED HIS STILL UNFINISHED HISTORICAL PROGRAM. SO, AFTER VICTORY, WE THOUGHT THAT WE HAD TO THINK OF A DIFFERENT PROGRAM FOR NICARAGUA.

WE REJECTED DOGMAS OR SCHEMES WITH REGARD TO THE METHOD OF STRUGGLE TO ACHIEVE VICTORY OR THE MODEL THAT WOULD BE VIABLE FOR NICARAGUA IN THE LATIN AMERICAN CONTEXT. WE BEGAN WITH THREE BASIC TENETS: A MULTIPARTY SYSTEM, A MIXED ECONOMY, AND SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC JUSTICE.

EXERCISING THIS RIGHT, WE SAID: THIS IS THE PATH. AND THE UNITED STATES SAID: THAT IS NOT THE PATH. TIGHTLY CLINGING TO ITS IMPERIALISTIC POLICY, THE UNITED STATES DECIDED TO DESTROY THE NICARAGUAN REVOLUTION AND ORGANIZED A MILITARY, POLITICAL, AND ECONOMIC ONSLAUGHT.

YOU ARE FAMILIAR WITH THIS STORY AND ITS TRAGIC TOLL OF 60,000 VICTIMS.

WE HAVE BEEN ABLE TO DEFEND NICARAGUA AND THE GAINS ATTAINED BY THE REVOLUTION, BECAUSE THIS DEFENSE WAS HEADED BY THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE WHO, ARMED WITH THEIR CONSCIENCE AND COURAGE, TOOK UP WEAPONS TO DEFEND THEIR HOMELAND'S SOVEREIGNTY AND TERRITORIAL INTEGRITY. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1172 (SYNCHRONETICS)

MANAGUA (NICARAGUA), 16 MAR 90 (BARRICADA) -- [SPEECH] [NICARAGUAN PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] THE GOVERNMENT THAT TAKES OFFICE ON 25 APRIL CAN REST ASSURED, AS CAN MANY LATIN AMERICAN GOVERNMENTS, THAT THERE WILL NEVER AGAIN BE ANOTHER MILITARY COUP IN NICARAGUA. THE HUMBLE PEOPLE, THE PEASANTS, AND THE WORKERS CAN REST ASSURED THAT THE ARMY WILL SAFEGUARD THE FATHERLAND'S SOVEREIGNTY, IT WILL NOT TURN THE CANNONS AGAINST THE WORKERS.

I NEVER SAID THAT THE FSLN WOULD PERPETUALLY REMAIN IN THE GOVERNMENT, BUT THAT THE PEOPLE WOULD PERPETUATE THEMSELVES IN POWER. THAT I DID SAY!

OTHERS WILL SAY THAT THE SANDINISTS MADE MANY CONCESSIONS, BUT IF WE HELD ELECTIONS, IT WAS BECAUSE WE WERE CONVINCED THAT WE COULD LOSE, A NEW MODEL IN LATIN AMERICA THAT NOT ONLY GUARANTEES THE EXISTENCE OF DEMOCRACY, BUT ITS DEVELOPMENT AND DEEPENING. IT IS DEMOCRATIC TO CONSTANTLY QUESTION DEMOCRACY TO REFRESH, STRENGTHEN, AND DEEPEN DEMOCRACY.

THE CLEANEST AND MOST OBSERVED ELECTORAL PROCESS IS THE ONE THAT WAS CARRIED OUT IN NICARAGUA. WE HAVE NOTHING TO HIDE. THE REPORTERS SAID THAT IF WE WON THEY WOULD LEAVE, BUT SINCE WE LOST THEY HAVE STAYED ON TO SEE IF WE WILL SURRENDER POWER ON 25 APRIL.

ALTHOUGH IT IS TRUE THAT THE FSLN SUFFERED AN UPSET IN THE ELECTIONS, AS A POLITICAL FORCE THAT HAS BEEN THE VANGUARD OF THE PROCESS THAT LED THE COUNTRY TO DEMOCRACY, INDEPENDENCE, DIGNITY, AND SOVEREIGNTY, THE FSLN IS NOW CONSOLIDATING THE RESULTS OF DEMOCRACY. IT IS NOT TRUE THAT THE REVOLUTION HAS BEEN DEFEATED, BECAUSE IT HAS EMERGED FROM THE ELECTIONS STRONGER.

I AM PREPARING TO ACT AS THE OPPOSITION ALONGSIDE THE PEOPLE WHEN I AM NO LONGER PRESIDENT ON 25 APRIL. I AM A DEPUTY, BUT I PREFER TO BE IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS, THE FACTORIES, AND THE COUNTRYSIDE. I HAVE TOLD THE NICARAGUANS THAT WE MUST CONSOLIDATE THIS PROCESS, WHICH MEANS THE CONSOLIDATION OF DEMOCRACY IN NICARAGUA. WE MUST BE MORE CREATIVE AND IMAGINATIVE THAN EVER, BECAUSE WE WILL FACE NEW CHALLENGES THAT WILL BE ENRICHING TO US AS A REVOLUTION.

TO BE A CLANDESTINE OPPOSITION IS NOT THE SAME AS TO RULE FROM ABOVE. WE WILL NOW GOVERN FROM BELOW, AND WE WILL DEFEND POPULAR AND NATIONAL INTERESTS. THE RETURN OF SOMOZISM IS NOT SOUGHT. THE ELECTORAL VICTORY DOES NOT MEAN A RETURN OF THE COUNTERREVOLUTION, THAT CONTINUES TO THREATEN NICARAGUA. IF THE COUNTERREVOLUTION IS NOT DISARMED, THE NEW GOVERNMENT WILL ALSO HAVE TO CONFRONT THE COUNTERREVOLUTION, AND WE WILL FIGHT AS WE NEVER DID BEFORE.

THE UNITED STATES LIFTED THE EMBARGO AND OFFERED AID TO NICARAGUA. WE WILL NOT BE LIKE RIGHT-WING EXTREMISTS WHO SABOTAGE ECONOMIC EFFORTS. RESOURCES HAVE NOT BEEN OFFERED TO A CERTAIN PARTY, BUT TO ALL OF THE PEOPLE. NICARAGUA NOT ONLY DESERVES INTERNATIONAL COOPERATION, IT SHOULD BE INDEMNIFIED BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT.

WE HAVE FELT THE SOLIDARITY OF PEOPLE THE WORLD OVER, WE HAVE FELT THE SOLIDARITY OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, WHO HAVE ALSO BEEN MURDERED BY THE COUNTERREVOLUTION IN OUR FATHERLAND. I HAVE HEARD OF EMOTIONAL EXAMPLES OF SOLIDARITY, SUCH AS BRYAN WILSON'S, WHO SAT IN FRONT OF A TRAIN THAT RAN OVER HIM, AND WHO TELLS ME HE FEELS PROUD TO BE ONE OF THE THOUSANDS OF AMPUTEES FROM THE WAR IN NICARAGUA.

THE BLOOD OF CHILEANS, AMERICANS, AND EUROPEANS WAS SHED IN NICARAGUA. I MUST THANK THIS HEROIC AND EXEMPLARY CHILE FOR THE MANNER IN WHICH IT HAS DISPLAYED ITS FONDNESS FOR THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE THROUGH ME, AND I MUST TELL YOU THAT TODAY, MORE THAN EVER, THE SOLIDARITY OF PEOPLE WHO DEFEND THE CAUSE OF FREEDOM, SOVEREIGNTY, DEMOCRACY, AND INDEPENDENCE IS INDISPENSABLE.

THE FUTURE, IT IS SAID, BELONGS TO THE PEOPLE, BECAUSE THE PRESENT AND THE PAST ALSO BELONG TO THEM. THE REVOLUTION SHOULD BE REFRESHED, IT SHOULD BE WATERED WITH FRESH RAIN; ONLY THEN WILL THE TREES TURN GREEN AND THE FLOWERS BLOOM, ONLY THEN WILL THE REVOLUTIONARY PROCESSES BE UNDERSTOOD. WE COULD TALK FOR HOURS AND HOURS, BUT THIS IS NOT THE TIME TO TALK. IT IS THE TIME TO ACT.

THIS VISIT TO CHILE WILL BE UNFORGETTABLE FOR ME BECAUSE OF THE HAPPINESS, OPTIMISM, AND CONFIDENCE REFLECTED IN THE FACES AND IN THE EYES OF THE CHILEAN PEOPLE.

THIS NIGHT WILL BE UNFORGETTABLE FOR ME. THEREFORE, I WISH TO PAY HOMAGE TO THOSE WHO WERE EXAMPLES OF LATIN AMERICAN DIGNITY AND ARE WITH US ALWAYS IN CHILE, NICARAGUA, AND LATIN AMERICA: SALVADOR ALLENDE AND PABLO NERUDA. LONG LIVE NICARAGUA!

DEV-MUC3-1173 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 16 MAR 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE SALVADORAN ARMED FORCES CHARGED TODAY THAT A GROUP OF GUERRILLAS ATTACKED A CONTINGENT OF SOLDIERS IN THE TOWN OF VICTORIA, NORTHEASTERN CABANAS DEPARTMENT, FROM A SETTLEMENT FOR DISPLACED PERSONS. THERE WERE NO CASUALTIES.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) HAS STATED THAT THE REBELS FIRED M-60 MACHINEGUNS AT A PATROL OF SOLDIERS PASSING BY THE SANTA MARTA SETTLEMENT, WHERE SOME 3,000 DISPLACED PERSONS LIVE.

THE MILITARY REPORT SAID THAT THE INCIDENT TOOK PLACE ON 15 MARCH AND THE SOLDIERS DID NOT ANSWER THE FIRE.

HOWEVER, THE CHRISTIAN COMMITTEE FOR DISPLACED SALVADORANS (CRIPDES) DENIED THAT THERE ARE ANY ARMED PERSONS IN THIS SETTLEMENT, WHERE THE PERSONS WHO RECENTLY CAME BACK FROM THE HONDURAN CAMP OF MESA GRANDE ARE LIVING.

TOMASA RUIZ, SPOKESPERSON FOR CRIPDES, SAID THAT THE CHARGES "ARE A DIRECT THREAT" TO THE SECURITY OF THE DISPLACED PERSONS IN SANTA MARTA. "THIS DOES NOT MEAN," SHE ADDED, "THAT THERE ARE NO CONFRONTATIONS TAKING PLACE OUTSIDE THE CAMP, BUT THERE ARE NO ARMED PERSONS INSIDE THE CAMP."

THE ARMED FORCES HAVE SAID THAT THE GUERRILLAS ARE HIDING AMONG THE CIVILIAN POPULATION IN ORDER TO ATTACK THE SOLDIERS.

ON 11 FEBRUARY, ONE ADULT AND FOUR MINORS WERE KILLED AND 16 OTHERS WERE WOUNDED WHEN A SALVADORAN AIR FORCE HELICOPTER STRAFED A CAMP OF DISPLACED PERSONS IN CORRAL DE PIEDRAS, CHALATENANGO DEPARTMENT. ON THAT OCCASION THE ARMY SAID THAT THE GUERRILLAS ATTACKED THE GOVERNMENT TROOPS FROM THE SETTLEMENT OF REFUGEES WHO RETURNED TO THE COUNTRY LATE LAST YEAR, AFTER HAVING LIVED NEARLY ONE DECADE IN THE HONDURAN CAMPS.

IN ADDITION, THE ARMED FORCES SAID THAT THREE SOLDIERS HAD BEEN WOUNDED DURING FIGHTING WITH THE GUERRILLAS IN THE TOWN OF SAN JOSE GUAYABAL, IN THE CENTRAL CUSCATLAN DEPARTMENT.

THESE CHARGES WERE MADE PUBLIC ON 16 MARCH WHEN THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) ANNOUNCED A SUSPENSION OF SABOTAGE ACTIONS ON PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION, BUSINESS ESTABLISHMENTS, AND THE TELECOMMUNICATIONS CENTER, AS WELL AS ATTACKS ON CIVILIAN OFFICIALS.

THE ARMY ALSO MAINTAINED THAT THE REBELS BLEW UP FIVE ELECTRICITY POSTS IN SAN VICENTE AND MORAZAN DEPARTMENT IN THE CENTER AND NORTHEASTERN PARTS OF THE COUNTRY. THE REBELS ALSO HARASSED SOLDIERS WHO WERE GUARDING AN ELECTRICITY STATION IN A TOWN OF SANTA ANA DEPARTMENT AND A MILITARY CHECKPOINT ON THE BRIDGE OVER THE ACELHUATE RIVER IN AGUILARES, NORTH OF SAN SALVADOR.

ACCORDING TO THE MILITARY REPORT, THESE HARASSMENT ACTIONS BY THE REBELS DID NOT CAUSE ANY CASUALTIES.

DEV-MUC3-1174 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SANTIAGO, 13 MAR 90 (BARRICADA) -- [REPORT] [MONICA ZALAQUETT] [TEXT] U.S. VICE PRESIDENT DAN QUAYLE TALKED WITH PRESIDENT DANIEL ORTEGA DURING AN OFFICIAL LUNCH AND TOLD HIM THAT HE FULLY AGREES WITH THE NEED TO DEMOBILIZE AND DISARM THE CONTRAS BEFORE 25 APRIL TO GUARANTEE A NORMAL TRANSITION OF POWER TO THE NEW GOVERNMENT.

DANIEL SAID IN A STATEMENT TO BARRICADA: "VICE PRESIDENT QUAYLE TOLD ME THEY ARE WORKING ON AN IDEA SO THAT THE CONTRAS ARE NOT AROUND BY 25 APRIL. HE STATED HIS POLITICAL WILLINGNESS TO DO THIS, AND I BELIEVE HIS POSITION WAS VERY CONSTRUCTIVE."

WHEN ASKED WHAT STEPS WILL BE TAKEN TO CARRY THIS OUT, HE REPLIED: "WE -- AND NOT ONLY THE NICARAGUANS AND CENTRAL AMERICANS, BUT ALSO THE UNITED STATES -- MUST NOW PUT WORDS INTO DEEDS TO PUT THE POLITICAL WILL INTO ACTIONS THAT WILL ENABLE US TO DISARM AND DEMOBILIZE THE CONTRAS BEFORE THAT DATE."

REFERRING TO CERTAIN ATTEMPTS BY UNO SECTORS TO ESTABLISH A SYMMETRY BETWEEN THE CONSTITUTIONAL ARMED FORCES OF NICARAGUA AND THE CONTRAS' TERRORIST FORCES, DANIEL POINTED OUT: "NO, NO, NO, NOBODY HAS PROPOSED THIS. NONE OF THE PRESIDENTS WITH WHOM I HAVE TALKED THINKS ALONG THESE LINES."

ORTEGA INSISTED THAT THE CONVERSATION WITH THE U.S. VICE PRESIDENT HAD BEEN "FRANK, FRIENDLY, DIRECT, AND VERY RESPECTFUL," AND THAT QUAYLE "IS CERTAIN THAT THE TRANSFER OF POWER WILL BE CARRIED OUT ON 25 APRIL. HE ALSO STATED HIS WILLINGNESS TO COOPERATE SO THAT NICARAGUA DOES NOT HAVE TO LIVE IN A FAR MORE CRITICAL SITUATION THAN THE ONE IT IS CURRENTLY FACING IN EVERY SECTOR."

DANIEL CONSIDERED THE MEETING, WHICH OCCURRED DURING LUNCH, AS "VERY POSITIVE, AND I FIND HIM CONSTRUCTIVELY INCLINED TOWARD ALL THE EFFORTS THAT WE, THE NICARAGUANS, HAVE EXERTED, AND WHICH CULMINATED WITH THE 25 FEBRUARY ELECTIONS."

THE PRESIDENT ALSO REFERRED TO CONVERSATIONS HELD DURING THE FLIGHT BETWEEN CARACAS AND SANTIAGO DE CHILE WITH THE PRESIDENTS OF SPAIN, VENEZUELA, COSTA RICA, AND HONDURAS, CONFIRMING: "WE ALL AGREE THAT THE CONTRAS SHOULD BE IMMEDIATELY DISARMED AND DEMOBILIZED."

ORTEGA TALKED BRIEFLY WITH QUAYLE YESTERDAY MORNING DURING THE TE DEUM OFFERED AT THE METROPOLITAN CATHEDRAL FOR THE PRESIDENTS WHO WERE INVITED TO THE INAUGURATION OF CHILEAN PRESIDENT PATRICIO AYLWIN. WHEN DANIEL ENTERED THE CATHEDRAL, THOSE ATTENDING THE TE DEUM APPLAUDED HIM WHILE HE GREETED THE HEADS OF STATE WHO WERE THERE. WHEN QUAYLE ENTERED, HE APPROACHED DANIEL AND GREETED HIM IN A FRIENDLY MANNER, WHILE THE THRILLED CROWD CONTINUED TO APPLAUD.

PERSONS WHO OVERHEARD THE BRIEF CONVERSATION REPORTED TO BARRICADA THAT QUAYLE TOLD DANIEL THAT IF HE WISHED TO SEND A MESSAGE TO BUSH HE WOULD DELIVER IT, THEREBY AGREEING TO WAIT UNTIL AN APPROPRIATE TIME TO HOLD THEIR CONVERSATION. THIS MOMENT OCCURRED SEVERAL HOURS LATER DURING THE OFFICIAL LUNCH.

DURING THE MORNING DANIEL ALSO MET WITH MEMBERS OF THE POLITICAL PARTIES OPPOSED TO THE OUTGOING PINOCHET GOVERNMENT. HE EXPLAINED TO THEM THE RESULTS OF THE NICARAGUAN ELECTIONS, WHICH HE DESCRIBED AS "A TACTICAL DEFEAT BUT A STRATEGIC VICTORY FOR THE FSLN."

SHORTLY AFTERWARD THE PRESIDENT MET WITH CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY LEADERS, INCLUDING PARTY PRESIDENT ANDRES ZALDIVAR. AT THIS MEETING THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATS SAID THAT THE NICARAGUAN ELECTORAL PROCESS WAS CLEAN AND OPEN, AND THEY PRAISED THE FSLN'S FULFILLMENT OF ITS DEMOCRATIC OBLIGATIONS. THEY ALSO PRAISED PRESIDENT ORTEGA'S ATTITUDE AND THE WIDESPREAD INTERNATIONAL RECOGNITION HE HAS OBTAINED.

IN THE AFTERNOON, PRESIDENT ORTEGA SPOKE BRIEFLY TO NEWSMEN AFTER VISITING "LA MONEDA" PRESIDENTIAL PALACE TO OFFER HIS OFFICIAL GREETINGS TO CHILEAN PRESIDENT PATRICIO AYLWIN. "I HAVE TRANSMITTED THE GREETINGS OF THE NICARAGUAN PEOPLE TO THE CHILEAN PEOPLE AND HAVE MADE REFERENCE TO THE LONG-STANDING FRIENDSHIP THAT UNITES THE TWO NATIONS," DANIEL TOLD NEWSMEN ON THE PATIO OF THE "LA MONEDA" PALACE, THE SAME PLACE WHERE PRESIDENT SALVADOR ALLENDE FELL FIGHTING FOR HIS PEOPLE ON 11 SEPTEMBER 1973.

"IT IS AN HONOR FOR ME TO BE HERE, SHARING THIS HISTORICAL MOMENT WITH THE CHILEAN PEOPLE. I AM CONVINCED THAT WE WILL CONTINUE WORKING TOGETHER WITH THE PEOPLES OF THE CONTINENT TO BUILD AN INDEPENDENT, FREE, LATIN AMERICAN FATHERLAND WITH SOCIAL AND ECONOMIC JUSTICE AND WITH TRUE PEACE, SOVEREIGNTY, AND DEMOCRACY," ORTEGA TOLD THE JOURNALISTS, WHO RESPONDED WITH APPLAUSE.

DEV-MUC3-1175 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SANTIAGO, 21 MAR 90 (RADIO CHILENA NETWORK) -- [TEXT] TWO INDIVIDUALS SHOT FORMER GOVERNMENT JUNTA MEMBER GUSTAVO LEIGH GUZMAN AT POINT BLANK RANGE THIS MORNING. GENERAL LEIGH WAS ATTACKED AT HIS OFFICE AT BARRIO ALTO. HIS CONDITION IS VERY SERIOUS. HE WAS HIT FIVE TIMES DURING THE ATTACK AT AROUND 1100 [1500 GMT] THIS MORNING. GEN. GUSTAVO LEIGH IS BEING TREATED AT THE MILITARY HOSPITAL.

INTERIOR MINISTER ENRIQUE KRAUSS, LEGISLATORS, CHURCH OFFICIALS AND OTHER AUTHORITIES VISITED THE HOSPITAL TO CHECK ON LEIGH'S CONDITION.

PRESIDENT PATRICIO AYLWIN SUSPENDED ALL AUDIENCES AS A CONSEQUENCE OF THE SAVAGE ATTACK. MINISTER SECRETARY OF GOVERNMENT ENRIQUE CORREA SAID THE ATTACK WAS TREMENDOUSLY REGRETTABLE AND CONDEMNABLE.

INTERIOR UNDER SECRETARY VELISARIO VELAZCO SAID THE GROUP RESPONSIBLE FOR THE ATTACK WILL BE SENTENCED WITH MAXIMUM SEVERITY. CATHOLIC CHURCH AUTHORITIES, LEGISLATORS FROM ALL PARTY BLOCS, BUSINESSMEN, ENTREPRENEURS, WORKERS, AND THE PUBLIC IN GENERAL CONDEMNED THE ATTACK TERMING IT A SHOCK AGAINST THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.

DOCTOR FRANCISCO ALAMAN SAID FORMER AIR FORCE COMMANDER LEIGH IS FOR THE TIME BEING OUT OF IMMEDIATE DANGER OF DEATH. THE OTHER GENERAL WOUNDED IN THE ATTACK, RETIRED GENERAL ENRIQUE RUIZ, WAS HIT BY THREE BULLETS AND IS BEING TREATED AT THE AIR FORCE HOSPITAL.

SO FAR THE MILITARY HOSPITAL HAS NOT RELEASED ANY OFFICIAL REPORT ON LEIGH'S CONDITION. THE MANUEL RODRIGUEZ PATRIOTIC FRONT, AUTONOMOUS FACTION, HAS CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ATTACK.

DEV-MUC3-1177 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [INTERVIEW WITH LEMOS BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] JARAMILLO OSSA HAS SAID THAT FOR THE PAST FOUR YEARS HE HAD ASKED THE GOVERNMENT FOR PROTECTION, THAT HIS LIFE WAS IN DANGER, AND THAT HE HELD THE GOVERNMENT DIRECTLY RESPONSIBLE FOR WHATEVER HAPPENED TO HIM. THAT IS WHAT JARAMILLO OSSA SAID.

[LEMOS] DID YOU SAY FOR THE PAST 4 YEARS?

[REPORTER] THAT IS WHAT JARAMILLO OSSA SAID, THAT THE GOVERNMENT WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR HIS SAFETY DURING THE PAST 4 YEARS. HE ALSO SAID THAT WHATEVER HAPPENED FROM THEN ON WOULD ALSO BE BLAMED ON YOUR STATEMENT, AND THAT THE BEST SERVICE YOU COULD GIVE THE COUNTRY WOULD BE TO RESIGN.

[LEMOS] I ALREADY REPLIED TO A QUESTION ABOUT MY RESIGNATION. I CANNOT RESIGN BECAUSE I AM NOT GUILTY. BY RESIGNING I WOULD BE ADMITTING MY GUILT TO SOMETHING I HAD NOTHING TO DO WITH. HOWEVER, I AM GLAD THAT YOU MENTIONED THAT THIS HAS BEEN OCCURRING FOR THE PAST 4 YEARS. I WAS A JOURNALIST FOUR YEARS AGO.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] MADE A MISTAKE A FEW DAYS AGO BY AGAIN LINKING THE UP WITH THE FARC?

[LEMOS] I PREFER NOT TO DISCUSS THIS TOPIC NOW. I DO NOT THINK THAT THIS IS THE BEST TIME TO DISCUSS THAT SUBJECT.

AFTER THIS SITUATION HAS SETTLED, I WILL HAVE TO FILE A FORMAL STATEMENT AT THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE WHERE I HAVE BEEN SUMMONED BY THE UP. AS A GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL, I AM OBLIGED TO APPEAR BEFORE THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE TO EXPLAIN MY ACTIONS, BUT NOW IS NOT THE MOMENT TO EXPLAIN ANYTHING.

[REPORTER] [QUESTION INDISTINCT]

[LEMOS] OF COURSE, THE PRESIDENT IS VERY DISTRESSED, AS WE ALL ARE. WE BELIEVE THIS IS A TERRIBLE; THERE IS NO JUSTIFICATION FOR SOMETHING LIKE THIS TO HAPPEN. IT IS EVIDENT THAT PEOPLE WHO ARE SEEKING A GOAL OPPOSITE TO THAT OF THE GOVERNMENT ARE INVOLVED IN THIS. THE GOVERNMENT WANTS A FREE ELECTORAL PROCESS; IT IS COMMITTED TO THAT.

TODAY, WHEN WE HAVE A COMPLETELY ORDERLY ELECTORAL PROCESS, IT WOULD BE ABSURD, ILLOGICAL, IRRATIONAL, AND SENSELESS FOR THE GOVERNMENT TO PROMOTE ACTIONS THAT RUN COUNTER TO ITS GOAL OF ENSURING THAT ITS TERM ENDS IN PEACE AND THAT THE ELECTIONS WILL TAKE PLACE NORMALLY.

[REPORTER] THE UP HAS AGAIN CAST DOUBT OVER THE GOVERNMENT'S GUARANTEES FOR THE CANDIDATES AND THE PARTY.

[LEMOS] I BELIEVE THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS DONE EVERYTHING HUMANLY POSSIBLE TO GUARANTEE THE SAFETY OF CANDIDATES, NOT ONLY THE SAFETY OF UP MEMBERS, BUT OF ALL PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES, REGARDLESS OF THEIR AFFILIATION.

[WORDS INDISTINCT] IN THEIR COMMUNIQUE, EVIDENCE OF THE FACT THAT DR JARAMILLO'S BODYGUARDS REACTED AND, I UNDERSTAND, BY KILLING ONE OF THE ASSASSINS, AT LEAST THAT IS WHAT I HAVE HEARD, AND ARRESTED ANOTHER ONE, WHICH HAS BEEN CONFIRMED, SHOWS THAT THE GOVERNMENT IS INDEED OFFERING PROTECTION.

THEREFORE, DR. JARAMILLO WAS INDEED ENJOYING GOVERNMENT PROTECTION JUST AS THE OTHER PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES ARE. WHAT HAPPENS IS THAT THE ASSASSINS CARRY OUT SURPRISE ATTACKS. AT A GIVEN MOMENT, AN APPROACHING PERSON CAN CAN PULL OUT A WEAPON AND KILL WHOMEVER HE WANTS. THERE IS NO 100-PERCENT PREVENTION AGAINST THIS. THIS HOLDS TRUE NOT ONLY IN COLOMBIA BUT IN MANY COUNTRIES IN THE WORLD. THE VERY COURSE OF THESE TERRIBLE EVENTS OF THIS MORNING AT THE AIPORT SHOW THAT DR JARAMILLO WAS INDEED PROTECTED.

[REPORTER] THE UP HAS JUST ANNOUNCED THAT IT WILL FILE SUIT AGAINST YOU FOR THIS ASSASSINATION.

[LEMOS] THAT IS FINE. IF THE UP HAS ANY EVIDENCE THAT I AM INVOLVED IN DR. JARAMILLO'S ASSASSINATION, THEN IT MUST FILE SUIT, BECAUSE OTHERWISE, IT WOULD BE ACTING AS AN ACCOMPLICE TO THIS ASSASSINATION. I BELIEVE THAT SUITS MUST BE FILED BY THOSE WHO SUSPECT THAT A GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL, AND MYSELF PARTICULARLY, MAY BE INVOLVED IN THE ASSASSINATION, TO ENSURE THAT THE INCIDENT IS INVESTIGATED. THEREFORE, I BELIEVE THAT THIS IS GOOD NEWS AMID A SEA OF BAD NEWS THAT WE HAVE HEARD TODAY.

[REPORTER] [WORDS INDISTINCT] ONLY RESPONSIBILITY FOR PHYSICAL SAFETY, BUT THERE IS ALSO POLITICAL RESPONSIBILITY. YOU ARE BEING ACCUSED OF POLITICAL IRRESPONSIBILITY AND OF NOT RESPONSIBILE FOR PHYSICAL SAFETY. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1180 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, 22 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [REPORT] [EDUARDO CARRILLO] [TEXT] RADIO CADENA NACIONAL HAS LEARNED THAT DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL OSCAR BOTERO RESTREPO HAS ORDERED THE INDEFINITE CONFINEMENT OF NATIONAL POLICE AND MILITARY FORCES TO THEIR BARRACKS. THEY ARE TO STAY THERE UNTIL IT IS CLEAR THAT THE PUBLIC ORDER SITUATION RESULTING FROM THE ASSASSINATION OF BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA, PATRIOTIC UNION [UP] PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, IS UNDER CONTROL.

MEANWHILE, A NATIONAL SECURITY COUNCIL MEETING IS TAKING PLACE AT THE NARINO PRESIDENTIAL PALACE. THE PARTICIPANTS ARE DISCUSSING THE INCIDENTS THAT DISRUPTED THE DAILY LIVES OF ALL COLOMBIANS TODAY WHEN A TERRORIST KILLED UP PRESIDENT BERNARDO JARAMILLO AT THE EL DORADO INTERNATIONAL AIRPORT.

WE HAVE ALSO LEARNED THAT PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO AND GOVERNMENT MINISTER CARLOS LEMOS SIMMONDS HAVE BEEN IN CONSTANT CONTACT WITH THE POLICE AUTHORITIES AND THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY, DAS, IN AN EFFORT TO LEARN ALL THE DETAILS FOLLOWING THE ATTACK ON JARAMILLO. [PASSAGE INDISTINCT] THE OFFICES OF THE DAS.

TO AVOID CONFUSING REPORTS AND MISINTERPRETATIONS, ALL REPORTS HAVE BEEN RELEASED THROUGH THROUGH THE GOVERNMENT MINISTRY, WHICH IS HEADED BY DR. CARLOS LEMOS SIMMONDS.

DEV-MUC3-1181 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 22 MAR 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] OTTO SORTO MILLA, THE SON-IN-LAW OF GENERAL RAFAEL VILLAMARIONA, CHIEF OF THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE, WAS WOUNDED IN AN ATTACK IN SAN SALVADOR TODAY AND IS IN "SERIOUS CONDITION," ACCORDING TO MILITARY SPOKESMEN AND DOCTORS.

THE SOURCES POINTED OUT THAT SORTO MILLA, 25, WAS MACHINEGUNNED FROM A MOVING VEHICLE WHILE LEAVING HIS HOME, LOCATED IN THE LUXURIOUS SAN FRANCISCO NEIGHBORHOOD IN SOUTHWEST SAN SALVADOR.

DOCTORS TOLD ACAN-EFE THAT GEN. VILLAMARIONA'S SON-IN-LAW IS "IN SERIOUS CONDITION" AT A PRIVATE HOSPITAL, WHERE HE WAS ADMITTED AT 1030 (1630 GMT), BUT THEY DID NOT SPECIFY WHERE THE BULLET WOUNDS WERE OR THE NUMBER OF BULLETS THAT HIT HIM.

MILITARY SPOKESMEN SAID THAT SORTO MILLA HAD BULLET WOUNDS IN SEVERAL PARTS OF THE BODY, BUT THEY REFUSED TO PROVIDE MORE DETAILS AS LONG AS THE POLICE ARE CONDUCTING INVESTIGATIONS TO CAPTURE THE ASSAILANTS.

GEN. VILLAMARIONA, CONSIDERED TO BE ONE OF THE HARD-LINE MILITARY CHIEFS OF THE ARMED FORCES, WAS APPOINTED TO HIS PRESENT POST IN JANUARY OF THIS YEAR REPLACING GENERAL RAFAEL BUSTILLO, WHO WAS APPOINTED MILITARY ATTACHE IN ISRAEL.

THE SALVADORAN AIR FORCE (FAS) PLAYED A KEY ROLE DURING THE LAST GUERRILLA MILITARY OFFENSIVE IN NOVEMBER 1989, AND IT WAS ACCUSED BY OPPOSITION GROUPS, HUMANITARIAN ORGANIZATIONS, AND THE CATHOLIC CHURCH OF INDISCRIMINATELY BOMBING POOR NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE CAPITAL TO DISLODGE REPORTED GUERRILLA REDOUBTS.

THE ATTACK ON SORTO MILLA TOOK PLACE A WEEK AFTER THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) SUSPENDED ITS ATTACKS ON CIVILIAN GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES TO CONTRIBUTE TO THE CREATION OF CONDITIONS FOR THE RESUMPTION OF THE DIALOGUE WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S GOVERNMENT.

OFFICIAL SOURCES HAVE NOT DISCLOSED WHO THEY BELIEVE CARRIED OUT THE ATTACK OR PROVIDED ANY BACKGROUND INFORMATION ON SORTO MILLA.

DEV-MUC3-1182 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, NO DATE (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [INTERVIEW WITH LLOREDA BY REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] AMID ALL THE CONFUSION AND ALARM THAT TODAY PREVAILS THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY, WHAT WOULD DR. LLOREDA DO TO RESTORE PUBLIC TRANQUILITY? WHAT IS THE IMMEDIATE AND MOST URGENT THING TO DO?

[LLOREDA] JUAN, I BELIEVE THAT SECURITY IS NO LONGER AN ACADEMIC ISSUE; IT HAS BECOME AN ANGUISHED NEED FOR COLOMBIA. THIS WILL PROBABLY MEAN THAT WE WILL HAVE TO MAKE MANY SACRIFICES IF WE WANT TO PUT A STOP TO VIOLENCE WITHIN A FEW YEARS. IN FACT, WE WILL HAVE TO SACRIFICE SOME OF THE BROAD AND GENEROUS FREEDOM WE HAVE ALWAYS ENJOYED IN THIS COUNTRY. GIVEN THESE DEPLORABLE ACTIONS, THE SECURITY ISSUE HAS BECOME A PRIORITY, BECAUSE ONE CANNOT LIVE IN A SOCIETY IN WHICH ITS MEMBERS ARE CONTINUOUSLY THREATENED. THIS NOT ONLY REFERS TO DR. JARAMILLO OSSA'S DEATH, BUT ALSO TO OTHER DEATHS THAT SOMETIMES DO NOT APPEAR WHERE THEY SHOULD, MEANING THE FRONT PAGE OF THE NEWSPAPERS.

A WEEK OR TWO AGO THE POLICE SAID THAT WE HAVE HAD AN AVERAGE OF 54 VIOLENT DEATHS PER DAY SO FAR THIS YEAR. IF THIS CONTINUES, WE WILL HAVE MORE THAN 12,000 MURDERS IN COLOMBIA BY THE TIME PRESIDENT BARCO TURNS OVER POWER ON 7 AUGUST. I BELIEVE, AND I THINK YOU SHARE THE SAME VIEWPOINT, THAT WE HAVE A WORLD RECORD FOR INSECURITY AND VIOLENCE. THEREFORE, WE CANNOT TAKE THE RISK OF ALLOWING THE PROCESS OF MORAL COLLAPSE AND THE STATE OF INSECURITY THAT PREVAILS IN THE COUNTRY TO CONTINUE.

WE MUST STRENGTHEN THE STATE SO THAT IT CAN SUCCESSFULLY COUNTER VIOLENCE. THE PLEBISCITE AND THE CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY I HAVE BEEN PROPOSING INCLUDES THE NEED FOR THE STATE TO HAVE EFFICIENT INSTRUMENTS TO COUNTER VIOLENT ACTIONS. THIS IS NOT, LIKE I SAID IN THE BEGINNING, AN ACADEMIC ISSUE; AND IT IS NOT A PROPOSAL PRESENTED BY IDEALISTIC YOUTHS. IT IS THE EXPRESSION OF A NATION THAT COULD DISAPPEAR OR LOSE ITS FREEDOMS AND DEMOCRACY, IF WE DO NOT ACT DECISIVELY AND RESOLUTELY. THIS IS NOT A PROBLEM BETWEEN POLITICAL PARTIES.

YESTERDAY I PRESENTED MY GOVERNMENT PLATFORM AND I ISSUED A PROPOSAL TO DR. [CESAR] GAVIRIA -- REGARDLESS OF THE 27 MAY ELECTORAL RESULTS, WE MUST REACH A PATRIOTIC AGREEMENT. WE CAN NOW DO IT IN HOMAGE TO BERNARDO JARAMILLO SO THAT THE IDEA OF A PLEBISCITE IS SPONSORED. THUS, WE WILL BE ABLE TO MAKE A THOROUGH INSTITUTIONAL REORGANIZATION. WE MUST SIT DOWN AND THINK ABOUT COLOMBIA, RATHER THAN ELECTORAL LEADERS AND ORGANIZATIONS. THIS IS THE ONLY WAY WE CAN OFFER SOLUTIONS TO FUTURE GENERATIONS, BECAUSE THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE ARE NOW LOOKING TO THEIR FUTURE WITH UNCERTAINTY AND FEAR.

[REPORTER] THANK YOU, DR. LLOREDA, YOU ARE VERY KIND.

[LLOREDA] THANK YOU.

DEV-MUC3-1183 (SYNCHRONETICS)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 22 MAR 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] PANAMANIAN FOREIGN MINISTER JULIO LINARES ANNOUNCED TODAY THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAD GRANTED SAFE-CONDUCTS TO FIVE FORMER OFFICIALS OF THE DEPOSED REGIME, HEADED BY GENERAL MANUAL ANTONIO NORIEGA. THE FIVE FORMER GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS ARE PRESENTLY AT THE ECUADORAN EMBASSY.

ACCORDING TO THE ANNOUNCEMENT, FORMER PUBLIC WORKS MINISTER RENE BULTRON, FORMER LABOR MINISTER CESAR MARTANS, FORMER MORTGAGE BANK MANAGER JULIO SHAIK, FORMER TOURISM INSTITUTE DIRECTOR BERNARDO DOMINGUEZ, AND FORMER HYRAULIC RESOURCES AND ELECTRIFICATION INSTITUTE DIRECTOR OVIGILDO HERRERA, ARE THE FORMER OFFICIALS WHO WILL BE ABLE TO TRAVEL TO ECUADOR WITHIN THE NEXT FEW DAYS.

LINARES ADDED THAT THE DECISION TO GRANT A SAFE-CONDUCT TO FORMER DEMOCRATIC REVOLUTIONARY PARTY LEGISLATOR LUIS "LUCHO" GOMEZ -- PRESENTLY AT THE CUBAN EMBASSY -- HAS BEEN REVOKED BECAUSE HE FACES CHARGES OF "KIDNAPPING AND PHYSICAL AND PSYCHOLOGICAL TORTURE AGAINST THE PANAMANIAN CITIZEN HERNAN ARIAS."

THE PANAMANIAN FOREIGN MINISTER ALSO REJECTED THE POSSIBILITY OF BREAKING RELATIONS WITH MEXICO OR PERU. ACCORDING TO HIS EXPLANATION, THE SITUATION WITH CUBA IS DIFFERENT. TODAY, PANAMA GAVE CUBAN AMBASSADOR LAZARO MORA FIVE DAYS TO QUIT THE COUNTRY "BECAUSE OF THE UNJUSTIFIED ATTACKS BY THE CUBAN GOVERNMENT AGAINST THE NATIONAL GOVERNMENT."

FORMER PANAMA NATIONAL BANK MANAGER RAFAEL AROSEMENA HAS TAKEN REFUGE AT THE MEXICAN EMBASSY. AROSEMENA IS CHARGED WITH ALLOWING A FORMER COMMAND STAFF MEMBER OF THE ELIMINATED PANAMA DEFENSE FORCES [FDP] TO CASH CHECKS MADE OUT TO THE BEARER FOR $12 MILLION. THE FORMER FDP MAYORS HERACLIDIS SUCRE MEDINA AND GONZALO GONZALEZ CONTINUE TO STAY AT THE PERUVIAN EMBASSY IN PANAMA. THEY ARE CHARGED WITH SEVERAL CRIMES.

DEV-MUC3-1184 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, 22 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] TENSION PREVAILED THIS EVENING IN THE CAPITAL AFTER THE BODY OF PATRIOTIC UNION [UP] CANDIDATE BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA WAS TRANSFERRED TO THE OVAL ROOM IN THE NATIONAL CONGRESS, WHERE HE WILL LIE IN STATE UNTIL HIS FUNERAL ON 24 MARCH.

BOGOTA MAYOR ANDRES PASTRANA ARANGO DECREED A DRY LAW AT NOON, AND SUSPENDED CLASSES IN PRIVATE AND PUBLIC ELEMENTARY AND HIGH SCHOOLS TOMORROW, 23 MARCH.

THE PRESIDENT ATTENDED A SECURITY COUNCIL MEETING AT NATINO PALACE AND THE MILITARY COMMANDERS TALKED WITH JOURNALISTS WHEN LEAVING THE PREMISES. DEFENSE MINISTER OSCAR BOTERO SAID THAT THE MEDELLIN CARTEL PLANNED AND CARRIED OUT THE ASSASSINATION UPON INSTRUCTIONS FROM PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, WHO MADE A DOWN PAYMENT OF 300,000 PESOS TO ANDRES ARTURO GUTIERREZ, THE ASSASSIN HIRED TO PERPETRATE THE CRIME.

THE ASSASSIN, A 16-YEAR-OLD YOUTH, IS RECOVERING FROM HIS WOUNDS AND, IN A PRELIMINARY DECLARATION TO THE AUTHORITIES, HE CONFIRMED WHO ORDERED THE ASSASSINATION.

MOREOVER, DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] DETECTIVE EDISON SANCHEZ MENDIETA, WHO WAS WOUNDED THIS MORNING AT THE AIRPORT TERMINAL, WAS RELEASED THIS AFTERNOON.

REFERRING TO THE WAY IN WHICH THE WEAPON WAS SMUGGLED INTO THE AIRPORT, THE AUTHORITIES SAID THAT THIS ISSUE IS BEING THOROUGHLY INVESTIGATED BY SECURITY ORGANIZATIONS -- BECAUSE IT COULD HAVE BEEN ASSEMBLED INSIDE THE PREMISES OR SMUGGLED IN WITH THE COMPLICITY OF A MAINTENANCE WORKER.

RIOTS, CLASHES, AND THE BURNING OF TIRES AND FIVE BUSES WAS REPORTED IN SEVERAL HIGHER EDUCATION CENTERS OF BOGOTA, SUCH AS THE FREE UNIVERSITY, THE PEDAGOGICAL UNIVERSITY, THE NATIONAL UNIVERSITY; AND IN NEIGHBORHOODS SUCH AS POLICARPA SALAVARRIETA, GARCES NAVAS, AND SOACHA. THESE ACTIONS RESULTED IN THE WOUNDING OF A POLICEMAN, WHOSE CONDITION IS STILL CRITICAL.

TEACHERS WHO ARE MEMBERS OF FECODE [COLOMBIAN FEDERATION OF EDUCATORS] HAVE ORDERED A TWO-DAY STRIKE STARTING TOMORROW. BANANA FARM WORKERS IN URABA, WHERE THE ASSASSINATED LEADER WORKED AS A LABOR LAWYER, REACTED SIMILARLY.

TRANSPORTATION ACTIVITIES HAVE NOTICEABLY DECREASED IN THE CAPITAL SINCE THE MAYOR URGED THE CITIZENRY TO GO HOME EARLY IN THE EVENING.

THE ASSASSINATED CANDIDATE'S BODY IS CURRENTLY LYING IN STATE IN THE OVAL ROOM OF THE NATIONAL CONGRESS.

DEV-MUC3-1186 (SYNCHRONETICS)

MEDELLIN, 23 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] DIEGO MONTANA CUELLAR, PRESIDENT OF THE PATRIOTIC UNION [UP], HAS RECEIVED A LETTER SIGNED BY PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA, IN WHICH HE EMPHATICALLY DENIES ANY PARTICIPATION IN THE ASSASSINATION OF BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA.

THE LETTER, WHICH CARRIES ESCOBAR GAVIRIA'S SIGNATURE AND FINGERPRINT, WAS ALSO SENT TO THE MEDELLIN MEDIA.

IN HIS LETTER TO THE UP, ESCOBAR GAVIRIA STATED: I ALWAYS LIKED, ADMIRED, AND RESPECTED BERNARDO JARAMILLO.

ESCOBAR GAVIRIA DISCLOSED THAT HE MET SEVERAL TIMES TO INTERCEDE WITH GONZALO RODRIGUEZ GACHA TO ENSURE THAT JARAMILLO OSSA'S LIFE WOULD BE RESPECTED. ESCOBAR GAVIRIA ADDED: THIS CAN BE CONFIRMED BY MANY MEMBERS OF JARAMILLO OSSA'S POLITICAL MOVEMENT AND EVEN BY SOME OF HIS DAS [ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY] BODYGUARDS WHO WERE WITNESSES AT THOSE MEETINGS. [SENTENCE AS HEARD]

IN HIS LETTER TO MONTANA CUELLAR, ESCOBAR GAVIRIA SAID HE WAS AMAZED BY HOW EASILY AND QUICKLY THE GOVERNMENT HAS FOUND SOMEONE TO BLAME.

STATE SECURITY AGENCY SPOKESMEN SAID ON 22 MARCH THAT THEY HAVE PROOF LINKING ESCOBAR GAVIRIA TO THE ASSASSINATION. THE ASSOCIATED PRESS [AP] HAS ALSO RECEIVED TELEPHONE CALLS IN WHICH AN ALLEGED SPOKESMEN OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL CLAIMED RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ASSASSINATION OF JARAMILLO OSSA.

IN HIS LETTER TO THE UP, ESCOBAR GAVIRIA DISAVOWS THOSE CALLS, STATING: WHY SHOULD I ATTACK SOMEONE WHO WAS FIRMLY OPPOSED TO COLOMBIA SURRENDERING TO THE UNITED STATES?

DEV-MUC3-1188 (SYNCHRONETICS)

LIMA, 16 MAR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] IT WAS REPORTED TODAY THAT MEMBERS OF THE PEASANT DEFENSE PATROL KILLED, WITH CLUBS AND MACHETES, THREE PEASANTS ALLEGEDLY INVOLVED WITH TERRORISTS AND KIDNAPPED 17 OTHERS IN A TOWN OF THE ANDEAN PROVINCE OF AYACUCHO, 576 KM SOUTHEAST OF LIMA.

WITNESSES TOLD THE POLICE THAT AT LEAST 300 MILITIAMEN FROM THE VICHOS AND CONDORAY DISTRICTS, 17 KM FROM AYACUCHO, ATTACKED THE SANTA BARBARA VILLAGE EARLY ON 15 MARCH AND OVERPOWERED THE RESIDENTS WITH MACHETES AND CLUBS.

WITNESSES SAID THAT THE MILITIA MEMBERS KILLED BROTHERS EFRAIN, ISAAC, AND MAXIMO PRADO, ON CHARGES OF BEING LINKED WITH SHINING PATH TERRORISTS, AND KIDNAPPED 17 ALLEGED SHINING PATH TERRORISTS WHO WERE TAKEN TO AN UNKNOWN PLACE.

ACCORDING TO THE POLICE AT LEAST 40 "MEMBERS OF THE PEASANT DEFENSE PATROL" FROM VICHOS AND CONDORAY DIED IN A CLASH WITH TERRORISTS IN JANUARY. THE TERRORISTS THEN HEADED FOR THE NEIGHBORING TOWN OF SANTA BARBARA, WHERE PEASANTS ALLEGEDLY HELPED THEM.

THE SOURCE SAID THAT "IF THE CHARGE MADE BY THE PEASANTS IS PROVEN TO BE TRUE, THE REASON FOR THE ATTACK COULD BE IN RETALIATION FOR THE GREAT NUMBER OF PEASANT DEFENSE PATROL MEMBERS KILLED TWO MONTHS AGO."

THE SO-CALLED "PEASANT DEFENSE PATROLS" WERE CREATED BY THE ARMY FOUR YEARS AGO TO STRUGGLE AGAINST SHINING PATH TERRORISTS IN DISTANT PLACES WHICH LACK SECURITY FORCES.

THE NATIONAL POLICE HAVE REPORTED THAT A LARGE NUMBER OF PEOPLE APPARENTLY DIED IN A CLASH BETWEEN A POLICE PATROL AND A COLUMN OF TERRORISTS IN THE INTERIOR OF THE ANDEAN PROVINCE OF TARMA, 350 KM EAST OF LIMA.

THE SOURCE SAID THE FIREFIGHT EARLY YESTERDAY LASTED SEVERAL HOURS AND THAT IT WAS NOT POSSIBLE TO KNOW HOW MANY PEOPLE DIED IN THE CLASH DUE TO THE POOR COMMUNICATIONS SYSTEMS.

SENATOR ENRIQUE BERNALEZ, WHO SPECIALIZES IN POLITICAL VIOLENCE, TODAY REPORTED THAT TERRORISM HAS CLAIMED THE LIVES OF AT LEAST 607 PERUVIAN SO FAR THIS YEAR, INCLUDING CIVILIANS AND MILITARY.

DEV-MUC3-1191 (SYNCHRONETICS)

LIMA, 16 MAR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE MAOIST SHINING PATH TERRORIST ORGANIZATION AND THE TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA) ARE STAGING ATTACKS IN AN ATTEMPT TO MAKE THE PEOPLE BOYCOTT THE 8 APRIL PERUVIAN ELECTIONS.

A BOMB EXPLODED EARLY THIS MORNING NEAR THE HOUSE OF HEALTH MINISTER PAUL CARO GAMARRA. CARO'S WIFE SAID THAT THE HOUSE, WHICH IS IN THE PORT OF EL CALLAO, LACKS POLICE PROTECTION.

THE HEADQUARTERS OF THE CENTER-RIGHTIST DEMOCRATIC FRONT (FREDEMO), WHOSE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE IS THE WRITER MARIO VARGAS LLOSA, WAS BOMBED LAST NIGHT. THE MRTA CLAIMED THE ATTACK THROUGH LEAFLETS LEFT AT THE SCENE.

THE MRTA ALSO PLANTED EXPLOSIVES AND LEFT LEAFLETS BESIDE FIVE FREDEMO PLACARDS.

FORTY MEMBERS OF FREDEMO WERE AT THE HEADQUARTERS, WHICH IS ON AN IMPORTANT LIMA AVENUE, WHEN THE ATTACK OCCURRED. NOBODY WAS INJURED. DAVID CIFUENTES, A DEPUTY CANDIDATE OF THE RULING AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE (APRA) TODAY SAID THAT THERE IS A TERRORIST PLOT TO KILL THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES.

ON 14 MARCH CIFUENTES ESCAPED UNHARMED FROM AN ATTACK ON THE CAR IN WHICH HE WAS TRAVELLING. HIS BODYGUARD DIED IN THE ATTACK WHICH OCCURRED 40 KM FROM THE CITY OF CAJAMARCA.

THE TERRORISTS PLACED BIG STONES AT A CURVE IN THE ROAD WHICH CAUSED THE VEHICLE TO RUN OFF THE ROAD. THE ATTACKERS THEN OPENED FIRE ON THE CAR.

CIFUENTES FELL OUT OF THE VEHICLE AND BROKE HIS ARM IN TWO PLACES, AND IS NOW IN HOSPITAL.

SHINING PATH MEMBERS RECENTLY MURDERED 19 PEOPLE, INCLUDING 10 CHILDREN, IN A SMALL VILLAGE NEAR HUANCAYO CITY, 415 KM SOUTH OF LIMA. THIS ACT CLEARLY SHOWS THAT THE MAOISTS ARE DETERMINED TO CONTINUE KILLING AND DESTROYING.

SOME 300 PEOPLE WERE MURDERED BY THE SHINING PATH DURING THE BOYCOTT OF THE MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS ON 12 NOVEMBER 1989.

THE ATTACKS PERPETRATED BY THE MRTA LAST NIGHT BELIES THE ALLEGED ANNOUNCEMENT THAT THEY WILL CEASE TO USE VIOLENCE. THIS ANNOUNCEMENT WAS PUBLISHED BY A LOCAL NEWSPAPER TWO DAYS AGO.

UNITED LEFT DEPUTY GUSTAVO ESPINOSA, IN A STATEMENT TO THE DAILY ONDA, SAID THAT IF THE MRTA IS TRULY SEEKING A POLITICAL WAY TO TURN IN THEIR WEAPONS "THEY WOULD CONTRIBUTE TO THE PACIFICATION OF THE COUNTRY."

HOWEVER, ESPINOSA SAID THAT ONE CANNOT CONSIDER AN END TO THE VIOLENCE UNTIL THERE IS MORE PROOF OF THEIR ANNOUNCEMENT.

DURING THE PAST 10 YEARS, THE SHINING PATH AND THE MRTA HAVE PERPETRATED MORE THAN 16,000 ATTACKS WHICH HAVE CAUSED DAMAGE ESTIMATED AT $10,000. THIS ESTIMATE WAS PREPARED BY THE CONGRESSIONAL COMMISSION IN CHARGE OF ASSESSING THE EFFECTS AND CAUSES OF POLITICAL VIOLENCE IN PERU.

DURING PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA'S TERM OF OFFICE THE TERRORISTS HAVE PERPETRATED 10,621 ATTACKS, WHICH REPRESENTS AN AVERAGE OF MORE THAN SIX ATTACKS PER DAY DURING HIS FIVE YEARS IN POWER.

FATAL VICTIMS OF POLITICAL VIOLENCE AMOUNT TO APPROXIMATELY 19,000, OF WHICH 700 HAVE DIED DURING 1990.

DEV-MUC3-1192 (SYNCHRONETICS)

CLANDESTINE, 22 MAR 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] IN PREVIOUS BROADCASTS WE REPORTED HONDURAN TROOP INCURSIONS INTO SALVADORAN TERRITORY. WE HAVE RECEIVED NEW REPORTS OF SUCH INCURSIONS.

HONDURAN TROOPS ENTERED 2 KM INSIDE SALVADORAN TERRITORY, IN ZANCUDO VILLAGE, IN THE AREA OF SABANETAS CANTON, PERQUIN JURISDICTION, AT 1200 ON 19 MARCH. THEY TOOK 22-YEAR-OLD GILBERTO MOLASCO, SON OF PATRICIO RODRIGUEZ, AND 17-YEAR-OLD ANDRES ARGUETA, SON OF EMIMESIO ARGUETA. THEY WERE TAKEN FROM THEIR HOMES AND THEIR WHEREABOUTS ARE UNKNOWN.

ON 17 MARCH, THE TROOPS ARRIVED IN PALO BLANCO VILLAGE AND THEY SEARCHED THE HOUSE OF LEONOR VELIZ, THREATING TO CAPTURE HER SON, CRISTIANO BENITEZ. THEY BEAT HIM UP, ACCUSING HIM OF BEING A GUERRILLA, AND THEY STOLE THEIR DOCUMENTS AND MONEY. THEY ALSO TOLD THEM NOT TO REPORT THE ACTION TO THE RED CROSS, THREATING TO KILL THEM IF THEY DID SO.

THE RESIDENTS OF THESE BORDER VILLAGES ISSUE AN APPEAL TO THE INTERNATIONAL HUMAN RIGHTS ORGANIZATIONS BECAUSE THEY ARE CONCERNED ABOUT THE FATE OF THE TWO YOUTHS CAPTURED BY HONDURAN ARMY TROOPS.

DEV-MUC3-1194 (SYNCHRONETICS)

CARACAS (VENEZUELA), 11 MAR 90 (EL NACIONAL) -- [REPORT] [OJEDA] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] ACCORDING TO OFFICIAL GN REPORTS, VENEZUELA, WHERE BANKING IS LOSELY CONTROLLED AND NO LAWS AGAINST MONEY LAUNDERING EXIST, A SYSTEM OR DEPARTMENT OF FINANCIAL INVESTIGATIONS IS TO BE ESTABLISHED.

GN COMMANDER GENERAL MANUEL IBEDACA ROMERO AGREED TO TALK ABOUT THE TOPIC DURING A RECENT INTERVIEW WITH EL NACIONAL.

[OJEDA] GENERAL, MUCH HAS BEEN SAID ABOUT VENEZUELA'S ALLEGED VULNERABILTY TO THE INTERNATIONAL DRUG TRAFFICKING CARTELS. IS THIS TRUE? IS THERE A DANGER THAT VENEZUELA COULD BECOME AN OPERATIONAL BASE FOR THE COCAINE MAFIA? IS IT TRUE THAT HEAVY INVESTMENTS HAVE BEEN DETECTED NEAR THE BORDER AND OTHER AREAS OF THE COUNTRY, WITH MONEY OF WHICH NO ONE KNOWS THE SOURCE? WHAT IS BEING DONE TO CONTROL THIS FLOW OF CAPITAL?

[IBEDACA] I SHARE THIS CONCERN. IT IS VERY SIMPLE: WHEN YOU ARE IN A BUILDING OR A HOUSE AND THERE ARE PROBLEMS IN YOUR NEIGHBOR'S HOUSE, THIS OF COURSE DIRECTLY AFFECTS YOU BECAUSE OF THE UNREST, BECAUSE THERE MIGHT BE AN UNCOMFORTABLE SITUATION WHERE FOR EXAMPLE, YOU MIGHT HAVE TO TESTIFY.

IBEDACA THUS BEGINS HIS EXPLANATIONS WITH A SIMPLE, EASY-TO-UNDERSTAND DOMESTIC ANALOGY. HE ADMITS THAT VENEZUELA "IS IN A SITUATION THAT SHOULD REALLY CATCH OUR ATTENTION, BECAUSE VENEZUELA BORDERS COLOMBIA AND WE KNOW THAT COCA IS PRODUCED MAINLY IN BOLIVIA, PERU, ECUADOR, AND IS PROCESSED IN COLOMBIA. COLOMBIA IS AMERICA'S GREAT COCAINE LABORATORY. DRUG TRAFFICKERS HAVE RECENTLY SUFFERED HARD SETBACKS THROUGH RECENT ACTIONS BY THE COLOMBIAN ARMY AND NATIONAL POLICE IN WHICH THE HEADS OF THESE ORGANIZATIONS HAVE BEEN KILLED AND GREAT AMOUNTS OF MONEY AND COCAINE AND A NUMBER OF AIRPLANES HAVE BEEN SEIZED. TO TRANSPORT WHAT IS LEFT, THEY WILL, OF COURSE, HAVE TO LOOK FOR A BETTER PLACE AND THIS IS WHERE WE HAVE SEVERAL VULNERABILITIES."

[OJEDA] LIKE WHAT?

[IBEDACA] THE EXTENSIVE BORDER, THE PLAINS NEAR IT WITH CLANDESTINE LANDING STRIPS; THE PROXIMITY TO EASY-TO-USE PORTS AND AIRPORTS. THROUGH THE ANTIDRUG TRAFFICKING SERVICES AND TOGETHER WITH THE DISIP [DIRECTORATE OF INTELLIGENCE AND PREVENTION SERVICES] AND THE METROPOLITAN POLICE, WE HAVE A PLAN AND WE HAVE TAKEN DEFINITE ACTIONS TO FIGHT IT. AWARE OF THIS, WE HAVE ESTABLISHED A SYSTEM OF INVESTMENT CONTROLS IN THESE STATES NEAR COLOMBIA. WE ARE RECEIVING REPORTS OF PROPERTY REGISTRATIONS, BUT WE NEED TO TAKE MORE EFFECTIVE MEASURES, BECAUSE WE NEED GREATER CONTROL AND SUPERVISION IN THIS AREA, ESPECIALLY COMMERCIAL OPERATIONS.

IN 1986, THREE YEARS AFTER THE DRUG LAW WENT INTO EFFECT, THE GN'S ANTIDRUG DIVISION MADE A RECORD CONFISCATION OF 29,698 KILOS OF MARIJUANA (NEARLY 30 TONS), A FIGURE THAT DROPPED SIGNIFICANTLY IN 1988, AND INCREASED IN 1989.

SINCE IT WAS FOUNDED BY GENERAL GERMAN SEPULVEDA SIERRA, THIS OFFICE HAS BEEN IN CHARGE OF COORDINATING AND PLANNING ACTIONS THAT THE GN DEVELOPS AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING, EVEN THOUGH IT IS LIMITED BY THE DRUG LAW AS AN ADJUNCT TO THE TRIBUNALS. IN OTHER WORDS, THE FILES MUST BE TURNED OVER TO THE JUDICIAL TECHNICAL POLICE [PTJ].

IT IS CURRENTLY CALLED THE DIRECTORATE OF THE SERVICES AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKING AND IS DIRECTED BY BRIGADIER GENERAL RAMON GUILLEN DAVILA, WHO ALSO AGREED TO TALK TO EL NACIONAL.

[GUILLEN] THE FIGHT AGAINST DRUGS HAS BEEN A JOB OF THE GN DURING ALL OF ITS EXISTENCE. I HAVE BEEN IN IT SINCE I WAS A SUBLIEUTENANT. NOW IT IS CALLED THE "MODERN CRIME" AND ONE OF THE MOST DIFFICULT WARS TO FIGHT.

[OJEDA] PRECISELY BECAUSE OF THAT WAR, THE BIG COLOMBIAN TRAFFICKERS HAVE PROPOSED TO THEIR COUNTRY'S GOVERNMENT FORMULAS TO ACHIEVE PEACE AND RETIRE FROM THE DRUG BUSINESS. ARE THESE PROPOSALS FROM THE DRUG CARTELS SINCERE? WE ASKED THE GENERAL.

[GUILLEN] I THINK THAT IT IS ONLY A STRATEGY TO GAIN TIME AND SEEK THEIR OWN SOLUTIONS. IT IS NOT STRANGE THAT THEY ARE PRETENDING TO TURN VENEZUELA INTO AN "OPERATIONAL BASE." THERE IS DEMOCRACY AND LIBERTY OF MOVEMENT AND INVESTMENT HERE. IN JUST SAN ANTONIO DEL TACHIRA, THERE ARE 76 EXCHANGE HOUSES AND ONLY ONE MEETS THE REQUIREMENTS OF THE LAW. WHEN WE HAVE PRESSURED THE PERACAL TAX REGISTRY, WE GOT COMPLAINTS FROM A LOT OF PEOPLE. THE VENEZUELAN AIR AND HIGHWAY SYSTEM IS VERY FAVORABLE TO THEM. NEIGHBORING COUNTRIES CONNECT WITH EUROPE THROUGH VENEZUELA. A LOT OF MERCHANDISE GOES THROUGH IN TRANSIT, AND WHEN THEY SEIZE A SHIPMENT, WHAT THEY SAY IS THAT THE AIRPLANE "CAME FROM VENEZUELA." [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1195 (SYNCHRONETICS)

LIMA, 27 MAR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE ATTACKS ON FIVE OFFICES OF THE DEMOCRATIC FRONT (FREDEMO), WHICH IS HEADED BY MARIO VARGAS LLOSA, ON THE OFFICE OF THE RULING AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE, APRA, AND AGAINST ONE TELEPHONE EXCHANGE, TWO BANKS, ONE STORE, AND ONE MOVIE THEATER, SHOW THAT TERRORISM IN PERU CONTINUES TO BE USED IN AN ATTEMPT TO BOYCOTT THE 8 APRIL ELECTIONS.

ONE GIRL WAS WOUNDED DURING THE EXPLOSIONS THAT OCCURRED IN LIMA YESTERDAY, AND FOUR INDIVIDUALS WERE ARRESTED WHILE LOOTING TWO SHOE STORES AND A MARKET AND URGING PEOPLE TO JOIN THEM.

THE ATTACKS SERIOUSLY DAMAGED THE OFFICES OF THE POLITICAL PARTIES, ESPECIALLY THAT OF THE FREDEMO, BUT NO ONE WAS INJURED.

THE PAGINA LIBRE NEWSPAPER TODAY REPORTED THAT SEVEN ALLEGED MEMBERS OF THE MOVEMENT OF THE REVOLUTIONARY LEFT (MIR) WERE ARRESTED IN THE CITY OF TRUJILLO, 570 KM NORTH OF LIMA. THE MIR IS A FACTION OF THE PRO-GUEVARA TUPAC AMARU REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT (MRTA).

THE MAOIST SHINING PATH TERRORIST ORGANIZATION HAS CALLED FOR "AN ARMED STRIKE" -- A STRIKE UNDER THREAT OF DEATH -- IN LIMA TOMORROW. THIS IS THE THIRD ARMED STRIKE TO BE CALLED BY THIS ORGANIZATION SO FAR THIS MONTH.

A 48-HOUR ARMED STRIKE WAS CALLED IN AYACUCHO, THE BIRTHPLACE OF THE SHINING PATH ORGANIZATION AND THE OTHER ONE IN HUANTA.

PRESIDENT ALAN GARCIA YESTERDAY DELIVERED 170 PATROL CARS TO THE NATIONAL POLICE. HE URGED THE POLICE TO RESOLUTELY FACE THE INCREASING WAVE OF TERRORISM AND TO MAKE USE OF ALL AVAILABLE RESOURCES.

THE NATIONAL POLICE YESTERDAY COMMISSIONED A SQUAD OF 16 MOTORCYCLES TO PATROL THE CITY AND TO GO DIRECTLY TO THE SITES OF ATTACKS.

IT IS EXPECTED THAT SUBVERSIVES WILL INCREASE THE NUMBER OF ATTACKS IN A WAVE OF TERROR BEFORE THE ELECTIONS AND THIS IS WHY THE POLICE AND MILITARY FORCES HAVE BEEN PUT ON ALERT.

ABOUT 100,000 POLICEMEN HAVE BEEN PUT ON ALERT THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY FOLLOWING THE MURDER LAST WEEK OF FOUR CANDIDATES FOR DEPUTIES, AN APRA LEADER, AND THE MANAGERS OF SEVERAL BUSINESSES IN LIMA, AND OTHER CITIES.

LIMA AND CALLAO HAVE BEEN PLACED IN A STATE OF EMERGENCY, WHICH MEANS THAT INDIVIDUAL GUARANTEES HAVE BEEN SUSPENDED.

YESTERDAY AYACUCHO WAS LEFT IN DARKNESS AFTER A SHINING PATH ATTACK. AT LEAST THREE PEOPLE WERE KILLED, SEVERAL WERE WOUNDED, AND VARIOUS ARRESTS WERE MADE BY THE POLICE.

YESTERDAY WAS THE MOST VIOLENT DAY IN AYACUCHO SINCE LAST NOVEMBER WHEN MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS WERE HELD. THE ELECTIONS WERE THEN ANNULLED BECAUSE OF THE HIGH NUMBER OF NULL AND BLANK VOTES.

LAST WEEK IN HUANCAYO, 415 KM SOUTHEAST OF LIMA, AN APRA CANDIDATE FOR DEPUTY WAS MURDERED. YESTERDAY AN INDIVIDUAL WAS WOUNDED WHEN A CAR BOMB EXPLODED CAUSING EXTENSIVE MATERIAL DAMAGE.

YESTERDAY IN CHICLAYO, IN NORTHERN PERU, A BOMB WAS THROWN AT THE HOUSE OF FREDEMO CANDIDATE FOR DEPUTY MIGUEL ANGEL BARTRA, WHO WAS NOT IN THE HOUSE AT THE TIME.

IN LA LIBERTAD DEPARTMENT A TERRORIST GROUP TOOK OVER THE GUADALUPITO TOWN EARLY YESTERDAY MORNING IN AN EFFORT TO FIND THE LOCAL APRA SECRETARY GENERAL AND THE TOWN'S MAYOR.

WHEN THE TERRORISTS COULD NOT FIND THEM, THEY BLEW UP THE OFFICES OF THE MUNICIPALITY AND THE POWER STATION CAUSING AN OUTAGE IN THE ZONE.

THE STRIKES AFFECTING 100,000 WORKERS IN THE COUNTRY CONTINUE AND THE STRIKERS HAVE REJECTED THE "LABOR TRUCE" UNTIL THE ELECTIONS ARE OVER THAT HAD BEEN REQUESTED BY INTERIOR MINISTER AGUSTIN MANTILLA.

MANTILLA SAID THAT THE STRIKES "ARE BORDERING ON THE SEDITIOUS AND THE CRIMINAL."

IN THE LAST 10 YEARS POLITICAL VIOLENCE IN PERU HAS CAUSED 19,000 DEATHS, OF WHICH 700 HAVE OCCURRED SO FAR THIS YEAR.

DEV-MUC3-1197 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, 29 MAR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE REFORMIST SECTOR OF THE LEFTIST PATRIOTIC UNION (UP) TODAY RESIGNED FROM THE PARTY'S NATIONAL COORDINATING BOARD, CREATING AN UNPRECEDENTED CRISIS IN ITS FIVE YEARS OF POLITICAL LIFE.

DURING THE SECOND DAY OF ITS PLENUM, TWELVE OF ITS 20 MEMBERS, INCLUDING UP PRESIDENT DIEGO MONTANA CUELLAR, RESIGNED FROM THE NATIONAL COORDINATING BOARD, WHICH ALSO INCLUDES ACTIVISTS OF THE COMMUNIST PARTY OF COLOMBIA (PCC).

ACCORDING TO SOURCES CLOSE TO THE UP, THE REFORMIST FACTION RESIGNED FROM THE COORDINATING BOARD BECAUSE IT BELIEVES THAT WHAT IS NEEDED IN COLOMBIA IS A BROAD SOCIAL DEMOCRATIC MOVEMENT, SUCH AS THAT ADVOCATED BY UP PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE BERNARDO JARAMILLO OSSA, WHO WAS ASSASSINATED ON 22 MARCH.

THE LEFTIST SOURCES CONSULTED BY EFE INDICATED TODAY THAT THE POSSIBILITY OF PARTICIPATING IN THE 27 MAY PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONS, AT LEAST WITH A JOINT UP AND PCC CANDIDATE, IS GROWING MORE DISTANT.

WHILE THE UP'S REFORMIST FACTION REJECTS THE ARMED PATH AS A MEANS TO ACHIEVE POWER, THE SECTOR KNOWN AS THE RADICALS, IN OTHER WORDS, THE EIGHT MEMBERS WHO DID NOT RESIGN FROM THE COORDINATING BOARD, AGREE ON USING DIFFERENT FORMS OF STRUGGLE, INCLUDING GUERRILLA STRUGGLE.

THE EIGHT MEMBERS WHO DID NOT RESIGN BELONG TO THE PCC.

IN ADDITION TO MONTANA, LEADERS ANGELINO GARZON, GUILLERMO BANGUERO, ALBERTO ROJAS PUYO, JULIO SANTANA, AND LUIS EMIRO VALENCIA WERE AMONG THOSE WHO RESIGNED.

AT THE SAME TIME, 12 MEMBERS OF THE NATIONAL COMMITTEE, ANOTHER SECTION OF THE PARTY, ALSO RESIGNED. THEY ARE ALSO FROM THE REFORMIST FACTION.

THE FRICTION WITH THE REFORMISTS OR PERESTROYKA SUPPORTERS BEGAN ON 28 MARCH, THE FIRST DAY OF SESSIONS OF THE PLENUM, WHEN ANGELINO GARZON CHARGED THAT THE PCC HAD INTERCEPTED JARAMILLO OSSA'S LETTERS.

ANOTHER REASON FOR THE DIVISION WITHIN THE COLOMBIAN LEFT WAS THE NOT VERY FAVORABLE RESULTS IN THE 11 MARCH LEGISLATIVE AND MUNICIPAL ELECTIONS, WHEN THE UP AND THE PCC LOST SEVERAL SEATS IN THE COLOMBIAN CONGRESS.

UP TO 22 MARCH, THE DAY WHEN JARAMILLO WAS ASSASSINATED, HE WAS THE SINGLE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE OF THE UP AND THE PCC, BUT AFTER HIS DEATH, BOTH PARTIES AGREED TO HOLD A PLENUM TO DECIDE WHETHER THEY WILL PARTICIPATE IN THE ELECTIONS.

DEV-MUC3-1198 (SYNCHRONETICS)

MOSCOW (USSR), 27 MAR 90 -- [COMMENTARY] [LEONID LEVCHENKO] [TEXT] OBVIOUS PROGRESS HAS BEEN MADE IN SOLVING THE REGIONAL CONFLICT IN CENTRAL AMERICA. VENEZUELAN PRESIDENT CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ WILL MEDIATE A MEETING IN CARACAS BETWEEN SALVADORAN REBELS AND A GOVERNMENT DELEGATION. CONFIDENTIAL NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN GUATEMALAN GUERRILLAS AND REPRESENTATIVES OF THE NATIONAL RECONCILIATION COMMISSION WILL ALSO BE HELD IN THE NORWEGIAN CAPITAL, OSLO.

LISTEN WHAT OUR COMMENTATOR LEONID LEVCHEKO HAS TO SAY:

THESE TWO MEETINGS HAVE ONE POINT IN COMMON: BOTH HAVE BEEN MADE POSSIBLE THANKS TO THE INITIATIVE AND THE MEDIATION OF THE MOST DIVERSE CIRCLES, WHICH ARE INTERESTED IN PUTTING OUT THE FIRE IN CENTRAL AMERICA. THE CARACAS MEETING COINCIDES WITH THE START TODAY OF THE OFFICIAL VISIT BY SALVADORAN PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI.

VENEZUELAN CHIEF OF STATE CARLOS ANDRES PEREZ, WHO WELCOMED CRISTIANI, HAS ALREADY HELD TALKS WITH THE SALVADORAN REBELS DELEGATION.

THE VENEZUELAN CHIEF OF STATE WILL ACT AS MEDIATOR IN THE DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND THE REBELS WHEN THEY SIT AT THE NEGOTIATING TABLE. THE OSLO MEETING WAS CONCEIVED AT THE INITIATIVE OF THE LUTHERAN AND CATHOLIC CHURCHES. THIS IS A BIG ADVANCE IF ONE CONSIDERS THAT THE FIRST AND LAST DIRECT NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT AND THE GUERRILLAS TOOK PLACE IN OCTOBER 1987 IN SPAIN. THEY WERE THEN SUSPENDED AND NEVER RESUMED.

[PASSAGE INDISTINCT] BUT IT HAS NOT BEEN EASY TO ADVANCE TOWARD NATIONAL RECONCILIATION IN ALL THE COUNTRIES INVOLVED IN THE CENTRAL AMERICAN CONFLICT. BEFORE THE ESQUIPULAS AGREEMENT WAS SIGNED IN 1967 BY THE CENTRAL AMERICAN PRESIDENTS, MANY INTERNATIONAL FORCES, WHICH HINDERED A SOLUTION, WERE INVOLVED IN THE CENTRAL AMERICAN CONFLICT.

THE MILITARY CHIEFS OF EL SALVADOR AND GUATEMALA ALSO REJECTED THE NEGOTIATION PROCESS, ASSUMING THAT THEY COULD DEFEAT THE REBEL MOVEMENT. IN FACT, DURING 10 YEARS OF CIVIL WAR MORE THAN 70,000 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KILLED IN EL SALVADOR AND IN NEARLY 30 YEARS OF CONFLICT IN GUATEMALA MORE THAN 100,000 HAVE BEEN KILLED.

IT IS OBVIOUS THAT THE FRATRICIDAL WAR IS ABSURD BOTH IN EL SALVADOR AND IN GUATEMALA. IT IS TIME THAT, FOLLOWING THE EXAMPLE OF NICARAGUA, OTHER COUNTRIES CONTRIBUTE TO RESTORE PEACE IN THE AREA. THIS IS WHY THE REPORTS COMING FROM CARACAS AND OSLO HAVE BEEN GREETED WITH GREAT INTEREST. IT IS CLEAR THAT A JUST SOLUTION IS POSSIBLE IN CENTRAL AMERICA IF ONLY THE PRINCIPLES OF INTERNATIONAL LAW ARE STRICTLY FOLLOWED AND THE COUNTRIES' SOVEREIGNTY IS RESPECTED BY NOT MEDDLING IN THE INTERNAL AFFAIRS OF OTHER STATES.

THIS IS THE ESSENCE OF THE SOVIET VIEW ON CENTRAL AMERICA.

DEV-MUC3-1199 (SYNCHRONETICS)

NO CITY, NO DATE (FBIS) -- [TEXT] BOGOTA DOMESTIC SERVICE IN SPANISH AT 0230 GMT BEGINS TO BROADCAST LIVE OR RECORDED A SPEECH BY PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO VARGAS FROM THE NARINO PALACE IN BOGOTA. RECEPTION IS FAIR TO POOR.

BARCO BEGINS HIS ADDRESS BY EXPRESSING HIS CONCERN OVER THE DISNFORMATION CAMPAIGN SURROUNDING THE RECENT EVENTS THAT HAVE TAKEN PLACE. HE GOES ON TO CITE THE VARIOUS ITEMS BEING PUBLISHED BY THE COUNTRY'S MEDIA CONCERNING SECRET DEALINGS WITH DRUG TRAFFICKERS, A RELAXATION OF ACTIONS AGAINST THE DRUG TRAFFICKERS, AND OTHER STORIES WHICH HE INSISTS ARE NOT TRUE.

HE BLAMES NARCOTERRORISM FOR THE VIOLENCE AND CONFUSION WARNS THAT SOME PEOPLE ARE BEGINNING TO BLAME THE GOVERNMENT. BARCO NOTES THAT THE GOVERNMENT RESPECTS THE MEDIA AND SUGGESTS THAT PUBLIC OPINION IS BEING MANIPULATED. HE THEN TOUCHES ON THE CONTROVERSY REGARDING THE KIDNAPPING OF THE SON OF THE SECRETARY GENERAL OF THE PRESIDENCY. BARCO SAYS: "THE GOVERNMENT, IN THE CASE OF THE KIDNAPPING OF DR. MONTOYA'S SON, AS ON OTHER UNFORTUNATE OCCASIONS, INCLUDING THE CASES OF DR. ANDRES PASTRANA AND DR. ALVARO GOMEZ, AND EVEN CASES IN WHICH MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN KDNAPPED BY SUBVERSIVES, HAS CONSIDERED AS APPROPRIATE AND VALUABLE THE EFFORTS MADE BY THOSE WHO PERFORMED HUMANITARIAN DUTIES AND SHOWED GOOD WILL FOR THEIR RELEASE." HE ADDS THAT NEITHER THE SECURITY COUNCIL NOR THE PRESIDENT CAN BE PREVENTED FROM ASCERTAINING INFORMATION WHICH COULD LEAD TO THE RELEASE OF HOSTAGES.

BARCO SAYS THAT THE STRUGGLE AGAINST NARCOTERRORISM HAS NOT BEEN EASY. HE ADDS THAT KEEPING THE HOPES OF THE NATION ALIVE, RATHER THAN ENHANCING THE COUNTRY'S IMAGE, IS THE GOAL. HE ADDS THAT THE COUNTRY WILL NOT SURVIVE WITH ITS PROBLEMS, NOTING HIS UPCOMING EUROPEAN TRIP TO SPEAK OUT AGAINST THE DANGERS OF DRUG TRAFFICKING AND TO REAFFIRM THE COUNTRY'S GOOD NAME.

IN ENDING HIS ADDRESS, BARCO URGES CALM AND WARNS AGAINST DIVISION, ADDING THAT THIS IS THE GOAL OF THE ENEMIES OF THE FATHERLAND. HE URGES EVERYONE TO DEFEND THEIR DEMOCRACY.

BARCO ENDS HIS ADDRESS AT 0250 GMT.

FURTHER AS WARRANTED.

DEV-MUC3-1200 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, 31 MAR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [THE "EXTRADITABLES"] [TEXT] 1. ON 28 MARCH 1990, THE ARMY AND THE NATIONAL POLICE ELITE CORPS CARRIED OUT MILITARY OPERATIONS IN THE HIGHER PARTS OF ENVIGADO MUNICIPALITY.

2. IN SAID OPERATIONS, THE ELITE CORPS ARRESTED COLOMBIAN CITIZENS FREDDY LOPEZ OSPINA AND JOSE CRISTANTO RETAVISTA ARZON, WHO REMAIN MISSING.

3. IN THE PAST FEW MONTHS IN MEDELLIN, IT HAS BEEN THE CUSTOM OF THE ELITE CORPS TO ARREST PEOPLE AND TAKE THEM TO THE CARLOS HOLGUIN POLICE ACADEMY, WHERE THEY ARE TORTURED AND EXECUTED BY MEMBERS OF THE BOGOTA DIJIN [DIRECTORATE OF JUDICIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS], WHO ARE IN THE CAPITAL OF ANTIOQUIA.

4. WE HAVE DENOUNCED THESE EVENTS PUBLICLY ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS, BUT PRESIDENT BARCO HAS RESPONDED IN STATEMENTS TO THE PRESS THAT THOSE MEMBERS OF THE ELITE CORPS ARE DEFENDERS OF DEMOCRACY.

5. THE COMMANDER OF THE ELITE CORPS IN ANTIOQUIA, AND COLONEL PELAEZ, CHIEF OF THE BOGOTA DIJIN, ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE MURDER OF ALL OUR COMRADES AND FOR THE DISAPPEARANCE OF THE TWO AFOREMENTIONED CITIZENS.

6. IN PREVIOUS COMMUNIQUES, WE PUBLICLY REQUESTED THE CREATION OF SEPARATE PRISONS AND THE PERMANENT ESTABLISHMENT OF A BRANCH OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE IN SUCH PRISONS, BUT THE GOVERNMENT, AN ACCOMPLICE, HAS BEEN SILENT WITH REGARD TO OUR PROPOSALS.

7. IF THE CITIZENS WHO WERE ARRESTED IN ENVIGADO ARE NOT PRESENTED TO THEIR RESPECTIVE FAMILIES, IN REPRISAL WE WILL PLACE A BOMB CONTAINING 5,000 KG OF DYNAMITE IN ONE OF THE MAIN RESIDENTIAL NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE BOGOTA OLIGARCHY.

8. FOR EACH COLOMBIAN WHO IS TURNED OVER TO THE UNITED STATES, WE WILL PLACE A 5,000-KG BOMB IN THE CAPITAL OF THE REPUBLIC.

9. WE WILL EXECUTE PROGOVERNMENT JUDGES, TRAITOROUS POLITICIANS, TORTURERS, AND THE MAIN MEMBERS OF THE (CANO) FAMILY.

THE EXTRADITABLES, 30 MARCH 1990

DEV-MUC3-1202 (SYNCHRONETICS)

CLANDESTINE, 2 APR 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATEMENT] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] PRESIDENTS DANIEL ORTEGA SAAVEDRA, OSCAR ARIAS SANCHEZ, RAFAEL LEONARDO CALLEJAS, MARCO VINICIO CEREZO AREVELO, ALFREDO CRISTIANI:

IN EL SALVADOR A SERIOUS DIALOGUE-NEGOTIATION PROCESS HAS BEGUN THANKS TO THE MEDIATION OF THE UNITED NATIONS THROUGH ITS SECRETARY GENERAL MR. JAVIER PEREZ DE CUELLAR. THIS IMPLIES THAT ANY PEACE FORMULA MUST TAKE INTO ACCOUNT THIS NEGOTIATION PROCESS TO ENSURE THAT IT IS BASED ON OUR PARTICULAR REALITY AND THE GUARANTEES OFFERED BY THIS INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATION.

WE BELIEVE THAT THE NEGOTIATION'S MAIN OBJECTIVE SHOULD BE THE COUNTRY'S DEMOCRATIZATION, BECAUSE WHILE PEACEFUL CENTRAL AMERICAN AND WORLD DEVELOPMENTS ARE MARKED BY A CONSOLIDATION OF DEMOCRACY, EL SALVADOR IS QUITE FAR FROM EXPERIENCING THIS.

THE ARMY HOLDS SOCIETY'S REAL POWER. THIS PREVENTS JUSTICE BEING APPLIED IN THE HORRENDOUS ASSASSINATIONS OF MONSIGNOR ROMERO, JESUIT PRIESTS, FENASTRAS [SALVADORAN WORKERS NATIONAL UNION FEDERATION] MEMBERS, AND DR. HECTOR OQUELI. UNDER SUCH CONDITIONS, IMPUNITY CONTINUES TO BE INSTITUTIONALIZED AND IT IS NOT POSSIBLE TO ENFORCE RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS.

DAILY LIFE IS MARKED BY REPRESSION AGAINST THE POPULAR MOVEMENT AN FREQUENT MURDERS, WHILE ARENA [NATIONALIST REPUBLICAN ALLIANCE] APPLIES PRESSURES AND FORCES, BY VARIOUS MEANS, THE RESTRICTION OF INFORMATION TO THE MEDIA BY LIMITING FREEDOM OF SPEECH.

IT IS THEREFORE EVIDENT THAT EL SALVADOR IS THE COUNTRY THAT HAS FAILED TO COMPLY WITH THE MAIN GOALS OF ESQUIPULAS II -- THE ACHIEVEMENT OF NATIONAL RECONCILIATION, DEMOCRATIZATION, AND A NEGOTIATED POLITICAL SOLUTION.

THIS SITUATION, WHICH IS ACCOMPANIED BY A PERMANENT STATE OF SIEGE IS WORSENED BY GREAT RESTRICTIONS ON THE POLITICAL SYSTEM THAT PREVENT THE DEVELOPMENT OF CIVILIAN SOCIETY.

IT SUFFICES TO MENTION THE CASE OF THE ELECTORAL SYSTEM: IN NICARAGUA, A COUNTRY WITH HALF OF OUR COUNTRY'S POPULATION, THE SUPREME ELECTORAL COUNCIL REGISTERED 1.9 MILLION CITIZENS IN ONLY FOUR SUNDAYS; IN EL SALVADOR, IN EIGHT YEARS, THE ELECTORAL REGISTRY REGISTERED 1.6 MILLION CITIZENS FOR THE RECENT ELECTIONS AND ONLY 1 MILLION ACTUALLY VOTED. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1203 (SYNCHRONETICS)

CLANDESTINE, 2 APR 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [STATEMENT] [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GENERAL COMMAND] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] IN CONTRAST, EL SALVADOR, WHICH HAS THE SECOND LARGEST POPULATION IN CENTRAL AMERICA, HAS THE SMALLEST PARLIAMENT WITH ONLY 60 DEPUTIES.

THE SOCIAL CONFLICT IS WORSENED BY A WAR THAT NO ONE HAS WON. THE TIME HAS COME TO LET CIVILIAN SOCIETY WIN. TO ACHIEVE THAT WE REQUIRE:

-- THE PURGING, RESTRUCTURING, AND REDUCTION OF THE ARMY AND MOVEMENT TOWARD A CIVILIAN SOCIETY, AN ABSOLUTELY DEMILITARIZED SOCIETY.

-- THE END OF IMPUNITY THROUGH THE TRIAL AND PUNISHMENT OF THE MASTERMINDS AND PERPETRATORS OF THE ASSASSINATION OF MSGR ROMERO, FENASTRAS MEMBERS, JESUIT PRIESTS, AND DR. OQUELI. THESE TRIALS ARE THE FOUNDATION THAT WILL ENSURE THAT REFORM OF THE JUDICIAL SYSTEM IS CREDIBLE.

-- GUARANTEES OF THE FRAMEWORK OF DEMOCRATIC LIBERTIES.

-- VIA A PLESBICITE IN THE 1991 ELECTIONS, THAT THE NEXT ASSEMBLY IMPLEMENT AMENDMENTS TO THE CONSTITUTION, SUCH AS THE EXPANSION OF THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY AND THE CREATION OF A CONSTITUTIONAL FRAMEWORK FOR THE DEMILITARIZATION OF SOCIETY.

-- REFORM OF THE ELECTORAL SYTEM TO REGISTER, BY MAY THIS YEAR AT THE LATEST, NEARLY 3 MILLION ELIGIBLE SALVADORAN VOTERS TO ALLOW THEM TO PARTICIPATE IN THE 1991 ELECTIONS.

-- THE CARRYING OUT OF THE UPCOMING ELECTIONS WITHOUT A MILITARY PRESENCE AND WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF INTERNATIONAL OBSERVERS AT LEAST SIX MONTHS BEFORE AND UNTIL THE INSTALLATION OF THE NEW ASSEMBLY.

THE FMLN IS WILLING TO REACH ACCORDS ON ALL THESE ISSUES AND TO IMPLEMENT SIMULTANEOUS STEPS FROM A DE-INTENSIFICATION OF THE WAR AND AN END OF HOSTILITIES TO ACCORDS TO END THE ARMED CONFLICT AND THE REINCORPORATION OF OUR FORCES INTO POLITICAL LIFE IN KEEPING WITH AND PARALLEL TO THE AFOREMENTIONED MEASURES TAKING PLACE.

WE EXPRESS OUR WILLINGNESS TO FULLY SUPPORT A NATIONAL REGISTRATIO DRIVE TO GIVE ALL ELIGIBLE SALVADORAN VOTERS THE OPPORTUNITY TO VOTE AND CONTRIBUTE TOWARD ENSURING THAT THE UPCOMING ELECTIONS, AS WAS THE CASE IN NICARAGUA, WILL HELP ESTABLISH THE BASES FOR LASTING PEACE.

PRESIDENTS: THE FMLN'S OBJECTIVES ARE DEMOCRATIZATION, RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, ESTABLISHMENT OF A GENUINE LEGAL STATE, DEMILITARIZATION, AND ESTABLISHMENT OF A NATIONAL ECONOMIC POLICY AS THE ONLY MEANS TO ENSURE THAT OUR PEOPLE WILL PEACEFULLY MOVE UP TO BETTER LEVELS OF WELL-BEING AND DEVELOPMENT. IN THIS REGARD, WE BELIEVE THAT YOUR BEST CONTRIBUTION WOULD BE TO HELP PROMOTE DEMOCRATIZATION IN EL SALVADOR AND TO ADVOCATE A NEGOTIATIONS PROCESS THAT IS BEGUN AT THE UNITED NATIONS.

[SIGNED] FMLN GENERAL COMMAND: COMMANDERS SALVADOR SANCHEZ CEREN, FRANCISCO JOVEL, SHAFICK JORGE HANDAL, EDUARDO SANCHO, AND JOAQUIN VILLALOBOS.

DEV-MUC3-1204 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, 31 MAR 90 (EFE) -- [REPORT] [JUAN JORGE FAUNDES] [TEXT] KIDNAPPING IS ONE OF COLOMBIA'S MOST PROFITABLE INDUSTRIES TO THE EXTENT THAT, ACCORDING TO POLICE STATISTICS, FOUR PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KIDNAPPED EVERY DAY SO FAR IN 1990, A FIGURE DOUBLE THAT OF THE SAME PERIOD IN 1989. THE JUDICIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS DIRECTORATE [DIJIN] THIS WEEK REPORTED THAT 326 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN KIDNAPPED FOR EXTORTION PURPOSES SO FAR THIS YEAR.

DIJIN SAID THAT THE NUMBER OF KIDNAPPINGS IN THIS PERIOD DOUBLED THE NUMBER OF KIDNAPPINGS DURING THE SAME PERIOD IN 1989.

ACCORDING TO THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTMENT OF SECURITY [DAS], IN 1989, CATTLEMEN PAID 2 BILLION PESOS ($5 MILLION) TO KIDNAPPERS AND BLACKMAILERS WHO THREATENED CAPTURING OR ASSASSINATING THEM IF THEY FAILED TO PAY.

ACCORDING TO DAS, GUERRILLAS OR CRIMINALS STOLE 10,000 HEAD OF CATTLE IN 1989 AND HAVE STOLEN 1,500 OF THE ANIMALS SO FAR IN 1990.

SOURCES CONSULTED BY EFE, BOTH POLICE SOURCES AND THOSE WHO STUDY THE COLOMBIAN REALITY, HAVE POINTED OUT THAT GUERRILLAS PARTICIPATE IN 20 TO 30 PERCENT OF THE KIDNAPPING BUSINESS AND COMMON CRIMINALS IN 70 TO 80 PERCENT.

THESE PERCENTAGES OF PARTICIPATION IN THE INDUSTRY OF KIDNAPPING ARE ONLY ESTIMATES NEARLY IMPOSSIBLE TO CHECK BECAUSE IN MANY CASES GUERRILLAS KIDNAP PEOPLE TO FINANCE THEIR ACTIVITIES AND DO NOT CLAIM RESPONSIBILITY FOR IT.

IN ADDITION, MANY PEOPLE ARE KIDNAPPED BY COMMON CRIMINALS, BUT THE CRIME IS REPORTED AS BEING PERPETRATED BY GUERRILLAS IN AN ATTEMPT TO COVER UP THE MALEFACTOR'S ACTIONS.

ACCORDING TO THE DAS, CORDOBA, IN THE COUNTRY'S NORTHEAST, IS THE DEPARTMENT MOST AFFECTED BY THIS KIND OF CRIME. OTHER HARD HIT DEPARTMENTS ARE ANTIOQUIA IN THE NORTHWEST, SANTANDER IN THE NORTHEAST, AND CAUCA IN THE SOUTHWEST.

ACCORDING TO THE DAS REPORT, THE SITUATION HAS BECOME SO UNTENABLE THAT ITS SEEMS IMPOSSIBLE TO RESTORE SOCIAL BALANCE IN CORDOBA ON A MID-TERM BASIS BECAUSE THE POPULATION HAS ACCUSTOMED ITSELF TO COEXISTING WITH THESE IRREGULARITIES OR REPULSING THEM WITH MECHANISMS OTHER THAN THOSE STIPULATED BY LAW.

MECHANISMS OTHER THAN THOSE STIPULATED BY LAW REFERRED TO BY THE DAS ARE USUALLY CATTLEMEN ORGANIZING THEMSELVES INTO SELF-DEFENSE PARAMILITARY GROUPS OR DEATH SQUADS.

THESE PARAMILITARY GROUPS DEFEND THEIR PROPERTIES OR MOUNT RAIDS AGAINST PEASANTS CONSIDERED ACCOMPLICES OR INFORMANTS OF LEFTIST GUERRILLAS OR COMMON CRIMINALS WHO BLACKMAIL THEM.

ACCORDING TO THE DAS, ONE OF THE CAUSES OF THIS SITUATION IS SOCIAL DISRUPTION AND THE PRECARIOUS ECONOMIC SITUATION OF THE COMMUNITIES LOCATED IN MUNICIPALITIES AND LOCALITIES THAT LACK THE MOST BASIC SERVICES, A REALITY THAT IS MOST GLARING IN CORDOBA.

FIVE GUERRILLA GROUPS ARE ACTIVE IN COLOMBIA. THE MOST BELLIGERENT AND THE ONE THAT HAS USED KIDNAPPING TO THE FULLEST EXTENT IS THE PRO-CASTRO NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY [ELN].

THE OTHER GROUPS ARE THE COMMUNIST REVOLUTIONARY ARMED FORCES OF COLOMBIA [FARC], THE MAOIST PEOPLE'S LIBERATION ARMY [EPL], THE INDIGENIST QUINTIN LAME, AND THE TROTSKYIST REVOLUTIONARY WORKERS' PARTY [PRT].

DEV-MUC3-1205 (SYNCHRONETICS)

MADRID (SPAIN), 2 APR 90 (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [TEXT] THE GUATEMALAN VICE PRESIDENT ARRIVED IN MADRID THIS AFTERNOON. ON HIS ARRIVAL HE SPOKE TO OUR CORRESPONDENT, HECTOR ARENAS, AT BARAJAS AIRPORT.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ARENAS] GUATEMALAN VICE PRESIDENT ROBERTO CARPIO WHO IS NOW IN SPAIN SAID THAT HIS GOVERNMENT SUPORTS THE CONCILIATION COUNCIL MEETING TAKING PLACE IN OSLO, WHERE TALKS ARE BEING HELD WITH THE GUATEMALAN GUERRILLAS TO PUT AN END TO THE CLIMATE OF VIOLENCE WHICH THIS CENTRAL AMERICAN COUNTRY HAS BEEN EXPERIENCING FOR YEARS; SCORES OF PEOPLE ARE DEAD OR MISSING. ACCORDING TO VICE PRESIDENT CARPIO THE INTERNATIONAL SITUATION TODAY IN NO WAY JUSTIFIES TERRORIST ACTIONS OR ARMED MOVEMENTS.

[CARPIO, IN PROGRESS] ...THIS IS GOOD PROGRESS AND IN THIS CONNECTION TO RECOGNIZE THAT OUR COUNTRIES HAVE CHANGED. IT IS NOT THE GUATEMALA OF FIVE OR SIX YEARS AGO, WHEN THERE WERE AUTOCRATIC AND MILITARY REGIMES. TODAY WE ARE IN A PROCESS OF DEMOCRATIZATION AND IN THIS CONNECTION WE ALL OUGHT TO INVOLVE OURSELVES IN IT. THEREFORE, I THINK, THIS IS THE BEGINING OF SOMETHING WHICH COULD END THE ARMED STRUGGLE IN GUATEMALA, AS IT SHOULD ALSO END THROUGHOUT ALL CENTRAL AMERICA. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1207 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 APR 90 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [EXCERPTS] [REPORTER] WHAT IS THE POSITION OF THE ARMED FORCES CONCERNING THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT IN NICARAGUA AND THE UPCOMING DIALOGUE TO BE HELD IN GENEVA BETWEEN THE REBELS AND THE GOVERNMENT? WILL THE ARMED FORCES SEEK SUPPORT FOR THE DIALOGUE AND A SOLUTION TO THE CONFLICT?

[PONCE] LAST WEEK THE ARMED FORCES RELEASED A PUBLIC MESSAGE TO THE PEOPLE EXPLAINING THEIR STAND AND MENTIONING THREE BASIC POINTS:

FIRST, THE ARMED FORCES SUPPORT A DIALOGUE THAT SEEKS PEACE IN THE COUNTRY THROUGH MECHANISMS OF UNDERSTANDING AND AGREEMENT.

SECOND, THE ARMED FORCES EXPRESS THEIR LOYALTY TO THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC IN THESE EFFORTS AND OTHER EFFORTS HE MAY UNDERTAKE TO FIND THE PEACE WE ALL CHERISH IN THIS COUNTRY.

THIRD, WE POSSESS THE MORAL CONVICTION AND THE OBEDIENCE -- AS ORDERED BY THE CONSTITUTION -- AS WELL AS THE HUMANISTIC AWARENESS TO PROMOTE AND PROTECT THE HUMAN RIGHTS OF ALL SALVADORANS.

THOSE ARE THE BASIC POINTS INCLUDED IN OUR MESSAGE TO THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE THAT WE ANNOUNCED LAST WEEK.

AS FOR THE PRESIDENTIAL SUMMIT BEING HELD IN NICARAGUA, THE ARMED FORCES WHOLEHEARTEDLY SUPPORT THE EFFORTS UNDERTAKEN BY OUR GOVERNMENT TO FIND THE MECHANISMS THAT WILL LEAD US TO PEACE IN THE REGION. THAT IS WHY THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC HAS OUR FULL SUPPORT IN THIS ENDEAVOUR FOR FINDING PEACE AND DEMOCRACY THROUGHOUT CENTRAL AMERICA.

CONCERNING THE DIALOGUE IN GENEVA, I BELIEVE THAT TOMORROW THERE WILL BE A BRIEFING WITH THE PARTICIPATION OF DELEGATES FROM THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] TOGETHER WITH THE UN SECRETARY GENERAL, WHO WILL ANNOUNCE THE MECHANISMS TO BE FOLLOWED IN THIS DIALOGUE BETWEEN THE GOVERNMENT AND THE FMLN.

[REPORTER] WHAT DO THE ARMED FORCES THINK ABOUT THE EIGHT BOMBS THAT WERE DETONATED YESTERDAY AND KILLED SIX SOLDIERS AND ONE CIVILIAN? WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT THIS NOW, SINCE IT IS EVIDENT THAT EXPLOSIVES ARE AGAIN BEING USED AGAINST THE PEOPLE?

[PONCE] WE, THE ARMED FORCES, FEEL THAT THESE EVENTS ARE CARRIED OUT BY THE TERRORISTS WITHIN THE FMLN WHO DO NOT BELIEVE DIALOGUE IS A MECHANISM FOR ACHIEIVING PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY. THESE INDIVIDUALS BELIEVE THAT VIOLENCE IS WHAT WILL LEAD THEM TO POWER. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1208 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 3 APR 90 (RADIO CADENA YSKL) -- [NEWS CONFERENCE WITH COLONEL RENE EMILIO PONCE, CHAIRMAN OF THE ARMED FORCES JOINT CHIEFS OF STAFF, BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTERS] [EXCERPTS] [CONTINUED] [PONCE] THEY ARE COMPLETELY OUT OF CONTEXT IN HISTORY. THEY HAD CLEARLY ANNOUNCED THAT THEY WOULD NOT USE CAR BOMBS FROM NOW ON, BUT THEY USED ONE YESTERDAY NEVERTHELESS. THIS ACTION IS CONDEMNABLE FROM EVERY VIEWPOINT BECAUSE THE MEMBERS, RATHER THE ALUMNI, OF CETIPOL [POLICE INSTRUCTION CENTER] WHO WERE VICTIMS OF THIS ATTACK WERE UNARMED. THEY WERE SIMPLY DOING SOME PHYSICAL EXERCISES. IT IS ALSO DEPLORABLE THAT A BAKER WAS KILLED AND THAT A 12-YEAR-OLD YOUTH GOING TO SCHOOL WAS INJURED.

WE BELIEVE THAT THESE EVENTS DO NOT CONTRIBUTE AT ALL TO THE CREATION OF THE APPROPRIATE ATMOSPHERE FOR SEEKING PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY. THIS AND MANY OTHER ACTS OF VIOLENCE WHICH HAVE RECENTLY OCCURRED CONTRADICT THE IMAGE THAT THE FMLN HAD PREVIOUSLY TRIED TO CREATE WITH ITS DECISION NOT TO CONTINUE SABOTAGING THE PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION AND COMMUNICATIONS SECTORS, AS WELL AS BUSINESSES. ALL THESE ACTIONS HAVE CONTINUED TO OCCUR. WE WANT TO BELIEVE THAT THESE ACTIONS HAVE BEEN CARRIED OUT BY TERRORISTS WHO ARE OUT OF THE FMLN LEADERS' CONTROL, BECAUSE, AS I SAID, THIS DOES NOT HELP AT ALL TO CREATE THE APPROPRIATE ATMOSPHERE IN WHICH TO SEEK PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY.

[REPORTER] COLONEL, REFERRING TO THE STATE OF SIEGE, WILL THE ARMED FORCES INSIST ON KEEPING IT OR NOT? THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY PRESIDENT COMMENTED ON THIS YESTERDAY.

[PONCE] THIS IS A POLITICAL DECISION ANYWAY, AND IT IS ADOPTED BY THE ASSEMBLY -- SOMETIMES UPON REQUEST FROM...

[REPORTER, INTERRUPTING] THE DEFENSE MINISTRY, YOU SAID.

[PONCE] WE, AS AN ARMED CORPS AND WITH THE INTENTION OF HELPING CREATE THE APPROPRIATE ATMOSPHERE FOR PEACE IN OUR COUNTRY, WILL MAKE NO REQUEST TO EXTEND THE STATE OF EMERGENCY AND [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[REPORTER] DOES THIS MEAN THAT THE ARMED FORCES DECIDED THIS BECAUSE THE SITUATION OF VIOLENCE HAS DISAPPEARED?

[PONCE] TAKING INTO ACCOUNT THE FACT THAT CURRENT VIOLENT ACTIONS MIGHT COME FROM GROUPS OUTSIDE THE CONTROL OF FMLN LEADERS, WE BELIEVE THAT THE COUNTRY'S SITUATION IS NOT NORMAL ENOUGH TO SAY THAT THERE IS NO VIOLENCE. HOWEVER, AS A CONTRIBUTION TO THAT PROPITIOUS ATMOSPHERE FOR THE DIALOGUE, I BELIEVE THAT IT IS ADVISABLE TO LIFT IT.

[REPORTER] I HAVE TWO QUESTIONS: WHAT IS THE ARMED FORCES' POSITION REGARDING [WORDS INDISTINCT]?

[PONCE] AS FOR THE FIRST QUESTION, YOU ARE REFERRING TO STATEMENTS BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC. I BELIEVE THAT IN DUE TIME HE WILL HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO EXPLAIN THOSE STATEMENTS. I UNDERSTAND THAT THE NEWSMAN DISTORTED HIS WORDS, BUT THE PRESIDENT HIMSELF WILL HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO MAKE THE RESPECTIVE CLARIFICATION.

I WILL, HOWEVER, STATE THAT ACCORDING TO THE REPORTS THAT HAVE BEEN ISSUED BY THE DIRECTOR GENERAL OF THE NATIONAL POLICE AS TO WHETHER AT ANY TIME COLONEL BENAVIDES HAS LEFT THE HANDS OF THE NATIONAL POLICE, HE CLEARLY SAID THAT AT NO TIME HAS BENAVIDES DONE THIS. HE IS UNDER THE ORDERS OF THE 4TH PENAL JUDGE, AND AT NO TIME HAS THE 4TH PENAL JUDGE AUTHORIZED COL. BENAVIDES TO LEAVE THE CONFINES OF THE JAIL.

THE PERSON WHO MADE THE ACCUSATIONS SHOULD PRESENT SOME EVIDENCE, A PHOTOGRAPH FOR EXAMPLE. OTHERWISE, THIS IS ALL MERE SPECULATION. THAT IS A VERY DELICATE CASE, AND SPECULATIONS CAST A NEGATIVE IMAGE ON THE ARMED FORCES AND THE COUNTRY ITSELF, AND EVEN ON THE ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE IN OUR COUNTRY.

CONCERNING WHAT COULD HAPPEN IN THE TRIAL OF THE MURDER OF THE JESUITS, THE JUSTICE AUTHORITIES WILL DETERMINE WHAT WILL BE DONE. WE WILL RESPECT THAT DECISION. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1209 (SYNCHRONETICS)

PANAMA CITY (PANAMA), 4 APR 90 (CIRCUITO RPC TELEVISION) -- [TEXT] APPROXIMATELY 800 HEAVILY ARMED COLOMBIANS WITHOUT IDENTIFICATION DOCUMENTS WERE DISCOVERED CONDUCTING ILLEGAL ACTIVITIES AT THE BORDER BETWEEN PANAMA AND COLOMBIA, ACCORDING TO GOVERNMENT AND JUSTICE MINISTER RICARDO ARIAS CALDERON.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [ARIAS CALDERON] THERE ARE COLOMBIANS WITHOUT IDENTIFICATION AT THE BORDER. THERE ARE REPORTS THAT THEY HAVE BEEN ENGAGED IN ILLEGAL ACTIVITIES. THERE WAS AN ATTACK IN PUERTO OBALDIA, IN WHICH A NATIONAL POLICEMAN WAS KILLED BY SOME COLOMBIAN NATIONALS. THIS IS BEING INVESTIGATED. THE COLOMBIAN NATIONALS HAVE NOT YET BEEN IDENTIFIED. IT IS POSSIBLE THAT BOTH INCIDENTS ARE LINKED. WE ARE CONCERNED ABOUT THIS AND THE GOVERNMENT AND JUSTICE MINISTRY WILL TAKE THE PROPER MEASURES AT THE PROPER TIME.

[REPORTER] DO YOU KNOW WHAT TYPE OF ILLEGAL ACTIVITIES THEY ARE CONDUCTING THERE NOW?

[ARIAS CALDERON] THEY ARE PROBABLY CONDUCTING CONTRABAND- RELATED ACTIVITIES. [END RECORDING]

DEV-MUC3-1210 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 30 MAR 90 (DIARIO LATINO) -- [TEXT] INTERNATIONAL NEWS DISPATCHES HAVE REPORTED ON PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI'S REMARKS ABOUT WHY THE NEFARIOUS DEATH SQUADS HAVE APPEARED AND STILL THRIVE IN THE COUNTRY.

CRISTIANI'S REMARKS, MADE IN CARACAS, HAVE BEEN THE CAUSE OF CONCERN FOR LOCAL AND FOREIGN OBSERVERS BECAUSE HE USES A STRANGE AND TWISTED LOGIC TO ANALYZE THE SALVADORAN SOCIAL REALITY. HE HAS SAID THAT THE DEATH SQUADS APPEARED IN RESPONSE TO THE FORMATION OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN]. EVEN WORSE, HE SAID THAT THESE SQUADS WILL CONTINUE TO OPERATE IN OUR COUNTRY AS LONG AS THE FMLN CONTINUES TO CARRY OUT POLITICAL AND MILITARY ACTIVITIES.

CRISTIANI'S REMARKS HAVE CALLED THE ATTENTION OF UDN, WHICH CANNOT HELP BUT REJECT AND REFUTE ASSERTIONS DESIGNED TO CONFUSE THE LOCAL AND FOREIGN PUBLIC OPINION ON THE TRUE CAUSES OF VIOLENCE IN THE COUNTRY AND THE FMLN'S APPEARANCE AND DEVELOPMENT IN THE NATIONAL SCENARIO.

FIRST, CRISTIANI'S ASSERTIONS REPRESENT MORAL SUPPORT FOR THE GROUPS AND BANDS OF ASSASSINS WHO, EMBEDDED IN AND PROTECTED BY THE STRUCTURES OF POLITICAL AND ECONOMIC POWER, HAVE ASSASSINATED WITH IMPUNITY TENS OF THOUSANDS OF LOWLY SALVADORANS.

SECOND, CRISTIANI MISTAKES THE CASE FOR THE EFFECT BY SAYING THAT "VIOLENCE ENGENDERS VIOLENCE" AND THAT, THEREFORE, THERE WILL BE DEATH SQUADS AS LONG AS THERE ARE GUERRILLAS. THE TRUTH IS THAT THE DEATH SQUADS WERE ACTIVE EVEN BEFORE THE FMLN WAS ORGANIZED. HAS CRISTIANI PERHAPS FORGOTTEN THE ASSASSINATIONS PERPETRATED BY THE WHITE HAND [LA MANO BLANCA], THE WHITE WAR UNION [LA UNION GUERRA BLANCA], AND OTHER GROUPS THAT HAVE BEEN SPREADING TERROR FOR MANY YEARS?

THIRD, VIOLENCE AND HOSTILITY HAVE ALWAYS BEEN PRESENT IN EL SALVADOR SINCE THE SPANISH INVASION AND CONQUEST AND WORKERS HAVE ALWAYS BEEN FAVORITE VICTIMS.

WE HEREBY STATE THIS, FULLY COGNIZANT OF THE COUNTRY'S HISTORY. THE VIOLENCE OF THE PEOPLE HAS RESPONDED, AS A LAST DITCH RESORT, TO THE GENERALIZED VIOLENCE OF THE SALVADORAN GOVERNMENT AND STATE.

LET US KEEP IN MIND OUR FOREBEARS' RESISTANCE TO THE SPANISH INVADERS; THE PEASANTS' AND INDIANS' PERSISTENT REBELLION AGAINST THE SOCIAL INJUSTICE OF COLONIAL TIMES; THE HEROIC ACTIONS AND THE PATRIOTIC ATTEMPTS THAT CULMINATED IN INDEPENDENCE; ANASTASIO AQUINO'S REBELLION; THE PEASANTS' AND INDIANS' RESISTANCE TO WORKING FOR THE NEW LANDOWNERS WHO DISPOSSESSED THEM OF THEIR COMMON LANDS DURING THE 1881 AGRARIAN REFORM; THE REBELLION OF WORKERS AND PEASANTS IN 1932; THE HISTORIC ACTION AGAINST DICTATOR MARTINEZ IN 1944; THE RANK AND FILE STRUGGLE AGAINST TYRANT LEMUS; THE PEOPLE'S STRUGGLE AGAINST THE ELECTORAL IMPOSITION IN THE 1970'S; AND THE UNYIELDING STRUGGLE OF AN ENTIRE PEOPLE FOR DEMOCRACY AND PEACE WITH SOCIAL JUSTICE, WHICH IS CURRENTLY UNDERWAY. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1211 (SYNCHRONETICS)

CLANDESTINE, NO DATE (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [INTERVIEW WITH FMLN COMMANDER SANCHO BY UNIDENTIFIED REPORTER] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [REPORTER] COMMANDER, THE FIGHTERS, EVEN SALVADORAN CITIZENS IN GENERAL, DO NOT UNDERSTAND CERTAIN ATTITUDES OF THE FMLN OR SOME OF THE COMMUNIQUES ISSUED BY THE FMLN GENERAL COMMAND. WE SPENT EIGHT OR NINE YEARS FIGHTING THE CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY [PDC] AND JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE. WE REMEMBER [WORDS INDISTINCT] THE ASSASSINATION OF HERBERT ANAYA SANABRIA. HOWEVER, WHEN DUARTE DIED, A COMMUNIQUE WAS ISSUED DECLARING A TRUCE SO THAT THE FUNERAL COULD TAKE PLACE PEACEFULLY. HOW SHOULD WE VIEW ALL OF THESE APPARENT CHANGES OF POSITION BY THE FMLN?

[SANCHO] AS FOR JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE, WE HAVE TO POINT OUT THAT ADDITION TO BEING A POLITICAL FORCE, THE FMLN HAS HUMAN SENSITIVITY. WE THOUGHT IT WAS APPROPRIATE FOR US TO TAKE THIS HUMANE ACTION BY DECLARING A TRUCE SO THAT MR. DUARTE COULD BE BURIED. WE ALSO HAVE TO MENTION THAT THE PDC AND ALL OF THE LEFTIST FORCES OF THE COUNTRY CAN CONTRIBUTE TOWARD THE DEPOLARIZATION OF SOCIETY. THE TRUCE WAS A GESTURE, IT WAS TO MAKE THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE SEE THAT IT IS POSSIBLE TO DEPOLARIZE SOCIETY AND THAT EACH OF US CAN MAKE A CONTRIBUTION.

THAT IS WHY WE INSIST THAT ONE MUST NOT RETURN TO ONE'S ELECTORAL OR POLITICAL HEGEMONIC PLANS, BECAUSE THAT WOULD OBSTRUCT THE UNITY OF THE PEOPLE, WHICH IS NEEDED TO ISOLATE THE FASCISTS.

[REPORTER] COMMANDER, THERE WAS A DISCUSSION AT THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY WHEN DUARTE DIED BECAUSE THE PDC LEGISLATORS MOTIONED TO NAME HIM THE FATHER OF DEMOCRACY IN EL SALVADOR. [WORDS INDISTINCT] WHAT IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN JOSE NAPOLEON DUARTE, WHO WAS IN POWER FOR ALMOST 10 YEARS, AND ROBERTO D'AUBUISSON? WHAT IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THESE TWO POLITICIANS?

[SANCHO] WE BELIEVE THAT DUARTE WAS A FIGHTER FOR DEMOCRACY. HE HAD HIS OWN BELIEFS, HE HAD HIS OWN PERSONALITY, AND HE REALLY HAD CHARISMA; WE CANNOT DENY THAT. OF COURSE, WE CANNOT COMPARE HIM TO A CRIMINAL WHO IS BEING SOUGHT BY JUSTICE. I WOULD SAY THAT D'AUBUISSON IS A FUGITIVE FROM JUSTICE, WHO HAS SOUGHT SHELTER FROM HIS IMMUNITY AS A DEPUTY. HIS IMMUNITY AS A DEPUTY DOES NOT PRECLUDE HIS CRIMES. THERE IS NO COMPARISON BETWEEN DUARTE AND [WORDS INDISTINCT] WHO IS WELL-KNOWN, BUT IS VIOLENT AND UNPOPULAR.

[REPORTER] TO END THE FIRST PART OF THE INTERVIEW, ARE YOU OPTIMISTIC ABOUT A POSSIBLE CONCERTED EFFORT BY POPULAR AND DEMOCRATIC FORCES IN THE COUNTRY OR DO YOU BELIEVE THAT EACH WILL GO HIS OWN WAY. ARE YOU OPTIMISTIC ABOUT A CONCERTED EFFORT?

[SANCHO] A CONCERTED EFFORT IN A POLITICAL STRUGGLE OF ALL THE FORCES IN THE COUNTRY SHOULD NOT ONLY BE SEEN AS A POSSIBILITY, BUT MUST BE SEEN AS A POLITICAL NECESSITY FOR THE UNITY OF ALL POPULAR AND NATIONAL SECTORS, BECAUSE THIS WOULD BE THE ONLY FORMULA TO REBUILD THE COUNTRY, TO REUNITE THE COUNTRY, AND TO RECONCILE THE COUNTRY. THIS CAN ONLY BE DONE WITH A CONCERTED POLITICAL EFFORT. I BELIEVE THERE WILL BE OPPORTUNITIES OVER THE NEXT FEW MONTHS FOR CONCERTED POLITICAL EFFORTS, WHICH WILL REALLY GIVE NEW HOPE TO THE LARGE MAJORITY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. WE MUST NOT FORGET ABOUT THE LARGE MAJORITY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE, BECAUSE SOMETIMES WE SPEAK ON BEHALF OF CERTAIN GROUPS OF THE COUNTRY AND NOT ON BEHALF OF THE MAJORITIES.

DEV-MUC3-1213 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 6 APR 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] FIVE SOLDIERS WERE KILLED AND FIVE WERE WOUNDED DURING A FIERCE GUERRILLA ATTACK THIS MORNING IN THE CITY OF SUCHITOTO, CUZCATLAN DEPARTMENT, IN THE CENTRAL PART OF THE COUNTRY, MILITARY SPOKESPERSONS HAVE REPORTED.

THE SOURCES INDICATED THAT THE REBEL ATTACK BY RIFLE FIRE BEGAN AT 0120 TODAY AND LASTED FOR FOUR HOURS. AFTER THIS, THE ARMY WAS IN CONTROL OF THE SITUATION. THE NUMBER OF REBEL CASUALTIES IS NOT KNOWN.

THE FIGHTING BEGAN WHEN FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) GUERRILLAS ATTACKED THE LAS GUARAS BRIDGE GUARD POST IN THE CITY OF SUCHITOTO, 44 KM FROM SAN SALVADOR.

THE MILITARY SOURCES SAID THAT EARLY THIS MORNING THE ARMY WAS IN CONTROL OF THE SITUATION. HOWEVER, ARTILLERY UNITS ARE CONDUCTING A COMBING OPERATION IN AN EFFORT TO CAPTURE THE REBELS.

GUERRILLAS ACTIVITIES HAVE INCREASED OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS AFTER THE FMLN SIGNED AN AGREEMENT WITH THE GOVERNMENT LAST WEDNESDAY IN GENEVA (SWITZERLAND) TO CONTINUE THE DIALOGUE TO RESOLVE THE 10-YEAR CONFLICT IN THE COUNTRY.

FMLN GUERRILLAS ATTACKED ARMED FORCES POSITIONS IN THE NORTHERN AND SOUTHERN PARTS OF THE CAPITAL FOR MORE THAN A HALF HOUR YESTERDAY, RESULTING IN TWO REBELS BEING KILLED AND ONE WOUNDED, ACCORDING TO MILITARY REPORTS.

THE FMLN HAS ALSO INTENSIFIED ITS SABOTAGE OF ELECTRICITY PYLONS, ABOVE ALL IN THE CAPITAL. THIS WEEK THE FMLN REBELS BROUGHT DOWN AT LEAST 20 ELECTRICITY PYLONS, CAUSING POWER OUTAGES IN DIFFERENT PARTS OF THE COUNTRY.

DEV-MUC3-1214 (SYNCHRONETICS)

BOGOTA, 6 APR 90 (DPA) -- [TEXT] THE CRIMINAL DRUG MAFIAS OPERATING IN COLOMBIA ANNOUNCED TODAY THAT THEY WILL INCREASE THEIR TERRORIST ATTACKS ON "THE INDUSTRIAL AND POLITICAL OLIGARCHY" IN RESPONSE TO THE ALLEGED DISAPPEARANCE OF SEVERAL OF THEIR ACCOMPLICES.

IN A COMMUNIQUE SENT BY TELEFAX TO SEVERAL NEWS MEDIA, "THE EXTRADITABLES," SPOKESMEN FOR THE MAFIAS, SAID THAT THEIR "WAR" WILL BE CARRIED OUT HENCEFORTH BECAUSE OF THE "DISAPPEARANCE, TORTURE, AND ASSASSINATION" OF SEVERAL DRUG TRAFFICKERS AT THE HANDS OF THE DIRECTORATE OF JUDICIAL POLICE AND INVESTIGATIONS (DIJIN).

ACCORDING TO THE CRIMINALS, WHO AGAIN DESCRIBED THEMSELVES AS A "POLITICAL-MILITARY" ORGANIZATION, "THE PROBLEM OF THE EXTRADITION HAS BEEN RELEGATED TO A SECONDARY STATUS, SINCE OUR MAIN MOTIVE FOR THE WAR WILL BE THE TORTURE, ASSASSINATION, AND DISAPPEARANCE OF OUR COMRADES."

A FEW DAYS AGO, IN A SIMILAR MESSAGE, THE CRIMINALS SAID THAT THEY WOULD PLACE 5-TON DYNAMITE BOMBS IN "NEIGHBORHOODS OF THE BOGOTA OLIGARCHY," IN REPRISAL FOR OFFENSIVE ACTIONS BY THE AUTHORITIES.

YESTERDAY, A CAR-BOMB WITH 800 KG OF DYNAMITE WAS LEFT BY DRUG TRAFFICKERS IN AN EXCLUSIVE SECTOR OF THE CAPITAL. HAD IT NOT BEEN FOR A DEFECT IN THE DETONATOR, IT WOULD HAVE KILLED AT LEAST 5,000 [NUMBER AS RECEIVED] PEOPLE.

ACCORDING TO THE CRIMINALS, THE RESURGENCE OF TERRORIST ATTACKS IS DUE TO THE "DISAPPEARANCE" LATE LAST MONTH OF JOSE RETAVISTA GARZON, FREDDY LOPEZ OSPINA, AND BROTHERS OMAR AND GUILLERMO PEREA RIVERA, WHO REPORTEDLY WERE ARRESTED BY THE POLICE IN THE NORTHWESTERN TOWN OF ENVIGADO.

HOWEVER, ACCORDING TO AN INVESTIGATION CARRIED OUT YESTERDAY BY THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE, THESE PERSONS ARE NOT CONFINED IN ANY GARRISON OF THE ELITE FORCE, A POLICE ANTITERRORIST CORPS.

"THE EXTRADITABLES" NOTED THAT "THE GOOD FAITH OF THE ATTORNEY GENERAL'S OFFICE IN NO WAY SATISFIES OUR DEMANDS, BECAUSE THE MISSING COMPANIONS WERE TAKEN OUT OF THE SCHOOL (POLICE HEADQUARTERS) AND EXECUTED BY ORDER OF DIJIN DIRECTOR OSCAR PELAEZ CARMONA, WHOM THEY ACCUSE OF "MASTERMINDING" SEVERAL MASSACRES.

THE DRUG TRAFFICKING MAFIA ALSO SAID THAT THE KILLINGS OF POLICEMEN HAD BEEN SUSPENDED (14 UNIFORMED POLICEMEN HAVE BEEN KILLED IN MEDELLIN SINCE LAST MONDAY) AND THAT THEY HAD NEVER PARTICIPATED IN "TORTURE," BUT, THEY ADDED, "WE WILL INTENSIFY OUR STRUGGLE AGAINST THE INDUSTRIAL AND POLITICAL OLIGARCHY, WHICH IS AN ACCOMPLICE TO THE ASSASSINATIONS."

THE WAR AGAINST THE DRUG MAFIAS IN COLOMBIA, WHICH APPEARS TO HAVE EXPERIENCED A VIOLENT RESURGENCE, BEGAN LAST AUGUST AFTER MERCENARIES AT THE SERVICE OF THE CRIMINAL GROUPS ASSASSINATED IN THE SPACE OF A FEW HOURS A MAGISTRATE, A POLICE COLONEL, AND PRESIDENTIAL HOPEFUL LUIS CARLOS GALAN.

DEV-MUC3-1215 (SYNCHRONETICS)

CLANDESTINE, 6 APR 90 (RADIO VENCEREMOS) -- [TEXT] IT HAS BEEN REPORTED THAT ON 6 APRIL AT 0230, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT [FMLN] GUERRILLAS ATTACKED POSITIONS THAT WERE BEING GUARDED BY UNITS OF THE LIGHTNING BATTALION OF MILITARY DETACHMENT NO. 5 IN LAS GUARAS BRIDGE, LOCATED ON THE HIGHWAY THAT RUNS FROM SAN MARTIN TO SUCHITOTO, AND IN SAN PEDRO PERULAPAN, CUSCATLAN DEPARTMENT. THE FMLN GUERRILLAS ATTACKED FOUR POSITIONS WITH RIFLE FIRE AND ROCKET LAUNCHERS.

AFTER 40 MINUTES OF ATTACKS, WE HAD TAKEN OVER THREE POSITIONS AND FORCED THE FOURTH ONE TO FLEE. IN THIS ATTACK, WE INFLICTED 13 CASUALTIES ON THE ENEMY. THE CASUALTIES WERE INFLICTED IN THE AREA OF SUCHITOTO, WHILE THE WAR MATERIEL WGS SEIZED IN SAN PEDRO PERULAPAN IN CUSCATLAN DEPARTMENT.

WE INFLICTED 13 CASUALTIES IN THE AREA OF SUCHITOTO, INCLUDING A SUB-SERGEANT AND A WOUNDED CORPORAL. IN THE AREA OF THE LAS GUARAS BRIDGE, WE SEIZED FIVE M-16 RIFLES, ONE M-79 ROCKET LAUNCHER, 8,200 CARTRIDGES, 38 GRENADES FOR M-79 ROCKET LAUNCHERS, 11 KNAPSACKS, AND OTHER WAR MATERIEL.

WE ALSO REPORT THAT COMRADE WILLIAM HEROICALLY FELL IN COMBAT, STRUGGLING TO TEAR DOWN THE FASCIST WALL AND URGING THE FATHERLAND TO UNITE FOR DEMOCRACY.

DEV-MUC3-1216 (SYNCHRONETICS)

PARIS (FRANCE), 5 APRIL 90 (AFP) -- [TEXT] COLOMBIAN LEADER VIRGILIO BARCO BRIEFED FRENCH PRESIDENT FRANCOIS MITTERRAND HERE WEDNESDAY ON THE EFFORTS MADE BY BOGOTA TO FIGHT THE COUNTRY'S POWERFUL COCAINE TRAFFICKERS.

MR. BARCO TOLD REPORTERS AFTER THE MEETING AT THE ELYSEE PALACE THAT THE FRENCH LEADER, WHO VISITED BOGOTA IN OCTOBER 1989, HAD SAID ONCE AGAIN THAT HE WAS "VERY INTERESTED" IN THE DRUG PROBLEM.

FRENCH SOURCES SAID THE COLOMBIAN PRESIDENT HAD INFORMED MR. MITTERRAND OF THE EFFORTS TAKEN BY HIS GOVERNMENT AGAINST DRUG TRAFFICKERS AND DESCRIBED THEM AS ENCOURAGING.

MR. BARCO WAS QUOTED AS SAYING THAT HE WAS PARTICULARLY OPTIMISTIC ABOUT CONTROLLING IMPORTS OF CHEMICALS NEEDED BY TRAFFICKERS TO MAKE COCAINE. ASKED ABOUT BRINGING MEMBERS OF A POWERFUL GROUP OF DRUG BARONS KNOWN AS THE "THE EXTRADITABLES" TO TRIAL, MR. BARCO SAID IT WOULD "DEPEND ON EACH INDIVIDUAL CASE."

THE TWO PRESIDENTS ALSO DISCUSSED THE COFFEE MARKET, FRENCH SOURCES SAID. COFFEE IS COLOMBIA'S MAIN LEGAL CASH CROP, AND PRICES HAVE PLUNGED IN THE PAST YEAR WITH THE COLLAPSE OF A MARKET AGREEMENT BETWEEN PRODUCER AND CONSUMER COUNTRIES.

MR. BARCO VISITED STRASBOURG, EASTERN FRANCE, EARLIER WEDNESDAY WHERE HE ADDRESSED THE EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY PARLIAMENT AND APPEALED FOR EASIER ACCESS TO EUROPEAN MARKETS FOR COLOMBIAN GOODS. IN AN ADDRESS TO THE BODY, MR. BARCO ASKED THE EEC TO REDUCE CUSTOMS DUTIES ON COFFEE. MR. BARCO, WHO HANDED OUT PACKETS OF COLOMBIAN COFFEE TO EURO-MPS [MEMBERS OF PARLIAMENT], ALSO ASKED THE COMMUNITY TO LIFT TARIFFS ON FLOWERS, AND QUOTAS ON THE QUANTITY OF BANANAS EXPORTED TO THE 12 EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY NATIONS.

EARLY IN THE SPEECH, ECOLOGIST MPS HELD UP SIGNS LISTING VICTIMS OF ALLEGED COLOMBIAN ARMY "ASSASSINATIONS." THE PRESIDENT OF PARLIAMENT, SPAIN'S ENRIQUE BARON CRESPO, SPOKE OF "CONCERN IN THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT OVER THE MANY INSTANCES OF POLITICAL VIOLENCE WHICH HAVE CAUSED DEATHS IN COLOMBIA." MR. BARCO ADMITTED "CERTAIN GROUPS HAVE MANAGED TO CONTAMINATE SOME ELEMENTS OF THE STATE FORCES" BUT SAID "THE GOVERNMENT HAD SEPARATED ITSELF FROM SUSPECT OFFICIALS," OR THAT THEY WERE AT LEAST UNDER INVESTIGATION.

MR. BARCO IS TO VISIT BELGIUM AND BRITAIN FOLLOWING HIS STAY HERE.

DEV-MUC3-1217 (SYNCHRONETICS)

LIMA, 7 APR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE "SHINING PATH" TERRORIST ORGANIZATION IS KEEPING THREE PERUVIAN CITIES UNDER PRESSURE WITH THREE "ARMED STRIKES"-- STRIKES ENFORCED BY DEATH THREATS--THAT BEGAN TODAY IN AN EFFORT TO FORCE A BOYCOTT OF TOMORROW'S GENERAL ELECTIONS.

AYACUCHO, THE CAPITAL OF THE SOUTHERN DEPARTMENT OF AYACUCHO, IS UNDER A STATE OF MILITARY EMERGENCY. THERE IS NEITHER ELECTRICITY NOR WATER IN THE CITY, AND EVERY ACTIVITY HAS BEEN SUSPENDED AS A RESULT OF THE THREE-DAY "ARMED STRIKE" CALLED AS OF TODAY. THERE IS NO TRANSPORTATION EITHER, STORES ARE CLOSED, AND THE STREEETS ARE PATROLLED BY THE ARMY AND THE MILITARY POLICE. ROADS LINKING AYACUCHO WITH THE DEPARTMENTAL PROVINCES OF CANGALLADO AND LA MAR WERE BLOCKED BY SHINING PATH TERRORISTS WITH STONES AND TREE TRUNKS. THE 55-KM ROAD LINKING AYACUCHO WITH THE CITY OF HUANTA IS GUARDED BY 4,000 MEMBERS OF THE "PEASANT PATROLS," WHICH ARE OPPOSED TO THE "SHINING PATH." THERE ARE A FEW VANS ON THE ROAD, UNDER MILITARY SURVEILLANCE. "SHINING PATH" TERRORISTS HAVE DESTROYED A SUSPENSION BRIDGE LINKING AYACUCHO WITH THE PROVINCE OF JULCAMARCA, WHICH WAS THUS FORCED INTO ISOLATION.

CANDIDATES FOR DEPUTY FROM AYACUCHO DEPARTMENT FOR THE RULING APRA (AMERICAN POPULAR REVOLUTIONARY ALLIANCE), THE VARGAS LLOSA-LED DEMOCRATIC FRONT (FREDEMO), AND THE UNITED LEFT, AS WELL AS FOREIGN AND LOCAL JOURNALISTS WHO WILL COVERING THE ELECTION IN THAT AREA ARE ALL LODGED IN A HOTEL IN AYACUCHO. "SHINING PATH" HAS THREATENED TO BLOW UP THE HOTEL, WHICH IS HEAVILY GUARDED BY THE POLICE.

MEANWHILE, THE PEOPLE OF AYACUCHO ARE CHECKING THE VOTER LISTS TO FIND OUT WHERE EACH VOTER WILL HAVE TO CAST HIS VOTE TOMORROW.

THE SHINING PATH ALSO CALLED FOR AN "ARMED STRIKE" FROM TODAY UNTIL MONDAY IN HUARAZ, CAPITAL OF THE ANCASH DEPARTMENT, BORDERING LIMA DEPARTMENT TO THE NORTH. THE CITY WAS PARALYZED AND IN THE DARK FOLLOWING THE DESTRUCTION OF A HIGH-TENSION PYLON SIX KM FROM THE CITY. AS THE RESULT OF THAT ATTACK, FIVE PROVINCES OF ANCASH WERE LEFT WITHOUT ELECTRICITY.

THE SHINING PATH TERRORISTS HURLED EXPLOSIVES AT A MARKET IN HUARAZ, INJURING 15 PEOPLE. THE HUARAZ-LIMA ROAD WAS BLOCKED FOR 15 HOURS WHEN SHINING PATH GUERRILLAS SET TWO TRUCKS LOADED WITH MINERALS ON FIRE. ANCASH DEPARTMENT LIES OUTSIDE THE AREA UNDER THE STATE OF EMERGENCY THAT ENCOMPASSES HALF OF PERU, INCLUDING THE METROPOLITAN LIMA AREA.

HUANCAYO, 415 KM SOUTHEAST OF LIMA, IS COMPLETELY PARALYZED BY THE "ARMED STRIKE" IMPOSED BY THE SHINING PATH. ALL ACTIVITIES-- BANKS, COMMERCE, MARKETS, PUBLIC TRANSPORTATION--HAVE BEEN SUSPENDED. SINCE FRIDAY THERE HAVE BEEN EIGHT BOMBINGS OF PUBLIC AND PRIVATE FACILITIES. A CAR WAS DESTROYED BY A BOMB. THE CITY'S ELECTRICITY SUPPLY HAS BEEN CUT, FOLLOWING THE DESTRUCTION OF THREE HIGH-TENSION PYLONS. ALSO AFFECTED WAS THE ELECTRICITY SUPPLY IN THE ENTIRE MANTARO RIVER VALLEY, WHERE THE COUNTRY'S LARGEST HYDROELECTRIC PLANT IS LOCATED. THIS PLANT SUPPLIES 80 PERCENT OF PERU'S ELECTRICITY.

SINCE LAST YEAR, SHINING PATH TERRORISTS HAVE BEEN EXTENDING THEIR ACTIVITIES FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF AYACUCHO TO THE STRATEGIC DEPARTMENT OF JUNIN, BORDERING THE DEPARTMENT OF LIMA. JUNIN PROVIDES MOST OF LIMA'S FOOD.

DEV-MUC3-1219 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 9 APR 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] THE ARMED FORCES REPORTED TODAY THAT 10 GUERRILLAS WERE KILLED AND SIX WERE WOUNDED DURING BATTLES IN THE LAST FEW HOURS IN VARIOUS AREAS OF EL SALVADOR. THEY ADDED THAT A CHILD ACTIVATED A MINE, INJURING HIMSELF AND TWO SOLDIERS.

ACCORDING TO SOURCES, THE REBEL CASUALTIES INCLUDED AN UNIDENTIFIED COMMANDER KNOWN AS "ERNESTO," WHO DIED IN A CLASH IN JUCUAPA, USULUTAN DEPARTMENT, 110 KM EAST OF SAN SALVADOR. ANOTHER GUERRILLA WAS ALSO KILLED IN THE FIGHTING THERE.

THE ARMED FORCES PRESS COMMITTEE (COPREFA) REPORTED THAT "AN AK- 47 RIFLE AND DOCUMENTS BEING ANALYZED BY MILITARY INTELLIGENCE WERE SEIZED" FROM "ERNESTO."

IT ADDED THAT FOUR GUERRILLAS OF THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) WERE KILLED ON 8 APRIL IN CLASHES WITH THE GOVERNMENT TROOPS IN COLON, LIBERTAD DEPARTMENT, 19 KM EAST OF SAN SALVADOR.

THREE OTHER REBELS WERE KILLED AND SIX WERE WOUNDED IN A CLASH IN CABANAS DEPARTMENT, 70 KM FROM THE CAPITAL.

COPREFA REPORTED THAT ANOTHER GUERRILLA WAS KILLED IN ANTIGUO CUSCATLAN, ON THE SOUTHWESTERN OUTSKIRTS OF SAN SALVADOR, WHERE AN FMLN COLUMN ATTACKED UNITS OF THE ELITE ATLACATL BATTALION.

MILITARY SOURCES INDICATED THAT TWO SOLDIERS WERE WOUNDED WHEN TROOPS FOUGHT GUERRILLAS IN SAN MIGUEL DEPARTMENT, IN CENTRAL EL SALVADOR.

DEV-MUC3-1224 (SYNCHRONETICS)

SAN SALVADOR, 14 APR 90 (ACAN-EFE) -- [TEXT] SALVADORAN MILITARY SPOKESMEN REVEALED TODAY THAT A REBEL CELL, IN WHICH TWO HONDURAN WOMEN ARE MEMBERS, CLANDESTINELY INTRODUCED INTO THE COUNTRY, THROUGH HONDURAS, SEVERAL PISTOLS, THOUSANDS OF ROUNDS OF AMMUNITION, SOVIET RIFLES, MEDICINE, AND EXPLOSIVES FOR THE GUERRILLAS.

IN THE FIRST REPORT, THE MINISTRY OF DEFENSE SAID DEFINITIVELY THAT "THE WEAPONS CAME FROM NICARAGUA, THROUGH HONDURAS, DESTINED FOR TERRORISTS IN EL SALVADOR."

THE SECOND MILITARY REPORT ON THIS MATTER SAID THAT "THE NICARAGUAN PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION RESULTS HAVE NOW MADE STEPPED-UP GUN-RUNNING FROM THAT COUNTRY A SHORT TERM POSSIBILITY, NOT ONLY FOR OUR COUNTRY BUT FOR OTHER COUNTRIES IN THE CENTRAL AMERICAN REGION.

IN A COMMUNIQUE, THE SALVADORAN DEFENSE MINISTRY SAID THAT THE ARMS AND MEDICINE WERE INTRODUCED INTO EL SALVADOR IN 19 TRIPS OVER A YEAR'S TIME FROM SAN PEDRO SULA (HONDURAS).

THE MILITARY SOURCE SAID THAT THE REBEL CELL, CONSISTING OF SALVADORANS TITO OLIVIO DUBON AND FELICIANO GARCIA SORTO AND HONDURAN WOMEN ADILIA AND AMINTA DUBON RAMIREZ, "HAD THE MISSION" OF SECRETLY TRANSPORTING ARMS AND MEDICINE INTO THE COUNTRY.

ACCORDING TO THE MILITARY COMMUNIQUE, 155 AK-47 RIFLES, 45 PISTOLS, 60,000 ROUNDS FOR VARIOUS CALIBER RIFLES, 126 GRENADES FOR RPG-7'S, MEDICINE, AND MATERIALS FOR MAKING EXPLOSIVES WERE CLANDESTINELY BROUGHT INTO EL SALVADOR BETWEEN APRIL 1989 AND 7 APRIL 1990.

TITO DUBON AND GARCIA SORTO WERE ARRESTED ON 7 APRIL IN COLOLACA MUNICIPALITY, IN HONDURAS' LEMPIRA DEPARTMENT, WHILE TRYING TO INTRODUCE THE ARMS SHIPMENT INTO THE COUNTRY INSIDE THE SECRET COMPARTMENTS OF A TRUCK.

ACCORDING TO THE MILITARY INFORMATION, THE FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT (FMLN) CELL USED TWO DIFFERENT ROUTES FOR THE TRIPS, DEPARTING FROM THE CITY OF SAN PEDRO SULA.

"ON ROUTE 1, 12 TRIPS WERE MADE BETWEEN JUNE 1989 AND 7 APRIL 1990. ROUTE 2 WAS USED FOR THREE TRIPS BETWEEN APRIL AND MAY 1989 TO A PLACE LOCATED IN MERCEDES, OCOTEPEQUE DEPARTMENT, WHERE THE FMLN TERRORISTS PICKED UP THE WEAPONS AND OTHER WAR MATERIEL," THE DEFENSE MINISTRY REPORTED.

THE REPORT DOES NOT SPECIFY THE ROUTE USED FOR THE REMAINING FOUR TRIPS, IN WHICH THE SAME FOUR PEOPLE TOOK PART.

THE TWO HONDURAN WOMEN, NOW UNDER DETENTION, GAVE THE SALVADORANS FALSE DOCUMENTATION TO PASS AS HONDURANS, ACCORDING TO THE MILITARY INVESTIGATIONS.

DEV-MUC3-1225 (SYNCHRONETICS)

HAVANA (CUBA), 5 APR 90 (INTERNATIONAL SERVICE) -- [TEXT] VARIOUS INTERNAL AND EXTERNAL FACTORS HAVE MADE POSSIBLE THE MEETING IN OSLO, NORWAY'S CAPITAL. AT THE END OF MARCH, A GUATEMALAN NATIONAL REVOLUTIONARY ARMY [URNG] DELEGATION, REPRESENTING ITS GENERAL COMMAND, MET WITH A NATIONAL RECONCILIATION COMMISSION [CNR] DELEGATION, ACCREDITED TO SUPPORT THE GUATEMALAN GOVERNMENT AND ARMY TO FIND A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE VERY GRAVE CRISIS THAT IS AFFECTING THE COUNTRY IN GENERAL. IT IS WORTH NOTING THAT THE POLITICAL WILL AND BROAD INITIATIVE REPEATEDLY DISPLAYED BY THE URNG GENERAL COMMAND, WHICH SEEKS A POLITICAL SOLUTION TO THE INTERNAL ARMED CONFLICT WITH THEIR PARTICIPATION, HAS RECEIVED WIDESPREAD WELCOME AMONG THE POPULATION AND HAS CAUSED GREAT DOMESTIC AND INTERNATIONAL REPERCUSSIONS RESULTING IN THE APPROVAL AND SUPPORT OF A BROAD AND REPRESENTATIVE SEGMENT OF GUATEMALAN POLITICAL AND SOCIAL SECTORS.

AS MAY BE RECALLED, IT HAS BEEN THE MILITARY AND GOVERNMENT WHO HAVE OBSTINATELY REFUSED TO TALK TO THE GUATEMALAN ARMED INSURGENTS. THIS HIGHLIGHTS THE WEAKNESSES, ISOLATION, AND CONTRADICTIONS WITHIN THE ARMY AND THE RULING CHRISTIAN DEMOCRATIC PARTY. THE ARMY'S SECTOR MOST RELUCTANT TO TALK WITH THE GUERRILLAS IS BENT ON RESOLVING GUATEMALA'S ARMED CONFLICT BY WAY OF THE MILITARY, NOTWITHSTANDING THAT IT CONTRADICTORILY REFUSES TO ACKNOWLEDGE THEIR EXISTENCE.

IT IS THIS SECTOR THAT THE TROOPS AND SOME OFFICERS -- NOT PRECISELY THE SELF-NAMED MOUNTAIN OFFICERS -- BLAME FOR THE HARD SETBACKS AND SEVERE BLOWS INFLICTED BY THE GUERRILLA FORCES, THE FAILURE OF THE COUNTERINSURGENCY STRATEGY, AND THE ARMY BEING BOGGED DOWN. FOR THE MILITARY LEADERSHIP UNDER THESE CONDITIONS, THE SITUATION IS SOMETHING LIKE AN ALLEY, THE WAY OUT OF WHICH COULD BE SEEN IF DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL HECTOR GRAMAJO OPTED TO FOLLOW AND RESPECT THE LETTER AND SPIRIT OF THE OSLO AGREEMENTS.

IN THE CASE OF GUATEMALA, HOWEVER, IT IS NOT JUST SIMPLY ENDING AN UNDECLARED WAR THAT HAS LASTED NEARLY 30 YEARS. IN THE OPINION OF THE GUATEMALAN REVOLUTIONARIES, THE HELP OF ALL WHO FAVOR DEMOCRACY AND PEACE IS NEEDED TO LAY DOWN THE BASIS FOR A GREAT NATIONAL ACCORD THAT WILL ENSURE FOR GUATEMALA A SERIOUS PROCESS OF DIALOGUE AND TALKS SO AS TO RESOLVE THE HISTORIC AND ROOT STRUCTURAL CAUSES THAT HAVE GENERATED THE DOMESTIC ARMED CONFLICT, WHICH STILL REMAINS INTACT. THESE JUSTIFY AND GIVE VALIDITY TO THE DEMOCRATIC PROJECT, AND THE PATRIOTIC AND POPULAR STRUGGLE BY THE ARMED GUATEMALAN REVOLUTIONARY MOVEMENT.

COMPLIANCE AND IMPLEMENTATION OF THE BASIC AGREEMENT TO SEEK PEACE THROUGH POLITICAL MEANS, SIGNED IN THE NORWEGIAN CAPITAL ON 30 APRIL, DEPENDS THEN ON THE WILL AND POLITICAL ATTITUDE OF THE SIDES IN THE CONFLICT. THE GUATEMALAN REVOLUTIONARIES ARE PRECISELY THE ONES WHO HAVE SHOWN THE MOST WILLINGNESS AND WILL, AND WHO HAVE MADE THE MOST EFFORTS IN FAVOR OF PEACE IN GUATEMALA. THEIR WIDESPREAD POLITICAL AND DIPLOMATIC INITIATIVES AND THEIR MEANINGFUL ADVANCES IN THE BATTLEFIELD PERMIT THE INSURGENTS TO SIT DOWN AT THE NEGOTIATING TABLE WITH ENOUGH RESOURCES AND CONDITIONS TO ENSURE THAT THE OSLO AGREEMENTS ARE RESPECTED AND COMPLIED WITH; THAT GUATEMALA ENTERS INTO A TRUE PROCESS OF DEMOCRACY IN ITS INSTITUTIONS AND STRUCTURES, WITH BROAD NATIONAL SUPPORT AND INTERNATIONAL SOLIDARITY; AND THAT PEACE IS REESTABLISHED -- AN HONORABLE PEACE WITH DIGNITY THAT GUARANTEES SOCIAL JUSTICE AND INDEPENDENCE, PROGRESS, AND WELLBEING.

DEV-MUC3-1226 (BOEING)

SANTIAGO, 7 APR 90 (FORTIN MAPOCHO) -- [EDITORIAL] [TEXT] THROUGH HIS SPOKESMAN, U.S. PRESIDENT GEORGE BUSH HAS ANNOUNCED THAT HE WILL VISIT CHILE IN SEPTEMBER. THIS VERY IMPORTANT POLITICAL EVENT DEMONSTRATES THE EXTENT OF THE CHANGE THAT HAS OCCURRED IN THE COUNTRY SINCE THE 14 DECEMBER 1989 ELECTIONS.

THE ISOLATION HAS BEEN BROKEN AFTER A 16-YEAR PERIOD, AND IMPORTANT WORLD PERSONALITIES ARE BEGINNING TO VISIT US.

ITALY HAS CONSIDERED CHILE TO BE ONE OF ITS FIRST PRIORITIES FOR ECONOMIC AID AND TRADE. RELATIONS BETWEEN OUR COUNTRY AND BULGARIA WERE RESUMED ON FRIDAY AFTER 16 YEARS OF DICTATORSHIP. PREVIOUSLY, OTHER SOCIALIST COUNTRIES TOOK THE SAME PATH, AND IT WAS ONLY A FEW DAYS AGO THAT THE MEXICAN PRESIDENT VISITED OUR CAPITAL TO CONFIRM THAT LINKS HAD BEEN RESUMED BETWEEN THE TWO NATIONS.

IN GENERAL PINOCHET'S OPINION, CHILE WAS AT WAR FOR THE 16 YEARS OF THE DICTATORSHIP. CURIOUSLY, THE ALLEGED ALLIED CAMP, THE WESTERN COUNTRIES THROUGH THEIR CHIEFS OF STATE, REFUSED TO TALK WITH HIM OR EXTEND HIM INVITATIONS. FURTHERMORE, IT WAS CONSIDERED DISGRACEFUL TO HAVE ANY LINKS WITH THE REIGNING REGIME THAT HAD VIOLATED EVERY TYPE OF HUMAN RIGHT ACCORDING TO 16 SENTENCES HANDED DOWN BY THE UNITED NATIONS.

FOR THE UNITED STATES, RELATIONS WITH CHILE WERE ANNOYING AND THAT COUNTRY MADE IT KNOWN. THE DICTATORSHIP'S COMMANDOS TRAVELLED TO WASHINGTON TO KILL ORLANDO LETELIER. FOR THIS OPERATION THEY VIOLATED BORDERS AND LAWS WITH FALSE PASSPORTS TO CONDUCT THIS TERRORIST ACT THAT IS STILL CONSIDERED A BLACK MARK AGAINST CHILEAN JUSTICE.

NEVER IN THE HISTORY OF CHILEAN-U.S. RELATIONS HAVE THINGS BEEN SO LOW AS DURING THE PAST 16 YEARS.

ONLY IN LIGHT OF THIS BACKGROUND DATA CAN THE IMPORTANCE OF GEORGE BUSH'S VISIT BE EVALUATED. ALL THIS MARKS THE BEGINNING OF A NEW ERA WITH THE RE-INSTATEMENT OF OUR NATION IN THE PLACE THAT IT HAS ALWAYS HISTORICALLY OCCUPIED, THE RECOVERY OF OUR INFLUENCE, AND THE IMPORTANCE OF THIS COUNTRY'S FUTURE COMMITMENTS.

BUSH'S VISIT IS THE MOST VISIBLE DEMONSTRATION THAT "THE WARS" HAVE ENDED AND THAT INTERNATIONAL POLICIES ARE TODAY BUILT ON THE BASIS OF UNDERSTANDING AND COOPERATION.

DEV-MUC3-1227 (BOEING)

PORT-AU-PRINCE (HAITI), 19 APR 90 (RADIO SOLEIL NETWORK) -- [TEXT] A DELEGATION FROM LA FANMI SE LA VI [LITERALLY,"THE FAMILY IS LIFE", AN ORGANIZATION HEADED BY FATHER JEAN BERTRAND ARISTIDE] IS GOING TO PARTICIPATE IN THE INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON STREET URCHINS BEING HELD 23-30 APRIL IN BUENOS AIRES, CAPITAL OF ARGENTINA. THE REVEREND FATHER JEAN BERTRAND ARISTIDE, WHO LEADS THIS LITTLE SOCIETY, WILL LEAVE HAITI ON 20 APRIL. HE WILL BE HEADING THE HAITIAN DELEGATION TO THIS CONFERENCE.

FATHER ARISTIDE SAID HE IS LEAVING WITH MUCH CHAGRIN IN HIS HEART BECAUSE NOT ONLY ARE THE UNDERCOVER DETECTIVES STILL ARMED BUT THE JUDICIARY HAS AS YET TO SHOW THAT CHANGE IS BLOWING OVER THE COUNTRY.

FATHER ARISTIDE POINTED THE FINGER AT MRS. ERTHA PASCAL TROUILLOT, WHO MUST SHOULDER HER RESPONSIBILITY BEFORE THE ENTIRE WORLD, WHICH THINKS THE HAITIAN ARMY IS UNDER THE ORDERS OF THE NATION'S PRESIDENT, LIKE THE HEAD OF THE ARMY DECLARED ON 13 MARCH 1990. FATHER ARISTIDE FEELS ONE CANNOT COUNT ON THE HAITIAN ARMY TO PROVIDE SECURITY DURING THE ELECTIONS. FATHER ARISTIDE SAYS THAT, EVEN THOUGH A PART OF THE ARMY IS HONEST, THE TREND TODAY DICTATES ORGANIZED VIGILANCE BRIGADES IN ADDITION TO THE HONEST PART OF THE ARMY, IF WE DO NOT WANT A REPEAT OF 29 NOVEMBER 1987. FATHER ARISTIDE SAYS YES TO ELECTIONS BUT FIRST, JUSTICE. IF NOT, THE OAS AND THE UNITED NATIONS CAN GO AHEAD AND COME TO HAITI, BUT IT WILL BE LIKE WASHING ONE'S HANDS AND PATTING THEM ON THE DUSTY GROUND TO DRY THEM.

REGARDING THE WAY THE POPULATION IS PROVIDING ITS OWN JUSTICE BY BURNING PEOPLE ALL OVER THE COUNTRY, FATHER ARISTIDE SAID THAT THE POPULATION ACTS THIS WAY BECAUSE THE JUDICIAL AUTHORITIES DO NOT DO THEIR DUTY; AND THAT IF THE MINISTRY OF JUSTICE DOES NOT DECIDE TO HURRY UP, THEY [NOT FURTHER IDENTIFIED] MIGHT AS WELL SHUT IT DOWN AND RE-OPEN IT WITH BRAND NEW PEOPLE.

REGARDING THE RUMORS CIRCULATING TO THE EFFECT THAT FATHER ARISTIDE IS PLANNING TO RUN IN THE FUTURE ELECTIONS IN HAITI, FATHER ARISTIDE DECLARED: ARISTIDE HAS NEVER BEEN POWER-MAD. NOR HAS HE EVER HANKERED TO BE PRESIDENT. FATHER ARISTIDE SAID, FURTHER, AND WE QUOTE: I HAVE CHOSEN TO REMAIN AT THE SIDE OF THE MASSES. I WILL DO WHAT THE MASSES ASK ME TO DO, AS HAS ALWAYS BEEN THE CASE. [NO REFERENCE OF CLOSING OF QUOTATION AS HEARD]

LAST, FATHER ARISTIDE ASKED THE HONEST MEMBERS OF THE ARMED FORCES TO GO OVER AND STAND AT THE SIDE OF THE MASSES. BY SO DOING, THEY WILL GO DOWN IN HISTORY AS PEOPLE WHO WORKED TO SET HAITI ON THE ROAD TO DEMOCRACY.

THUS, FATHER ARISTIDE HELD A PRESS CONFERENCE THIS MORNING, TO ANNOUNCE THAT HE WAS GOING ON A TRIP TO REPRESENT LA FANMI SE LA VI AT THE INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE ON STREET URCHINS THAT IS BEING HELD IN ARGENTINA.

DEV-MUC3-1228 (BOEING)

BUENOS AIRES, 21 APR 90 (DYN) -- [TEXT] DEFENSE MINISTER HUMBERTO ROMERO SAID TODAY THAT ARGENTINA HAS "SUSPENDED AND FROZEN" THE "CONDOR" MISSILE PROJECT. HE ALSO DENIED INTERNATIONAL PRESS REPORTS THAT THE MISSILE WAS BEING BUILT IN SECRET WITH IRAQ FOR POTENTIAL USE AGAINST ISRAEL.

DURING A MEETING WITH REPORTERS THIS AFTERNOON, ROMERO SAID: "THE PROJECT WAS SUSPENDED BECAUSE OF A POLITICAL DECISION, AND ALSO BECAUSE WE DO NOT HAVE FUNDS TO FINANCE THIS TECHNICAL PROJECT."

THIS IS HOW THE MINISTER IMPLICITLY ALLUDED TO THE REPEATED PRESS REPORTS FROM EUROPE, THE UNITED STATES, AND THE MIDDLE EAST ABOUT ARGENTINE PARTICIPATION IN THE CONSTRUCTION OF ONE OF THE STAGES OF THE IRAQI MISSILE SYSTEM.

ALTHOUGH HE DID NOT SPECIFICALLY MENTION IRAQ, ISRAEL, OR THE REPORT ON THE MISSILE, ROMERO SAID: "WE WANT TO PUT THIS TO REST IN THE FACE OF PUBLICATIONS THAT APPEAR IN THE INTERNATIONAL PRESS EVERY SO OFTEN." HE ADDED: "WE ALWAYS SAID THE PROJECT NEVER REPRESENTED ANY RISK OR DANGER FOR ANYONE, BUT AT ANY RATE THE PROJECT WAS SUSPENDED, IT IS FROZEN."

THIS WEEK IRAQI PRESIDENT SADDAM HUSSEIN SAID HIS COUNTRY CAN WAGE A TOTAL WAR AGAINST ISRAEL THROUGH THE USE OF MEDIUM-RANGE STRATEGIC MISSILES THAT CAN REPORTEDLY CARRY CHEMICAL WEAPONS. HUSSEIN ALSO SAID ANY ISRAELI EFFORT TO BOMB THE IRAQI MISSILE MANAUFACTURING PLANTS WOULD BE FUTILE BECAUSE "OUR MISSILES ARE MADE IN PARTS IN DIFFERENT AREAS OF THE WORLD."

ON SEVERAL OCCASIONS OUR COUNTRY HAS BEEN MENTIONED AS THE MANUFACTURER, IN COOPERATION WITH EGYPT AND IRAQ, OF MEDIUM-RANGE -- ABOUT 800 KM -- BALLISTIC MISSILES. EACH TIME ARGENTINA HAS CATEGORICALLY DENIED THIS. THE ARGENTINE AIR FORCE SUCCESSFULLY DEVELOPED THE "CONDOR I" AND "CONDOR II" PROJECTS. IT HAS BEEN ASSURED THAT THESE ARE FOR PUTTING A DOMESTIC SATELLITE IN ORBIT.

THE LAST MISSILE TEST WAS MADE JULY L989 AT THE CHAMICAL AIRSPACE BASE, LA RIOJA PROVINCE, WHERE A STAGE OF THE "CONDOR" MISSILE TRAVELLED MORE THAT 160 KM.

DEV-MUC3-1231 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, 25 APR 90 (CANAL DOCE) -- [COMMUNIQUE] [COLONEL SIGIFREDO OCHOA PEREZ] [TEXT] 1. THE ATTITUDE OF CERTAIN BAD ARMED FORCES MEMBERS SHOULD NOT BE USED TO CREATE A NEGATIVE IMAGE OF THE ARMED FORCES IN GENERAL. QUITE THE CONTRARY, IT IS APPROPRIATE TO PURGE THE RANKS AND GET RID OF THOSE BAD MEMBERS, SO THAT THEY DO NOT CONTINUE TO HARM THE REMAINING MEMBERS.

2. THIS PUBLIC STATEMENT ABOUT THE NEED FOR A PURGE IS SIMPLY THE REPLY TO A HISTORICAL REQUIREMENT, BECAUSE WHOEVER REPORTS THE ISSUE DOES NOT CAUSE THE DAMAGE.

3. IN REFERENCE TO THOSE WHO CARRIED OUT THE ORDER TO ASSASSINATE THE JESUITS, THEY WERE ACTUALLY DOING THAT -- CARRYING OUT ORDERS. I HAVE ONLY SAID IN PUBLIC WHAT THE PEOPLE HAVE BEEN SAYING AND EXPRESSING IN A LOW VOICE.

4. THEREFORE, A NATIONAL COMMENTARY DOES NOT ENDANGER THE COUNTRY OR THE ARMED FORCES. THOSE WHO DECIDED TO ADOPT A DECISION, WHOSE SUBSEQUENT CONSEQUENCES THEY SHOULD HAVE ASSESSED, ARE THE ONES WHO ENDANGERED THE U.S. MILITARY AID AND -- IN THE PROCESS -- WITTINGLY OR UNWITTINGLY PLAYED INTO THE FMLN'S [FARABUNDO MARTI NATIONAL LIBERATION FRONT] HANDS.

5. WE SUPPOSE THAT THERE IS INFORMATION ON THE ISSUE AND THAT IT IS EXCLUSIVELY IN THE HANDS OF CERTAIN GROUPS WHICH, FOR ONE REASON OR ANOTHER, HAVE FAILED TO TURN IT OVER TO THE APPROPRIATE PERSONS.

6. JUST AS THE GOVERNMENT OF THE REPUBLIC AND A VAST MAJORITY OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE EXPECTED, A FULL INVESTIGATION AND SOLUTION OF THIS CRIME WHICH SHOOK THE WORLD, ALL GOOD SALVADORANS TRUST THAT JUSTICE WILL PREVAIL AND THAT THOSE WHO VIOLATED THE LAW WILL ANSWER FOR THE CRIME THEY HAVE PERPETRATED.

DEV-MUC3-1234 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 26 APR 90 (EMISORAS CARACOL NETWORK) -- [REPORT] [JAIRO CORREA] [TEXT] THE CALLER IDENTIFIED HIMSELF AS ZAPATOCA -- THIS MUST BE AN ALIAS. HE SAID HE IS AN ACTIVE MEMBER OF THE EXTRADITABLES GROUP WITH HEADQUARTERS IN MEDELLIN. HE SAID THAT CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ'S DEATH WAS A RESULT OF A COIN TOSS OVER CESAR GAVIRIA, RODRIGO LLOREDA CAICEDO, CARLOS PIZARRO, AND ALVARO GOMEZ. TODAY'S BAD LUCK FELL ON CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ.

THE CALLER SAID THAT HE WAS ACTING UNDER THE ORDERS OF KIKI CASTANO AND HENRY PEREZ AND THAT THE TWO PEOPLE KILLED INSIDE THE PLANE WERE RECRUITED BY PIRINA, DON JAIRO TAZCON, THE HEAD OF THE MEDELLIN HIRED ASSASSINS. HE ADDED THAT THIS SERIES OF CRIMINAL ATTACKS WILL CONTINUE AS LONG AS THE GOVERNMENT DOES NOT GIVE THEM POLITICAL - MILITARY TREATMENT. HE SAID THAT THE EXTRADITABLES HAVE SET ASIDE THEIR STRUGGLE AGAINST EXTRADITION. THEY ARE NOW DEMANDING POLITICAL - MILITARY TREATMENT AND HAVE THREATENED TO CONTINUE WITH THIS TYPE OF ACTION. THEY WARN THAT THEY HAVE WHAT THEY HAVE CALLED AN IRANIAN-MADE Z-5 K, WHICH ACCORDING TO ZAPATOCA WILL BE USED FOR THE FIRST TIME IN BOGOTA WITHIN THE NEXT FEW DAYS.

DEV-MUC3-1235 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 26 APR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] A FEW MINUTES AGO AN OFFICIAL SPOKESMAN FROM THE NATIONAL SOCIAL SECURITY FUND [CNPS] READ THE FOLLOWING COMMUNIQUE CONFIRMING THE DEATH OF MR. PIZARRO.

[BEGIN RECORDING] [UNIDENTIFIED SPOKESMAN] THE CNPS REGRETS TO INFORM THE PEOPLE THAT PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ WAS ADMITTED TO THE EMERGENCY ROOM THIS MORNING, AFTER HAVING BEEN SHOT SEVERAL TIMES IN THE HEAD AND NECK A FEW MINUTES EARLIER. THESE SHOTS CAUSED VERY SERIOUS NEUROLOGICAL AND CEREBRAL WOUNDS AS WELL AS GRAVE WOUNDS TO THE FACE AND NECK.

DESPITE THE EFFORTS OF A TEAM OF DOCTORS, INCLUDING GENERAL SURGEONS, NEUROSURGEONS, ANESTHESISTS, OPHTHALMOLOGISTS, DOCTORS FROM THE INTENSIVE CARE UNIT, AND OTHER STAFF MEMBERS OF THE CNPS, IT WAS NOT POSSIBLE TO SAVE HIS LIFE AND HE DIED [7-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] [END RECORDING]

...GOT INTO AN ALTERCATION WITH THE M-19 LEADERS WHO WERE THERE AT THE TIME SHOUTING SLOGANS. THEY DID NOT ALLOW THE CNPS SPOKESMAN TO FINISH READING THE COMMUNIQUE.

THE AUTHORITIES HAVE AGAIN CORDONED OFF THE AREA. THE M-19 MEMBERS ARE PROTESTING THE MURDER OF PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ [7-SECOND BREAK IN RECEPTION] I WOULD LIKE TO MENTION THAT THE NATIONAL POLICE, THE F-2, AND THE ADMINISTRATIVE DEPARTAMENT OF SECURITY ARE CURRENTLY LOOKING FOR AT LEAST TWO COLLABORATORS OF THE PAID ASSASSIN WHO MURDERED M-19 LEADER PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ.

THE AUTHORITIES HAVE REPORTED THAT AT LEAST TWO MEN COLLABORATED WITH THE MURDERER INSIDE THE HK-1400 PLANE THAT WAS FLYING BETWEEN BOGOTA AND BARRANQUILLA. THE AUTHORITIES HAVE ALSO REPORTED THAT THE MACHINEGUN USED BY THE PAID ASSASSIN, WHO IDENTIFIED HIMSELF AS ALVARO RODRIGUEZ, WAS HIDDEN IN THE BATHROOM. NOW THE AUTHORITIES ARE TRYING TO ESTABLISH IF THE WEAPON WAS PLACED THERE AT THE BUCARAMANGA AIRPORT, WHERE THE PLANE HAD BEEN FOR THE PAST FEW HOURS, OR IF IT WAS PLACED THERE IN BOGOTA.

THE POLICE HAD SEARCHED THE PAID ASSASSIN TWICE BEFORE THE INCIDENT BUT DID NOT FIND ANY WEAPONS.

DEV-MUC3-1236 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 26 APR 90 (EFE) -- [TEXT] THE GOVERNMENT HAS ANNOUNCED A TOTAL OFFENSIVE TO CAPTURE MEDELLIN CARTEL BOSS PABLO ESCOBAR GAVIRIA FOLLOWING THE DEATH YESTERDAY OF NINE PEOPLE IN AN ATTACK BY THE EXTRADITABLES IN MEDELLIN.

THE OFFENSIVE WAS ANNOUNCED AT THE END OF AN URGENT MEETING OF THE SECURITY COUNCIL CALLED BY GOVERNMENT MINISTER HORACIO SERPA URIBE, WHO IS ACTING PRESIDENT BECAUSE OF PRESIDENT VIRGILIO BARCO'S TRIP TO NICARAGUA TO ATTEND THE INAUGURATION OF PRESIDENT VIOLETA CHAMORRO.

SERPA SAID THAT ESCOBAR HAS BECOME ENEMY NO. ONE AND NOTED THAT ALL OF THE AUTHORITIES' EFFORTS ARE NOW CENTERED ON HIS CAPTURE. THE MINISTER SAID THAT ESCOBAR IS BEHIND THE VIOLENCE ONSLAUGHT AND ASKED THE POPULATION TO COOPERATE WITH THE AUTHORITIES' EFFORTS TO CAPTURE HIM. "PABLO ESCOBAR IS BEHIND THE VIOLENCE ONSLAUGHT," THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER SAID.

NINE PEOPLE DIED AND APPROXIMATELY 50 WERE WOUNDED WHEN A CAR LOADED WITH 200 KG OF DYNAMITE EXPLODED IN A HEAVILY POPULATED DISTRICT IN MEDELLIN KNOWN AS LAS AMERICAS. POLICE SOURCES SAID THAT THE CAR BOMB, WHICH WAS CAMOUFLAGED WITH CONSTRUCTION WASTE, WAS SET OFF BY REMOTE CONTROL AT A PASSING ELITE POLICE PATROL.

THE EXPLOSION SERIOUSLY DAMAGED OVER 10 PRIVATE VEHICLES AND AT LEAST THREE BUSES WITH PASSENGERS AS WELL AS A DOZEN BUSINESS ESTABLISHMENTS AND PRIVATE RESIDENCES.

DEFENSE MINISTER GENERAL OSCAR BOTERO RESTREPO SAID THAT THE ATTACK WAS THE WORK OF THE EXTRADITABLES, THE ARMED WING OF THE MEDELLIN CARTEL, ONE OF THE BIGGEST DRUG PROCESSING AND DRUG TRAFFICKING ORGANIZATIONS IN THE WORLD. MEDELLIN, COLOMBIA'S SECOND LARGEST CITY, IS THE HOME OF THE CARTEL AND OF ITS ARMED WING--THE EXTRADITABLES--WHICH DESCRIBED THEMSELVES IN MARCH AS A POLITICAL-MILITARY ORGANIZATION AND DECLARED WAR ON THE COLOMBIAN STATE.

THE EXTRADITABLES ANNOUNCED AT THE TIME THAT THEY WERE RELEGATING THEIR STRUGGLE TO PREVENT THE EXTRADITION OF COLOMBIANS TO THE UNITED STATES TO SECOND PLACE AND THAT THEIR TOP PRIORITY WOULD BE TO FIGHT THE STATE, THE OLIGARCHY AND THE MEMBERS OF THE POLICE WHO KIDNAP, TORTURE AND MURDER THE MEMBERS OF THEIR ORGANIZATION AND THEIR FAMILIES.

YESTERDAY'S ATTACK WAS THE SECOND TO BE CARRIED OUT AGAINST COLOMBIA'S SPECIAL ANTIDRUG AND COUNTERINSURGENCY ELITE POLICE CORPS. ON 11 MARCH ANOTHER CAR BOMB LOADED WITH OVER 100 KG OF DYNAMITE WAS EXPLODED AGAINST A POLICE VEHICLE ON THE FREEWAY SOUTH OF MEDELLIN. EIGHT POLICEMEN AND NINE CIVILIANS WERE KILLED IN THE EXPLOSION.

DEV-MUC3-1237 (BOEING)

BOGOTA, 26 APR 90 (RADIO CADENA NACIONAL) -- [TEXT] GOVERNMENT MINISTER HORACIO SERPA URIBE, WHO HAS JUST LEFT THE NATIONAL SOCIAL WELFARE INSTITUTE, HAS DENOUNCED CARLOS PIZARRO LEONGOMEZ' ASSASSINATION. HE ADDED THAT NO THOUGHT HAS BEEN GIVEN TO SUSPENDING THE ELECTIONS IN THE WAKE OF THIS DEVELOPMENT, AND ADDED THAT THE COUNTRY MUST NOT BE LEFT IN VIOLENT HANDS.

THE GOVERNMENT MINISTER COMMENTED FURTHER ON THE TOP M-19 [19 APRIL MOVEMENT] LEADER'S ASSASSINATION:

[BEGIN RECORDING] [SERPA] THE OCCURRENCE OF SUCH SAD AND CRIMINAL DEVELOPMENTS IS TRULY A DISGRACE. IT HAS SADDENED EVERYBODY VERY MUCH. I FEEL THAT THIS WAS NOT ONLY AN ATTACK AGAINST FORMER CANDIDATE PIZARRO BUT AN ATTACK AGAINST THE COUNTRY, DEMOCRACY, AND THE ELECTORAL PROCESS. I FEEL THAT WE MUST RESPOND TO AGGRESSIVENESS AND CRIME WITH FEELINGS OF CONCILIATION AND PEACE.

[REPORTER] HAS ANY THOUGHT BEEN GIVEN TO SUSPENDING THE ELECTIONS AFTER THIS ASSASSINATION, BEARING IN MIND THAT PIZARRO WAS ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT CANDIDATES?

[SEPRPA] HE WAS UNDOUBTEDLY ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT CANDIDATES. THE GOVERNMENT ALWAYS THOUGHT SO. IN ADDITION, THE GOVERNMENT HIGHLY REGARDS THE PEACEMKING PROCESS IT HAS BEEN CARRYING OUT WITH THE M-19, IN WHICH PIZARRO WAS UNDOUBTEDLY A KEY PLAYER. WE HAVE ADOPTED SOME DECISIONS IN THIS REGARD. I AM GOING TO MEET WITH THE HEAD OF STATE AND ALL OF US WILL BE CLOSELY WATCHING THE SAD DEVELOPMENTS WHICH COLOMBIA IS EXPERIENCING WITH A DESIRE TO MEET THE NEED FOR TRANQUILLITY AND COEXISTENCE WHICH, UNFORTUNATELY, WE HAVE NOT HAD THUS FAR.

[REPORTER] MR. MINISTER, WHAT DOES THE FACT THAT TWO PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES HAVE BEEN ASSASSINATED IN LESS THAN 40 DAYS REPRESENT TO THE GOVERNMENT? HOW DOES THE GOVERNMENT LOOK BEFORE THE NATION AND THE WORLD?

[SERPA] WELL, I REPEAT, THIS IS A VERY SAD CIRCUMSTANCE. THIS IS EXTREMELY WORRISOME, OF COURSE. LIKE ALL COLOMBIANS, WE ARE TROUBLED OVER THE FACT THAT WE ARE CONSTANTLY BEING FLOODED WITH CRIME AND BLOODSHED. THE GOVERNMENT IS DOING THE IMPOSSIBLE TO PROTECT ALL CITIZENS AND TO GUARANTEE THE ELECTIONS AND THE NORMAL DEVELOPMENT OF COLOMBIANS' LIVES. HOWEVER, THERE ARE DELUDED MINDS AND THERE ARE CRIMINALS WHO ARE INTERESTED IN DAMAGING THE COUNTRY. THIS IS AN ATTACK AGAINST COLOMBIA, AGAINST THE COLOMBIAN PEOPLE.

[REPORTER] MR. MINISTER, HAVE YOU AT ANY TIME THOUGHT OF ADOPTING SPECIAL MEASURES? WHAT IS THE STATUS OF THE PUBLIC ORDER SITUATION IN COLOMBIA AT THIS TIME? WHAT REPORTS DO YOU HAVE?

[SERPA] NO, THERE IS CALM IN GENERAL. THE GOVERNMENT IS VERY WORRIED, OF COURSE. WE ARE GOING TO MEET NOW TO DISCUSS THIS TERRIBLE CASE.

[REPORTER] HOWEVER, DO YOU NOT THINK THAT IT IS VERY DIFFICULT TO GO ON CAMPAIGNING IN PUBLIC AT THIS MOMENT?

[SERPA] I WOULD NOT DARE MAKE ANY ASSERTION IN THIS REGARD. WHAT I FEEL IS THAT WE MUST NOT YIELD A SINGLE CENTIMETER TO THE VIOLENT PEOPLE AND THE CRIMINALS. [END RECORDING]

SERPA MADE THESE STATEMENTS A FEW MINUTES AGO AS HE LEFT THE NATIONAL SOCIAL WELFARE INSTITUTE, WHERE AN AUTOPSY IS BEING PERFORMED AT THIS MOMENT ON PIZARRO'S BODY.

DEV-MUC3-1238 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] THE IMPORTANT THING IS THAT THIS IS THE GOVERNMENT'S CLARIFICATION, WHICH REPRESENTS THE GOVERNMENT'S STAND.

[MODERATOR] DAVID RIVAS OF AFP.

[RIVAS] MR. PRESIDENT, YOUR REPLIES TO PREVIOUS QUESTIONS HAVE ALREADY ANSWERED MY FIRST QUESTION. I WOULD LIKE TO ASK YOU SOMETHING, HOWEVER. NOW THAT THE DIALOGUE PROCESS IS ABOUT TO START, THE TWO SIDES HAVE APPARENTLY HARDENED THEIR POSITIONS. THE FMLN COMMANDERS HAVE SAID THAT, TO END THE WAR IN EL SALVADOR, THERE MUST BE A SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEMS OF INJUSTICE AND LACK OF DEMOCRACY. THE MINISTER OF JUSTICE, IN TURN, SAID RECENTLY THAT THE FMLN MUST RETURN TO CIVILIAN LIFE AND THAT THERE IS NO NEED TO NEGOTIATE. I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW WHAT WILL BE NEGOTIATED AND WHAT WILL BE DONE TO END THE WAR THROUGH A DIALOGUE WITH THE FMLN.

[CRISTIANI] I AM SURPRISED BY THE REMARKS THAT YOU ARE ATTRIBUTING TO DR. SANTAMARIA, BECAUSE HE IS VERY WELL INFORMED ABOUT WHAT HAS HAPPENED SO FAR. HE IS VERY MUCH AWARE THAT THERE IS POINT TWO OF THE GENEVA AGREEMENT, WHICH NOTES THAT POLITICAL AGREEMENTS MUST BE REACHED IN ORDER TO PUT AN END TO ARMED CONFRONTATION AND THE VIOLENCE THAT IS AFFECTING THE CIVILIAN POPULATION. SUBSEQUENTLY, THERE WILL BE A PROCESS FOR DISARMAMENT AND DEMOBILIZATION, REFERRED TO AS THE TOTAL SUSPENSION OF HOSTILITIES IN THE AGREEMENT. I BELIEVE THAT IT IS A MATTER OF REACHING AGREEMENTS. WE, AS A GOVERNMENT, ARE INVOLVED IN THIS BECAUSE WE SEE THE SUFFERING OF THE SALVADORAN PEOPLE. WE BELIEVE THAT IT IS NOT FAIR FOR THEM TO LIVE IN A CLIMATE OF VIOLENCE IN WHICH THERE ARE SO MANY KILLED, SO MUCH DESTRUCTION, AND SO MANY PROBLEMS.

AS A GOVERNMENT, WE HAVE ALWAYS ASKED: WHAT ARE THE PROBLEMS BARRING THEIR RETURNING TO CIVILIAN LIFE? THEY ARE THE ONLY GROUP THAT HAS NOT JOINED THE SALVADORAN DEMOCRATIC PROCESS. WHAT DO THEY WANT? LET US SEE IF THERE IS ANYTHING REASONABLE THAT CAN BE DONE. THE POLITICAL PARTIES HAVE EXPRESSED WILLINGNESS TO CONSIDER ALL THAT COULD FOSTER OR CONSOLIDATE THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS IN OUR COUNTRY. WE BELIEVE THAT THERE WILL BE NO PROBLEMS. I CANNOT SEE ANY HARDENING BY THE GOVERNMENT. I BELIEVE WE HAVE BEEN FLEXIBLE. WE HAVE SAID THAT THE GOVERNMENT HAS BEEN IMMEDIATELY ACCEPTING AS ITS OWN ANY CONSENSUS REACHED BY THE PARTIES. IN OTHER WORDS, AT LEAST YOUR REMARK ON THE GOVERNMENT IS NOT TRUE. I REPEAT, PERHAPS IN THE STYLE OF THE PREVIOUS QUESTION, THAT WE DO NOT WANT TO BE BIASED. IN DUE TIME, WE WILL SEE WHETHER THE FMLN HAS OR HAS NOT BEEN INFLEXIBLE OR HARDENED OR WHATEVER. IT WILL DEPEND ON WHETHER THE FMLN'S PROPOSALS ARE REASONABLE OR NOT.

[MODERATOR] PABLO YACU OF [WORDS INDISTINCT].

[YACU] MR. PRESIDENT, CONCERNING THE ECONOMY, SOME OF THE OPPOSITION POLITICIANS I TALKED WITH OVER THE PAST FEW DAYS HAVE TOLD ME THAT THEY ARE A LITTLE CONCERNED. THEY THINK THAT, BECAUSE DIFFICULTIES HAVE ARISEN, BECAUSE THERE IS A NEW SITUATION IN THE COUNTRY, AND BECAUSE THE VOLUME OF THE U.S. AID HAS DIMINISHED, THE COUNTRY IS RAPIDLY TAKING STEPS THAT OTHER LATIN AMERICAN COUNTRIES HAVE ALREADY TAKEN, TO MEET WITH THE SO-CALLED CONSULTING GROUP FORMED BY THE LEADING WORLD CREDIT INSTITUTIONS AND REQUEST LARGE LOANS TO STABILIZE THE BALANCE OF PAYMENTS. THESE POLITICIANS TOLD ME THAT THEY ARE CONCERNED BECAUSE THIS WOULD IMPOSE A HEAVY BURDEN ON THE NEW GOVERNMENT, WHICH WOULD ASSUME OFFICE AFTER 1994.

[CRISTIANI] WELL, I THINK THE OPPOSITION POLITICIANS SHOULD TRY TO UNDERSTAND THAT MANY OF THE MEASURES, WHICH CERTAINLY ENTAIL A SACRIFICE FOR THE VARIOUS NATIONAL SECTORS, ARE RESPONSIBLY TAKEN BECAUSE OF THE COUNTRY'S ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL PROBLEMS. MANY PEOPLE WILL SAY IT IS NOT NECESSARY TO DO THIS OR THAT. I WOULD ONLY LOOK AT WHAT HAS HAPPENED TO OTHER COUNTRIES WHICH, EVEN WITHOUT THE DESTRUCTION AND VIOLENCE CAUSED BY AN IRREGULAR FORCE, SUCH AS THE FMLN, HAVE EXPERIENCED MUCH MORE SERIOUS PROBLEMS THAN THOSE ENCOUNTERED BY EL SALVADOR AT PRESENT. WE WOULD ALSO ENCOUNTER THOSE PROBLEMS IF WE FAIL TO TAKE MEASURES. NEARBY IS NICARAGUA, THE INFLATION RATE OF WHICH HAS REACHED 1,700 PERCENT, ITS FOREIGN DEBT IS ENORMOUS, AND IT IS IMMERSED IN DRAMATIC PROBLEMS. NO MEASURES WERE TAKEN IN DUE TIME IN BRAZIL AND ARGENTINA, ALTHOUGH THESE MEASURES WERE PAINFUL. IF THEY ARE NOT TAKEN ON TIME, THEY WILL BE MUCH MORE PAINFUL LATER, BECAUSE EVENTUALLY SOMETHING WILL HAVE TO BE DONE TO CHECK THE ECONOMIC CRISIS THAT HAS BEEN CREATED. AT THIS TIME, WE ARE TRYING TO STABILIZE THE ECONOMY TO START ITS EFFECTIVE RECOVERY. IT IS BASED ON THIS RECOVERY THAT WE WILL AVOID FOREIGN INDEBTEDNESS, WHICH FOR MANY OTHER COUNTRIES HAS BEEN AN EASY WAY OUT AND AN ALTERNATIVE, WHEN THEY SHOULD HAVE ACTED RESPONSIBLY CONCERNING ECONOMIC PROBLEMS. [CONTINUED]

DEV-MUC3-1239 (BOEING)

SAN SALVADOR, NO DATE (DOMESTIC SERVICE) -- [INTERVIEW WITH PRESIDENT ALFREDO CRISTIANI BY MODERATOR AND REPORTERS] [TEXT] [CONTINUED] [CRISTIANI] YES, I THINK THAT YOU SHOULD TELL THIS TO THE JUDGE AT THE 4TH PENAL COURT. FRANKLY, AS I SAID, THIS CASE IS NOW IN THE HANDS OF THE COURT. THE JUDGE IS THE ONE WHO CAN ORDER FUTURE INVESTIGATIONS INTO THE CASE. YOUR QUESTIONS RELATE TO DOUBTS AND CONCERNS THAT THE JUDGE HAS BEFORE HIM. HE CAN SUMMON ANYONE TO TESTIFY. I UNDERSTAND THAT HE HAS ALREADY SUMMONED SOME TOP OFFICERS.

I CAN ONLY SAY THIS: YOU HAVE JUST MENTIONED A MEETING IN WHICH SUPPOSEDLY I WAS PRESENT. YOU ALSO SAID THAT IT WAS AT THAT MEETING THAT THE MURDER WAS PLANNED. THERE IS MUCH SPECULATION, THEREFORE I THINK THAT WE MUST REMAIN COOL-HEADED. IN OTHER WORDS, PEOPLE ARE SPECULATING WHEN THEY SAY THAT THIS COULD HAPPEN, THIS COULD HAVE HAPPENED, OR THIS COULD NOT HAVE HAPPENED. FOR EXAMPLE, SOME HAVE SAID THAT THERE IS A COVER UP, BUT COLONEL RIVAS HIMSELF WAS THE ONE WHO DISCOVERED WHO COMMITTED THE CRIME.

THERE ARE MANY QUESTIONS, WHICH IS NATURAL. HOWEVER, THAT DOES NOT MEAN THAT ...[CHANGES THOUGHT] FOR EXAMPLE, I MADE A STATEMENT FOR THE PROGRAM "60 MINUTES;" I WAS INTERVIEWED FOR AN HOUR AND A HALF, BUT OBVIOUSLY MY REPLIES WERE NOT AIRED FOR SOME REASON. HOWEVER, I SAID THAT IT IS NO SECRET IN OUR COUNTRY THAT THERE HAVE BEEN MANY PEOPLE, A GREAT NUMBER OF PEOPLE, WHO FEEL THAT AT ONE TIME OR ANOTHER SOME OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS WERE IN FACT LINKED TO THE FMLN. THEREFORE, IN THIS CASE, ALL THOSE WHO HAVE SAID ANYTHING TO THAT EFFECT WOULD HAVE TO BE INVESTIGATED. WOULD THAT BE CALLED FOR? WHAT I MEAN IS THAT IT IS VERY DIFFICULT TO MAKE A DECISION BASED ON SPECULATION.

FURTHERMORE, DURING THE INVESTIGATIONS -- CONDUCTED BY THE INVESTIGATIVE COMMISSION OF CRIMINAL ACTIONS, AN AUXILIARY LEGAL ORGAN -- WE THOUGHT IT WAS CONVENIENT AT A GIVEN TIME, SINCE WE HAD ENOUGH EVIDENCE ON A GROUP OF PEOPLE WE BELIEVE COMMITTED THE CRIME, THAT THE CASE SHOULD BE HANDLED BY THE JUDICIAL BRANCH.

THEREFORE, THE JUDICIAL BRANCH TODAY CONTINUES TO INVESTIGATE THE CASE AND DECIDES WHETHER TO INTERROGATE SOMEONE OR NOT. IF THERE IS ANY DOUBT, THE JUDICIAL BRANCH CAN ORDER THE COMMISSION TO INVESTIGATE THIS OR THAT. WHETHER SOMEONE IS INTERROGATED BY A JUDGE OR BY THE COMMISSION IS IRRELEVANT; THE JUDGE MUST DECIDE. I BELIEVE THAT IN THIS CASE THE JUDGE SHOULD INVESTIGATE. AS I SAID BEFORE, I THINK THAT THERE HAS BEEN PROGRESS. I UNDERSTAND THAT THE HONOR COMMISSION WILL BE SUMMONED, AND THAT ANOTHER MAY BE SUMMONED AFTERWARD.

[REPORTER] COULD YOU TELL US IN ENGLISH. YOU SAID THAT YOU DO NOT THINK THAT IT IS NECESSARY, THAT MANY PEOPLE HAVE CRITICIZED THE JESUITS, AND IF YOU ARE GOING TO START INVESTIGATING PEOPLE, WHY NOT INVESTIGATE EVERYONE WHO HAS CRITICIZED THE JESUITS. THE FACT REMAINS, HOWEVER, THAT NOT EVERYBODY IS IN A POSITION TO REPROVE THE JESUITS, NOT EVERYONE WAS IN THE MILITARY HIERARCHY, NOT EVERYONE WAS INVOLVED IN THE ALTO MANDO [PRECEDING WORDS IN SPANISH]. THERE ARE [WORD INDISTINCT] PEOPLE IN THE ALTO MANDO WHO ARE KNOWN TO HATE THE JESUITS, WHO ARE KNOWN TO HAVE CRITICIZED THEM IN THE PAST. WHY DO YOU NOT THINK THAT THIS WOULD BE CORRECT FOR THOSE PEOPLE TO BE INVESTIGATED DIRECTLY?

[CRISTIANI] FIRST OF ALL, I WOULD SAY THAT THE VAST MAJORITY OF OFFICERS IN THE ARMED FORCES AT ONE POINT OR ANOTHER, WHETHER LATELY OR EARLIER, THAT THERE WAS A WIDESPREAD BELIEF OF SOME SORT OF PARTICIPATION BY THE ...[CORRECTS HIMSELF] SOME OF THE JESUIT PRIESTS WITH THE FMLN. THIS IS NOT FOR US AT THIS POINT AND TIME TO DECIDE WHETHER IT IS TRUE OR UNTRUE. IT IS SIMPLY SOMETHING THAT WAS BELIEVED OUT THERE, AND THEREFORE, IT IS UP TO THE JUDGE TO DECIDE WHETHER HE WILL ONLY INTERVIEW ONE PERSON WHO BELIEVED THIS, OR WHETHER HE IS GOING TO INTERVIEW MANY PEOPLE.

THERE HAS BEEN ALSO THE FACT THAT IT WELL COULD HAVE BEEN THE ACT OF THE FMLN, THE ACT OF INDIVIDUAL GROUPS. THERE WERE ALSO SPECULATIONS AT THE BEGINNING WHEN THE ASSASSINATION WAS COMMITTED AS TO WHO COULD HAVE COMMITTED THE CRIME. SO THERE ARE OTHER GROUPS THAT COULD HAVE COMMITTED THE CRIME, AND THEREFORE, THERE COULD BE OTHERS THAT WE COULD HAVE FOLLOWED THE [WORD INDISTINCT] INVESTIGATING. BUT, I THINK IT IS ALL UP TO THE JUDGE NOW [TO DECIDE] WHO WILL HE CALL TO TESTIFY, WHO WILL HE CALL TO INTERROGATE, AND IF HE FINDS ANY NEED, HE HAS ALL THE POWER TO INSTRUCT THE INVESTIGATIVE UNIT TO FOLLOW THROUGH ON ANYTHING THAT HE REACHES. IT IS NOT UP TO EXECUTIVE BRANCH RIGHT NOW TO DECIDE WHO IS GOING TO COME UP WITH TESTIMONY WITH THE JUDGE. IT IS UP TO THE JUDGE TO DECIDE. [CONTINUED]